This module will briefly review some of
the mathematical concepts that
will help you understand the topics
covered in this statistics course.
In this video, we'll be focusing on five
concepts, factorials and
summations, the equation of a line, and
the exponential function, as well as the
natural logarithm.
So, jumping right into factorials.
Factorials are denoted with an exclamation
point as shown here.
The formal definition for a factorial, and
I'll repeat this,
is that it's the product of all positive
integers less than or equal to the number.
Again, it's the product of all positive
integers less than or
equal to this number.
Now, if I say that in another way that's
like saying that when you
take the factorial of a number, you're
multiplying all the positive whole
numbers between that number and the number
1.
So, let me illustrate that with an
example.
3 factorial, whats 3 factorial?
It's 3 times 2 times 1, and that's equal
to 6.
Okay, the key takeaway here is that 3
factorial is simply a number,
3 factorial is equal to 6.
Let's go over another example.
What's 6 factorial?
So, we're going to be multiplying all the
numbers between 6 and 1.
So, that means 6 factorial is going to
equal 6 times 5
times 4 times 3 times 2 times 1.
And we're going to do a little bit of Math
here.
And we're going to figure out that 6
factorial is equal to 720.
Again, the big takeaway here, being that 6
factorial is simply a number.
It's equal to 720.
It's you can think about it as if it's
another way of writing 720.
One thing to know about factorials is that
you
can only take the factorial of a positive
integer.
You can't take factorials of negative
numbers and get a real solution.
One thing you'll have to remember about
factorials is what 0 factorial equals.
0 factorial equals 1.
Again 0 factorial is defined as 1.
Before I move on to summations one last
thing I
want to go over with factorials is a trick
for how to simplify them.
Let's say you come across a problem 13
factorial divided by 10 factorial.
Because you know the definition of the
factorial,
you're thinking to yourself, gosh these
are going to be really large numbers.
I'm going to have to multiply 13 times 12
times 11 times 10, all the way down to 1.
Do that again on the bottom.
Well, you can also rewrite this top part.
But instead of going all the way down to
1, you can stop here and
finish off this expression with 10
factorial.
And the reason I'm going to do that is so
that I can cancel out the same expression
on the top and bottom of this fraction.
Remember, I can do this because 10
factorial is a number.
I don't know what number it is, off the
top of my head.
It's a very large number, but I can cancel
that.
And that leaves me with something very
manageable.
13 time 12 times 11, which happens to
equal 1716.
So, this is just a trick for simplifying
factorials
if you ever come across a problem like
this.
Summations are expressed with the capital
Greek letter sigma, okay?
And whenever you see a summation symbol,
I want you to focus on these three areas,
okay?
This first part on the bottom of the
sigma,
it represents the lower bound of the
summation.
This top part, number 2 represents the
upper bound, very intuitive.
And then this third part,
on the side is the expression that you're
going to be summing over.
And let me illustrate what I mean by that
with an example.
Okay?
So lets say your index variable right
here.
Your lower bound is going to be one.
You're going to be going all the way to 6
,and we're going to be iterating over i.
What does that mean?
Well, it means we're going to start at 1.
And every time we add a term to this
expression,
we're going to iterate i by 1 until we
reach 6.
So, that means 1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4 plus
5 plus 6.
Okay?
And that equals 21.
Just like with factorials,
this complicated looking expression is
just a number.
It's another way of writing 21.
Another key point here is to realize that
I'm adding all of
these because these are all equal to i.
And that's the expression that we're
summing over.
Okay, let me illustrate this with another
example.
So, very similar to the last one, except
we're going to be summing over 7 i.
Okay, so this is going to look like this.
We're going to start at the lower bound,
okay, and end when we reach the upper
bound.
Whatever that definition is.
In this case, it's still 1 and 6.
So, what we're going to do here is
multiply 7 times 1.
7 times 2.
Okay.
All the way until we reach 7 times 6.
And you might realize that you can take
out the 7 from this expression, okay?
To give yourself something that looks like
this.
7 times the quantity 1 plus 2 plus 3 plus
4 plus 5 plus 6.
Of course, and because we did this last
problem, we know that, that's 21.
So, this expression right here results in
7 times 21, okay.
So, let me rate, rewrite that in another
way.
So, that results in 7 times this
summation.
If you'll look at these two carefully,
what you'll realize is that all I did was
move this 7 to the outside.
Okay?
This illustrates one property of
summations, there are multiple properties.
I won't go into them in this video.
But I just wanted to give you a taste of
what knowing these properties can do and
how they can help you simplify much more
complicated expressions.
One more example with summations.
Now, let's imagine that you have some
data.
Okay, let's imagine that you have five
data points labeled x 1 to x 5, okay?
And let's imagine that these values are 2,
4, 6, 8, and 10.
Okay, we call this we say that these data,
this data is indexed.
And what that means is that this first
point, okay, corresponds to x sub 1.
Second point corresponds to x sub 2, etc.
And each of these points corresponds to an
actual value in the data set.
So, I can use the summation to sum either
part or this whole set of numbers.
Okay, and let me illustrate that.
Lets say with something like this.
Okay, so what is this expression going to
equal?
Well, if I write it out, this is going to
be x sub 3 plus x sub 4 plus x sub 5,
which corresponds to 6 plus 8 plus 10,
which is 24, okay?
So, this real illustrates a more practical
example of
how you can think about summations.
And how they can be helpful to you.
When thing about large sets of data.
Probably the most common form that you'll
encounter when you're looking at
the equation of a line will be slope
intercept form,
and that will work like this.
y equals mx plus b.
You've probably seen this before.
So, m represents the slope, b represents
the y intercept.
Okay, that's the point at which this line
intersects the y axis.
And y and x are, of course, the y
coordinate.
The corresponding y and x coordinates for
points that lie on this line.
Now, let's illustrate what we just went
over, again, with an example.
Lets say y equals 2x plus 6.
Now, if I ask you what the slope is,
you're going to tell me that the slope is
2.
Because this 2 corresponds to this m.
Okay?
And similarly, if I ask you what the y
intercept is.
You're going to tell me that it's 6,
because it corresponds to b.
More accurately, the y intercept in this
case is going to be 0 comma 6.
Now, let me talk a little bit more about
the slope.
So, slope is defined as the change in y
over change in x.
And another way of remembering that is by
remembering this phrase rise over run.
And again, I want to illustrate all these
concepts with the example from before.
And this time I'm going to graph this.
So, this is your y axis and this is your x
axis.
So, we know that the y intercept is 6.
So, I'm going to pick this point to be the
y intercept.
And I know that the slope is 2.
So, I'm going to go up two points for
every one point that I go over.
Or do the, and also do the opposite.
Go down two for
every one point that I moved to the left,
one unit I moved to the left.
And connecting these dots, gives me the
graph of this line.
Moving onto the exponential function.
The exponential function is denoted like
this with the letter e.
Sometimes you might see it written like
this.
Don't get confused, these are the same
things.
It's important to note that e is a number.
e is equal to 2.71828, etcetera, etcetera,
etcetera.
And so if you find yourself forgetting
this it might be useful
to remember e to the x as approximately
equal 2.72 raised to the x.
Now, if you want to check to make sure
you're doing this right.
e to the 3 will equal 20.085, and you can
use
that in Google or your calculator to check
that you're doing this the right way.
All the normal rules of exponents also
apply to the exponential function.
And what I mean by that let's say e to the
0.
Any number raised to the power to zero
will equal 1.
also, any number raised to a negative
exponent will be
one over that number raised to the
positive exponent.
And that's where I want to leave the
exponential function.
Please do note that the exponential
function is used very commonly in
the sciences.
And that's because it has some appealing
Mathematical properties that
allow scientists to model a behavior they
see in nature very, very well.
Moving on to the natural log you can write
the natural logarithm like this,
log base e of x or more commonly as ln of
x.
And the main idea that I want you to take
away with regard to this course is
that the natural log and the exponential
function are inverses of each other.
And what that means is that they undo each
other.
So, the natural log of e to the x will
just be x.
And some other like e, to the natural log
of x will also be x.
And this is important because when we're
doing certain statistical regressions,
we're going to have an expression that
looks like this, and
we're going to want to know.
We're going to just want to isolate what's
inside the natural log.
And so, we're going to raise this to the e
to get that middle part.
All the rules about logarithms also apply
to natural log.
And I'll illustrate a few of those here.
So, the log of 1 will always equal 0.
The log of 0 will always be undefined.
And you can't really take the natural log
of a negative number.
At least you won't that won't result in a
real solution.
So, that concludes this Math review and I
hope you found it useful.