[MUSIC]
Welcome back.
I'm Dr. Larry Chu.
Hi, and I'm Dr. Agnieszka Trzcinka.
Now in this segment, we're going to talk
about something that's a little
anxiety-producing for residents who are
new to cardiac anesthesia, and
that is setting up the room.
There's a lot different things we need to
do to set up the room.
We want to give you an overview of that.
Agnieszka, can you tell us a little bit
about what you're going to cover in
your lecture?
Of course.
So setting up cardiac OR, takes up more
time than preparation for other cases.
So make sure you give yourself extra time
to do so.
The things that we're going to focus on is
the setting up anesthesia machine,
airway equipment, all the proper managers,
infusion lines, supplies for
line placements, all the medications that
you will need for the case, as well
as trying to coordinate the equipment for
TEE examination, if it's needed.
Wonderful.
I can't wait to see your lecture.
Let's get started.
The following presentation outlines
information on basic cardiac OR
set-up as it is done at the Brigham and
Women's Hospital.
Please be aware that the set-up might be
different at your institution.
You should start in a step-wise fashion
making sure that you
have a working section.
Perform standard anesthesia machine
checkout, and have all necessary airway
equipment including a large 8.0 or 8.5
endotracheal tube.
The equipment in a cardiac OR
includes standard ASA monitors, plus the
following devices.
Triple transducer with pressure bag.
Reflex transducer corresponding to
arterial line,
yellow transducer corresponding to PA
catheter, and blue one to CVP monitoring.
Head of the bed set up includes
defibrillator pads, which are located in
the OR supply cabinet, defibrillator
3-lead EKG, and standard 5-lead EKG.
You may also place a jaw pad as a cushion
under patient's head.
Equipment in the pocket of the right pole
includes fibrillator and pacer.
Make sure that you test batteries for the
pacer.
And test fibrillator for
power to ensure that both devices will
work properly during the case.
Defibrillator is located on the right side
of the bed,
and is usually tested by the nursing
staff.
But please make sure that the cable is
connected to the defibrillator pads placed
on patient.
Cardiac anesthesia carts are different, so
familiarize yourself with the drawers.
Cardiac non-controlled medications are in
the top drawer and include most of
the resuscitation medications that may be
needed during the case.
You may have to obtain them from pharmacy
for the first case of the day.
On top of the cart, place the medications
that will be needed for
beginning stages of the case.
If possible, fill out the medication
request sheet.
And leave it at the pharmacy the night
before scheduled surgery, so
that the medications will be ready for
pick up, saving your time in the morning.
The requested medications may vary
depending on patients' past
medical history and planned surgery.
However, the usual induction syringes
include standard emergency
syringes of phenylephrine, ephedrine,
atropine and
succinylcholine, and additional syringes
for fentanyl, propofol or
etomidate, non-depolarizing neuromuscular
blocking agent,
esmolol, phenylephrine diluted to 40
mcg/mL concentration,
epinephrine diluted to 8 mcg/mL or 4 mcg/L
concentration, and
nitroglycerin diluted to 40 mcg/mL
concentration.
Also, confirm presence of heparin in your
cardiac kit, and
place it on the top of the cart as well.
Some extra medications that can be kept on
the side wing of the blue
cart include albumin, but only if the
attending has specified its use,
cardiac drips in pre-mixed bags of
phenylephrine 320 mcg/mL,
epinephrine 16 mcg/mL, and norepinephrine
32 mcg/mL,
aminocaproic acid or tranexamic acid,
again, only if your attending has
specified its use, insulin drip and
antibiotics which for cardiac cases
usually include vancomycin and cefazolin
administered based on patient's weight.
On the left pole, you can set up the fluid
warmer and four-channel Alaris pump.
You may organize your infusions in which
ever way makes sense to you.
Here, we have an example from the left, of
Amicar infusion, VIP line,
which is a vasoactive infusion port with
1L normosol on
microdrip with a gang of four, and
cefazolin.
On the right pole, you can set up your
bolus line,
with 1L normosol on half of walrus tubing
attached to gang of four.
Central line will be placed in patient
after induction.
You can set up a tray with all necessary
supplies that include four
triple-lumen catheter, miltilumen CVC kit,
mayo stand cover, one sterile half-sheet,
one set of gloves, gown,
probe cover for ultrasound, central line
dressing kit, and two sterile flushes.
Depending on the case,
you may be told that patient needs central
venous access via Cordis with a slic.
Cordis is an introducer sheath that can be
used for rapid volume delivery
during resuscitation or for subsequent
placement of a Swan-Ganz catheter.
Slic is a single lumen infusion catheter.
However, most often in clinical practice,
there is,
refers to triple-lumen catheter that locks
into the top of a Cordis.
Please discuss with the attending what
central line access is needed for
the case and set-up accordingly.
Thank you very much for watching and good
luck.
Wonderful lecture.
Learned a lot.
Great pictures, I love pictures.
I learn so much visually.
Now Agnieszka, one thing that I would love
to do though is to
try to place those pictures in a frame of
reference to the room itself.
Would you be willing to walk around the
room with me so
we can kind of see where everything goes?
Of course, let's get started.
All right, Agnieszka, so, I really would
love for you, you to show me in the same
order that you did your talk earlier where
things are located in the room.
Can we start that way?
Of course, let's get started.
So, as in the presentation, we're going to
start at the anesthesia workstation,
making sure that the anesthesia machine is
properly checked out for
the day, and that we have all of the
airway equipment nicely laid out.
And, ensuring that we have a large 8.0 or
8.5 endotracheal tube.
Perfect, what's next?
Of course, let's focus on the monitors.
So as we head in toward the bed, we have
the triple transducer,
we have the defibrillator 3-lead EKG,
standard ASA 5-lead EKG, as well as the
defibrillator pads.
On the right side of the bed, we have the
pacer, fibrillator, and defibrillator.
Make sure that the cable from the
defibrillator is connected to our
defibrillator pads before we get the case
started.
So, that's actually a really important
point because sometimes people forget
to connect it to the cable.
And of course, if you want to activate
that in an emergency,
you need to have it connected already.
That's right, that's [UNKNOWN].
Okay, what's next?
All right, let's focus on the anesthesia
cart, which is right here.
So keep in mind that the anesthesia, cart
in a cardiac room is quite different.
Remember that in our first drawer,
we have the non-controlled resuscitation
medications.
And then on the top of our cart, we have
all of the medications needed for
induction in beginning stages of the case.
Here in the bucket on the side, here, we
have some extra medications.
And just as we discussed in the PowerPoint
presentation,
discuss with the attendings which extra
medications you may
need before you check them out from the
pharmacy.
Now one thing that I'll note is that for
cardiac anesthesia, often,
your carts are different than the carts
for pediatrics or general anesthesia.
And so you may wish to look at the cart at
your institution and familiarize it
with yourself, especially when you're just
beginning cardiac anesthesia.
myself, I notice one thing that's missing
from your cart and that's protamine.
Mm-hm.
Is there a reason that you just don't have
it here available because so
it'd be convenient for dosing?
Simply because it's very important to
administer protamine
at exactly the right time during the
surgery,
making sure that you really converse with
the surgeon about when to give it.
And so for the safety factor at the
Brigham and
Women's Hospital, we do not keep it in our
anesthesia cart but rather,
we keep it all across the room in the
cardiac, OR, nursing staff room.
And when the time comes for the protamine,
administration, we ask for
the protamine to be brought to us.
Great.
And Dr. Weyden will have a great lecture
about protamine and heparin, and why it's
important for us to institute these safety
measures, later in the course.
Well, let's continue.
What's next?
Sure.
Let's go to the left side of our bed.
Here, we have the fluid warmers set up,
as well as the four-channel Alaris
infusion pump.
here, we also have the VIP which stands
for the vasoactive infusion port.
Every institution might be a little bit
different how we set this up.
At the Brigham, we set up on their micro
dripper connected to this gang of four.
However, at your institution, you may
connect this line and program your
Alaris pump to deliver a certain, rate of
the, infusion to the patient.
So, check with the attending before you
set this up.
Wonderful.
And, finally, what's, what's next?
All right.
So, we move on to the right side of the
bed.
And right here on the right pole, we
always have a set up for the bolus line.
And here we just have a regular tubing
with the gang of four, set up and
ready to go, for infusion to the patient
when the central line is placed.
Talking about central lines, do you have
all that equipment?
We certainly do.
We can move on over here.
And here we have a tray with all of the
unopened supplies needed for
the placement of the central line.
Please refer to the PowerPoint
presentation and
what exactly you may need, for the central
line placement.
Well, I see it's really nice to have all
your equipment organized in one place on
the Mayo stand, so that you can access it
quickly.
And more importantly, what I've noticed
from your set up, Agnieszka,
is that it's very standardized, so you
know, that you have everything you need.
You know where it is.
And, and how to get it quickly.
That's correct.
It helps to [UNKNOWN] take out the
equation when
perhaps things gets stressful when you're
taking care of a sick patient,
knowing exactly when things are in a room
and how things are set up.
Wonderful.
Yup.
Great.
That was a lot of fun.
I have a better sense now of where
everything is in the room, but
I do have a question for you.
Mm-hm.
What do you do when you don't have an hour
to set up a room?
What if a heart comes crash and
back for take back or, or you have an
emergent cardiac surgery,
tell me what are the essential things that
I need to do to get a room ready quickly.
For emergency cases, you will have to
focus on the basics,
making sure you have a working anesthesia
machine, proper airway equipment to
be able to intubate the patient, induction
medications and
vasopressors diluted properly to ensure
the induction's done safely.
You may also call for extra help to be
able to
bring extra equipment that is necessary
for emergent case.
Wonderful.
Well you know, I feel so much better about
setting up a room now.
I think, you know, to summarize what we
learned here.
We learned that setting up a room really
involves time whenever possible.
Get there early, it's better to get there
early and
get your room set up and be prepared.
and, and that involves getting your
airway, your drugs,
your infusions, your line, your
equipment's set up.
And that's really the process that, of
anticipating and planning your needs.
And if you're organized, and you have
everything set up in a regimented,
standardized fashion, which many
institutions do.
Mm-hm.
Then you're going to be able to make sure
you're always prepared.
And isn't it great to be prepared?
Indeed.
And, we hope this module's help prepare
you a little bit better for
your cardiac anesthesia rotation.
And we'll see you next time.
Thank you.
Bye.
[MUSIC]