[MUSIC]
>> Hi, I'm Dr Larry Chu.
>> Hi, I'm Dr Lauren Cornella.
>> And I'm Dr John Fox.
>> Welcome to this course on An
Introduction to Cardiac Anesthesia.
Now, the first thing I want to let you
know is that this is a priming course.
It's not meant to help you achieve
proficiency in cardiac anesthesia.
Because of course,
that's what you're going to learn when you
take your cardiac anesthesia rotation.
Now, what we hope is that this online
course can help be a primer or
an introduction to the field of cardiac
anesthesia,
that you can take before your cardiac
anesthesia rotation.
So that when you begin your cardiac
anesthesia rotation, you can hit
the ground running and that you have some
basic understanding of what you'll be
doing and what you'll be learning through
your time on cardiac anesthesia.
So Lauren, can you tell the students a
little bit about what they might expect to
learn in this course?
>> Sure.
I think this course will offer you a
really good introduction to the basics of
cardiac anesthesia.
I think there are a lot of things about
your cardiac anesthesia rotation that
are different from what you might have
done in previous rotations.
There's a lot of different pharmacology, a
lot of different physiology.
Different lines,
different monitors different machines that
you might not have had exposure to before.
So I think with this course,
you'll be given a primer to some of the
things you might see in the cardiac ORs,
some of the drugs that you might use, some
of the physiology and pharmacology.
And I think that you'll be given an
introduction, so that you'll feel
a little bit more comfortable on the first
day of your cardiac anesthesia rotation.
>> Wonderful.
So, John, tell me what are your thoughts
about what students can get out of
this course?
>> Well, Dr. Chu, in the years that I've
taught cardiac anesthesia, I've
found residents have been very, sometimes
apprehensive to start the rotation.
And that's, as Lauren has said,
because of a lot of new environment, new
monitors, new equipment.
New staff and
sometimes also because of the intensity of
what goes on in the cardiac room.
These patients are very ill and sometimes
they don't do well.
And that is something that people have to
sort of address to, or adjust.
additionally, one good thing that they
will learn in the cardiac
anesthesia rotation is the concept of
teamwork.
One person once told me that cardiac
anesthesia and
cardiac surgery is the ultimate team
sport.
There are a variety of individuals who are
involved in this,
including nursing, profusion, surgeons,
and the anesthesia team.
Additionally, you'll learn about
checklists.
And the years that I,
even before checklists became popular, we
were doing checklists in it.
And that's part of things that you'll
learn in addition to the other procedures.
Once you learn cardiac anesthesia, the
lessons you learn, and
the medications you learn, and the comfort
you get in dealing with ill patients,
you can take into the care of patients in
the other aspects of the operating room.
>> Well I think those are all great
points.
And our goal in this course is to help
prepare you for this great experience.
I think you know,
personally speaking, after I completed my
cardiac anesthesia rotation, I felt so
much more comfortable dealing with the
hypotensive patient, or patients with
cardiovascular disease, evaluating
cardiovascular functions in patients for
pre-operative the preoperative assessment
for patients undergoing surgery.
And so I, I agree.
I think there are so many lifelong lessons
that you'll take with you after you
complete cardiac anesthesia.
And it's really our honor to help start
you on that journey.
So, let's get started.
[MUSIC]