[MUSIC]
Welcome back.
I'm Doctor Larry Chu.
>> Hi and I'm Doctor Yneshya Tachinka.
>> Now, in this segment we're going to
talk about a typical
day in cardiac anesthesia.
And also talking about the flow of a case,
what you can expect from beginning to end.
For the perioperative care for the patient
undergoing cardiac surgery.
So, let's start off.
A typical day in cardiac anesthesia, it
actually starts the day
before when you get pre-operative
assessment information on your patient.
Can you tell us really briefly about what
to expect there?
>> Of course.
So, you will meet your patient the night
before the surgery.
When you will obtain the past medical
history,
review any work up that might have been
obtained, and get the consent form.
Now, this process can be quite involved
depending on the complexity of the case.
So make sure you allow yourself up to at
least an hour to complete this process.
And then you call your attending and
fellow to discuss the plan for
the next day,.
Which would include induction, conulation
plan, graft plan, and
possible need for TE.
>> And of course Doctor Renton Weidman's
done a great
module on preoperative assessment and
consent of the cardiac patient.
And that's in this course, and you'll get
that later.
So watch out for that episode later.
So we, we've done our, our prep work.
Now it's the day the beginning of the day,
and we need to get our room ready, setting
up for our case.
Tell me a little bit about that process.
When do you arrive?
What's involved?
>> Setting up the cardiac OR requires more
time and preparation for
other cases, so make sure you allow
yourself extra time to do so.
On average, arrive about an hour before
you are scheduled to see a patient.
Just to make sure you get your proper
medications, and set up the OR.
>> Excellent advice and again, I'll note
we have a great module on room setup.
So, watch out for later, too.
Many more details to follow.
The goal of this segment really, is to
give you an overview of the day.
So now, keeping going on the day.
Let's talk a little bit about meeting your
patient, and of course,
bringing back to the room for induction.
>> You will meet your patient in a pre-op
area where you will place the large
pour IV and arterial line.
Then you will ensure that the surgical and
nursing staff are available before you
bring the patient back to the operating
room.
>> Okay, we're in the OR.
We're ready to induce.
Can we go and just push the Propofol now?
>> Not quite yet.
We have to make sure that all the proper
monitors are placed on the patient.
Make sure that the plan that you discussed
with the attending is still in effect.
And then you will induce the patient,
taking into consideration particular
proper physiology.
And any aspects that might have been
discussed the night before.
>> Okay, perfect.
Now you mentioned some lines, an arterial
line,
an IV are there any other lines that we
may need for a cardiac anesthesia case?
>> So, depending on the particular
institution,
you may either place the arterial line in
the pre-op area or in the operating room.
At the Brigham Women's Hospital, we place
essential lines when we
bring the patient into the room and after
the induction.
But you can double-check regarding the
details regarding that
with your attending.
>> Okay, wonderful.
Any other lines that you need to place?
P-A catheters, continuous cardiac output
monitors, all the fancy stuff?
I imagine that might be dependent on your
patient.
>> Indeed, that's the case.
So, you may have to place the PA catheter,
but
again that's going to be dependent on the
particular surgery.
And particular part of the physiology that
you're dealing.
>> Okay.
So, let's say that you
did all the lines according to what you
discussed with your attending.
At this point in the case you know, this
is where, you know,
the you may want to do a transesophageal
echocardiography examination.
Tell me a little bit about that.
Do you do it in everybody?
Are there are certain patients you don't
want to do it in?
You know, what can the resident expect to
get out of this part of the case?
>> So the T-exam will be obtained on some
of
the patients depending on the type of
physiology and the surgical plan.
The T-exam is usually done by either the
attending or
the cardiac anesthesia fellow.
And things that they're looking for are
any particular valvular abnormalities and
LB function before we start the operation.
>> Okay, wonderful.
Now, can residents expect to achieve
competency?
Complete competency, in transesophageal
cardiography during their
initial cardiac anesthesial rotation?
>> Depending on the institution, and the
residency program,
there may be opportunities for the
residents to learn some of the TE skills.
However, I do not think there's enough
time to become completely competent in
this particular study.
>> Well that's what fellowship is for,
right?
>> Indeed.
>> [LAUGH] Okay, well now,
to do this surgery and access the heart,
we have to do a sternotomy.
Tell me a little about what are the
considerations to think about for
the resident at this point of the case,
when they're opening up the chest.
>> Sternotomy, main valve marked
humodynamic changes.
Depending on the particular institution,
you will administer a large dose opioid.
At the Brigham women's hospital, we
administer a large dose of fentanyl.
However, particular use of a drug and
a dose will have to be discussed with your
attending.
>> Great.
Now, let me ask you a question.
Are there any special considerations for
patients who are coming back for
repeat heart surgery in terms of this part
of the case, this sternotomy?
>> Patients who have had previous
sternotomy,
have increased risk of scarring that may
form between the heart and the sternum.
In those cases, you should have blood
products available in the room and
ready for immediate transfusion if needed
in a case of bleeding.
>> That's very important information.
I'm glad you mentioned it.
Let's talk a little bit about the next
phase, which is cardio pulmonary bypass.
And don't worry.
I know you're worried out there.
It's a complicated subject.
We have a great lecture coming in, in this
course on cardiopulmonary bypass.
But Anyeshka, can you please just tell me
the basic considerations that
residents should be aware of at this
point?
When we're preparing to put the patient
onto the cardiopulmonary bypass machine?
>> Of course.
Prior to going to bypass, there are a
couple of steps that you need to consider.
One is administration of Heparin.
The timing of the administration of
Heparin will have to be
discussed with the surgical team.
To make sure that we do not impede with
too much bleeding in the surgical field.
The dose of the Heparin will have to be
discussed with your attending and
the perfusionist team.
Cannulation will be done by the surgical
team.
And you'll have to pay a special attention
to make sure that the blood
pressure is not too markedly increased.
The goal of blood pressure at this stage
will have to be discussed between
surgical team and your attending, as well.
>> Wonderful.
So, now we have everything we need to get
the patient over on
cardiopulmonary bypass.
The patient is now in cardiopulmonary
bypass,
the surgeons are ready to do their
operation.
I think this would be a perfect time to go
and get a cup of coffee.
>> Not quite yet, Dr. Chu.
>> Oh.
>> We shall stay in the room and
make sure that we pay attention to the
patient and to the surgical field.
First, you're going to have to talk to the
perfusionist and make sure that
the patient is properly anesthetized
during this stage of the surgery.
Also, you will have to take a look and
make sure that the surgery is
going well to anticipate any possible
complications coming off of bypass.
Also, Society of Cardiovascular
Anesthesiologist recommends,
that a member of the anesthesiology team
stays in the operating room at all times.
>> Well, you know, I was being a little
facetious.
Of course anesthesia, we're very
important.
We need to be there at all times.
But now that the operation's over, okay.
We can now begin preparations to wean the
patient off of cardiopulmonary bypass.
In order to get their own heart working so
we can get them out of the operating, tell
me, operating room.
Tell me a little bit about what that
involves.
>> Of course.
There are certain things that you have to
consider before taking the patient off of
bypass in a safe fashion.
These are, in general, making sure that a
patient has a normal temperature.
That the heart's rhythm and
rate are within normal limits, and assess
the need for possible pacing.
You have to make sure to remember to
ventilate a patient at this time.
Double check that the labs are within
normal limits in terms of
the electrolytes and hematocrit level.
And also, you have to consider if you need
any ionotrope assistance in order to
get the patient off of bypass at this
time.
>> Wonderful.
So, let, let's go ahead, we're, we're
ready, we're going to come off bypass.
Now, of course a couple more steps that
we're not going to go into detail now
about, but you have to decanulate or
remove the canulas.
You have to reverse the effects of your
anti-coagulation and
then it's closing time, right?
Now should we just expect that we can
extubate the patient on
the table,we're going to go get a cup of
coffee, and send the patient home?
>> No time for coffee just yet.
In our institution, we transfer the
patient up to the ICU intubated.
And you have to make sure that you take
with you all of
their resuscitation medications that you
may need.
To make sure that their trip to the ICU is
a safe one.
>> Wonderful.
So we're in the ICU, we dropped the
patient off,
now I can get my cup of coffee.
>> Not quite yet.
We have to make sure that the ICU team
feels comfortable taking care of
our patient during post-operative period.
This requires the interdisciplinary sign
out, including the anesthesia and
surgical teams.
Making sure that we give information about
the patient's past medical history,
a brief overview of the operative course.
As well as any medications that the
patient is currently on.
>> Okay, wonderful.
Now, all you need, I'm going to get my
caffeine fix, and
we've sent our patient off, and it's a
wonderful day.
>> [LAUGH] It has been a wonderful day,
but
we're always curious to see how the
patients are doing the day after.
And so, you should remember to take a look
at how the patient is
doing the day after the surgery.
And make sure that you
pay attention to any complications that
might have occurred.
>> Wonderful.
Well, I think this has been a great
segment.
I think you've learned a lot.
Just to recap what we learned this
segment.
We talked about how your day starts the
day before with your
preoperative assessment.
To make sure you call your attending the
night before to come up with a plan.
To on the day of the surgery to arrive
early, acc, allow for
about an hour of time to set up your room.
And then, of course, going through the
flow of a case.
From meeting your patient in a
pre-operative area
until dropping them off at the ICU.
To pay attention to all those different
steps and more importantly for
you as a resident, all those opportunities
for learning.
So, there's a lot more to share with you
in this course, and
we look forward to seeing you next time.
Bye!
>> Bye, good luck.
[MUSIC]