[MUSIC]
>> Hi, I'm Dr Larry Chu.
>> Hi, I'm Dr Lauren Cornella.
>> And I'm Dr John Fox.
>> Well, in this segment, it's really our
chance to say goodbye to you,
as sad as that is.
I've had a fantastic time doing this
course.
I know.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
>> Well, we know this course has provided
a very good introduction to
the cardiac anesthesia pod.
I think that some last tips of advice
maybe would be to take everything you
can from this rotation.
I think you're going to learn a ton.
I think you're going to really take care
of patients really well.
And you're going to learn a lot of
techniques and tips and
knowledge that's going to take you even in
your non-cardiac OR rotations.
I think something you're going to find
across the board about your rotation is
that everyone will be fair and happy to
teach you.
Cardiac, anesthesia, tendings, fellows are
really looking forward to each you.
There's so much to learn and so I think
you're going to learn a lot.
I think you'll also find that everyone
else in the room will be
really receptive to teaching you as well.
I know that the [UNKNOWN] have really
tought me a lot,
the nurses know a lot of information, and
so
really try to get the most you can from
every single day and every single case.
And on behalf of everyone, we wish you
well.
We know you're going to love it.
>> Wonderful.
Well, again it's been a blast.
I can't wait to do this again,
maybe on a different a cardiac anesthesia
course in the future to come.
Hopefully.
And we'll see you later.
Have fun in cardiac anesthesia rotation.
[MUSIC]