[MUSIC]
>> Welcome back, I'm Doctor Larry Chu.
>> Hi, I'm Doctor Lauren Cornella
>> Now, in this segment,
we're going to talk about a topic that can
be confusing for
residents but, of course, we have a great
teacher here, Lauren, to explain it to us.
And it's cardiopulmonary bypass.
Of course, it's one of the very unique
things to cardiac anesthesia.
And we're not going to be able to make you
an expert on cardiopulmonary bypass.
That's not the goal of this module.
We want to give you an overview of the
process.
Lauren, what can the learners expect to
learn here?
Well, we'll be splitting this module into
two parts.
Part one is going to discuss going onto
bypass, and
I'll just tell you briefly some of the
major steps that you're going to see in
the operating room to get our patient onto
cardiopulmonary bypass, and then,
in part two of the module I'll go over the
weaning process.
How do we wean the patient off of
cardiopulmonary bypass?
I'll go some of, over some of the major
steps.
Now, you'll see some variations to these
steps in some cases, but
in the majority of cases, the steps are
going to be almost the same in every case.
So, if you can get a good introduction to
what we're calling CPB light, then you'll
be able to modify your knowledge when you
see it in specific cases.
One of the most central parts of cardiac
anesthesia is the process of
cardiopulmonary bypass.
So, in order for us to manage going on to
bypass and
going off of bypass, we need to have a
good understanding of it.
And you'll get a good basic understanding
from this module.
>> Great.
Well I'm super excited.
Let's get started.
>> Hi, this is Dr. Lauren Cornella.
We're going to be discussing the basics of
cardiopulmonary bypass.
I've split this tutorial into two parts.
In part one,
we're going to be discussing the basic
steps to go onto cardiopulmonary bypass.
And then in our next module, part two,
we'll be discussing how to wean our
patient from cardiopulmonary bypass.
Going on to bypass usually follows five
main steps.
Now, in each case, these steps might not
be exactly the same.
But by learning the concepts, you can be
able to follow your specific case and
know what's going on.
So briefly, let's go over the five steps
that are involved in
getting your patient on to cardiopulmonary
bypass.
The first step is to establish
anticoagulation.
The next step is that the surgeons are
going to cannulate somewhere on
the arterial tree.
Now usually this is the ascending aorta,
but it can also be the right axillary
artery or the femoral artery.
Then, the surgeons are going to do venous
cannulation where they put
a cannula in one of the venous structures.
Usually this is the right atrium but
sometimes the surgeons can choose to do
what's called bicable cannulation where
they put a cannula in both the superior
vena cava and the inferior vena cava.
Or they can do what's called percutaneous
femoral venous canulation in which they
put a long cannula into the femoral vein
which extends all the way up into the SVC.
Then we're going to actually put the
patient onto cardiopulmonary bypass and
I'm going to explain how we do that and
then,
if the surgery requires the heart to be
still,
we're going to have to arrest the heart,
which means stop it from beating.
And we'll go into how we do that, this as
well.
Then, the surgeons will begin operating on
the heart.
Let's delve into this deeper.
So, this picture is going to help us
visualize the steps for
going on to bypass.
Let's orient you to the picture a little
bit.
Follow my orange dot, this structure here
is the right atrium.
This structure here is the right
ventricle.
This structure here is the left atrium.
And this structure here is the left
ventricle.
Up here, on the right side of the heart,
we have the SVC and we have the IVC which
empty into the right atrium.
On the left side of the heart, coming out
the ascending aorta,
right here, are the two coronary arteries,
the right coronary artery and the left
main coronary artery.
Further down the arterial tree,
the first takeoff of the great vessels is
the innominate artery here.
And that splits into the right common
carotid and right axillary artery.
Further down the aortic arch,
we have the left common carotid artery and
the left subclavian artery.
Here we have the descending aorta which
then will
split eventually into the femoral
arteries.
[SOUND] Now that we're oriented to our
picture,
let's begin with the steps to getting your
patient onto cardiopulmonary bypass.
The first step for getting your patient
safely out to cardiopulmonary bypass is to
establish anticoagulation.
Anticoagulating the patient is extremely
important to prevent
clotting inside the cardiopulmonary bypass
machine.
Now, in the majority of cases, the
anticoagulant of choice will be Heparin,
but in some instances you do choose a
different anticoagulant, so
make sure you check with your attending,
and the perfusionist in each case.
Heparinization actually begins with
drawing a baseline ACT,
which is an activated clotting time.
You draw this in a blood sample and give
it to the perfusionist.
The perfusionist will then calculate the
appropriate dose of
heparin for the patient.
Don't heparinize the patient until the
surgeon specifically asks for it.
At the appropriate time the surgeon will
ask for
heparin to be given to the patient.
Approximately three minutes after you
would administer the heparin, you should
draw a post Heparin ACT to ensure that the
patient is adequately anticoagulated.
After the patient is effectively
anticoagulated the surgeons will
begin to cannulate the patient for
cardiopulmonary bypass.
In almost all instances the side to be
cannulated first is the arterial side.
And I've drawn this in red so
that we remember that this is the arterial
cannula and it goes on the arterial tree.
The most common place to cannulate
arterially is the ascending aorta.
It is off,
also possible to cannulate the right
axillary artery or the femoral artery.
And these are done in some instances, so
you should discuss with your attending
what the cannulation plan will be.
But in the vast majority of cases the
ascending aorta is the site of
arterial cannulation.
In some instances, the surgeons will ask
for an epi-aortic ultrasound probe so
that they could scan the ascending aorta
for any plaque or calcification.
They will then put sutures on the
ascending aorta, and
they will put a cannula in the ascending
aorta, and I'll draw that here, like this.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
They'll then need to de-air this cannula,
fill it completely with the patient's
blood, and
then they'll bring the arterial line up
from the cardiopulmonary bypass machine.
When both sides are properly deaired,
they will attach the arterial line to the
arterial cannula.
They'll then test this line, which means
that the profusionist will infuse a little
bit of crystalloid through this line to
make sure that it's patent and
to make sure that the pressure required to
infuse that crystaloid is normal.
Then the arterial cannulation is complete.
The third step is venous cannulation,
in which the surgeons need to place a
cannula on the right side of the heart
in order to drain the venous blood to the
cardiopulmonary bypass machine.
Now, in the vast majority of cases the
venous cannulation of choice will
be a cannula directly into the right
atrium.
There are other options though.
If the surgeon needs a bloodless right
atrium for the surgery, for instance,
in a tricuspid valve replacement or repair
of an interatrial septal defect.
The surgeons will then do by bicaval
cannulation, which means putting
a cannula in the SVC and the IVC and
connecting those two cannulas together.
There is a third option for venous
cannulation, which is percutaneous femoral
venous cannulation in which the surgeons
put a cannula into the femoral vein.
And this cannula is a long cannula that
extends all the way from the femoral vein
all the way up into the SVC.
And that's how it drains the venous blood.
But since we're doing an intro, we're
going to talk about the cannulation for
the most comos, common venous cannulation,
which is in the right atrium.
After we've cannulated the aorta,
the surgeons will turn their attention to
the right atrial cannula.
They'll put some sutures on the right
atrium, and then, they'll put
a cannula directly into the right atrium,
and that's indicated by this blue.
It's important to realize that there will
be a cross clamp already on
this right arterial cannula.
It's there before they cannulated the
right atrium and
it'll stay there until we decide to go on
bypass.
But, now that the surgeons have canulated
the right atrium, this venous cannula
is attached to a venous line which goes to
the cardiopulmonary bypass machine.
>> The fourth step is to begin
cardiopulmonary bypass which means that we
are going to drain all of the venous blood
out of the venous cannula,
put it into the cardiopulmonary bypass
machine where it will get oxygenated,
the carbon dioxide will be removed.
The blood will be heated or cooled
depending on what's appropriate.
The blood will get filtered and
then it will get returned to the arterial
cannula into the ascending aorta.
This doesn't happen automatically though.
Someone has to decide to go on bypass,
usually the surgeon.
In order to get on bypass, we have to
remove this clamp on the venous line.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That means that the blood will start to
drain out of the right atrium,
into the cardiopulmonary bypass machine.
The perfusionist will start cycling the
machine.
And this arterial blood
will then get transfused in the arterial
cannula back to the patient.
Now we're on full cardiopulmonary bypass.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The fifth and final step is to arrest the
heart if the surgeons need to
operate on a still heart, which most cases
do require.
In order to do this, the surgeon will
place an antegrade
cardioplegia cannula here, in the aortic
root.
If they're planning on doing retrograde
cardioplegia, that goes here,
in the coronary sinus.
Not all cases require retrograde
cardioplegia, so
talk to your attending for specifics.
But if the plan is for
retrograde cardioplegia, that goes there
in the coronary sinus.
Now we are not quite ready to give
cardioplegia.
We're missing one important thing, that's
the aortic cross-clamp.
We're currently on full cardiopulmonary
bypass, but
the heart is still moving because arterial
blood is still being
delivered into the ascending aorta here
and going down the coronary arteries.
If blood goes down the coronary arteries,
the heart beats.
That's just what it does.
But in order to give cardioplegia down the
coronary arteries and
stop that cardioplegia from being washed
out by this arterial blood supply,
we need to put an aorta cross cramp on the
ascending aorta.
The aorta cross cramp would then go here,
in between the arterial cannula, which is
here, and
the antegrade retrocardio, the antegrade
cardioplega which is here.
So, in effect.
The aortic cross clamp separates the
coronary circulation, where cardioplegia
is going to go here and the systemic
circulation
which is all of the oxygenated blood from
the cardiopulmonary bypass machine.
Again, this is important and sometimes
really confusing.
The aortic cross clamp is put on so that
those two circulations are separated.
And, so that the systemic profusion from
the arterial cannula here,
doesn't wash out our cardioplegia.
So, what happens is the surgeon puts on
the aortic cross clamp and
then administers antegrade and retrograde
cardioplegia, if that's their plan.
Then they begin their surgical operation.
Come back for part twp and
we'll discuss how to wean the patient from
cardiopulmonary bypass.
Hi, this is Dr Lauren Cornella.
Welcome to Part two of our cardiopulmonary
bypass tutorial.
In this part, we're going to discuss how
to come off of bypass.
Coming off of bypass involves six major
steps,
with a few smaller steps in between.
The first major step is reperfusion of the
myocardium.
And we're going to talk about all of these
steps in further detail in
just a little bit.
This firs step, reprofusion of the
myocardium is when we remove
the aortic cross clamp, the arterial blood
will go down the coronary arteries and
the heart will restart.
Then we need to prepare the heart to
perform the cardiac output.
By this I mean that we need to ensure that
the heart has adequate rate,
rhythm, contractility, after load,
normal electrolytes, and normal
temperature, and we
have to be ventilating in, before we can
begin to come off cardiopulmonary bypass.
When everyone has decided that it's time
to actually ween from
cardiopulmonary bypass, we clamp the
venous line.
This means that we're going to stop
removing the venous blood from the right
atrium, and that venous blood is going to
remain in the heart.
Thus, the heart is going to take over the
cardiac output from the bypass machine,
and we're going to regain our pulsatile
blood pressure.
Once we're off bypass, and we're happy
with our cardiac rate,
rhythm, contractility, afterload, blood
pressure, and
our surgical repair, the surgeons will ask
for a Protamine test dose.
We'll test dose the Protamine to make sure
that
the patient doesn't have any reaction.
If the Protamine test does is safe,
we'll transfuse the rest of the residual
volume that's in the arterial cannula and
then we'll decannulate both the venous
side and the arterial side.
During or after decannulation, we'll
reverse the anticoagulation with
first 50% of the Protamine dose and then
100% of the Protamine dose.
We're going to talk about all of these
steps in further detail so let's tie them.
So, let's recap where we were at the end
of part one of this module.
Our patient was on full cardiopulmonary
bypass.
The surgeons had applied the aortic cross
clamp, and
had administered antergrade and retrograde
cardioplegia.
This made the heart stop.
Then they had begun their surgical
procedure.
That's where we are right now.
And now we're going to discuss how to wean
our patient from cardiopulmonary bypass.
In case you missed part one, let me orient
you to this picture,
which I should say is definitely not
anatomically correct,
just a representation of what it, the
patient actually looks like.
Here is the SVC.
Here is our venous cannula, which is
draining the venous blood.
Here's the patient's IVC here.
This is the patient's right atrium, here's
the right ventricle,
this is the left atrium, and this is the
left ventricle.
On the arterial side, here are the two
coronary arteries right here, and
right here, this green dot here was
antegrade cardioplegia and this green here
is retrograde cardioplegia.
This purple line was our aortic
cross-clamp, which I'm just going to
thicken up right here.
Here, on the arterial tree, is our aortic
cannula and that's where
the oxygenated blood is coming from the
cardiopulmonary bypass machine.
And then we have the arteries of the
aortic arch.
Here's the right axillary artery, the
right common carotid artery,
the innominate artery, the left common
carotid and the left subclavian.
Now that we're oriented to our picture
again, let's be,
begin to discuss how we wean the patient
from cardiopulmonary bypass.
The first step to coming off
cardiopulmonary bypass is to
reperfuse the patient's myocardium.
Now this heart has been receiving
cardioplegia and is still right now.
So, we can't even think about coming off
cardiopulmonary bypass until the heart
begins to beat again.
How do we do that?
Well, we discussed earlier in part one of
the tutorial that
the purpose of the aortic cross clamp is
to
separate the coronary circulation from the
systemic circulation, so that
the systemic circulation from the aortic
cannula doesn't wash out the cardioplegia.
But here that's exactly what we want to
happen.
We want to wash out the cardioplegia and
we want the heart to restart again.
So, in order to do this, we remove the
aortic cross clamp from the aorta,
and the surgeons take out their
cardioplegia cannulus.
This means that this warm,
oxygenated blood from the arterial cannula
is now going to go down the coronary
arteries, wash out all the cardioplegia
and the heart is going to restart.
Now that the heart has reprofused and
starts to beat, we need to prepare the
heart to perform the cardiac output.
That means that we're going to take
eventually,
we're going to take the blood from the
cardiopulmonary bypass machine and
we're going to allow the patient's heart
to generate the cardiac output.
But, this doesn't happen instantly.
We almost have to perform a checklist in
our head of all the conditions that
have to be met before we can definitively
wean from bypass.
By that I mean, we have to make sure the
patient has good rate.
You can't come off cardiopulmonary bypass
if the patient's rate is 29.
So if the rate is not adequate,
you may need to pace the patient with a
temporary pacer.
You need to make sure that the patient has
a good rhythm.
Ideally, it would be in sinus rhythm, but
if you need to pace or
if you need to defibrillate the heart, we
need to get the patient back into
an acceptable rhythm to perform the
cardiac output.
You also need to assess the contractility.
The best way of doing this is to look over
the drapes and
to look at the heart directly.
If you have a trans-esophageal echo,
you can also look on the echo to assess
contractility.
We have to make sure that we had adequate
afterload.
Now, the best way to assess this is to ask
the profusionist if they've been
running any vasopressors recently.
We also need to make sure that our
important electrolytes are normal,
specifically potassium, pH and calcium.
Because, large abnormalities of these
electrolytes will
prevent us from successfully getting off
cardiopulmonary bypass.
The patient also has to be warm.
That's another part of the checklist.
And the last thing we have to do before we
come off bypass is start to ventilate.
Remember, we're going to start putting
blood back into the cardiac chambers.
That blood is going to go to the lungs,
and in order for
us to successfully get off cardiopulmonary
bypass we have to oxygenate that blood and
remove the carbon dioxide.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If we've met all of those conditions,
we're ready to wean from cardiopulmonary
bypass.
What is weaning from bypass really mean?
Well, it means that instead of draining
the blood out of the right atrium and
putting it in the cardiopulmonary bypass
machine,
we're going to keep the blood in the right
atrium and put it inside the heart.
So the way we do this is we take a cross
clamp and
we cross clamp this venous cannula.
If we put a cross clamp across the venous
cannula,
we'll be no longer draining venous blood
out of their atrium.
And the blood that is coming from the SVC
and the from the IVC,
will then remain in the heart, and start
going through the heart,
through the lungs and out the ascending
aorta.
So in essence, weaning from
cardiopulmonary bypass occurs because we
clamp the venous line, and we deliver that
venous blood
back to the heart, and the heart performs
the cardiac output.
Once the venous cannula is completely
clamped, we are off bypass.
Once we're off bypass, and if the heart
looks good, the heart is
adequately contributing to the cardiac
output, oxygenation looks good,
ventilation looks good, we're happy with
the cardiac contractility.
We're happy with the blood pressure, and
we're happy with our surgical repair
whether we did a valve replacement,
a valve repair, then it's time to give a
protamine test dose.
So, in essence, once you're off bypass and
you're sure that you're going to
stay off bypass because things look good,
it's time to test dose with Protamine.
Usually this is done with a 10mg dose of
Protamine to check for a reaction.
But this could be very
institution-specific, so
please check with your attending and the
perfusionists and the surgeons for
exactly how they like to test dose the
Protamine.
Once the test dose of Protamine has been
safely given to the patient,
we no longer need the venous cannula.
So, the surgeons will decannulate the
venous side.
Before we can decannuate the arterial side
though, it's important to
remember that there's still blood in the
cardiopulmonary bypass machine,
in this cannula, all the way up until it
enters the patient.
And sometimes, this can be from 800 to
1000 ccs of blood.
So before we can decannulate the arterial
cannula,
we need to transfuse all of this residual
volume to the patient.
Some surgeons like to do this in the
arterial cannula, some surgeons actually
decannulate the arterial side and insert
that cannula into the right atrium.
Check with your attending what your
institution likes to do.
But the bottom line is that we need to
transfuse this residual volume to
the patient before we can decannulate
completely the arterial side.
Once we've transfused that residual volume
then we can decannulate the arterial side.
So, here I am representing that on our
diagram.
So now, we have no further cannulas in the
patient.
We've transfused all of our residual
volume.
And the patient is completely
decannulated.
Now, we were previously only at our
Protamine test dose.
Usually, if after three minutes the
patient is stable,
the surgeon will tell you to continue with
the Protamine.
At our institution we continue to 50% of
the total Protamine dose,
then recheck with our surgeons.
If the surgeons are happy, they will tell
us to continue to full dose Protamine.
Again, this is very important and very
institution-specific, so
please check with your attending, your
surgeons, and
your perfusionists for how this is
normally done at your institution.
Excellent communication regarding both
heparinization and Protamine
is absolutely essential as mistakes in
these drugs can be catastrophic.
So make sure you know very clearly what
your surgeons, and what your perfusionist,
and what your attending wants before you
do any of these,
do anything with these drugs.
Once you're sure exactly what the surgeon
and
the profusionist would like you to do with
the Protamine,
you can continue to reverse the
anticoagulation with full dose Protamine.
After administering the full dose of
Protamine, in approximately three minutes,
you should obtain another ACT, activated
clotting time, and
give this to the profusionist.
The perfusionist will then run the sample
to make sure that you have
accurately reversed all of the heparin.
After the anticoagulation is completely
reversed,
you're done with that run of
cardiopulmonary bypass.
Congratulations, you've made it.
Thanks so much for watching this tutorial.
And we'll see you in the next module.
>> Great.
Well, what I'm going to do now is try to
summarize what we learned in this segment.
It's a little bit complicated but I'm
going to do my best.
Now, in part one, un Lauren explained the
steps involved in going onto bypass.
And of course, we first have to establish
adequate anticoagulation by administering
medications at your, your institution will
have individual policies for that.
But also, to establish that you've
achieved
effective therapeutic anticoagulation
before you continue further with
the steps with placing a patient on
cardiopulmonary bypass.
[SOUND] We also have to then place an
arterial catheter.
In this case, Lauren using a example of
the ascending aorta, for
placement of the arterial catheter.
But that could be different with different
patients.
And then, placing the venous cannula, in
the right atrium, in this case.
But again, it could be different for
different patients.
And finally, the transition to
cardiopulmonary bypass involves removing
the cross clamp from the venous cannula so
the patient can be put on to the
cardiopulmonary bypass machine.
Now, in part two, Lauren explained how we
wean patients off of cardiopulmonary
bypass so that the patient can then retake
over, generation of
cardiac output with their own heart, and
to do that, the first thing we have to do
is to remove the cross clamp from the
aorta so that we can reperfuse the heart.
Once the heart is reperfused,
that's the time when we really need to
assess cardiac function to make sure that
the heart can be able to generate adequate
cardiac output.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Once we
take the patient off of the
cardiopulmonary bypass machine.
And then, of course, we have to place the
clamp on the venous cannula, so
that the heart can begin to fill, and
take the cardiac output from the
cardiopulmonary bypass machine.
And then, once the heart is beating and
generating adequate cardiac output, that's
the time now we can decannulate.
We can take those cannulas out of our two
venous sites.
And then, once that's completely
established and done and we're not on
the machine anymore, of course, then we
can reverse the anticoagulation.
Again.
Each institution that you're attending
will have, methods for doing that.
So, very complex topic, but
I think Lauren, you did an amazing job at
actually making it understandable.
And again this is just an introduction.
>> Mm-hm.
>> An over view to this process and
I think, you know, you're going to be able
to learn much more on your cardiac
anesthesia rotation, and so we look
forward to seeing you next time.
[MUSIC]