[MUSIC]
[MUSIC].
Hi, I'm doctor, Larry Chu.
>> Hi, I'm doctor, Lauren Cornella.
>> And I'm doctor, John Fox.
>> Now in this segment,
we're going to talk about an overview of
the field of cardiac anesthesiology.
Now what I'd like to do is to have both
Lauren and John have a little discussion.
I want you to tell me a little bit about,
the overview of cardiac anesthesiology.
What does, what is the practice of cardiac
anesthesia,
what do cardiac anesthesiologist do?
Tell me a little bit about why you guys
got into the field.
And, of course, I also want to know a
little bit about,
the future of the specialty.
>> Well, Lauren, Doctor Chu, I got into
the specialty because it was fun.
I was able to, take care of really
critically ill patients.
I was able to learn and study the
physiology, the cardiovascular physiology.
And ultimately, I was able to participate
in
operations where the patients got better.
Where there was, indeed, a cure, if you
will.
Like aortic stenosis, mitral stenosis.
Once you operated on that and fixed the
valve, the patients did a lot better.
It followed, it, my personality.
That was what I had, what I found the best
of it, of, of cardiac anesthesiology.
additionally, it gave me the confidence to
take care of
any ill patient throughout the operating
suite.
Once you've done a cardiac anesthesia
rotation, and
you've learned about the medications, the
vasoactive and vasodilator drugs.
That you could translate to any other
patient for any other procedure.
And that, to me, was, was, was great.
The other thing I enjoy about the cardiac
anesthesia area
is the teamwork that's involved.
You get really close with the individuals
that are there.
And understand what, what, what happens,
how you can take care of individuals.
It's really, as I said, I found it really
fun.
>> I went into cardiac anesthesia for
many of the same reasons that John did,
that you did.
I thought, what attracted me was the
ability to
take care of really sick patients.
I wanted to be very comfortable taking
care of some of the sickest patients in
the operating room.
And I wanted to be comfortable with a lot
of different hemodynamic drugs.
I love the monitors that we use in cardiac
anesthesia.
And so, I saw it not only as a cardiac
anesthesia fellowship, but
maybe a fellowship in just taking care of
some of our sickest patients
in the operating room, and I knew that I
would translate some of
those skills to my practice in the
non-cardiac ORs.
I also saw how much trans-esophageal echo
was such a big part
of the cardiac anesthesia specialty, and
I thought that it was absolutely just a
really important skill to learn.
I saw the cardiac anesthesiologists that I
was working with making decisions about
the hemodynamic status of the patient,
discussing the surgical aspects of
the valve replacement or whatever we were
doing with the surgeons.
And I saw that transesophageal echo was
being used so
much more in the non-cardiac ORs to answer
really different, difficult inter
operative questions that I wanted to
become an expert in transesophageal echo.
So I thought that that was really an
important aspect, and,
I was excited to learn more about that.
>> And what Lauren is pointing out is the
actual teamwork approach that we end up
doing, in, in, as a cardiac
anesthesiologist.
It becomes, and I will add parenthetically
that when I started in
cardiac anesthesiology there was no
transesophageal echo.
Innovations come really quickly in the
cardiac anesthesia realm,
brought on by the surgeons, brought on by
the cardio, cardiologists, and
the other cardiovascular specialists who
we have the pleasure of working with.
And I know for a fact that there are
multiple innovations that
are happening right now in, in cardiac
anesthesia.
And I know Lauren and
I spent a lot of time in the
electrophysiology lab and in the cath lab.
I think that speak to Doctor Chu's
question of where we
think the specialty is going.
I think that, like John says, the
innovations in cardiac anesthesia,
cardiology, cardiac surgery, are rapidly
becoming more and more complex and we,
as cardiac anesthesiologists, are at the
center of a lot of those procedures.
So, just as we're maintaining our presence
in the cardiac anesthesia ORs.
We're in the electrophysiology lab.
We're in the cath lab.
We're up in the cardiac surgery ICUs, and
so
I think our role is expanding very rapidly
in future in
terms of kind of the perioperative care of
the cardiac patients.
>> Absolutely.
>> And we are really an integral part of
that, and so
I'm really excited to see that develop in,
you know, 5, 10, 15 years.
>> And we're taking the lessons we've
learned in the cardiac anesthesia
operating room, in terms of team work,
check lists, the surgical props,
and advancing that, and putting that into
cath lab and the electrophysiology area.
A final point, another point is a lot
adults now are getting, a lot
of patients are getting into adulthood who
have congenital heart disease.
And so, cardiac anesthesiology will allow
you a wide variety of specialties,
depending on your interest.
If you're interested in congenital heart
disease, you can learn about that,
because the advantage the, that your
knowledge will be needed as
these patients become adults and require
non-cardiac surgery.
>> Yeah, I think, just, this specialty is
really going to expand within cardiac
surgery, cardiac anesthesia, and you're
also going to be taking care of a lot of
patients in the non-cardiac ORs that have
been patients of ours in the cardiac OR.
So I think, I see it as a really great
opportunity to become very
well-rounded anesthesiologists, and
very confident taking care of some of our
sickest patients.
>> Could not agree more.
>> Wonderful.
I mean, I am so excited about cardiac
anesthesia, as a specialty, and
you talk about innovation.
This course itself is another example of
cardiac anesthesia taking
the initiative and innovation for online
learning and education.
so, I'm really excited about this course
and I think you guys will be too,
so we look forward to seeing you, at our
next episode.
See you soon!
[MUSIC]