[MUSIC]
>> Welcome back.
I'm Dr.Larry Chu.
>> And I'm Dr.Ren Weidman.
>> And in this segment, we're going to
talk about the pre-operative assessment of
patients undergoing cardiac surgery, as
well as some consent issues.
So Ren, tell me a little bit about what
you're going to cover in the lecture.
What are some important points that our
learners need to know when
they're thinking about performing a
pre-operative assessment and
consenting patients for a cardiac surgery
and cardiac anesthesia.
>> Okay, so the cardiac surgical patient
usually has a very thorough workup.
In just a little bit, we'll talk about
[COUGH] looking at some of
the extra tests to assess the cardiac
function in preparations for surgery.
We'll also discuss how to help them
prepare mentally and emotionally for
a very big procedure and, and get them
through the consent process as well.
>> Great.
Well, it sounds like there are some very
specialized things we need to know, so
let's go learn about them right now.
>> Okay.
Hi, this is Ren Weidman.
We're going to talk a little bit about the
Preoperative Evaluation and
Consent in preparation for cardiac
surgery.
So most cardiac surgery patients are very
well worked up.
Many of the elements, in fact, almost all
of the elements that we
apply to a regular work-up still apply to
patients undergoing cardiac surgery.
You're going to want to make sure you
access the airway
review allergies review pertinent medical
history, medications.
In addition, there are certain elements
which are specific to cardiac surgery
which should be reviewed and considered in
the pre-operative evaluation.
So we'll go through it by systems, and
just touch on the systems for which the,
the pre-operative work is different or in
which there are additional elements in
the cardiac surgical patient relative to
the non-cardiac surgical patient.
So first, we'll talk about the, the
obvious.
The cardiovascular exam.
So what you're going to want to do is,
is be sure you get a good history of the
patient's cardiac cardiac history.
Try to understand what the symptoms are,
when the onset was and what the patient's
pathway to surgery was.
How did they get from their symptoms to
being evaluated for cardiac surgery?
Try to flush out any prior cardiac
intervention, inter,
intervention's the patient may have had.
This includes surgeries, any stents any
pacers or AICDs.
And if the patient had a pacer, has a
pacer or
any AICD get an understanding for what the
indication was.
If the patient is pacer dependent or not
pacer dependent.
Who the manufacturer of the pacer or
the AICD was and when the pacer was last
interrogated.
This will help to make decisions during
the day of surgery about the management of
the pacer.
All patients coming in for a cardiac
surgery will have
had an echocardiogram done prior to the
day of surgery.
When you're reviewing the at, the report
from the echocardiogram make sure you
look for a left and right ventricular
function.
Focus on any Valvular lesions and their
severity, and
especially pay attention to those that are
moderate or severe in nature.
If you're doing a surgery or the patient's
scheduled for surgery targeting a valve.
Try to note that the pressure gradients
across that value.
For example, if, if the patient is
undergoing an aortic value replacement for
a stenosis get a sense for how severe the
pressure gradients are across that value.
And finally, take a look at the RVSP or
the PASP.
Recordings that are estimated by
echocardiography.
These are usually found in the assessment
of the tricuspid valve on the report.
As the, these estimates are used from
Doppler across the tricuspid regurgitation
gen.
This can help you to understand how the RV
functions, and also.
With the pulmonary vascular, vascular
[UNKNOWN] is, is like in your patient.
You also want to look for
anything that might be out of the ordinary
in the report.
A Thrombus mentioned, a PFO mentioned.
Something unique that, that you might not
expect.
Moving on to CATH, a vast majority of
patients will have some sort of
cardiac catheterization prior to surgery.
You want to look for significant lesions
and, and significant lesions
are technically considered, any lesion
that is greater than seventy percent.
Though I would say keep track of any
lesion that was greater than 50% even
though it has to be greater than 70% to be
considered obstructive.
Also try to remember the location or take
note of the location of the lesion.
Sometimes during catheterization there
will also be assessments of
the right heart pressures more directly
than those that are recorded on the echo.
And if that occurs they're usually done
for a reason, so
it's a good idea to to be aware of them
for that.
And finally, looking at the dominance,
whether it's left, right, or co-dominant,
can be, can be helpful in sort of avoiding
some of the pitfalls during surgery.
So Carotid Dopplers are not always
performed, but sometimes they are.
And when they are, they can significant
can, can affect things.
It can change the surgical plan, for
example, the surgeon might decide to add
a corrodid and direct the day of the
surgery in addition to the heart surgery.
Also, if there is significant carotid
disease in an attempt to maintain
adequate perfusion to the brain in
cardiopulmonary
bypass the perfusionist might decide to
target a perfusion pressure which is
higher than normal during the bypass
period if the patient has carotid disease.
So moving on let's next talk about some of
the, some of the things that we should pay
specific attention to in the neurologic
system.
So cardiac surgery, more so than other
surgeries, carries a,
a pretty significant risk of stroke.
For this reason, it's important to
establish a baseline in the patient so
that any, any observed neurologic deficits
in the post-operative period can be
compared to those assessed in the
pre-operative period and
be determined to be new, or, or just the
patient's baseline.
Moving on to the gastrointestinal system.
Quite common to cardiac surgery is the use
of a transesophageal echocardiogram.
A TEE adds the risk of esophageal injury.
It can happen in anyone, but
it is much more likely to in patients who
have preexisting esophageal disease.
So it's important to ask about existing
pathology.
Including Zenker's, diverticulum, any
stricture, any history of dilation,
any history of masses.
In addition to asking about already
diagnosed pathology,
symptoms should be reviewed to see if a
patient has any concerning symptoms for
esophageal pathology that might not yet
have been diagnosed.
And this includes, you know, problems
swallowing,
sensation of food getting stuck or
regurgitated food during eating.
And if the patient has one of these, one
of these conditions and, and
you're concerned about it, it's important
to talk to your attending early.
What you might want to do is, is, schedule
an EGD so you can look and, and,
and make sure that there is nothing that
is to problematic or
is nothing that would prevent you from
using a TEE.
again, it's best in this early as, as
nobody likes to be call last minute on
the day of surgery to do an emergency EED
before heart surgery.
Continuing on to medications.
As always, getting an accurate list of
medications is important, but
pay specific attention to medications
which are used for the cardiac systems,
includes beta blockers, ACE inhibitors,
calcium channel blockers, Statin's.
Also you want to look to, to see about any
anticoagulation medications.
Or any anti-platelet medications that the
patient might be on.
And with regards to the anticoagulants and
the anti-platelets pay attention to when
these were stopped if they were stopped.
finally, it's good to know when the
patient last took their beta
blocker; as usually, beta blockers are
continued, even on the morning of surgery.
So after reviewing the,
the preoperative history of the patient,
it's time to talk about the consent.
Consent for cardiac surgery contains the
normal elements that one might consent
a patient for for any anesthesia.
In addition you're going to want to review
the consent process for Arterial lines,
Central lines, TEE and the possibility of
a prolonged intubation or an ICU stay.
For an arterial line have the patient
understand that this will be
done awake but under local.
Anesthetic and probably with a little bit
of sedation on board.
The Central line on the TEE would be done
asleep.
Again, this is, this is the time that you
had mentioned to the patient that with
the TTE there's a very small risk of
esophageal injury, in a patient,
especially in a patient who has no prior
history of esophageal pathology.
And to clarify that, that we feel that the
information gleamed the benefit that we
gleamed from having a TEE definitely
outweighs the risk that
is imposed by introducing the prorogue
into the esophagus.
finally, when you're talking about the
post operative course prolonged intubation
is, is not uncommon, though it's, it's not
obviously what we aim for.
And this kind of brings us to
expectations.
So it's useful to go over the flow of the
day with patient, and
also with the patient's family, what they
can expect during,
the pre-operative visit, prior to going
back to the operating room.
With the pace you can expect in the
operating room prior to be,
to being put under anesthesia.
And then explaining to him or her, what
will happen to him after
he goes under anesthesia all the way to
the time that he gets to the ICU.
And then letting the family know that they
will get periodic updates or
on the surgical team during the operation,
they will be allowed to come, and, and
see their see their family member in the
ICU as soon as the patient gets there and
the nurses have had a chance to sort of
get things tucked in.
It's important, again to talk
about post-operative expectations that we
aim to extubate early.
But that we would much rather be
conservative and hold off,
hold off of extubation if, if we feel like
it's necessary.
We would much rather take a little longer
to extubate than extuate early, and
then have to reintabate.
And then address the patient's anxiety.
Again, anxiety is common in, in most
surgeries.
But especially in cardiac surgery anxiety
is, is quite prevalent.
Helping to address it and, and
acknowledging it is,
is a useful way of helping the patient to
feel more comfortable.
Let the patient know that anxiety is
normal.
That this is a big deal for them.
But for most, but that for most of the
patient,
most of the participants in the day
surgery, the anesthesiologist,
the perfusionist, the cardiac surgeons,
the nurses.
This is an everyday activity.
We see patients like, like this all the
time,.
And being aware of, of a patient's needs
usually helps them
to feel a little less anxious about
something that.
That is very normal to be just about.
So that's it.
Reviewing,
doing a thorough review of systems with
focus on specific elements which
might play into what one can expect on the
day of cardiac surgery is important.
And then adding some additional elements
that we discussed to
the consent process and helping the
patient and
the family members to know what to expect
the day of surgery and
during the time period immediately
following surgery, can be very beneficial.
Thank you for your time.
>> Well, that was a very interesting
lecture and very thorough.
Thank you.
I do have a couple questions, though.
You know, we don't always have the luxury
of having time to really
do a careful preoperative assessment and
consent in emergency situations.
So one of my questions is, in the really
emergent setting,
what are the essential points that I need
to know in terms of
pre-operative assessment of the patient
who's undergoing cardiac surgery.
>> That's a very good question.
Like with most emergencies,
one of the key elements is just to assess
the patient's airway.
You also want to know if your patient has
any allergies and if you
can get an idea for what medications he or
she is on, that can really be helpful.
In terms of emerging cardiac surgeries,
if you can get an understanding of the
left ventricular function,
how the heart is working in general, that
can be quite beneficial,
whether that's from the history from the
patient or going over old notes.
Or if your facility has the ability to do
a very quick TTE,
that can also definitely give you a good
idea for the heart function.
>> Wonderful.
Well, to summarize what we've learned in
this segment, the first thing is, for
a preoperative assessment, you really
start with the basics.
What you normally do for the preoperative
assessment of any patient undergoing
anesthesia, you want to get a careful
history of other comorbidities.
As well as the airway, as you mentioned,
but the difference is,
of course, with the cardiac patient that
you'll want to get a full evaluation of
cardiac function of lafrintricular
function, whether that is from
imaging studies like echnocartiography or
cath log studies, cathernization studies.
In addition, we want to really talk to the
patient.
Get a sense of the history of exercise
tolerance.
What can they do without getting short of
breath?
Do they have any angina or chest pain?
Those are of course the important factors
to to elicit from your patient.
The other thing, of course, is to get a
history of esophageal disease because
we do procedures in cardiac anesthesia,
trans esophageal epicardiography that
may be contraindicated in patients with
that type of disease.
Of course, also consenting the patient.
For issues such as having extra lines when
they wake up so
they're expecting they may have an
arterial line, extra IVs,
a central line or they may be intibated
post-operatively in the ICU.
You also want to know if they've been on
any anticoagulation medications.
Because they do factor into our anesthetic
plan if the patient is on those type
of medications.
And finally, of course, consenting these
patients in general.
We need to understand that for
many patients it's a very anxious time in
their life.
Maybe the most anxious time in their life.
There is a perception of cardiac surgery
and these procedures being high risk.
And so we as Anesthesiologist need to help
reassure our patients.
And help them come prepared emotionally,
as well, for the Anesthetic plan and
for the surgical procedure.
Great.
Well, we'll see you next time.
[MUSIC]