[MUSIC]
Hi I'm Larry Cheu.
>> Hi I'm Carly Guthrie.
>> And in this segment we're going to
learn about lines and
monitors and what you need to know for
cardiac anesthesia.
So Carly, tell me a little bit about what
students can expect to learn from you and
your lecture in this module.
>> So, what students should expect to
learn from this module is,
the indications, and the reasons why you
should put in an arterial line, and
the central line, and we'll also go
through some of the basics of what is
in a kit and how you can expect to set
that up so you're prepared for
your first day in cardiac anesthesia.
>> Wonderful.
Well you know, one of the things that
people really get experienced with,
on cardiac anesthesia, is line placement.
Is learning how to do the,
get a lot of experience in doing central
lines, and doing arterial lines.
So let's, let's dive in and watch the
lecture.
>> Hi, my name is Carly Guthrie and
today we're going to talk about placement
of Arterial and central lines.
First, let's start by talking about
arterial lines.
Some of the indications for arterial line
placement include the need for
continuous direct blood pressure
monitoring.
Or if your indirect blood pressure
monitoring fails,
it means your frequent arterial blood gas
sampling.
Or measurement of the blood glucose or
chemistries.
Let's talk about the arterial line
waveform.
First of all, any time you're replacing an
arterial line you
should place it under sterile conditions.
The waveform that you'll see once you
place the arterial line
will show a high pressure.
Which corresponds to the systolic
pressure, as seen in the image to
the right, and the lowest pressure, which
will correspond to the diastolic pressure.
The mean arterial pressure is a calculated
number, and
it's calculated by the equation, MAP is
equal to 2 times the diastolic pressure.
Plus the systolic pressure, divided by 3.
Additionally, you'll notice that the wave
form has a small dip or
the dicrotic notch or incisura, which will
coincide with the aortic valve closure.
You can see that also on the image to the
right.
That about sums up arterial lines, now
let's talk about central lines.
Indications for central line placement
include,
any patient in which you will need to use
vasopressors.
Patients that may have difficult
peripheral access.
Measurement of the central venus pressure,
especially anytime you'll have hypovolemia
or large fluid shifts during the case.
The administration of TPN or
hemodialysis, and anytime you'll need to
do frequent blood draws.
Normal CVP values.
Will be 5 to 10 centimeters of water in a
spontaneously breathing patient, and
3 to 5 centimeters higher, in a
mechanically ventilated patient.
In a normal patient, we believe that the
CVP or
Central Venus Pressure, closely
corresponds to the left atrial pressure,
and therefore, to left ventricular end
diastolic pressure.
However, this is true only in the absence
of right ventricular dysfunction,
in the absence of abnormal pulmonary
vascular resistance, and
in the absence of valvular disease.
Let's go through the CVP waveform.
First of all, the A wave corresponds to
the atrial contraction at end diastole.
The C wave is due to isovolemic right
ventricular contraction.
When the, tricuspid valve closes and
bulges back into the right atrium.
This occurs in early systole.
You'll notice that the C wave occurs after
the QRS oh the EKG and
the A wave occurs after the P wave.
The V wave is caused by filling of the
atrium with blood from the vena cava.
This happens while the tricuspid valve is
closed during late systole.
There are two descents.
Firstly the X descent is caused by atrial
relaxation,
which causes a decline in atrial pressure
during ventricular contraction.
This occurs in mid systole, so
you'll notice it occurs just before the T
wave of the EKG.
The Y descent is caused by a decrease in
atrial pressure as the tricuspid valve
opens and blood begins flowing from the
right atrium into the right ventricle.
Some tips to remember when you're looking
at CVP waveforms.
First of all, three of the waveform parts
are systolic events, the c,
the x, and the v.
Two of the waveform portions are diastolic
events,
this is the a wave and the y descent.
We use the EKG to properly identify the
parts of the waveform and
where they occur with reference to the
cardiac cycle.
The terms systole and diastole always
refer to ventricular events.
Lets move on and talk about pulmonary
artery catheters.
Pulmonary Artery Catheters are
triple-lumen catheters which have
a proximal port, for measuring the right
atrial pressure and distal port for
measuring the pulmonary artery pressure,
and a thermistor for
calculating cardiac output by
thermodilution.
Some values that you can get directly from
you PAC line include the cardiac output.
CVP, the right ventricular pressure,
pulmonary artery pressure, and
pulmonary capillary wedge pressure.
Also, you can get SvO2 and temperature
directly from your PAC line.
Indirect measurements include the cardiac
index,
the stroke volume resistance, and the
stroke volume.
Pulmonary capillary wedge pressure is used
to approximate left ventricular end
diastolic pressure.
Again, some normal values include a CVP of
0 to 8 millimeters of mercury,
right ventricular pressure of 15 to 30
over 0 millimeters of mercury,
pulmonary artery pressure of 15 to 30 over
5 to 15 millimeters of mercury.
And a pulmonary capillary wedge pressure
of 5 to 15 millimeters of mercury.
Indications for pulmonary artery catheter
placement include significant left
ventricular or right ventricular
dysfunction, significant valvular heart
disease, pulmonary hypertension, if you
think you'll have a long operative or
bypass time, or a recent or a current MI.
Again let's go through the waveform that
you may see with pulmonary artery
catheter placement.
You can see the waveform to the image to
the right.
As you path, pass through, first the right
atrium, then the right ventricle,
pulmonary artery, and then, when you
finally wedge your catheter.
Typical depths of catheter insertion from
the right IJ access include the right
atrium at 20 to 25 centimeters, the right
ventricle at 30 to 35 centimeters,
the pulmonary artery at 40 to 45
centimeters, and
the wedge at 45 to 55 centimeters.
The corresponding waveforms, as you see
there, the right atrium,
and then you'll have a large increase in
your systolic pressure when you
go into the right ventricle.
The pulmonary artery will then have a
increase in your diastolic pressure, and
then the wedge pressure will have
decreases in pressure as you can see.
[NOISE]
That concludes our brief
discussion of central lines, pulmonary
artery catheters and arterial lines.
Thank you very much for your attention.
Please feel free to see the corresponding
video about how to
place them and kit setups.
Thank you again, very much.
>> Carly, that was a great lecture, thank
you so much.
I, I do want to ask you though,
what if our viewers out there really
want to get more of
a sense of how this is actually done on
real patients, how lines are placed.
What can we do to help them?
>> Sure we thought of that.
So what we would like you to do now is go
to New England Journal of
Medicine's website, and look for
their, their examples on how to place
arterial and central lines.
And then we will come back and talk, talk
more about it.
>> Okay, great, and we put those links on
the course website, so you can click
through those links now, and then when
you're finished viewing those videos, come
back and we're going to show you how the
kits look, that we use for placing lines.
So we'll see you in a little bit.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Great, well Carley, we have a kit right
here in front of us.
Why don't you go through it for me and
show me some of the features.
>> Sure, so this is how I like to set up
my arterial line kits.
I use the board to place under the
patient's arm to keep it in
the correct position.
Then I clean it with a sterile cleaning
solution, and
cover it with a sterile drape.
This is our arterial catheter that we use.
Yours may differ at your institution.
At ours it's similar to our IV catheters,
in which it has the small plastic catheter
over the needle.
Once you insert that into the artery, you
can then put a line a,
the wire through the plastic portion,
collecting any blood that may
spill out in the gauze, and once the line
is in, then you connect the soft
plastic portion to the sterile saline
flush that you have preset up.
If you're doing your arterial line under
awake conditions, you can use
the lidocaine drawn up with a straw, and
use a small bore needle to inject it so
the patient is comfortable while you're
doing the procedure.
We then have a sterile adhesive locking
device, and
a sterile ecclusive dressing that you
place over the arterial line once it's in
place, and, and the saline has been
flushed.
>> Okay Carly, well looks like we have
another kit in front of us.
This one looks like it's for a central
line.
Why don't you take us through it?
>> Sure, so, I like to be very organized
when I put together my central line kit.
I have my disinfecting swab, then my
sterile dressing, and
I always have my ultrasound probe cover in
addition to the sterile ultrasound jab.
You'll have an assistant to put those
together when you're,
when you're doing your essential line,
it's very important.
Then, I set everything up in my kit.
I have the catheter here, which is your
Triple Lumin Catheter.
Now, it will come with these attached.
What I do is I take them off, and I put
these blue claves on.
As you see on the blue and the white part.
The brown port I leave open so that the
wire can go through,
and I always have a third clave ready for
when I have the line inside.
>> Now, tell me, Carly, why do you do
that?
>> It helps with our sterile technique.
The claves are they prevent any blood from
coming back, but
they also allow you to use alcohol or some
other sort of disinfectant so
that the line stays clean, and the patient
doesn't get an infection.
The other things you'll find in you kit
are a syringe,
with a needle attached to it.
Some people prefer to use this syringe,
there's others in the kit,
whatever your preference and your
institution's preference is.
The blue syringe will have a hole in the
back here, so
that you have the option of placing the
wire through.
This is the wire, we put the wire in
through the syringe or
through the needle after you've placed the
central line.
It is mobile here.
As you saw in the video, the steps can be
quite complex,
so we'll reference you back to the New
England Journal video for the exact steps.
Other things that are contained in the kit
are the dilator here.
Which goes over the wire and, and can help
open up the skin for
placement of the, of the line.
This is also true of the scalpel, which is
quite sharp and
should always be covered and, and used
safely so that no one gets injured.
The other things that come in the kit are
a transducer probe,
which we don't use very often at our, our
institution.
You can check with your attendings and
other teachers at your institution to use
that.
You'll also have an 18-gauge needle as
well as some stables for
fixing any of your ultrasound covers or
anything you might need to.
There's also lidocaine and
a syringe if you ever need to put in a
central line while the patient is awake.
Things which al, also come in the kit are.
The needle, with a needle driver to secure
the line after it is in place, and
then we also have our sterile [UNKNOWN]
dressing, and a patch, which helps
again with sterility to, make sure that
the, the area that the line is placed.
Does not have any bacteria that can in, go
into the patient.
>> Okay Carly well we have another kit in
front of us.
It looks similar to the last one but a
little different.
Can you explain it to us?
>> Sure, it is similar but there's a few
things that we'd like to point out.
So first of all you'll recognize this
sterile dressing,
again this is a line that should always be
placed under sterile technique.
You'll also have this syringe and
the needle that you will use to place the
the central line, and other
things you'll recognize are the lidocaine
if you do it under sterile conditions.
However, there's some very different
items.
This is a large introducer catheter.
You'll notice it doesn't have the triple
lumens, like we have on the other one.
It has one large one and it's 9 French so
it's used more often for
transfusing large volumes.
It also is handy because you can place
what's called a pulmonary artery catheter.
We have one curled up here, it's quite
long, and this goes into the patient,
much like you saw in both the New England
Journal video,
video as well as in our lecture we talked
about some of the indications and reasons.
Things that are different are, you'll have
a balloon on the end,
which actually is able to be pumped up,
with the,
a syringe that attaches especially here,
and has a little locking device.
So if you do blow the balloon up.
Then you can lock it in place, so that it
stays.
>> Oh Carly let me ask you a question.
>> Sure.
>> If you don't happen to have a 33,
3CC syringe can you stick a 20CC syringe
on that?
>> Absolutely not.
It's a good question, but no, it's really
important that you don't do something like
that and you use only the syringe that
comes with the kit or a small syringe.
Because you don't want to over fill the
balloon,
while it's in the pulmonary area because
you can actually rupture the artery.
>> Okay, well we don't want that.
>> We don't want that, absolutely not.
Other things that you'll notice in this
kit are, again, your scalpel,
which you use to help cut the skin, and
then you can insert the dilator.
Again, you'll notice that this is a larger
and longer dilator.
Which is necessary,
because as we mentioned before, this is a
much larger catheter that you'll place.
Other things that are different, and this
is something that I always forget.
You have to remember, make a note to
remember, to place this little
protective sheath onto your pulmonary
artery catheter, before you place it in
the patient, otherwise, you'll have to
take it out and start all over again.
Again, you'll notice that there's three
different ports here,
aside from the one that you use to blow up
a balloon, so
you can inject medications and infusions
like we do normally.
And that's basically it.
That's the big differences between this
one and the, and the central line.
>> And I see the wire there too.
>> You do have the wire here, and again,
at our institution, we actually on our
checklist, have a note.
That we make to remove all of the wires
and all of the dilators, so
that we all verbally confirm with
ourselves and the nurses and the surgeons.
That all of those have been removed from
the patient so
that we don't have any of them left
inside.
>> Wonderful.
Well I thought it was really helpful to
look at those kits, because it's always
great to get a sense of the equipment that
you're going to be working with, and I
encourage you out there watching, to take
a look at your own institution's kits.
They may be the same, they may be slightly
different, but
it's great to have a look at the equipment
that you'll be using.
So you're familiar with what you're
going to be
working with when you start doing these
procedures.
Now to recap what we learned in this
segment,
the first thing is that we really tried,
we really understood the indications for
when we want to use monitors and lines.
For instance an arterial catheterization
is useful when you want beat to
beat monitoring of hemodynamics, and you
may consider into,
central venous lines when you want to
infuse medications or
also, consider lines when you want to get
frequent blood draws.
We also talked about the importance.
Of having help, when you place a line.
Someone to monitor the well being, the
vital signs,
the human dynamics of the patient,
while your attention is focused on the
procedure and the task of placing lines.
Of course also consider using check lists
and
also keep in mind the importance of
sterilities.
Because avoiding line infections is really
our responsibility as practitioners,
physicians who are placing these lines, to
avoid iatrogenic complications and
injuries toward patents.
Your institution may have checklists,
to help ensure that these safety measures
are followed, and I encourage you to look.
Into your own institution's policies and
checklists to make sure that as you're
learning these techniques, that you're
doing them in the right way and following
the expectations of your institution.
So, we hope you learned a lot on this
episode, and we'll see you soon.
Thanks so much.
>> Bye.
[MUSIC]