[MUSIC]
>> Hi, I'm Dr. Larry Chu.
>> And I'm Dr. Ren Weidman.
>> On this segment, we're only going to
talk about two things.
But they're pretty important things,
aren't they, Ren?
>> They are.
So, in the Cardiac ORU, you'll be
introduced to a bunch of new medications.
The two most important medications, in our
opinion, are heparin and protamine.
The reason is, is because the improper use
of heparin and
protamine can result in catastrophic,
situations.
>> Oh my gosh.
Well,
I'm really interested in knowing, more
about these drugs.
Let's get started.
>> Okay.
Hi, this is Ren Weidman.
We're going to talk a little bit about
heparin and protamine, and
their role in the cardiac operating room.
So the vast majority of cardiac surgery,
requires the use of the cardiopulmonary
bypass machine.
The bypass machine contains non-biological
material.
And when the patient's blood is exposed to
this material,
it can result in the activation of a
clotting cascade.
For this reason, patients are usually
given an anticoagulant prior to
going under the cardiopulmonary bypass
machine.
More often than not, the anticoagulant of
choice is heparin.
Heparin has been around since the
inception of
the cardiopulmonary bypass machine and as
such is a tried and tested method.
It also has the, added benefit of being a
drug which is reversible.
Heparin acts on antithrombin III.
Antithrombin III binds and inhibits
thrombin.
And when heparin is in the bloodstream, it
augments the activity of antithrombin III
by about 1,000 fold, and thus results in
the anti-coagulated state.
Heparin is prepared in vials of 1,000
U/ml.
The textbook dosage of heparin required
for
the cardiopulmonary bypass machine, is
about 350 U/kg.
There are, machines that exist,
that can take a unit of patient's blood,
and can predict the appropriate amount
of heparin to achieve a desired level of
anti-coagulation.
But without those machines, usually using
the,
the standard dosage of 350 U/kg, is what,
what people do.
Now the timing of the administration of
heparin is also important.
It should be given just prior to
cannulation.
You obviously want to have the patient's
blood, anti-coagulated before
the cannula are introduced as the cannula
can results in, activation of coagulation.
But you don't want to give it too early,
as you don't want to thin the patient's
blood when it's unnecessary, as this can
result in excess bleeding.
Once the heparin has been given, you
want to test its effectiveness.
The effectiveness of heparin is tested by,
a test called the activated clotting time
or the ACT.
In this test, a small amount of patient's
blood is exposed to an activator,
usually clay or dirt.
And then the time to clotting is, is
recorded.
The goal here at the Brigham Women
Hospital, Brigham and Women's Hospital,
is an ACT of greater than 350 seconds
prior to going on to the bypass machine.
At other institutions, this score may
vary, but some institutions requiring
an ACT as high as 480 seconds before the
initiate, initiation of bypass.
And the dose of heparin to,
to achieve this, this target ACT, varies
from patient to patient.
Once cardiopulmonary bypass has started,
it's necessary to recheck the ACT on
occasion.
In order to maintain an appropriate level,
of anti-coagulation.
The half-life of heparin is, is about 60
to 90 minutes.
And usually the profusion is for recheck
the ACT, every 20 to 30 minutes.
And then give heparin as needed to again
maintain, a target ACT.
A couple final thoughts about heparin.
It's usually administered through a
central line to assure its,
its administration into the, into the
blood stream.
And one should also be aware of the
potential hypotension that
can result from the administration of
heparin.
If hypotension occurs,
it usually occurs over a period of about 5
to 10 minutes in a gradual fashion.
finally, being aware of whether or
not your patient has heparin-induced
thrombocytopenia or HIT is important.
If you patient does have HIT, it's
important to discuss with your attending,
with the perfusionist, what the
anti-coagulation strategy is,
as you most likely will not be giving the
patient heparin.
So now let's move our discussion on
protamine.
Protamine is, acts on heparin to reverse
its anti-coagulant activity.
It binds the heparin molecule and it
neutralizes it.
And the ability of protamine to reverse
heparin is one of the main reasons why
heparin is the preferred anticoagulant,
for cardiopulmonary bypass.
As it does reverse the anti-coagulation in
the blood,
it is also considered one of the most
dangerous drugs in cardiac surgery because
improper administration, of protamine can
have catastrophic results.
Protamine is prepared in vials with
concentrations of about 10 mg/ml.
And the text of dosage of protamine for
the reversal of heparin is 1 milligram of
protamine for every hundred units of
heparin.
And, again, the timing of the
administration, is critical.
The improper administration of protamine
before the appropriate time,
can be a catastrophic mistake and can
often result in the patient's death.
So let's start this slide over.
If protamine is administered before the
appropriate time,
the results can be catastrophic and can
very easily result in a patient's death.
Protamine should not be administered
before the patient is
off the cardiopulmonary bypass machine.
You can imagine what would happen if the
patient was given protamine while he or
she was still on the bypass machine.
The, the anticoagulant effect of heparin
would be reverse.
A clot would form which would damage the
ability of the cardiopulmonary bypass
machine to oxygenate the blood and to flow
the blood into the body.
It can also result in embolic phenomenon
with thrombus going to
vital organs such as the brain or the
kidneys.
As the result prior to the administration
of heparin, the surgeon,
the profusionist, and the attending
anesthesiologist should all
verbally agree that it is the appropriate
time to give protamine.
And each of these individuals has, has
separate items that they are considering
regarding whether or not it's appropriate
to reverse the protamine.
And therefore reverse the ability to go
back onto
the cardiopulmonary bypass machine.
Protamine in and of itself can also cause
some adverse reactions.
With the rapid administration of
protamine, you can cause hypotension.
For this reason, protamine should be given
in small boluses over time.
Protamine can also cause an anaphylactiod
or
an anaphylactic reaction with the expected
hypotension, vasodilation, flushing,
and bronchospasm that are often seen with
anaphylaxis.
Additionally, you can get a catastrophic
pulmonary vasoconstriction as
an reaction of protamine.
And this is, this occurs through a
thromboxane-mediated mechanism.
For this reason, the way we administer
protamine is, is very specific.
We initially give a test dose of 1
milliliter or 10 milligrams.
And wait two or three minutes to see if
the blood pressure drops or
if the CBP rises, as it would in, in, in
conditions of anaphylaxis and
catastrophic pulmonary vassal
constriction, respectively.
If the test dose is negative,
the anesthesiologist will announce going
to 50%, meaning 50% of the protamine.
He or
she then administers half of protamine
dose in a slow controlled fashion.
And as long as everything is good and as
long as the profusionist and the surgeon
are okay with it, the anesthesiologist
will then announce going to a 100%.
Once the anesthesiologist has
administered, all of the protamine dose,
he or she announces to the room that the
protamine is at 100%.
The key to all of this is closed-loop
communication, as the profusionist,
the anesthesiologist, and the surgeon, all
have very important factors to consider.
There definitely needs to be,
communication back and
forth between all three parties.
And the lack of this sort of closed-loop
communication and
mutual understanding of where we are in,
in terms of our active coagulation can
have,
very severe, very permanent adverse
reactions.
But if communication is kept open, then
heparin and
protamine can be used in a very safe
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Well, another great talk.
Thank you so much, learned a lot about
protamine and heparin.
Now, one of the things I want to ask you,
now that we know, the, the,
really severe implications of, of,
incorrectly dosing these drugs, do you
have any tips for me on how,
practical tips on how we can try to
prevent those things from happening?
>> It's a good question.
as, as, one might imagine, a,
a syringe swap in this situation can again
be catastrophic,
and, and, methods that are employed to
prevent that are, are always welcome.
And our specific institution, we keep the
protamine away, on the other side of
the room from the anesthesia area with, no
anesthesia carts containing any protamine.
So the time that protamine is to be
administered, the anesthesiologist
actually has to cross the room and pick it
up from the nurse and then come back.
And that's just again to be safe and
be sure that protamine is not administered
at an inappropriate time.
>> Well that's actually a great tip,
and what I want to do next is just to
summarize what we learn in a segment.
Of course, we learned that heparin is used
as an anticoagulant because we put our
patients in cardiopulmonary bypass, and
we want to make sure that the blood
doesn't clot in the pump, of course.
And that involves administering a dose of
heparin and,
your, institution has methods for
calculating what that dose is and
administer it according to what you've
already agreed to with your attending.
The important, and
you want to do that before you put your
patient on bypass, of course.
And you also want to confirm the efficacy
of the drug that you administer,
through an ACT, and finally protocols of
your institution so that
you know that the heparin has taken effect
before you put your patient on bypass.
Now of course, we know that protamine
reverses the effects of heparin, so
we don't want to give that drug until
after the patient's off of bypass.
So that's an important timing issue.
And also, we want to administer the
correct dose.
And again, each institution has methods
for,
for calculating the correct dose of how
pro, protamine.
And you should follow those at your
institution.
Ren gave us some great tips about how to
avoid syringe swaps.
And of course, closed-loop communication
is also very important with protamine.
We want to make sure that everyone in the
room has a shared mental model about
what's going to happen, so that we're
confirming that the protamine is being
administered at the correct time and the
correct dose for the patient.
And finally, we talked about,
severe adverse reactions that can occur
with administration of protamine.
Right?
Well, I
think we learned a lot about these two
drugs and
I think you'll be better prepared when you
start your cardiac anesthesia rotation.
We'll see you next time
[MUSIC]