As you probably already know, microbiology
is the study of microscopic organisms.
And these can be tiny single celled
organisms like bacteria or
colonies of cells like fungi.
Or even non-cellular entities like
viruses.
That need to live inside host cells, in
order to replicate.
Microbes live in every ecosystem on earth.
And the earliest ones have been around for
more three billion years.
The human microbe biome,
is the collection of around two hundred
trillion bacteria that live on the skin.
Inside the mouth, and eyes, and in the
gastrointestinal tract,
of the average adult human, there are ten
times as many microbes, as there are cells
in the adult human body, and many of these
microbes are commensals, they live in
peace with us, or even help us to do
things, like break down nutrients.
In the digestive tract, or produce
vitamins that keep us healthy, but
obviously, sometimes microbes can cause
disease, and
this happens in a variety of ways.
In order to cause disease, microbes need
to enter and
colonize a part of the body, they are not
supposed to inhabit, then they
have to find ways of persisting there or
replicating beyond their usual numbers.
In order for the species to survive, they
need to exit the host.
And through all of these activities,
microbes will evolve,
sometimes developing virulence factors
that help them survive and
potentially make them more pathogenic than
they were before.
The science and practice of immunology,
tries to
understand the host immune defenses, that
either keep commensal microbes in check,
or actively defend the body against
pathogenic ones.
Physical barriers like skin and mucus
membranes, help keep pathogens out and
a variety of specialized cells,
help to protect the host from disease
causing organisms,
the first line cells in the immune system
form part of the inate immune system.
They detect and
recognize potential pathogens, even if
they never encountered them before.
And they can then deploy a cascade of
other body defense,
including activating the adapted immune
systems with
the end goal of either eliminating the
pathogen or in the case of commensals.
Finding a way to tolerate the existing of
certain microbes in ways that
don't result in disease.
Through these encounters with microbes,
the adaptive immune system,
will remember certain pathogens and
store an arsenal of [UNKNOWN] in case that
pathogen every gets encountered again.
Most of the time.
The microbes in and
on the host, are successfully kept in
check, by the host's immune system.
But when the steady state is disturbed or
if the immune system, begins to behave
inappropriately towards host cells.
The result is a clinical presentation of
disease.
If the immune system becomes too weak, or
too strong, or if the microbes become to
aggressive or
go places they're not supposed to be in
the body, the equilibrium is disturbed and
physicians need to figure out what went
wrong.
By understanding the characteristics of
different microbes and
how the host immune system usually reacts
to them.
Physicians can recognize, collections of
signs and
symptoms and integrate that with other
details from the history and
physical exam, to lead to a list of likely
diagnosis.
Which can then be confirmed in many cases,
with the help of things like lab tests and
imaging.
Understanding the relevant microbiology
and immunology as it
applies to each patient, helps the
physician initiate the right therapy.
For example, choose the right antibiotic
for a specific type of bacteria.
Or recognize when the immune system, may
itself be causing damage to the body,
and the physician can then try to mediate.
Knowing when these diseases are most
likely to occur,
how different microbes are spread, and how
they cause disease.
This knowledge can help with prevention
efforts,
both at the level of the individual
patient and on the population level,
when we start thinking about the
epidemiology of a disease.
Using a framework of this kind can help
physicians approach a variety of
different diseases in an organized and
systematic way by trying to understand the
clinical presentation of a patient
as a result of the interplay between
microbes and the host immune system.
We'll be much more likely, to succeed in
managing the disease.