[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi, I'm Doctor Larry Chu.
>> Hi, I'm Doctor Kevin Jenner.
>> On behalf of the Stanford AIM Lab, I'd
like to tell you about an exciting new
course that we've developed in partnership
with the Medical College of Wisconsin.
Looking at the essentials of geriatric
anesthesia.
Really, an online course designed to give
an overview of some of
the essential issues associated with the
preoperative care of the new patients.
Now Kevin, tell me a little bit about why
someone want to
take a course about pediatric, about
geriatric anesthesia.
>> Well, geriatric anesthesia is becoming
ever more important in
the anesthesiologist's tool, toolbox.
And knowing the principles and concepts
around that, that govern the way in
which geriatric patients are different
from other patients is very important.
The American population is ageing, as our
populations all around the world, and
there are more patients who are living
longer and requiring surgical procedures
further into their into their geriatric
years than they were decades ago.
So, it's important to understand these
issues and be competent and confident when
caring for geriatric patients, so that we
can do that safely in the operating room.
>> And of course, these days, there are
just more surgical procedures available
that elderly patients are taking part of.
And that's really increasing the,
the number of anesthetics being provided
to elderly patients.
And, and we're going to talk about some of
those important issue in
preoperative care.
Including the physiology and
pharmacology relevant to changes as your
body ages and how we provide anesthesia.
We're going to talk also about ethics and
the important ethical issues
that can sometimes arise in patients who
are elderly.
And of course, post-operative issues like
cognitive dysfunction and
delirium are important, I think, for any
anesthesiologist to know about.
So we hope that you
will join us for this
online course, and
we look forward to
seeing you soon.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]