Hello, students.
We'll learn about a system that will
revolutionize molecular medicine.
The system is called CRISPR, which can
target any site in the genome.
What is CRISPR?
Well, what CRISPR stands for
[NOISE] is clustered regularly
interspersed short palindromic repeats.
The repeats are depicted here by back to
back triangles,
because they're palindromic.
And the repeats are separated from each
other by spacers,
each with a different DNA sequence.
[SOUND] There's a leader to initiate
transcription.
And there is a terminator to stop
[SOUND] Now [SOUND] turns out that CRISPR
is
the immune system in bacteria and archaea.
[SOUND] The first step in the, the immune
system is immunization.
[NOISE] We're depicting a bacterial cell
here.
And inside the bacterial cell are cas
genes.
The cas genes encode a multi-subunit
protein called cas.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Cas stands for CRISPR associated protein.
Now [NOISE] what happens [NOISE] when the
cell is infected by phage?
The phage is a virus.
That injects its DNA into the bacterial
cell.
That DNA is thus sent to go on and do its
dirty work.
But if the bacterial cell survives, it's
going to use the cas
system to develop a memory for what
happened.
And what can happen is that the cas
[NOISE] system
will process the phage DNA into spacers.
So the spacers are actually phage
sequences.
And then that spacer is incorporated
[NOISE] into the CRISPR array.
[SOUND] So that now, that blue
sequenceappears in the array.
[SOUND] So now, the bacteria is ready just
in case it's going to be infected again.
[NOISE] So, that's the second step.
[SOUND] Which is immunity.
The CRISPR array can be transcribed into
pre CRISPR RNA.
Turns out the palindromic sequences are
cites for cleavage.
[COUGH] So, the cleavage generates crisper
RNAs and
we'll be showing you one of them, the blue
one.
But the others are there, as well.
The cast system [NOISE] can make cas
protein.
[SOUND]
Which associates with the CRISPR RNAs.
Now, what happens this time if the phase
tries to infect the same bacterial cell.
[SOUND] It injects its DNA into the cell.
But this time, the CRISPR cas system
takes that DNA [NOISE] and chews it up.
[NOISE] So, how does it do that?
[SOUND] Well, the CRISPR RNA.
Base pairs with the phage DNA.
[SOUND] If [NOISE] [COUGH] the phage DNA
has a sequence PAM,
which stands for proto-spacer associated
module,
then the CRISPR system will chew up the
DNA.
So I'm, on the other hand, the CRISPR
array [SOUND] itself lacks [SOUND] PAM
sequences.
[SOUND] As a result, the system doesn't
digest itself preventing autoimmunity.
[SOUND] So, the CRISPR-cas9 system [SOUND]
makes double-strand breaks in DNA.
In Streptococcus pyogenes it turns out,
that single polypeptide performs all the
cas functions, so.
It's a single polypeptide with multiple
pyogenes instead of multiple proteins.
Cas9 cutting can be directed by a single
guide RNA [SOUND] provided you do
a little genetic engineering, which we'll
talk about in a minute.
The Cas9 PAM is short.
It's a nucleotide followed by two Gs.
And Cas9 cuts both DNA strands.
So, I'm showing you here, the CRISPR RNA
that
can base pair [SOUND] to the target DNA
[SOUND] which is here.
[SOUND] Now,
if the CRISPR RNA has another
RNA associated with it.
[SOUND] A tracer RNA for
transactivating CRISPR RNA, which base
pairs with the CRISPR RNA.
Then it can do its job.
And you can make this into a single RNA
[SOUND] molecule,
by putting in a linker loop.
[SOUND] Okay?
So once you have all these parts ready to
go [SOUND] and
the target DNA [SOUND] includes PAM
sequences.
Then the whole thing is held together
[SOUND] by the cas9 protein.
[SOUND] To actually, cut both
strands of the target DNA.
[SOUND] So that's how that works.
[SOUND] It turns out that CRISPR-cas9 can
be delivered in a lentivirus.
I'm showing here [SOUND]
a primo, a rudimentary lentivirus with two
long terminal repeats at the end.
And pure [UNKNOWN] gene that can be used
to [SOUND] select for
cells that take up the lentivirus.
But the guts of the system is [SOUND] two
transcriptional cassettes.
One cassette encodes the single guide RNA.
[SOUND]
And the other cassette encodes the cas9
protein.
So the CRISPR-cas9 can make DNA
double-strand break at the target site.
Then the double strand break is repaired
by non-homologous end joining to
create a mutation.
Or if the system is transduced with an
oligonucleotide with a very specific
sequence, hom, homologous recombination
can modify the cleaved [SOUND] site.
[SOUND] So [SOUND] how can you apply this
system?
You can apply this system using GeCKO.
What does GeCKO stand for?
[SOUND] GeCKO stands for
ss genome-scale CRISPR-cas9 knock-out.
It was applied to look for resistance
against the drug Vemurafinib.
Turns out Vemurafinib can treat about 50%
of malignant melanomas.
That's amazing.
Because prior to Vemurafinib there was not
affective treatment against melanoma.
But the problem was the drug only works
for seven months.
So then resistance develops.
So this group was interested in trying to
figure out mechanisms of resist,
resistance.
They transduced cells with a lentiviral
CRISPR library.
And then they grew the cells in a
Vemurafinib defined genes that
when mutated conferred resistance.
And they found such genes, which is a very
nice demonstration [SOUND] that
the system can lead to new discoveries.
Should MDs care?
Of course.
Thank you.