Hello students.
We're going to learn about gel
electrophoresis of biological molecules.
What is gel electrophoresis?
It's the application of an electric field
across a slab made from a gel matrix.
The gel is made from a polymer that
solidifies at room temperature.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The polymer is agarose, which is extracted
from seaweed.
Or polyacrylamide.
Here is a scanning electron micrograph of
agarose.
And you can see that this type of
gel contains all kinds of barriers and
pores, and it's.
Used to separate DNA molecules.
So a long DNA molecule traveling through
this gel would bump into an obstruction,
for example.
And then the front end might turn into a
blob.
And then with the continued application.
Of the electric field,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The DNA could begin sneaking through the
gel again.
So as a result the DNA molecule would move
in a discontinuous way through the gel.
Being retarded by the sitting properties
of the agorose and
the agorose would separate the DNA on the
bases of size.
Now here is a slab of agorose the slab of
agorose contains at the top some wells
that allow you.
To load the DNA samples.
So I'm going to load the DNA samples
inside the top of the agorose.
And then I'm going to hook the gel up to
an electric field,
and because the DNA is generally
negatively charged.
I'm going to hook up the electrodes so
that the positive charge is on the bottom.
And as a result the DNA will migrate down
the gel and separate according to size.
Now, what about separating biological
molecules?
You can separate, either RNA, DNA, or a
protein.
[COUGH]
The DNA,
as we mentioned before, is generally
negatively charged along, because it's.
Got fossH groups and it's phosphoid aster
backbone.
But DNA is very long so we cut it with a
restriction enzyme.
Okay then we have different sized DNA
molecules the restriction enzymes cut at
very specific sequences so
the DNA molecules end up cut into very
characteristic set of sizes.
Then we separate the DNA molecules
according to size by gel electrophoresis.
We block the DNA molecules on to solid
support, say natural cellulose.
And then, now that the DNA is on natural
cellulose.
We can denature the DNA, and
then hybridize the denatured DNA to a P32
labelled DNA probe.
The DNA probe will contain DNA sequences
that correspond.
To the gene we're particularly interested
in studying.
This clever procedure for
analyzing complex mixtures of DNA, is
called the Southern Blot.
Named after the inventor of the method, Ed
Southern.
What about RNA well RNA is single stranded
and
it often contains sequences that are self
complimentary.
And therefore can form secondary
structures.
The RNA needs to be denatured.
Prior to electrophoresis.
And in the denaturation process, we end up
with a extended piece of RNA.
Again, negatively charged because the RNA
has a phosphoidiester backbone.
And just as in the case of DNA, we can
separate.
The RNA molecules, like jello
electrophoresis.
We can blot the samples to match the
cellulose,
we do not need to denature, because the
RNA is already denatured.
And then we can hybridize the RNA to a P32
Ribo DNA probe to look for
the particular RNA species we are
interested in.
Now this is very similar to the analysis
of DNA.
So in an homage to Ed Southern, this
procedure is called a northern blot
[BLANK_AUDIO]
What about protein.
Well protein in addition to being able to
form blobs often contains.
Sulfhydryl bonds that hold the blobs into
place.
So, the proteins need to be reduced, in
order to break the disulfide bonds,
and denatured with sds sodium dodecyl
sulfate.
Is negatively charged.
And as a result, the protein ends up
coated with a negative charge,
just as in the case of RNA and DNA.
Just as before, one can do gel
electrophoresis of the different proteins.
One can blot the proteins over to
nitrocellulose.
And then in order to detect specific
proteins,.
What we would do would be, would be to
bind
the protein we're interested in to a
specific antibody.
And in a further homage to Ed Southern,
this is called a Western blot.
So Western blots analyze protein.
Northern blots analyze RA, and Southern
blots analyze DNA.
What about Southern?
Here's an example.
This is a southern blot using.
Probes derive from the fruit fly
Drosophila melanogaster.
These probes are for the UBX, Fitz, and
antennapedia genes.
These are homeotic genes that, basically
regulate the development.
Of the body pattern of the animal.
It turns out, that these genes are
strongly conserved in other animals.
Such as the beetle.
And even conserved in the chicken and the
mouse.
The beauty of Southern blot is that, the
hybridization of the DNA probe.
Doesn't have to be perfect so the dna
probe will hybernize word
the sequences that are similar but not
exactly complementary.
As a result you can find evidence for
these genes in all these species.
You can tell from the appearance of these
Southern blots.
That the hybridization to the chicken and
the mouse wasn't as strong.
Because there's more background here
between the bands.
And that means that the stringency,
stringency of the hybridization
was decreased, and to bring out to allow
the hybridization.
To the specific bands but as a result
there is a higher background.
What about northern blot.
This is a northern blot with three
isoforms of PPAR.
Delta, Alpha and gamma.
And it's analyzing RNA, from various
different tissues.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay?
And what these investigators are
interested in is.
Is the, are there any species expressed at
different levels in different tissues,
and you can see indeed they are.
You can see for example that this isoform
is expressed in most tissues but
not so much in liver.
This isoform is strongly expressed in
heart kidney liver and BAT
and this isoform has it's own specific
expression in only two tissues.
Now we know that these.
Changes across the board are real because
there is
a control link containing a very abundant
form of RNA, 18S ribosomal RNA.
And this serves as a control that verifies
that the same amount of total RNA.
Was loaded into each lane.
What about western blot to analyze
proteins.
This is the analysis of the wiscott algers
syndrome protein in peripheral blood mono
nuclear cells.
And this is an experiment.
Which shows a healthy control and
a patient with Scott Aldrich syndrome and
patient number one here is being analyzed.
As a function of number of months after
gene therapy.
And the hope is that they could
express the protein in the, the cells of
the patient.
And you can see.
At seven, 12, 15, 22, and 29 months.
You can see that the level of the protein
at seven months was very low.
At 12 months, it went up even higher.
And then, at 15 months, it went up higher
yet.
There's a hint that maybe the expression
went down at 22 and 29 months.
But if you look at the control,
which is GAPDH, a housekeeping protein.
You can see that, perhap, that it's, it
looks like the amount of protein
loaded in the lanes for 22 months and 20
29 months was somewhat less.
So that the decrease,
apparent decrease in expression at those
time points is probably not real.
So there you have it that's our survey of
jello electro freezes of
biological molecules.
Thank you.