Hello, students.
Today we will learn how to analyze gene
expression data sets when the data
sets are very large.
In fact, we want to analyze gene
expression across the entire genome.
On approach is unsupervised analysis.
You may already know something about your
samples.
But unsupervised analysis doesn't use the
information.
Instead, it simply looks at the data
without any preconceptions.
One example of unsupervised analysis is
called hierarchical clustering.
Imagine they chopped data from two
samples, X and Y.
The data are the levels of expression for
four genes.
And suppose the level of expression for
gene one in sample one in sample X is X1,
and
its level of expression in sample Y is Y1.
Similarly for gene two, it's X2 in
sample X and Y2 in sample Y.
And so on and so forth for this toy
example for genes three and four.
Now, it looks like something is going on
here, and in fact, that there is.
And that's something can
be measured by what's called the Pearson
Correlation Coefficient.
R [INAUDIBLE]
of X and Y.
And it's given by this formula.
And what the Pearson correlation
coefficient will do is give you
a value between plus one and minus one.
So, for perfect correlation R is 1.0.
For absolutely now correction is zero.
And, for anti correlation, where say the
level of expression if it's low
in sample X, it's always high in sample Y
and, and so on.
The R value is minus one.
Now, I've given you some examples here of
R values for examples with
many more data points, and these R values
go from plus one, down to minus one.
And you can see the R values of 0.8 and
0.4 show correlation that gets
progressively weaker down to R value of
zero, and
then anti-correlation from minus 0.4 to
minus 0.8 to minus one.
'Kay.
How does this play out?
Well.
Suppose now, you have three samples X, Y,
and Z,
and you calculate the Pearson correlation
coefficient between each pair of samples.
So you get values between X and Y of 0.2,
X and
Z of 0.8, and between Y and Z of -0.6.
The most highly correlated samples here
are X and Z.
So, I've put them together here in this
example and
to express that you want to draw.
You can draw a diagram that will allow you
to show graphically
what's happening, and you can see that X
and
Z are linked by two short branches on a
tree, and the branches go up to .8.
What about sample Y?
Well, you really want to know the
correlation between sample Y and
the mini cluster of X and Z.
One way of doing that is by using the
already calculated values
of the correlation between Y and Z which
is minus 0.6 and
between Y and X which is 0.2, and
take the average of those two numbers, to
give you minus 0.2.
And then, you can take that number and
draw a tree,
extend the tree diagram [SOUND]
to show the relationship between sample Y
and
the mini-cluster X and Z.
And, you can do the same thing with
additional samples, say, for
X prime and so on.
Okay.
So here's an example of real data.
[COUGH]
This shows samples going across the top
and genes going across the bottom.
And you can see a tree diagram showing
decreasing correlation.
In addition, I have to let you know that
the genes are also clustered.
Okay.
So now let's take a look at these samples.
We've kept track of what they are,
we've just allowed hierarchical clustering
to do its thing without any supervision.
So in yellow here are a bunch of samples,
for example from chronic lymphocytic
leukemia, and green here are a bunch of
sample from follicular lymphoma.
In a addition, the largest group of
samples [SOUND]
In blue here come from
an entity called diffuse large B cell
lymphoma.
And you can see that the clustering isn't
perfect, but it's pretty darn good.
All the samples that we know biologically
should be similar [UNKNOWN] are together.
Although it's not perfect, there are few
samples of
diffuse large B-cell lymphoma that have
gone elsewhere in the tree diagram.
Now, in conversely, the diffuse large
B-cell
lymphoma samples are mixed with samples
that came
from germinal center, GC, B-cells.
Okay.
And indeed, a few of the samples among the
diffuse large
B-cell lymphomas look like germinal center
B-cells.
And you can see that not all of them do,
so that what this heirchical clustering
has done is discovered that diffuse large
B-cell lymphomas are heterogeneous,
that some of them are germinal center
type,
and some of them are non-germinal center
type.
And then you can begin to do things that
are medically relevant.
So let's move on.
A second approach is to use supervised
analysis.
Supervised analysis looks at the data with
supervision.
You have information about your samples,
and supervised analysis uses that
information.
Suppose you have two classes of samples.
Thing one and thing two.
Supervised analysis will find the genes
with expression profiles that
differ between thing one and thing two.
An example of how this is done is the
method known as
Significant Analysis of Microarray or SAM.
Now, thing 1 and thing 2 could be samples
from Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma and
Follicular Lymphoma, or they could be
samples from cells before and
after exposure to ionizing radiation, etc.
And you're going to look for
genes,specifically, that are specifically
different between Thing 1 and Thing 2.
And here you see such a gene.
And then you find another one down here.
That's interesting, that's one such gene.
That's green, green, green, red, red, red.
The other one was red, red, red, green,
green, green.
And you look some more and oh, low and
behold here's another one green, green,
green, red, red, red.
And you get really excited.
You've discovered
three genes, but how reliable is that
discovery?
You could do the experiment over and over
again and
see if you keep getting the same answer.
But that's very expensive.
Instead you can do something called
permutation analysis.
And that is to make nonsensical
categories.
You'll call one set of genes T one and T
two, for example.
And of course the way you do this is you
take one of the samples from
Thing 2, say this one, and you move it
over to Thing 1, over here.
And you take one of the samples from thing
one and
you move it over here and call it T two.
So these are nonsensical categories.
And then you look for genes that might be
doing something between nonsensical
categories, and you see, look at that,
green, green, green, red, red, red.
And you can do this again, and call,
make some more nonsensical categories, say
top one and
top two and look for genes, and there's
one, green, green, green, red, red, red.
Now this allows you to calculate what's
called the false discovery rate.
If you get an average, say, of one gene
from nonsensical categories and
three discovered genes from the real
experiment.
So the false discovery rate is one out of
three.
[SOUND]
Or 33%.
In practice, we set our cutoffs to
achieve false subscribery rates much lower
than this, say 5%, 2%, or 1%.
So how does this play out in real life?
Well, here's some real data.
This is data from small, blue, round-cell
tumors,
which pretty much look the same under the
microscope.
And, the supervised analysis was done to
find a set of
genes that distinguish these tumors from
each other.
The tumors that are shown here are all
small, round, blue-celled tumors.
But they're Burkitt's Lymphoma in this
category, and Ewing's Sarcoma
in this category, and neuroblastoma in
this category, and
rhabdomyosarcoma in this category.
And there are a total of 43 genes that are
differentially expressed and
actually distinguish these categories from
each other.
Now, within each category, the data has
been organized by hierarchical clustering,
so that you can see whether there's any
variation among the tumors.
So there you have it, how to analyze gene
expression across the entire genome.
We've talked about two types of methods,
unsupervised methods,
example of which is hierarchical
clustering.
That's an exploration without fore
knowledge that seeks out
new hypotheses somewhat akin to Captain
Kirk.
These are the voyages of the Starship
Enterprise.
Its five year mission to explore strange
new worlds.
To seek out new life and new
civilizations.
To boldly go where no man has gone before.
The second type of method that we've
studied are the supervised methods.
One example of which is significance
analysis of microarrays.
That's a study with foreknowledge that
identifies differences between
sample classes.
It's the diametric opposite, as Dr. McCoy
said to Spock.
Your pulse is 242, your blood pressure is
practically non existent.
Spock replies, the readings are perfectly
normal for me doctor.
Thank you.
And as for
my anatomy being different from yours, I
am delighted.
Thank you
[BLANK_AUDIO]