Hello, students.
We're going to learn about how to measure
gene expression on a massive scale.
We will learn about two methods, DNA
microarrays and RNA sequencing.
So let's get started.
The first topic will be DNA microarrays.
These measure gene expression across the
genome.
They consist of arrays of microscopic
spots containing DNA probes for
every gene in the genome.
The first thing to do is to manufacture a
whole bunch
of these microarrays which can be used
over and over again.
And what you do in the manufacturing
process is you take DNA probes and
you attach them to a solid support.
So as a result, each gene will have a
specific location.
Or, if you want redundancy, multiple
locations.
The strategy of DNA microarrays exploits
our knowledge of the entire sequence for
the human genome.
In the second step you take the RNA sample
and
you label it with say, a fluorescent dye.
And the RNA sample is very
complicated with many kinds of RNA, but if
there is a spot on the solid
support that will hybridize to that RNA
sample, it will, you'll get hybridization,
of the labeled RNA and allow that spot to
light up.
And each spot here,
you'll, this is an example here of what a
microarray would look like.
Each spot reveals the level of expression
for a specific gene.
And under the microscope here, there's a
blow up, you can see that each
spot is lighting up to a different extent
depending on the level of expression.
[COUGH] And you get huge amounts of data.
[SOUND]
Okay.
So, now that you have a snapshot of my,
DNA macroarrays let's move on.
And talk about RNA-Seq or RNA sequencing
concept.
Now in RNA sequencing, you end up
revealing a snapshot of that part of the
genome that's transcribed.
There are a whole bunch of different kinds
of RNAs in the cell.
There are microRNAs, and
I'm going to draw all of the RNAs as
little, short wiggly lines.
So the microRNAs would be these short
wiggly lines, and
you have messenger RNAs, which.
[SOUND] Are longer and have poly A tails.
[SOUND] And finally you have ribosomal
RNAs,
which are the most abundant RNAs in the
genome.
And so I'm going to draw many, many wiggly
lines to indicate that.
The microRNAs are involved in gene
regulation.
The messenger RNAs, are involved in code
proteins.
And the ribosomal RNAs are part of the
translational machinery
that decodes the messenger RNAs.
So, what you want to do if your
interested in studying these things, is
you might want to isolate them.
For example, if your particularly
interested in microRNAs,
you would do a size selection and select
for the small RNAs in the mixture.
So you end up with a pool of microRNAs.
And then the next step is to use pi
throughput or
next generation sequencing methods to
sequence all the microRNAs.
How do you do that?
Well first you have to convert the
microRNAs into DNA and
you need a, a known sequence to get
started.
So, first, you get oligonucleotides,
or n oligonucleotide with a known
sequence.
And then, you get RNA ligase.
[SOUND] To attach these oligos of a known
sequence
to the three prime end of each of the
microRNAs.
And in step three, you anneal a
complementary oligonucleotide primer.
And the fourth step you add reverse
transcriptase, or
RT, to make a complimentary copy of the
microRNAs.
Extending the primers.
What about the messenger RNAs?
Well in the messenger RNAs you do what's
called oligo-T selection.
You have strings of Ts attached to beads,
and
what you do there is, first you take the
sample and
you hybridize to the beads.
And the species that hybridize to
the beads will be those RNAs with poly A
tails.
[SOUND] And in the second step,
you add reverse transcriptase or RT.
And you end up making a CD make copy.
With the messenger RNAs.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now.
What do you do now?
Well, now you use next generation
sequencing to sequence all of
these species, so lets concentrate on, for
now on the messenger RNAs.
So, these are the sequence leads you'd get
from RNA-Seq.
Here's a example of a gene.
And this gene, of course,
has exons in tan and introns in black.
Okay.
And the, when the gene is transcribed into
a pre-RNA it
gets spliced into a mature messenger RNA.
And then using the methods we just
described,
you can get short sequence reads off of
the messenger RNA.
[NOISE] And, what I'm showing you in red
here,
in this microscopic image, are,
are reeds, sequence reeds, that span.
[SOUND] Two exons.
[NOISE] And, they define, splicing events.
[NOISE]
So, let's summarize what we've talked
about.
[NOISE] For DNA micro arrays, we've
exploited the human genome sequence.
And we measure.
[SOUND]
Genomyte expression.
[SOUND] And for RNA-Seq methods, RNA
sequencing methods.
[SOUND]
We also exploit.
The human genome sequence.
[SOUND]
But
with the added exploitation of next
generation sequencing.
We also measure genome expression.
Because the more sequence reads we have
from a particular gene,
the higher the level of expression.
But in addition to that, we can find new
RNAs, unexpected surprises.
So there you have it, class.
Measuring expression across the entire
genome.
Thank you.
[BLANK_AUDIO]