[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
>> Hey, Doctor Lemmons.
Yeah, know what?
I'm here in the ED.
They asked me to come down and evaluate a
patient.
I'm with the neurosurgeon right now.
All right, I'll give you a call when I
know more.
Okay, bye.
Hey, Kevin.
>> Hi.
>> So this is, this is Mr. Williams.
We're coming down to evaluate him, because
a possible subdural hematoma.
>> Mm hm.
>> He just went to the CT scanner.
Looks like he does have a subdural
hematoma that may be expanding.
>> Okay.
>> From what I heard,
he's getting more abtunded.
>> Mm-hm.
>> He's not as responsive.
He has a history of hypertension,
depression, BPH, osteoarthritis, and
type-2 diabetes.
>> Mm hm.
>> Let's go evaluate.
>> Okay.
>> Hello, Mr. Williams.
>> Hi, hi.
>> And who are you?
>> Hi I'm his son.
>> Okay.
>> It's nice to meet you, sir, I'm, I'm
Dr. Jenner.
>> Oh, hi, nice to meet you, finally.
>> Hi, I'm Dr. Chu.
>> Very nice to meet you.
>> Hi.
>> So, in looking at your father's CT
scan,
it looks like his he, he does have a bleed
inside of his brain and we,.
>> Oh, wow.
>> So, that [CROSSTALK].
>> Okay.
>> So we, we do need to do surgery.
>> In,
in talking to the emergency room doctor,
he did say that there was a do not
intubate order that your, that your father
had signed, though, in the past, and
he saw that on his chart on the computer.
>> All right, he never told me about that.
So what, what does that mean?
>> That means, that means that we can't
intubate your father if he
doesn't want us to intubate him,
and put him on a ventilator like we need
to do for a surgical case like this.
>> But you can still take him to surgery?
>> No, we can't take him to surgery unless
we're able to do that
[MUSIC]
>> But he needs to have this repaired,
this, this bleed fixed.
>> He does, he definitely does.
So we're kind of in a, in a conundrum
here.
I, since he's not really talking with us
anymore and
he's, he's, he's not doing so well.
>> Oh, well, yeah.
>> We need to make a decision here.
What do you think we should do, Dr. Chu?
You know, if we don't intubate him and get
a breathing tube in in the next five or
10 minutes, we're looking at a very bad
situation.
Hopefully
>> Well, then let's do it.
>> Yeah, I can't, I can't find the
information on the computer.
>> Can we get the, can we get the DNA
paperwork.
>> I can't find it on the computer.
The computer system just went down.
>> Hm.
>> What do you think we should do?
[BLANK_AUDIO]