[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
>> Hi, I'm Dr. Larry Chu.
>> And I'm Dr. Kevin Jenner.
>> And on behalf of The Stanford
Anesthesia and Informatics Lab or AIM Lab.
I want to thank you for
spending your time with us to learn, about
the essentials of geriatric anesthesia and
more importantly, the perioperative
management of our elderly patients.
This is really an area of growing
importance in anesthesia as we
have many more patients who are elderly
coming in for
surgery, for surgical interventions in the
later parts of their life.
And so, I, I really hope that you will let
your colleagues as
well know about this resource, especially
if you've found useful for yourself.
You know, Kevin Jenner you, he is a,
an anesthesia resident for the Medical
College of Wisconsin.
He came here to the AIM Lab for
a month long research rotation where we
created this project together.
Kevin, I want to give you a moment to
thank people who made
your participation possible.
>> I'd like to thank Drs.
Tom Ebert and Dr. David Warltier of the
Medical College of Wisconsin.
Dr. Ebert is the Anesthesiology Residency
Program Director at the Medical College of
Wisconsin and Dr. Warltier is the Chairman
of the Department of Anesthesiology.
I'd like to thank them for allowing me to
come to Stanford to do this project.
And I'd also like to thank the DW Reynolds
Foundation for funding my participation
in this project through a generous grant
from the Medical College of Wisconsin for
the furtherance of medical education in
the area of geriatrics.
>> Again, thank you so much for
participating in this course with us.
And I look forward to seeing
you for our other AIM Lab
courses to come in the future.
Bye.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]