[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
Hi, I'm Kevin Jenner.
I'm an anesthesiologist resident at the
Medical College of Wisconsin.
I am here today with Dr. Steven Shafer, a
professor of anesthesiology at
Stanford University and the
Editor-in-Chief of Anesthesia & Analgesia.
This session will be about pharmacology
and
how it relates specifically to geriatric
patients.
Thank you for joining me Doctor, Doctor
Schapper.
>> Thank you.
>> To begin with do you have any general
recommendations as far as dosing and
administration of medications as it
relates to geriatric patients
in particular?
>> Well, first, just to say the obvious.
Elderly people need less drug.
And we can talk and we will talk a little
bit about why that is the case.
That's the general rule.
They're going to need less drug.
The key thing though in terms of assessing
the patient and
figuring out what dose to use is to
establish,
not just was is the physical age, but what
is the physiologic age of the patient?
Some elderly patients are, in fact, very,
very robust.
And they would need drug doses similar to
what you or I might need.
A lot of elderly, though, are on multiple
medications.
They have multiple comorbidities.
And these have to be taken into account,
when figuring out what drugs to give.
Additionally because the elderly are
typically on many drugs,
you have to look for the possibility of
interactions with drugs.
So the elderly patient requires a very
careful pre-operative assessment
of exactly where they are in terms of
their physiologic age,
not just their physical age, and also of
the many, many drugs that they're on,
what kind of interactions might affect
your dosing.
Because they are typically on, on multiple
drugs.
So the bottom line is, [LAUGH] they'll
need less.
You can pretty well assume that.
But how much less is really a function of
the polypharmacy,
the comorbidities, and requires very
careful assessment.
>> Okay.
Are there some specific causes that, or
changes in geriatric physiology that
lead to these differences in dosing
requirements for geriatric patients?
>> Well, my perspective is that of a
clinical pharmacologist.
Where I study the drugs,
and I really ask two questions, what is
the end organ sensitivity?
Of course, in anesthesia the end organ is
typically the brain.
And what do the pharmacokinetics look
like?
Pharmacokinetics basically says how high
do the blood levels go for
any given dosage you might give.
And what we see is certain categories of
drugs,
different behaviors in the elderly
patients for the opioids.
We've shown this for fentanyl, alfentanil,
sufentanil, remifentanil.
The elderly brain is simply more
sensitive.
So for the same concentration of drug in
the plasma or in the brain,
the elderly patient's about 50% more
sensitive.
>> So it'll have a greater effect at a
lower blood concentration?
>> Correct.
So, for example, if you're think about,
well, an elderly patient, I want to start
off with a bolus of fentanyl.
My typical starting bolus is 100
micrograms.
If you have an 85 year old patient,
you ought to start with 50 micrograms, or
maybe even less.
And it's not because the levels are
going to be higher.
It's because their brain is more
sensitive.
Conversely, you look at propofol.
The elderly brain has exactly the same
sensitivity to propofol as yours or mine.
The difference, in the case of propofol,
is that any given dose is a slightly
higher concentration.
The physiology around that relates to
what's called volume of distribution.
And the volume of distribution is
basically what size cup are you
pouring the drug into?
In the case of the elderly the cup's a
little bit smaller,
and when you pour it in your concentration
goes higher.
And that's actually a common physiologic
finding.
That elderly patients have smaller volumes
of distribution and
thus they tend to have slightly higher
levels.
So its those two processes, end organ
sensitivity and the kinetics,
primarily around volume of distribution,
that result in recurring of overdose.
>> Does clearance of medication have an
effect as well on how
the medication should be dosed?
>> Absolutely!
Clearance is, is really a fundamental
concept.
However, what's interesting about
clearance is,
where clearance is very important are, is
drugs people take, every single day.
Because their steady state levels, will be
determined by clearance, and
only clearance.
Since our drugs are so rarely at steady
state, when we give our drugs,
particularly our induction drugs,
clearance hasn't had much chance to
operate.
Now the clearance of the elderly is
reduced a little bit, but
not that much because hepatic blood flow,
for example, which is very important for
[UNKNOWN] clearance, isn't reduced very
much in the elderly.
Similarly, cardiac output in the elderly
actually is pretty well preserved.
They have different mechanics as far as
their myocardial function that allows them
to preserve cardiac output.
But by and large cardiac output does not
go down too much in the elderly.
But that gets back to that preoperative
assessment.
You have a patient in heart failure, well,
cardiac output is likely way down.
And they're going to need a substantially
reduced dose,
because of having a having heart failure.
>> Okay.
Are there any you mentioned propofol,
you mentioned opioids.
Are there any other specific drugs that
you would advise caution with
which anesthesiologists use on a day to
day basis?
>> Well, the answer of course, is, is yes.
A drug that I like a lot is ketamine.
And I use a fair amount of ketamine in
patients because I'm a real believer in
multi-modal analgesia.
And I like for patients to have as low an
opioid requirement as
possible after surgery.
But I do find in the elderly that you have
to be very judicious with ketamine.
Because the alteration in sensorium that a
younger person or
a middle aged person thinks is just kind
of interesting, and
they're very comfortable with for the
elderly there is a possibility of
increased confusion and waking up with
said element of post operative delirium.
So for drugs really, it is going to be a
tail of by tail I don't mean T-A-L-E,
but T-A-I-L a long tail of drug effect,
actually if you think of it.
I'm very careful with the elderly to try
to not have an altered sensorium at
the time of wake up which is why I like
using propophal which is associated with
a very clear headed emergence or a rapidly
dissipating mild anesthetic.
>> Okay.
What is your view of benzodiazepines and
their use for preoperative anxiolysis in
geriatric patients?
>> Excellent, excellent question.
And my own practices, I don't use them.
Bezodiozapenes have probably the largest
alteration in
sensitivity of any of the drugs that we
use.
A wonderful study by Bell an colleagues in
2009 as I recall.
Looked at the dose of benzodiazepine as
required for endoscopy.
So its not anesthesia per se its for
sedation for endoscopy.
And what they found is that a 40 year old
might need 10 milligrams, and an 80
year old need one and a half milligrams,
and the actual extrapolation was
that by age 95 you were all set for your
endoscopy with no benzodiazepine at all.
>> [LAUGH] Okay.
>> So, so the whole point is, there's a,
benzodiazepines are hugely sedating in the
elderly.
A very long tail, to the drug effect.
And that's why I tend not to use them at
all in the elderly.
Usually, my approach to the elderly for
angiolysis is to establish rapport,
and not to use pharmacological means.
>> Okay.
As, as far, you did mention a moment ago
about post-operative delirium.
Which is something that,
that's fairly common amongst geriatric
patients after surgery.
There are other conditions, such as
constipation, GI motility problems.
And problems with possible post-operative
apnea that also in
greater incidents amongst geriatric
patients.
>> Yes.
>> Are there specific drugs that you
would recommend using caution with when
dosing, or
just avoiding altogether in geriatric
patients to avoid those things as well?
>> Well for, for all patients but
particularly for geriatric patients,
I really like to provide as much analgesia
as I can from things other than opioids.
The whole notion of opioids sparing,
the side effects we're talking about,
constipation, respiratory depression,
death [LAUGH] from opioid overdose, these
are opioid side effects.
The difficulty though is nothing relieves
pain as well as opioids do.
And so, how can we assist the opioids in
doing that, and that
way reduce the dose of opioids that is, is
required to have a comfortable patient?
So, in the elderly,
I'm very conscious of trying to give other
medications over the course of
the anesthetic, so that when they wake up,
they are as comfortable as possible.
I'm very aggressive with the use of
regional anesthesia in the elderly even if
I have to combine it with a general
anesthetic.
I want the benefits of regional
anesthesia.
Local anesthetics, particularly Lidocaine,
are actually really good
anti-inflammatories.
There's a paper coming out in Anesthesia
and Analgesia that says that
the administration of lidocaine in the
postoperative period,
either intravenously or epidural both were
associated with a substantial decrease in
our acute and chronic pain following
surgery, an interesting finding.
So I use lidocaine.
If I have a block that's fine, if I don't
have a block I just give it intravenously.
But I want to have a local anaesthetic on
board in the elderly patients.
I do like ketamine, I hate the doses down
in the elderly.
And I'll try to cover it so we have some
propophol on board.
But I like the use of ketamine for
multimodal analgesia.
I'm going to use ketamine, I might as well
use magnesium.
There have been studies showing that
magnesium and
ketamine actually have synergy at the NMDA
receptor.
And so, if I use one, I use the, I can use
the other as well.
And essentially, get more NMDA blockage
out of the combination of
the two without really altering the
sensorium as much as if I
were doing the whole thing just with
ketamine.
I also give steroids to the elderly.
A number of studies has
shown that steroids are actually very well
tolerated in single doses.
They don't interfere with wound healing.
They don't increase the rate of infection.
But they are clearly analgesic.
And I'll try to either use gabapentin or
pregabalin for them, if I can add some
acetaminophen, and be careful about of
course because of the concern about liver
injury, but I'll add acetaminophen.
If I can add an NSAID, on an NSAID.
I try to think, what other things can I
bring to the table during the course of
the anesthetic to reduce the dose of
opioids in the elderly especially.
That's important for just the reasons you
said.
They're more likely to have respiratory
depression,
they're more likely to have LAS, and these
can be very,
very serious complications in the
post-operative period.
>> So it sounds like the only constant
when it comes to geriatric patients is
that there's higher, greater variability
amongst the geriatric population with
respect to their physiology and
pharmacology.
Some geriatric patients are more fragile,
while others are more robust.
Is this right?
>> That's exactly right,
and what you do during the course of the
anesthetic is learn which patient it is.
As I mentioned, you start with your
pre-operative assessment,
which gives you a pretty good idea where
you're going to be.
But just as we approach every other
patient,
every geriatric patient is an experiment.
And your job as the anesthesiologist is to
watch the response to your drugs,
be very quick to make an assessment, are
they responding too much,
just what you expected, or too little and
to adjust in real time.
It's how we practice anesthesia every day
with every other patient,
especially in these geriatric patients.
That learning in real time is more
important.
>> As you can see from our discussion
there are several key things to keep in
mind when working with geriatric patients,
specifically relating to pharmacology and
those geriatric patients.
What are some of those key points, Doctor
Shaffer?
>> Well, just to recap what we've just
discussed.
First thing to realize is that elderly
patients are on a spectrum,
from the very healthy elderly.
Where the dosing requirements may not be
very different from you and me.
To the elderly that are very debilitated,
on multiple medications,
where the dosing has to be very carefully
given.
The one thing you can always say is that
the elderly less drug than people who
are at sort of the middle age of life.
But how much less is very variable.
So the first thing is assessment.
You have to assess the patient very,
very carefully to know where they are on
the spectrum.
The next thing to understand is that there
are different aspects to why
elderly need less drugs.
Some of the elderly are more sensitive
because their brains are more sensitive,
for example, in the case of opioids.
Where the dose needs to be reduced by
about 50%.
However, some of the elderly are more
sensitive to
drugs because their pharmical kinetics are
different.
The drugs reach a higher concentration in
the blood.
That would be the case for propophol, but
it's not that big a reduction.
In the healthy elderly, typically the dose
in propophol is reduced about 20%.
Not that large a number.
The other aspect is that the elderly do
not handle some of
the problems that younger people handle,
and specifically drugs like ketamine.
There, there may be a little bit more of a
dis, the tendency for
the elderly patient to have delirium or a
dysphoric reaction to the drug.
So, you have to be very careful using
drugs that alter the CNS in
the sensorium in the elderly patient.
I think those would be the key points for
people to take out of this program.
>> Thank you doctor Shafer.
>> A pleasure.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]