[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
Hi, I'm Dr. Kevin Jenner.
I'm a resident in Anesthesiology at the
Medical College of Wisconsin.
In this module of the Essentials of
Geriatric Anesthesia course, we're going
to be talking to Dr. Lauren Milner, she's
joining me from the Center for
Biomedical Ethics, at Stanford University,
where she's a fellow.
She's also a committee member on
the Stanford Hospital Medical Ethics
Committee.
In this section, we have three objectives.
Those are to first discuss what should be
done with Mr.
Williams in this particular medical
situation.
Mr. Williams has a do not intubate order
that was seen in the computer, but
the computer system in unavailable.
So, how should a medical practitioner act
in the face of
ambiguous information regarding the
patient's wishes?
We'll also discuss the terms capacity,
competence, autonomy and surrogate
decision maker, and discuss how those
relate to making decisions for patients
who may not be able to make decisions on
their own, for their own medical care.
The third objective, will be to discuss
how medical professionals should act
when surrogate decision makers and
advanced directives conflict.
In those situations, what should the
medical,
what should the medical practitioner do?
Especially in emergency situations, this
can be perplexing, and
a decision needs to be made quickly.
Thank you for joining me today, Dr.
Milner.
>> Very happy to be here.
>> So in discussing Mr. Williams, and in
this particular situation, where
there's ambiguous information, how would
you suggest the anesthesiologist act?
So in this particular situation,
it's pretty clear that the
anesthesiologist should intubate.
And the reason for that,
is because although there was a suggestion
of documented evidence of wishes,
we don't actually have any documented
evidence of wishes.
And so, to be on the safe side.
And also because the son, who seems to be
an appropriate surrogate, and
is acting in the best wishes of his father
has said that his father would want to be
intubated.
>> Okay.
So, the anesthesiologist would,
would be doing the right thing in this
situation, to intubate him.
In the absence of a clear directive,
otherwise.
>> Absolutely.
>> Now in, in a situation where there is a
clear directive otherwise and
say you do have a do not intubate or do
not resuscitate order.
And you have a family member who's saying,
no, I, I want to override that.
What do you do in that type of situation?
>> Well, that's a much trickier situation.
But.
And when there's, again, unambiguous
written and
documented evidence of the patient's
wishes, that is what you do.
Even if a family member is protesting.
If the documented wishes are clear, then
that's how you proceed.
>> Okay.
So in an emergency situation,
if you have that documented evidence,
that is most important piece of
information you can have.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So, when it comes to co, some of these
complex issues, some topics and
some ideas are thrown around.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Especially the terms
competence and capacity.
You know, the patient has competence or
is competent to do this or they have
capacity to make this decision.
What exactly is meant by the terms
capacity and,
and how's it different from competence?
>> So that is a great question because
capacity and
competence do get conflated a lot.
So, competence really refers to a broader
situation that goes across time in terms
of their decision making capacity frankly
that's generally decided by the courts and
if a person lacks of competence it
generally means that they can't make any
decisions usually for an extended period.
Now in contrast capacity is both time and
situation dependent.
And can that determination of capacity can
be made by the clinician,
or Psychiatry or the Ethics Committee.
So, just as an example of this,
a patient may not have capacity to make
medical decisions.
But they might have the capacity to des,
assign a surrogate decision maker.
So it really depends, again, on what
you're asking.
And what time you're asking it at.
>> Okay.
>> If that makes sense.
>> It does.
It does.
So it sounds like capacity is,
is much more what we interact with in
a medical world where competence sounds
like it's more of a legal thing.
>> Mm-hm.
>> If a patient has the competence to, to
do something and
that's more of a long standing
determination made by a court.
>> Absolutely.
Again, capacity is really in the moment.
So we think about capacity a lot of times
by asking ourselves does the patient have,
it, do they clearly comprehend and
can they articulate the consequences of
different medical options.
And if they can, and they have a
reasonable rationale for why they want
a particular option, and they understand,
like I said, the consequences of all
the options, then they're deemed to have
capacity to make that choice.
>> Okay.
So as far as advanced directives and do
not resuscitate, do not intubate orders,
what, what is different between an
advanced directive.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And a do not resuscitate order?
Are they different or are they both the
same, what, what do they mean?
>> Oh sure.
So a do not resuscitate, do not intubate
is an order
that's given by a clinician, and that can
really happen at any time,
you can write it in the chart, it's very
fluid, you can make them.
We call it DNRDNI, or or you can make them
non-DNRDNI so where as an advanced
directive is,
is dictated by the patient and it's much,
much more comprehensive, generally.
A DNRDNI would be included in the advance
directive, but there can also, generally
there's instructions on who should be
making decisions for the pace, patient.
If they lack capacity.
There are, instructions on other medical
procedures they,
they would or would not want.
So it's, it's a much, much more detailed
and
thorough documentation of all kinds of
patient's wishes.
And again, that is really dictated by the
patient,
it is much more formal, it generally has
to be signed by a witness, so.
>> Okay, so it is a much more,
the advanced directive is probably what
this patient had in their chart and
in actuality, it's unlikely someone on a
patient we
had just rolled through the door, had
written a DNR or DNI order, so it is very.
It's, it's kind of surprising in this
particular situation.
You would, you would wonder what the
patient ac, actually wanted.
And it would be safe to err on the side
of, of intubating him, like you said,
in the absence of, of additional
information.
So in, in thinking about the patient's
son,
what is his role in this particular
situation.
>> So in this particular situation,
the son would serve as the father's
medical surrogate,
because the father, at this time, would
lack capacity to make decisions.
So that means that he, again, would be
making the decisions for the patient
because presumably he knows the patient
well enough to know his choices.
Certainly better.
Than you, you know, the doctor.
>> Doctor or nurse.
>> Who just met him or you know, a perfect
stranger.
>> Yeah exactly.
Okay.
>> So, until he would basically be
making medical decisions for
the father until such time that the father
could make medical decisions for himself.
>> Okay, and then when it comes to
surrogates,
I hear that there's a lot of complication,
in terms of
determining who exactly the patient's
surrogate decision maker should be.
In this case, it's pretty clear.
There's only one family member.
And it's a first degree relative.
An ad, an adult son of the patient.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Now, when you have a room full of,
you know, 20 family members and some
friends from high school and some other
friends and maybe distant relatives and
adopted children and whatnot.
>> Mm-hm.
>> How do you decide who's going to be the
patient's surrogate decision maker if
everyone can't agree on what should be
done for the patient?
[NOISE].
>> So again, a fabulous question, and I
can't stress enough how variable this is.
It really depends on what state you're
practicing in.
So here in California.
Surrogate decision makers are generally
signed by the medical team and
or the ethics committee if we're
consulted.
And based on how long a person has known
the patient,
if a person has had conversations with the
patient that might be
relevant to the decision that has to be
made.
And basically if they can act in a way,
what we call substituted judgement,
if they can put themselves in the patients
shoes and
decide what the patient would want.
But it really can be anyone an old friend
a neighbor,
it's just it really is dependent on the
relationship.
But that is certainly not true in other
states.
And there are a number of states in which
next of kin
is automatically the surrogate.
Or spouse is automatically the surrogate.
So it's very important that clinicians
know
what the surrogate decision-maker right,
rules are for their particular state.
>> And that would be a good question for
the medical ethics committee if you're
uncertain.
Is that right?
>> Absolutely.
So your medical ethics committee is really
the person or
the group that you can go to when you have
these types of questions.
Because they will know state regulations,
federal regulations, and
hospital policies that are all relevant.
To whatever your, your case or issue may
be.
>> So one of, one of the situations that
we deal with a lot in anesthesiology is
the spec, the suspension of DNR or DNI
order or the suspension of a patient's
advance directives when it comes to taking
a patient to the operating room.
I'm curious about what the timeframe is
regarding starting that suspension and
when that suspension ends.
Is it something that begins the second
they are on the operating room table and
the moment they reach the recovery room
it's over?
Or what, what are the rules and what are
your guidelines or
recommendations about this?
>> So, there really are no hard and fast
rules and,
as you can imagine, that's highly
dependent on the patient.
In some instances it might be appropriate
to suspend the DNR,
DNI as soon as they get into the operating
room,
and then reactivate it wh, the second they
go into recovery.
In other cases, that's not going to be
appropriate,
because they might still be at risk of
certain things while in recovery.
And so, the most important thing for you
to do in this situation is.
To talk to your patient, or
your patient's surrogate, before you take
them into the operating room.
And make sure that everyone's clear about
how long, or
what's appropriate, in terms of the
suspension of the DNR, DNI order.
>> Okay.
So
the patient has to make the decision
beforehand, and
that's the best way to do it.
>> Mm-hm.
Okay.
In, in medical ethics, it just seems
extremely complex.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And
when it comes to working with patients and
working with medically complex issues or
ethically complex issues, who should we
rely on?
Because we don't deal with this every
single day in the operating room.
We don't deal with this every day as an
anesthesiologist.
Who can we go to to help us with this?
>> The Medical Ethics Committee is here
for this purpose.
They are here to help doctors navigate the
incredibly complex
situations that they can get in ethically
especially.
They have a lot of resources.
They will know State regulations, hospital
policies, Federal guidelines,
specific cases, and they're really there
as a resource for doctors as I said to,
to help you deal with these complex
decisions and help you make the decisions.
So any time you have a question about
something like this.
It's very important that you go to your
hospital ethics committee.
>> Okay.
Well, thank you very much for
your time and for joining me today.
>> Oh, it was wonderful to be here.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]