[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
>> Hi, I'm Dr. Larry Chu.
>> And I'm Dr. Kevin Jenner.
>> Welcome back to this course on the
Essentials of Geriatric Anesthesia.
In this segment, we're going to talk about
pain.
Post-operative pain control in the elderly
patient.
We have three learning objectives for you
in this segment.
We're going to talk about how to assess
pain, the fifth vital sign,
especially in elderly patients and the
challenges that may arise there.
We're going to talk about the role of
regional anesthesia in pain management,
and we're going to wrap up by talking
about the WHO ladder and how,
how to use that as a model for pain
management in elderly patients.
So let's get started.
>> Let's get started.
>> So Kevin, talk to me a little bit about
challenges or
unique issues associated with assessing
pain,
which of course we know as the fifth vital
sign, in our elderly patients.
>> Well, it's important to remember that
elderly patients and
geriatric patients in general, may have a
decreased perception of pain.
As a result the same type of insult or
the same type of surgical procedure to a
geriatric patient may not result in
the same level of pain as it would in a
younger patient.
That being said, geriatric patients are
also more less likely to ask for
pain medication.
When it comes to treating their pain,
they're less likely to, to ask a nurse or
a doctor and
say, I have pain and ask for that
medication in order to treat that pain.
When geriatric patients are in the
immediate post-operative period,
that's why it's very important to reassess
their pain frequently and asked them
ever time that they're seen, do they have
pain and how much pain do they have.
Is it something that they find tolerable
or is it something that they deem,
that they would like to have treated.
It's important to use verbal over visual
scales, as well.
When it comes to working with patients,
we use the ten point scale with some
patients, sometimes a visual scale where
we have them point to a card indicating
how much pain they're in.
Studies have shown that the verbal scale
tends to work better than
visual techniques, in terms of identifying
someone's level of pain.
Now, when it comes to the Intensive Care
unit,
that can be a difficult situation, because
patients may be incubated and
assessing pain in them can be more
difficult.
How would you do that Dr. Chu?
>> Well, you know, it's a challenge.
obviously, an incubated patient can't talk
to you.
So, you're not going to be able to use
those verbal scales of assessment.
What you can do, is you can look at vital
signs, for
instance is the patient hypertensive or
tachycardic?
Does do, do those vital signs decrease
when you provide some pain medication.
That can give you some sense of if it's
pain that's causing the,
the, the, the aberration of vital signs.
Of course, you want to look for
also the appearance of discomfort,
grimacing and or agitation.
They can also lead you to suspect pain.
Of course, you have to understand that
post-operative delirium,
can also cause those signs and
you have to be able to in a sense tease
out, whether or not that's the cause.
And of course, you also can have some
confounding by comorbid conditions.
If the patient was on pre existing opioids
before surgery, for instance.
He or she may have some pre-existing
opioid analgesic tolerance, for instance.
And you need to consider that part of the
medical history when you're trying to
assess post-operative pain in these
patients.
And of course finally, in general we need
to
remember that elderly patients not only
perceive pain differently.
They maybe less likely to ask, for pain
medication.
So that's also something we need to
consider in the assessment of pain in
our elderly patients.
>> So we definitely have to make a
decision to offer pain treatment to
these patients, because they may not ask
for it.
Is that right?
>> And that's a very important pieces of
information that we need to keep in mind.
So, Kevin, let's talk a little bit about
regional anaesthesia.
Of course, we know regional anesthesia has
many benefits and we,
we talk about how it has less
side-effects.
How it can be better in managing
post-operative pain.
Does it also help with post-operative
delirium and cognitive dysfunction.
It is something that we should be doing
routinely for
all of our geriatric patients.
>> Well, it, that's a very good question.
Regional techniques for for anes, using a
regional technique for
a surgical procedure has actually not been
associated with a decrease in
post-operative cognitive dysfunction.
So it's important to note,
that the incidence of these things don't
seem to be affected by your choice to do
a general anesthetic versus using regional
techniques.
Some studies are con, contradictory on
this particular subject, but by and
large it sound like there's, there is no
significant or solid evidence that shows
regional techniques prevent post-operative
cognitive dysfunction or decline.
They can however,
be useful to reduce the amount of pain
medication that the patient needs.
Is that right, Dr. Chu?
>> Well, I mean, I, I think that's the
point.
If you, you know,
you want to provide superior analgesia or
minimizing other side effects.
And of course, opioids have a plethora of
side effects.
Not only analgesic opioid, analgesic
tolerance, you, you have you know,
decreased bowel mobility you, you have
pruritus you have sedation.
So, there's a lot of issues associated
with opioids that we
can avoid if we don't use regional
anesthetics.
So, if it doesn't necessarily prevent or
decreased incidence of post-operative
pruritus cognitive dysfunction, at least
we can use regional anesthesia to
decrease the other side effects associate
with opioid medications, in general.
So, Kevin, let's wrap things up.
Let's talk a little bit about this WHO
ladder and
how we might use it as a strategy for
treating pain in our elderly patients.
So, talk to me a little bit about this
division ladder.
Is it an actual ladder that you climb up?
What is this thing?
>> No, it's, it's it's not a natural
ladder.
It's a a mental technique or a mental
cognitive aid to help
you in determining what the appropriate
treatment is for a patient's pain.
The World Health Organization has made it
clear that pain is something that every
patient should have assessed in a medical
setting and pain should be treated,
if at all possible for patients.
It's, it's not something that we should,
we should do as an after thought.
It should be a primary concern of every
provider and,
especially anesthesiologists.
Now, to begin the later, the World Health
Organization re,
recommends using techniques, such as pet
therapy or music therapy,
which may assist the patient in coping
with their pain in the first place.
If the patient is comfortable, but still
has some pain, that's okay.
It's, it's up to the patient to decide
what level of pain they are willing to
tolerate and what level of pain is
comfortable for them.
It's not always possible to completely
eliminate pain.
So, it's important to know that these
things may actually help without getting
rid of pain in a pharmacological method.
In addition, if you're going to start
medications,
it's important to start with non-opioids
first.
Starting with things like NSAID,
non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs or
Acetaminophen can be particularly helpful
for
elderly patients, if they are candidates
for those medications.
It's important to consider their
comorbidities before you decide to
prescribe those medications.
There is a place for opioid medications,
though.
And that's once you've, once you've passed
that rung on the ladder
of adjuvant therapies, such as physical
therapy, or
pet therapy, or these NSAID and
Acetaminophens, then you get to opioid.
>> Well, let's talk a little bit about
that.
[CROSSTALK]
>> So, you know,
the thing is pain has to be treated.
yes, opioids bring with them their own
problems
associated with the side effects such as
decreased bowel mobility or pruritus.
And of course, may contribute to the
symptoms or signs of delirium or
cognitive dysfunction.
However, pain untreated can do the same
thing.
>> Exactly.
>> So, we do need to treat pain.
I think the idea with the ladder is, start
at the low rungs first.
And once we've found that the pain is
refractory to those lower
rung [UNKNOWN] treatments, then we have to
move on to opioids.
But if we're going to use opioids, let's
be smart about it.
Let's start low and go slow and what I
mean by that is, start with low doses, and
escalate those doses slowly until we can
get the pain under control.
In our elderly patients, especially we
want to be checking on them multiple times
a day, so that we don't just write an
order and see them the next day.
We want to know how are they doing after
the morning dose, did that help them?
If we had side effects, what were they?
How can we continually adjust this dose,
until we find the right balance of
analgesia versus side effects.
So re-assessing multiple times per day is
important.
And of course, so that we best understand
what we're doing,
really avoid doing a lot of things at
once.
You're going to look at opioids, let's
look at opioids.
Let's change that part of the pain
management formula and
see how that impacts pain management.
So I, I think that really is the essential
guide for how we can use the WHO ladder
for
guiding post-operative pain
management in our elderly patients.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]