[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
>> Hi, I'm Doctor Larry Chu.
>> And I'm Doctor Kevin Jenner.
>> And we're here today to talk to you
about a new
online course that we're going to be
launching on geriatric anesthesia.
And issues associated with it the
perioperative care of elderly patients.
Kevin, let's start off by just asking this
question, let's get it out of the way.
Are you going to be an expert in geriatric
anaesthesia after completing this course?
>> Absolutely not, this course is designed
as an introductory overview of
geriatric perioperative issues.
In order to become proficient in geria,
geriatric perioperative care, you will
need to seek additional resources and may
need to do additional study in the topic.
>> So we really want to give you an
overview, an introduction and
we're going to do that through several
ways.
We have several modules laid out for you.
We're going to talk a little bit about
physiology.
We're going to talk about pharmacology
associated with elderly patients.
We'll show you some examples in action
where we look at
ethical issues associated with the care of
elderly patients.
And we'll wrap it up with discussing some
post-operative issues.
So if that sounds good, let's get started.
>> Let's get started
[MUSIC]