[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
[SOUND] Wonder who that could be?
Hi, Dr. Levins.
Uh-huh.
Yeah, I know Dr. Harrison and I already
started that case.
Oh, okay.
Well, he, he's an 80 year old gentleman.
He fell at home.
He has a, subdural hematoma, so we're
going to evacuate.
The [UNKNOWN] were uneventful so far yeah.
Oh, I.
[CROSSTALK] No,
I just saw the surgeon come in the room.
Can I call you right back?
Okay.
Hey, Kevin.
>> Hey.
So this guy's an 80 year old gentleman,
subdural hematoma,
pretty straight-forward, craniotomy in
order to evacuate that.
Yeah, I'm going to go get the Mayfield
clamp and
we're going to prepare the turn the table.
>> Okay.
>> If you could make sure he gets,
Ceftriaxone.
>> Yeah.
>> Make sure he's comfortable for
that Mayfield clamp by the time I get
back.
>> Okay, I'll give him some Remifentanil
for that.
>> Okay.
Thanks.
>> All right.
Here we go.
There's the Remifentanil.
There we go, here's the remy.
Let me give him one micro cc.
So that'd be.
One micro kilo, that's two cc.
That's 100 kilos.
All right.
That should get him nice and comfortable.
Okay.
Get some of that, Ceftriaxone going here.
>> All right, I've got that Mayfield
clamp.
How's he doing?
>> Uh-huh.
>> Is he comfortable?
>> yeah.
Whoa, his blood pressure's really dropped.
>> What?
>> His, his blood pressure's
really dropped.
>> What have you given him?
>> I, all I gave him was the Remifentanil.
I haven't given him the antibiotics yet.
What do you want me to do?
>> Can you call my, call my attendee real
quick.
>> Okay.
>> I'm going to have to give him some
pressers here.
Try to get his pressure back up.
>> Yeah we need Anesthesiology staff for
room 6 stat.
Anesthesiology staff to room 6 stat.
>> [UNKNOWN]
>> Is he going to be okay?
[MUSIC]
>> Just give [UNKNOWN].
Let's hope that kicks in.
>> All right.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]