[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
Hi, I'm Doctor Larry Chu.
>> And I'm Dr. Kevin Jenner.
>> And welcome back to this course from
the Stanford AIM Lab
on Geriatric Anesthesia.
Now in this segment, we're going to talk
about delirium and cognitive dysfunction.
The specific learning objectives for this
segment include four things.
We're going to talk first about how to
recognize common causes of delirium in
elderly patients.
two, we're going to talk about some
effective prevention strategies.
We're also going to talk about appropriate
treatment options available for
elderly patients.
And finally, we're going to wrap things up
by talking about the purpose and
safe use of chemical and physical
restraints in the elderly.
So let's get started.
>> Okay.
>> So Kevin, talk to me a little bit about
some of the common causes of delirium and
cognitive dysfunction in elderly patient.
Well, there's several causes and it's best
to divide these up into immediate causes
and things that may occur later in a
patient's post-operative course.
Immediate causes may be things like a
response to discontinuation of
a psychiatric medication in the
perioperative period.
Hypoperfusion of the brain during a
surgical procedure or the post-operative
period, which may lead to a stroke or
other problems with cognitive decline.
In addition, if a patient has a
preexisting disability,
such as hearing loss or blindness.
That may manifest itself or
appear to clinicians as post-operative
cognitive decline,
if that's unrecognized and they don't
realize what's going on with that patient.
In addition, genetics sometimes plays a
role.
Some people are just more prone to
post-operate de,
delirium and cognitive decline than other
patients, and we aren't sure why.
What are some of the late causes, Dr. Chu?
>> Well, so some of the things that we
have to keep in mind is that later
on the patient can, for instance, have
worsening.
Other chronic conditions.
That can be a reason for seeing cognitive
dysfunction or delirium.
Of course, it could be an underlying
dementia that get,
gets unmasked later on, during the course
of the hospital stay.
Even infections, like urinary tract
infections, can cause delirium and
cognitive dysfunction in the elderly.
And of course, we don't want to forget
about disturbances in
strategic rhythm and, and also of course
sleep deprivation.
Being in a hospital, out of their natural
environment,
they just don't get the regular quality
sleep that they're normally getting.
So these are all important considerations
in thinking about the common causes of
delirium, and post-operative cognitive
dysfunction in elderly patients.
Well, now that we know some of the common
causes,
let's talk a little bit about effective
prevention strategies.
It's better to prevent these things from
happening in the first place.
Tell us a little bit about how you can do
that, Kevin.
>> Well, some of the things you can do is
continue a patient's mental health
medications if at all possible in the
perioperative period.
That can avoid things like worsening of a
patients depression which may
lead to cognitive decline and delirium in
the perioperative period.
In addition, if a patient has co-morbid
disease,
it's important to keep those under
control.
Having glucose levels that are very high
or very low maybe lead to
post-operative cognitive dysfunction in a
diabetic patient or in other patients.
So it's important to keep those things in
mind and to keep the patient as close to
homeostasis and normal as possible while
treating what they've preve,
presented to the hospital for in the first
place.
>> Now of course, one of the other things
that's really important is to
maintain really good sleep hygiene.
Right?
We want to make sure we're not waking up
our elderly patients in the middle of the
night unnecessarily.
So that it disturbs their circadian
rhythm, so
that they have really, disbalance in terms
of their normal sleeping patterns.
And it also bears mentioning that we
shouldn't be adding new medications
at this point that may worsen
post-operative cognitive dysfunction or
delirium by adding medications for sleep
or anxiety.
Let's first try to focus on minimizing
those disturbances in the first place so
we don't have to layer on pharmacologic
treatments that may further
complicate the issue.
So Kevin, let's assume we did implement
all of those preventative strategies, yet
we still see delirium or post operative
cognitive dysfunction.
Let's talk a little bit about our
treatment strategy in that scenario.
What are we going to do?
Well, it's important first and foremost to
go and assess the patient.
Keep in mind, delirium and post-operative
cognitive dysfunction lay in a spectrum.
There's some patients who may be extremely
agitated and
combative, and other patients who may just
be somewhat disoriented and
require reorientation in order to bring
them back to where they are.
It's important for a physician to go and
assess the patient before prescribing any
sort of treatment or medication for that
patient.
Also, keep in mind that frequent
reorientation may be needed for
patients and may be preferred to
pharmacologic techniques or
physical restraints depending on the
patient's situation.
Now, in the event of a patient who is
delirious, it's also important to un,
to identify the underlying cause, if you
can do so.
That may involve doing things like
ordering lab tests to see if
there's electrolyte abnormalities.
Or perhaps, studies to see if there's
urine urinary tract infection or
other problems.
Get the entire healthcare team involved.
The nurse, other members, other physicians
and
consultants, and try to figure out what
exactly is causing this.
And treat the underlying cause of their
delirium.
Delirium is usually a result of something
else that's going on.
Now, in the event of needing to use
pharmacological therapies,
things like like sedatives.
Benzodiazepines are, are somewhat risky in
patients who, of the geriatric population.
And it's important to dose those
appropriately for
the physiologic status of the patient that
you're working with.
Other treatments, such as Haldol, again,
need to be dosed appropriately for
a geriatric patient's body.
Every patient is different,
so keep that in mind when you are working
with geriatric patients.
Frequent reassessment will be necessary
too.
Now there is a place for, for physical
restraints as well.
>> There is.
>> What is that?
>> I mean, there, it is appropriate to use
physical restraints when the patient
is endangering themselves.
If you're concerned about fall risks.
But we need to also then be judicious.
And we need to reassess on a daily basis
if we're going to be using restraints.
Of course you may also have the resources
to arrange a one-on-one sitter,
and, and maybe that would be appropriate
for the patient.
And we wouldn't necessarily need to have
restraints.
In either case in this situation, I would
really recommend outreach to the patient's
family so that they understand what the
purpose of restraints are.
Why are we instituting these practices and
more importantly so they can become
engaged in the patient's care.
They can help reorient the patient.
They can be there to support their loved
one as they're recovering from
the surgery.
Of course, we also want to involve our
mental and
behavioral specialists early on in the
course of
the treating post-operative cognitive
dysfunction or delirium.
So we can really get a multi-disciplinary
approach to treating this problem.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]