[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi.
I'm Doctor Kevin Jenner.
I'm an Anesthesiology resident at the
Medical College of Wisconsin.
In this video we'll be discussing the
Essentials of Geriatric Physiology.
It's important to remember that this is
only an overview of this topic.
In order to become proficient, you will
need to do additional study and
seek out additional resources.
Before we begin I'd like to thank Doctor
Larry Chu and
the rest of the staff at the Stanford
Anesthesia Informatics and Media Lab,
here in Stanford, California for inviting
me here to participate in this project.
And for assisting me with the creation of
these videos.
So let's get started.
We'll begin by reviewing the objectives of
this particular module and
this particular video.
After you've finished viewing this video,
we hope that you'll be able to better
explain the concept of functional reserve,
and how it changes as patients age.
In addition, we hope that you'll be able
to describe some of the comorbidities that
are more common amongst geriatric patients
than amongst younger patients.
And lastly, we hope that you'll be able to
explain some of the changes of the aging,
and how they may affect the various
aspects of your anesthetic care and
postoperative care for geriatric patients.
Let's begin by discussing functional
reserve.
Functional reserve is the ability of a
person's body or
organ systems to adapt to and overcome
various physiologic stresses.
And as people age there's an overall
decrease in functional reserve.
The human body becomes less able to handle
physiologic stress.
Physiologic stress may result from injury
or
trauma, or from a surgical procedure or
delivery of an anesthetic.
Hospitalization is also a particularly
particularly common,
physiologic stress, that geriatric
patients may experience.
Keep in mind, not every patient ages in
exactly the same way.
Due to previous co, previous disease,
previous surgeries, or previous injuries.
Some patients may have a less,
less of a functional reserve than other
patients of the exact same age.
This is where the idea of a persons
physiologic age versus their true age
comes from.
When a person's chart says that they are
80 or 85 years old or any other age,
it's important to consider that that is
not a particular effective or
accurate marker at determining how old
that patient's body systems may be.
Patients with extensive comorbidities or
coexisting disease may actually
have a much older physiologic age than
their true age would lead you to believe.
That's why it's very important to perform
a thorough preoperative history and
physical examination on all of your
patients.
And especially on geriatric patients, in
order to determine how their organ systems
may behave under the physiologic stress of
anaesthetic, of an anaesthetic or
a surgical procedure.
In addition, organ systems within each
individual's body
may age differently as well.
Within one body, a person's kidneys or
lungs may behave maybe at
a different physiological age than their
heart or other organ systems.
Keep this in mind as well, since there is
no specific marker to
say how one's organ systems are doing in
general.
Each organ system must be discussed and
evaluated individually within a single
individual.
Frailty is something that we
sometimes hear about in the medical
profession as well.
And it's the concept that if a person's
functional reserve is not large enough or
not great enough in order to withstand a
physiologic stress.
That they may end up disabled or less
functional or
independent than they did when they came
to the hospital for
a procedure or, or prior to the
physiologic stress.
So, prot, frailty is basically saying you
know,
if, if a person is having problems with
organ systems and
then we add to that by performing an
anesthetic or doing a procedure.
That it may actually make things worse to
the point where they can never recover
exactly to the same point that they were
at before they came to the hospital.
Aging is associated with changes in the
brain and
neurologic systems which you should know
about.
These include things like a decrease in
overall cerebral brain mass.
And many patients who are geriatric do
have what could be
diagnosed as cerebral atrophy on head CT
or head MRI scans.
In addition, geriatric patients have a
decreased sensitivity to pain.
And painful stimuli compared with younger
patients.
Geriatric patients are also more likely to
have of these
common comorbidities than younger
patients.
They include things like Dementia,
Parkinson's Disease, Stroke, Peripheral
Neuropathy, Chronic Pain or Depression.
Keep in mind, things like Dementia are
particularly common amongst
geriatric patients, and very uncommon
amongst younger patients.
In fact, 13.9% of patients over the age of
70 have some form of dementia.
To break that down a little bit more,
Alzheimer's dementia,
perhaps the most well known of all of the
dementias is largely affects patients over
the age of 65 years.
In fact 5.2 million of the 5.4 million
total pe, individuals
in the United States diagnosed with
Alzheimer's dementia, are age 65 or over.
That means that, only 200,000 patients who
have Alzheimer's dementia
are under the age of 65 in the United
States.
One in eight patients over the age of 65
has some form of,
some variety or degree of Alzheimer's
dementia.
In addition, Parkinson's disease is more
common amongst the elderly.
Only 4% of patients with Parkinson's
disease are under the age of 50, while
96% of the patients who have Parkinson's
Disease are over the age of 50.
In all there's 500,000 to 1 million
patients in the United States with
Parkinson's Disease at any given time.
And 50,000 to 60,000 additional new cases
are diagnosed each year.
Stroke is also a disease that particu,
strokes are more common amongst geriatric
patients.
In all, there's about 795,000 strokes that
occur in the united states each year,
and three quarters of those are current
patients aged 65 and older.
Pain and peripheral neuropathy are
particularly common in geriatric patients.
A study that was performed and result, and
discussed in the American Journal of
Geriatric Pharmacology.
Of 1,000 geriatric patients living in the
community
with an average age of 75.3 years,
indicated that 74% of those patients
reported that they had pain at some point
during the preceding 30 days.
52% of the patients in that study
indicated that they had pain every day.
And 26% of those thousand patients
indicated that
their pain was agonizing in terms of its
severity.
Keep that in mind when working with
geriatric patients.
They may not be as sensitive to pain as
younger patients but
they may more commonly have daily pain or
frequent pain.
And they may be treated it with over the
counter medications that
it's important you ask about.
In addition geriatric patients suffer from
depression just as
other patient populations do.
Of the 31 million geriatric patients in
this country age 65 and
over five million of those patients have
some symptoms of depression and
one million of those 31 million patients
has some form of major depression or
some degree of major depression.
Keep this in mind as patients may be
taking medications that are related,
antidepressant medications.
And that may include tricyclic
antidepressants which can interfere with
some of the anesthetics or
oth, other medications that we may use in
in anesthesiology.
Next let's discuss Delirium and
Post-Operative Cognitive Dysfunction.
Delirium is defined as a change in mental
status that is characterized by
a reduced awareness of the environment,
and a disturbance in attention.
Both of these characteristics must be
present in order for
the diagnosis of delirium to be made.
Delirium is more common amongst geriatric
patients than amongst their
younger counterparts.
In addition, keep in mind that
post-operative delirium is,
is somewhat different, in terms of it's
prognosis than is medical delirium.
When patients present for a, to the
hospital for a surgical procedure, and
then develop delirium following that
operation, they're more likely to
recover fully from that delirium, than
patients who presented at the hospital for
a medical reason and subsequently
developed delirium during their
hospitalization without undergoing
surgery.
Keep in mind also that studies have shown
that there is a reduced risk of delirium,
in patients who receive a regional
anesthetic and not a general anesthetic.
So regional techniques may be useful in
reducing the risk of delirium in
geriatric patients.
Keep that in mind when choosing the
anesthetic technique that you'll be
using for your patients.
This is particularly important because
there is a well known
associated increase in morbidity and
mortality amongst patients who have some
form of post-operative delirium.
If we can avoid this, it's important that
we try to do so.
Post-Operative Cognitive Dysfunction is
somewhat, is different from delirium,
in that it is a deterioration in
Cognition, that tends to
be temporally associated with the
occurrence of a surgical procedure.
This may be particularly minor or
it may be major in the way it affects the
person's life.
It could be that they have word finding
difficulty for
a few weeks after the procedure that
improves with time.
It may be that they have trouble with
their memory shortly after a procedure,
and that also improves with time.
Post-Operative Cognitive Dysfunction is
something that can occur several days to
weeks after a patient undergoes a
procedure.
And it's important to keep this in mind if
a patient starts reporting some new
symptoms related to their mental health.
Immediately after a, a surgical procedure
and
the time thereabout after that procedure.
Also keep in mind that Post-Operative
Cognitive Dysfunction and
the risk of this is, is not decreased by
the use of regional anesthetic techniques.
So while regional anesthetic techniques
maybe,
may be useful to decrease the risk of a
patient having postoperative delirium.
It does not have the it is not possible
for
regional techniques, at least according to
current research, to decrease the risk of
post-operative cognitive dysfunction in
geriatric patients.
Let's continue our discussion with the
topic of the,
a patient's cardiovascular system and how
that changes as, as a patient ages.
Some of the changes that commonly occur in
geriatric patients include things like
decreased elasticity of the great vessels,
and the arterials.
There's also an increased risk of ple, of
the presence of atherosclerotic plaques.
And there are altered cardiac dynamics
that are important to
understand as a result of the previous two
conditions.
Or just due to a patients aging myocardium
and myocardial structure.
Comorbidities are particularly common
related to the cardiovascular system.
And these should be of particular interest
to the anesthesiologist,
since Anesthesiology is often referred to,
as the practice of autonomic medicine.
And the cardiovascular system is
particularly sensitive to changes in
autonomic physiology.
Patients may have comorbidity such as,
hypertension that's been long standing or
poorly treated over a long period of time.
They may have coronary artery disease or
have undergone previous cardiac surgery,
which may affect your anesthetic
management or anesthetic plan.
In addition they may have cerebral
vascular disease or
peripheral vascular disease that may it,
raise your suspicion for cardiac
disease or coronary artery disease, that
may not have been diagnosed in a patient.
Patients who are older also have an
increased risk of valvular disease such as
aortic stenosis, or other, or mitral
stenosis.
These things may occur more commonly in
geriatric patients than in
their younger counterparts.
And may be undiagnosed prior to your
physical examination in
the preoperative setting with that
patient.
Also, keep in mind that if a patient has
cardiovascular disease.
They may have an impaired ability to
exercise.
Which indicates an overall decrease in
functional reserve,
as we discussed earlier.
As patients age, there's also a decreased
response decreased responsiveness of
beta receptors, beta adrenergic receptors
too sympathetic stimuli.
As a result, the central nervous system in
geriatric patients tends to increase
the output of sympathetic tone in order to
cause the, cause
the same amount of increased beta response
in that an organ, in this case the heart.
So, as patients age there's a decreased
level or decreased sensitivity to beta
receptor stimuli to beta, beta adrenergic
stimuli.
And geriatric patients, as a result, are
commonly in a, in a what's described as
a constantly or chronically
sympathetically stimulated state.
In addition, diastolic dysfunction is
particularly common
amongst geriatric patients.
We'll discuss that next.
It is particularly important to
keep Cardiac Diastolic Dysfunction in mind
when working with geriatric patients.
Diastolic dysfunction is more common
amongst geriatric patients than
amongst their younger peers.
With diastolic dysfunction, there is an
abnormality of left ventricular filling,
as a result of a change in the timing of
diastole and
systole, in the cardiac cycle.
When working with, when reviewing the
cardiac cycle,
there's normally a extended period of
diastole.
During which the left ventricle relaxes
and
the left atrium provides some contribution
to filling.
When there is severe or moderate diastolic
dysfunction.
It's, there's a shortening of diastole in
the heart, and during the cardiac cycle,
and a prolongation of cystally, in the
cardiac cycle.
As a result, there's less time for
left ventricular relaxation, and less time
for filling of the left ventricle.
As a result, the left atrium must make a
greater contribution to
left ventricular filling.
And, if there's left atrial pathology or
dysrhythmia, there can be a,
this can lead to severe symptoms or
changes in a patient's physiology.
As they may not be able to tolerate this
change in cardiac output well.
Keep in mind that this is more, diastolic
dysfunction is
more common amongst geriatric patients
than amongst younger patients.
In fact in a review of patients who are 50
years and
younger who have some form of heart
failure,
only 15% of them have heart failure as a
result of diastolic dysfunction.
The vast majority are affected by some
form of systolic cardiac dysfunction.
However, when considering patients who are
70 years old, or older,
who have heart failure, over 70% of them,
have cardiac diastolic dysfunction,
that's directly contributing to their
heart failure.
This diastolic dysfunction lies on a
spectrum, keep in mind some patients may
not have any symptoms or may have very
mild symptoms that
they don't feel comfortable or that there
necessary to report to their doctor.
Diastolic Dysfunction may become worse in
the perioperative period due to
arrhythmias or dysrhythmias, or other
problems related to cardiac volume status.
Keep in mind the left atrium is having to
contribute more to the cardiac out,
to left ventricular filling and therefore
to cardiac output.
So anything that affects the rhythm of the
heart, or
left atrial function, may make diastolic
dysfunction worse.
Since patients are often undiagnosed or
asymptomatic who have diastolic
dysfunction, it's important for
you, as the anesthesiologist to keep this
in mind when assessing the patient.
Even if they don't have symptoms or any
other sort of
marker that would lead you to think that
they have diastolic dysfunction.
This may affect your anesthetic plan as
well, if you diagnose a patient with this,
or you know they have diastolic cardiac
dysfunction.
The, the hypothesis for why patients are
elderly or
geriatric, more commonly have diastolic
cardiac dysfunction, is that a,
a patient of that age group tends to have
less elastic great vessels and arterioles.
As a result of this decreased elasticity,
there's a decrease in the pressure transf,
transference by those vessels to the end
organ with each beat of the heart.
As the heart beats, much of the pressure
of cardiac, systole,
goes into causing a expansion in the great
vessels, based on their elasticity.
And tr, those vessels then, transfer that
pressure downstream to
the end organs and other tissues that are
perfused by the cardiac circulation.
As the vessels age, there is less of that
elasticity in the great vessels and
the arterioles, and as a result, the
myocardium must eject or
must contract for a longer period of time,
in order for
the same pressure wave to reach the end
organs and stay at those end organs.
To profuse them through the small
capillaries and small vessels that
are there which tend to be higher
resistance than the larger vessels.
In, in order to profuse those areas, that
cardiac systole or
ejection must be maintained for a longer
period of time.
Since that is occurring, the cardiac cycle
is in effect altered.
And as a result, systole is lengthened.
And diastole is shortened.
With less filling time available,
the left ventricle requires to a greater
degree on left atrium activity in
order to fill the left ventricle during
that shortened diastolic period.
If patients already have some difficulty
with profusion, or
difficulty with end organ disease.
Any interference in cardiac output, as a
result of arrhythmia, or dysrhythmia, or
a left atrial dysfunction may result in
serious complications for the patient.
That's why this is so
important to keep in mind when working
with our geriatric patient population.
Next, we'll discuss some of the changes
that can occur with a patient's lungs and
pulmonary system.
When it comes to geriatric physiology and
aging.
Some of the changes that commonly occur
include things like
changes in lung volumes, and decreased
compliance of the lungs.
There's also a change in central responses
to hypoxemia, and hypercarbia.
Patients become less sensitive to these
stimuli, so
the hypercarbia may not induce a patient
to begin breathing at a same,
at the same level in an 80 year old as it
does in someone who's much younger.
In addition, hypoxemia may not result in a
drive to take a breath
in an elderly patient.
At the same level as it does in a younger
patient.
These are important to remember, since
we're working a great deal with
pulmonary physiology in the operating
room, when we're delivering anaesthetics.
In addition, closing capacity, which is
the capacity at which or
lung volume at which a patient's small
bronchioles close and small airways close
thereby causing transient atelectasis in
small airways and small alveoli.
That's the capacity at which that closing
occurs in distal airways.
So closing capacity increases as a patient
ages.
And that means that as we age the closing
capacity becomes much closer to and
eventually does exceed the functional
reserve capacity,
functional residual capacity of our lungs.
So patients who are over the age of 65 are
more likely to have chronic atelectasis in
the distal portions of their small airways
than patients who are under that age.
As a result, there's an increased
ventilation and
perfusion mismatch in these patients.
And that's important to remember since
they,
again, don't have the same functional
reserve as patients who,
don't have, who are younger, and don't
have such a high closing capacity.
This'll be illustrated on the next slide
with a graph that demonstrates where this,
overlap occurs.
Comorbidities are particularly common in
geriatric patients.
And they may include things like, COPD and
Atelectasis.
They may also be more prone to pleural
effusions as a result of
electrolyte disturbances or other changes
in their pulmonary physiology.
Keep in mind, geriatric patients have,
have a longer life span during which to
accumulate damage from nicotine or tobacco
exposure.
Or environmental or workplace hazards
which may lead to lung disease.
If we look at the pulmonary volumes of an
individual as they
age by enlarged, the biggest change to
notice is the closing capacity, and
how that changes as patients age.
Closing capacity eventually increases to
the point
at which functional residual can, it
exceeds functional residual capacity.
When that happens,
those small airways in the distal
pulmonary system are chronically closed.
And they only open with coughing or
with particular maneuvers that might
increase a patient's lung volumes temp,
temporarily until they have an opportunity
to close again.
When patients are just breathing at steady
state and
on normal, on room air though, they may
chronically have
some atelectasis going on in the distal
segments of their airways.
Lastly, let's talk about the Renal system
and
how a patient's kidneys may change with
aging.
Keep in mind as patients age there's a
decrease in renal mass of
approximately 30%.
Compared to with when patients were in the
prime of their lives, and
they're much younger.
There's also a decrease in the number of
functional glomeruli,
also of approximately 30% compared with
when patients are younger.
Decreased muscle mass decreases the amount
of
creatinine released into the bloodstream.
So, patients with renal dysfunction may
not present with an elevated creatinine.
Unlike patients who are younger and have
renal disease.
Without that muscle mass, there's not as
much creatine that needs to be cleared,
and the kidneys may be able to clear it
quite easily.
In which case,
your laboratory result may indicate that a
patient's kidneys are functioning fine.
For the muscle mass that they have.
But the kidneys may not behave in the same
way when working to metabolize or
clear a medication that you administer.
This is important because many of the
medications we administer in
anesthesia are, are cleared by the kidney
or metabolized by the kidney.
And their metabolization may be altered as
a result of this decrease in
renal mass and renal function.
There's also a change in a patient's
thirst center responses and
many geriatric patients have a decreased
drive to drink, and as a result,
they may be chronically dehydrated.
Keep this in mind as patients may come for
a procedure and
may be more dehydrated from being NPO or
nothing by mouth.
For the preoperative period,
as well as just not drinking as much water
prior to becoming NPO.
So, when patients present, they may be
already quite dehydrated and
may need additional fluids during the
procedure,
depending on what the planned procedure
and anesthetic are.
There are comorbidities that are more
common, amongst geriatric patients,
related to the kidneys.
These include things like con,
chronic kidney disease, which is often
undiagnosed.
In fact, in the Jour, American Journal of
Kidney Disease in 2010, a study was
performed, in which, a, extremely large
cohort of geriatric patients was assessed.
For the presence of renal disease.
They took one sample group and ran
standard tests on that sample group,
in order to determine how many actually
have renal disease,
that could be diagnosed by a physician.
Of all of the people that they tested,
over 7,000 who were selected at random,
they did not have any, comorbidities that
made them think they were more likely or
more less likely to have renal disease to
begin with.
44% had some form, or some degree, of
chronic kidney disease.
When they took a random sample of medicare
beneficiaries of the same age, age 65 and
older, they found that only 7% of medicare
beneficiaries in the, the group that
they sampled had some diagnosis of chronic
kidney disease or renal failure.
So there's a large portion of our
population,
our geriatric population that has
undiagnosed renal disease.
And they may be coming to us for
procedures and we're tricked, or
we don't understand necessarily that they
have this renal disease.
Because the creatinine or other lab values
that we see,
don't indicate that they have renal, renal
disease.
Because their muscle mass is less, and
they don't have as much creatine to clear.
So keep this in mind, when we're working
with our geriatric patients,
they may have undiagnosed renal disease.
In addition, chronic dehydration,
can be very important, especially in the
postoperative period.
Patients who are elderly may not have as
much as a drive for thirst, or
a drive to drink water as other patients.
And as a result it may be more difficult
to transition them from IV fluids in
the postoperative period, to a diet or a
full diet and discontinue those IV fluids.
Keep that in mind that the ins and outs
for geriatric patients need to be
monitored somewhat more closely than for
more robust patients.
In order to determine if they're consuming
enough water for their hydration needs.
Also keep in mind that renal diseases
often
renal disease often occurs simultaneously
with other diseases.
Hepatorenal system syndrome is one of the
better known
multiorgan diseases involving the kidneys,
but other ones do exist, as well.
Renal disease may actually be an indicator
or
a marker of another medical condition that
needs to be diagnosed and
treated in order to help the patient's
overall health.
To conclude I'd like to thank you for
watching this video.
And we hope that you found it useful in
raising some of
the important points about geriatric
physiology, that may not commonly be
covered prior to taking a geriatric
patient to the operating room.
Or for an anaesthetic outside the
operating room.
When geriatric patients come to your, your
hospital or your clinic, it's important to
remember that, in general, there's an
increase in variability amongst these
patients, both between patients and within
a single patient.
True age does not equal physiologic age,
and
physiologic age does not equal true age in
the vast majority of patients.
Some geriatric patients are particularly
robust and have
a great functional reserve while other
ones, have a minimal functional reserve.
And could be upset or
have severe complications as a result of
any type of physiologic stress.
Those two patients may be of the same true
age, but
their physiologic age may be very
different.
Within an individual the organs systems
may age differently or
have different diseases that result in the
appearance of differing ages of those
organs or different, differing functional
reserves of those organ systems.
Keep this in mind too,
when you're evaluating patients before
taking them for surgery.
Also keep in mind that when geriatric
patients present with a disease,
they are more common, they more commonly
present with an atypical presentation.
They may have differing signs and
symptoms than what you're used to seeing
in patients who are younger.
And you may need to think a little bit
more outside the box when
working with geriatric patients.
We hope that you found this useful and
specifically the parts about the various
organ systems.
We hope that you found that particularly
useful since geriatric patients are more
commonly affected by comorbidities that
may play a role
in your anesthetic management and
anesthetic planning for those patients.
Thank you again, and we'll see you next
time.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]