This video is going to review for you the
mechanism of homologous recombination.
Homologous recombination will actually
repair DNA double-strand breaks.
And here is a picture of a DNA
double-strand break.
And here is a picture of homologous DNA
that is going to be
used as the template for repairing that
double strand break.
And I'm going to be very careful about how
I draw this diagram because I'm going to
put in the five prime and three prime ends
of the DNA at every location.
And, I've drawn with 5 prime and 3 prime
ends of
the homologous DNA in a way that will
allow the diagram to be very simple.
So, the first thing that happens after the
double strand break is created.
To send this down the pathway of
homologous recombination.
An exonuclease has to come along and
remove some of the DNA near the double
strand break, indeed,
what the exonuclease will do, is chew back
DNA to leave 3 prime protruding ends.
So I'm going to have my nuclease come in.
And create 3 prime protruding ends.
Then, after the 3 prime protruding ends
are created, one of the two, three prime
ends can then be used to hybridize the DNA
from the homologous chromosome.
So.
The homologous chromosome, which is drawn
in red,
then has to be partially denatured.
I'm going to draw it right here.
So here's the 5 prime and 3 prime ends.
Okay?
And.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Some of the DNA here is displaced.'
Kay?
And there are proteins that allow this to
happen.
In fact, the protein that allows this to
happen is RAD51.
So here is the protruding, over here is
the protruding
3 prime over hang, and you can do strand,
what's called strand invasion.
And, and it can invade the homologous DNA
duplex.
To displace one strand.
Now there is another strand of DNA from
the DNA double strand break.
And that strand I'm drawing right here.
Again, I'm going to keep track of the 5
prime and 3 prime overhangs.
All right.
So, now that strand invasion has occurred.
It has displaced some of the homologous
DNA,
the intact, from the intact chromosome.
And that is, that displacement forms a
structure that we call a D loop.
And the reason it's called a D loop is, if
you're falling asleep during this lecture,
your head will tilt 90 degrees, and you'll
suddenly wake up to see the letter D.
Okay.
Now that we've formed a D loop, DNA
polymerase can come along.
And at this point at this 3 prime
overhang,
it can begin copying the homologous DNA.
Similarly on the opposing strand, DNA
polymerase can copy the displaced DNA.
When this copying finishes,
ligase can bring the strands together on
the upper strand.
And when this copying gets to a certain
point, ligase can join.
And now what you have here is the
formation of two holiday junctions.
And this holiday junctions then need to be
resolved.
The reason this pathway has become very
important recently is because,
[SOUND] patients who have a hereditary
breast cancer,
because they have a mutation in either one
of two genes, BRCA1 or BRCA2.
BRCA1 or BRCA2.
If patients have, are carriers for
mutations in either of these genes,
they have a very high risk for getting
either breast or ovarian cancer.
Such patients have strong family histories
and the syndrome is
called Hereditary Breast and Ovarian
Cancer.
These genes are involved in homologous
recombination.
And their involvement in homologous
recombination is
to load RAD51 onto the protruding singe
strands, and
I'm going to draw some RAD51 molecules,
here's RAD51,
and here's the molecule, a little circle.
And these RAD 51 molecules.
Basically, facilitate the formation of, of
D-loop.
They facilitate stranded vision and
formation of the D-loop.
BRCA1 and BRCA2 work together to load
RAD51 onto
the protruding 3-prime overhangs.
So.
Tumors that arise in patients who have,
who are carriers for
mutations in BRCA1 and BRCA2.
All of those tumors have knocked out both
alleles of BRCA1 or both alleles of BRCA2.
And as a result their tumors are defective
in homologous recombination.
And recent developments have now
introduced drugs that can potential be
used to treat breast cancer.
Because they actually make cells defective
that are defective in,
homologous recombination particularly
susceptible.
While leaving, the patient's normal cells
alone because the patient
is heterozygous for mutation in
[INAUDIBLE] and so those cells,
those normal cells, have normal amalgamous
recombination.
Anyway, this is a very important pathway
and
I hope this has made the formation, of
these holiday junctions clear to you.
Thank you