Okay.
This is,
chapter three of our series on Homogolous
Recombination.
Here, we're going to describe something,
called unequal crossover,
so in unequal crossover, you can actually
get something called Gene Duplication.
And what I am going to do is, diagram for
you how this can happen.
The only way you can have unequal
crossover of courses, if
you have crossover and in the last section
we described how crossover can occur.
If you resolve the two holiday junctions
with one longitudinal cut and
one transverse cut.
And so I've drawn for you, or I've kept
for you here the diagram
of the cuts in the holiday junctions that
will lead to crossover.
And as a result of this you will have
a blue chromosome turning into a red
chromosome from here this blue chromosome.
Okay.
On the other side of the resolution of
the resolution of [INAUDIBLE] will
continue on as a red chromosome and
this red chromosome over here will
continue on as a blue chromosome.
Because the transverse cuts lead to
crossover.
So now imagine that you have a genome
where there are homologous sequences
scattered throughout.
Let me give an example.
This, and this did happen to the beta
globin gene.
Suppose you have beta globin genes and,
one beta globin gene and
it's surrounded by repeated sequences.
So I'm going to draw for you a beta globin
gene.
Here is a beta globin gene.
All right.
And it's surrounded by repeated sequences.
So this beta globin gene is surrounded by
repeated sequences.
And I'll draw for you a repeated sequence.
And in fact let's call this repeated
sequence, let's just in fact it's true.
That there are sequences called line
elements that actually,
could flank the beta globin gene.
So let me call this line element L1.
Okay?
L1.
And again, this is the beta globin gene.
And I'm going to describe to you how
unequal crossover can generate
duplication of the beta globin gene.
Imagine that the DNA undergoes homogolous
recombination but
it undergoes homogolous recombination by
lining up the homoged chromosomes.
But occasionally, it can produce a
misalignment because of these,
presence of these repeated sequences.
And as a result of that misalignment, this
is what could happen.
So, let me draw the beta globin gene over
here.
All right?
And there's another line element.
I'm running out of space, but bear with me
and
over here, the other side of the beta
globin gene
with the other line element that flanks
it, so.
So suppose during that homologous
recombination occurs.
By searching for the homology between the
line element on the upper chromosome and
the line element on the lower chromosomes.
As a result of that the homologous
recombination if it occurs between these
two line elements will lead to a
misalignment of the DNA.
And that will result in what's called a
cross-over.
I'll use that as the notation and
the way that would happen of course is by
homologous recombination up here
because we're going to imagine that the
line element L1 is here in
this region, L1, line.
Okay.
So the homologous recombination would be
occurring between two line elements.
So I've drawn say a blow up of the line
element here in the upper panel.
And and then you'll have resolution of the
holiday junctions.
In a way that leads to crossovers.
So this, this X here, indicates the
crossover.
As a result of that crossover,
you now have a resolution into two
different chromosomes.
One chromosome will have, two beta globin
genes.
So the upper chromosome here,
let's draw that in, we'll have one beta
globin gene.
Okay.
So you have one beta globin gene,
along with its line element, L1.
Okay.
And then you come over here, to this
downstream line element,
you have a modest combination with a
crossover.
And so, you would end up with a line
element.
Right?
.
Let's line them up.
Let's line up the line elements.
Oh boy.
Bad pun.
Okay.
Here we go with a second beta globin
gene and it's downstream line element.
Okay.
And, the lower chromosome will start
over here.
Do the un, the crossover, and come up
here.
And as a result of that.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You'll have this kind of a chromosome with
only a single line element,
and no beta globin genes.
So as a result of this unequal crossover,
one chromosome now
has two beta globin genes, and the other
chromosome has no beta globin genes.
And again, these are the products of what
we call unequal crossover.
So this is unequal.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Crossover.
And you can see, that this type of unequal
crossover can now lead to
a chromosome with no beta globin genes.
Or think of another situation, where you
have a primordial globin gene.
You may already know that there are many
different globin genes.
There's an alpha globin, there's a beta
globin and so on.
And what may have happened long ago was,
that there was a single globin gene,
flanked by repetitive sequences like this
line element to L1.
That primordial globin gene could've been
duplicated into two different primordial
globin genes which then could evolve
separately one to eventually becoming
the beta globin gene and the other
eventually becoming the alpha globin gene.
So that's how unequal crossover works.
Thank you.