This is Chapter 2 on our series on
Homologous Recombination, and
what this is, is going to be a description
of holiday junctions are resolved.
So I'm starting out with a diagram,
showing the formation of two holiday
junctions.
Following a double strand break in the
blue chromosome, and
the formation of the holiday junctions by
forming a D loop in conjunction
with the intact red chromosome, which did
not have the double strand break.
I've colored the DNA carefully.
According to the sequences that were
copied, so that when,
when a sequence was copied from three
prime overhang of the blue chromosome,
for example right here, but it was copying
off of the right chromosome,
I've drawn in red, and similarly down
here.
Where there's a three pry man for
the, blue chromosome that was then used as
the primer
for synthesizing DNA from the red
chromosome, so that's all in red.
So, this is two holiday junctions.
Now, holiday junctions.
Can be resolved by making cleavages,
because these two
chromosomes are now attached by the DNA at
two different locations.
And so, one way of making the cleavages is
by making two longitudinal cuts.
So, I'm going to draw in.
They cut here, okay?
That's a pair of longitudinal cuts, and I
could draw a pair of longitudinal cuts
here, and here, and
if I do make those cuts, then all I have
to do is take.
The three prime end of the blue chromosome
up here,
and join it to the five prime end of this
red piece of DNA.
So, that as a result of those two cuts, I
am now going to have the following.
So we're going to draw that in.
I'll have the red chromosome, and then the
red DNA and now the blue DNA.
So the 3 prime end, 5 prime end.
And now I'll put-
I'll put in what happens to the upper
strand, upper DNA here,
the upper piece of DNA.
I'm going to have the three prime end over
here, and we're going to come over here.
And we're going to come up to a cut on
that strand.
And that cut
[BLANK_AUDIO]
will allow
ligation.
At this point, let's continue with the
cuts at the other holiday junction.
So, this bottom strand on the upper
chromosome, is going to end up,
being joined, right at this point.
Okay.
After those cuts.
Now let's draw the resolution of the
holiday junction and
how it affects the bottom chromosome.
And as you can see, I'll draw this for
you, the bottom strand
of the bottom chromosome of course is
intact, nothing was ever done to it.
But the upper strand of course after the
cuts.
What will happen is, red DNA will get
ligated
to red DNA, there may be a little bit of
blue here,
but then that will be ligated to the red
DNA.
Just so.
Okay.
So the bottom strand of DNA
here is going to be virtually, completely
red.
So the intact, the original intact DNA
has, is been restored.
after the resolution of the holiday
junction.
The difference is the upper strand -
the upper DNA molecule, now has been
repaired by copying from
the anti chromosome and that's the areas
that were copied are shown in red here.
And this kind of resolution of the Holiday
junction,
actually converts some of the sequence in
the blue chromosome to red sequence.
And if the sequences aren't exactly the
same, you're going to have a,
a slight difference.
Of course, since this is modest
recombination,
the sequences are pretty close to the
same.
But.
There will be some differences depending
on whether the blue chromosome and
the red chromosome have exactly the same
sequences.
And, because they're slightly different,
we call this process here gene conversion.
So, the damaged chromosome has undergone a
gene conversion.
All right.
Now, there is a different way you can
resolve the holiday junctions and
we're now going to talk about that.
So I'm going to erase this way of
repairing, or
resolving the two holiday junctions and
show you a different way to resolve them.
So let's get the eraser, get ride of gene
conversion here.
And let's see -
I'm going to be judicious in how I do
this,
because I'm going to make one pair of cuts
the same.
And so, one pair of cuts will still be
these longitudinal cuts that I drew
previously.
But the other pair of cuts are going to be
transverse cuts, and
here are the transverse cuts.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
All right, now as a result of those
transverse cuts.
I'm going to have a different species.
So.
Let me erase things here.
Let's see, let's clean this thing up a
little bit.
Let's get rid of that.
Now, we're going to make these transfers
cuts and
I'm going to show them to you here.
Where the cuts are.
So imagine that this enzyme here nicks the
DNA.
Boom!
There it goes, and boom!
There it goes.
Let me restore that arrow so you can
remember where the cut was.
There you go.
And so, that is where the transverse cuts
are.
Now keeping track of the 3 prime and 5
prime ends, all right.
There's going to be a 3 prime end over
here.
Okay?
And a 5 prime end on this side of the cut.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
All right.
And
[BLANK_AUDIO]
there is no cut here, so this is still
okay.
And, there is no cut over here, so this is
still okay.
Alright.
But there was a cut down here, so I'm
going to redraw it for
you, drawing in the five prime and three
prime ends.
So.
I've made these two cuts.
I have four single stranded ends.
And those have to be rejoined in a common
attoric recombinational way.
So.
This.
Three prime end is going to end up joined
to this five prime end.
And this three prime end is going to be
joined to this five prime end.
So.
Let me denote that in the following way.
Just so we can keep track of bookkeeping.
I'm going to make a triangle here cause
this three prime end.
Is going to be joined to this five prime
end.
That's a triangle and it's two red pieces
of DNA.
Okay?
And then I'm going to make,
a circle over here to denote.
Which two ends are going to be joined?
So, the circles will be joined.
One circle from the red DNA and one circle
from the blue DNA.
So that's how these things are going to be
joined.
So now, all we have to do is redraw this
sort of unfolding things,
and the way we can unfold things.
Is we can flip this strand and this strand
over,
and let me just draw an arrow for you.
So there's going to to be a flip between
these two, and
I'm going to show you how that looks as a
result.
What you're going to see now
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This is the first half, and
then this is going to be that triangle on
the upper strand.
That's going to be joined to the triangle
on the lower strand after the flipping.
Okay.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this piece of DNA has been
flipped over
at this end.
This is intact, nothing has happened to
it.
So, that's the 5 prime in.
That's, now, the new upper DNA.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And now, the lower DNA, I'm going to draw
in here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
No.
My prime end, and here's the five prime
end of the lower DNA.
All right.
Remember
[BLANK_AUDIO]
that's going to be joined to the circle on
the upper strand, so
I'm flip that over to the blue DNA.
So I'm going to actually make a little
blue circle, so
you can see that it came together.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
All right.
And actually, let me draw just so you can
see that
there are two triangles here, and two
circles on the bottom.
So now you have two chromosomes that have
been restored and
they have been separated by resolution of
the holiday junction.
The resolution occurred, because of a
longitudinal cut.
At this holiday junction, and a transverse
cut at this holiday junction.
And as a result of the combination of the
longitudinal cut and
the transverse cut, okay?
What I end up with, is a chromosome, an
upper chromosome here,
that's starts out blue and ends up red.
And a lower chromosome here that starts
out red and ends up blue.
And so that is not an easy thing to draw
so
we have to congratua, congratulate
ourselves.
And, say Voila!
All right, what is this product called?
This product, this method of, or this
particular way
of resolving the two holiday junctions,
these products are now called a crossover.
So, I'll just write that.
Crossover from homogeneous recombination.
Okay, that was very complicated, but
if you keep track of the five prime and
three prime ends of the DNA.
You should be fine, so thank you very
much.