[SOUND]
This
is chapter two on our series on homologous
recombination, and what this is, is
going to be a description of how holiday
junctions are resolved.
So I'm starting out with a diagram showing
the formation of two Holliday junctions,
following a double-strand break in the
blue chromosome, and
the formation of the Holliday junctions,
by forming a D-loop in conjunction with
the intact red chromosome, which did not
have double-strand break.
I've colored the DNA carefully according
to the sequences that were copied so
that when, when a sequence was copied from
three time over
pane of the blue chromosome for example,
right here, but
it was copying off of the right chromosome
by drawing red and similarly down here.
Where there's three prime end for
the blue chromosome that was then used as
the primer for
synthesising DNA from the red chromosome
so that's all in red.
So this is two holiday junctions.
Now, holiday junctions can be resolved by
making cleavages, because
this two chromosomes are now attached by
the DNA at two different locations, and
so, one way of making the cleavages is by
making two longitudinal cuts.
So, I'm going to draw in.
They cut here.
'Kay.
That's a pair of longitudinal cuts,
and I can draw pair of longitudinal cuts
here, and
here, and if I do make those cuts, then
all I have to do is take.
The three prime end of the blue chromosome
up here, and join it to
the five prime end of this red piece of
DNA.
So, that as a result of those two cuts, I
am now going to have the following.
So we're going to draw that in, and I'll
have the red chromosome.
The red DNA and now the blue DNA.
So the three prime end, the five prime
end, and now I"ll put in what happens
to the upper strand, the upper DNA here,
the upper piece of DNA.
I'm going to have the three prime end over
here, and
we're going to come over here, and we're
going to come
up to a cut on that strand, and that cut
will allow ligation.
At this point let's continue, with the
cuts at the other Holliday junction.
So this bottom strand on the upper
chromosome is going to end up
being joined right at this point.
Okay.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
After those cuts, now, let's draw, the,
re,
resolution of the Holliday junction, and
how it affects, the bottom chromosome, and
as you can see, I'll draw this for you the
bottom strand of the bottom chromosome,
of course, is intact; nothing was ever
done to it.
But the upper strand, of course, after the
cuts.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
What will happen is red DNA will get
ligated to red DNA and
maybe a little bit of blue here, but then,
that will be ligated to the red DNA.
Just so, okay?
So, the bottom strand of DNA here is
going to be virtually completely red.
So the intact, the original intact DNA is,
is been restored.
After the resolution of the holiday
junction.
The difference is the upper strand, the
upper DNA molecule.
Now has been repaired by copying from the
intact chromosome, and
that's the areas that were copied are
shown in red here,
and this kind of resolution of the holiday
junction
actually converts some of the sequence in
the blue chromosome to a red sequence, and
if the sequences aren't exactly the same
you're going to have a slight difference.
Of course since this is homologous
recombination,
the sequences are pretty close to the same
but.
There will be some differences depending
on whether the blue chromosome and
the red chromosome have exactly the same
sequences, and
because they're slightly different, we
call this process here gene conversion.
So, the damaged chromosome has undergone a
gene conversion.
All right, now, there is a different
way you can resolve the holiday junctions,
and we're now going to talk about that.
So I'm going to erase this way of
repairing or
resolving the two holiday junctions, and
show you a different way to resolve them.
So let's get the eraser.
Get rid of gene conversion here, and,
let's see,
I'm going to be judicious in how I do
this, because, I'm going to make
[BLANK_AUDIO]
one pair of cuts the same.
And so one pair of cuts will still be
these longitudinal cuts that I drew
previously.
But the other pair of cuts are going to be
transverse cuts.
Here are the transverse cuts.
All right, now as a result of those
transverse cuts.
I'm going to have a different species.
So, let me erase things here.
Let's see, let's clean this thing up a
little bit.
Let's get rid of that.
Now, we're going to make this transverse
cuts,
and I'm going to show them to you here.
Where the cuts are.
So imagine that this enzyme here nicks the
DNA,
boom, there it goes, and boom, there it
goes.
Lemme restore that arrow so you can
remember where the cut was.
There you go, and so, that is where the
transverse cuts are.
Now, keeping track of the three prime, and
five prime ends, all right.
There's going to be a three prime end over
here,
okay, and a five prime end on this side of
the cut,
all right, and, there is no cut here.
So this is still okay, and, there is no
cut over here.
So this is still okay.
All right
[BLANK_AUDIO]
But there was a cut down here, so
I'm going to re-draw it for you.
Drawing in the five [UNKNOWN].
So, I've made these two cuts, I have four
single stranded ends, and
those have to be rejoined in a [UNKNOWN],
re-combinational way.
So, this three prime end is going to end
up joined to this five prime end,
and this three prime end is going to be
joined to this five prime end.
So let me denote that
in the following way, just so we can keep
track of book keeping.
I'm going to make a triangle here, because
this three prime end.
Is going to be joined to this five prime
end.
That's a triangle and it's too red pieces
of DNA, okay,
and then I'm going to make, a circle over
here to denote.
Which two ends are going to be joined.
So, the circles will be joined,
one circle from the red DNA and one circle
from the blue DNA.
So, that's how these things are going to
be joined.
So now, all we have to do redraw this sort
of unfolding things and
the way we can unfold things.
Is we can flip this strand and this strand
over and let me just draw an arrow for
you so that there's going to be a flip
between these two,
and I'm going to show you how that's looks
as a result.
What you're going to see now, this is the
first half
and then this is going to be that triangle
on the upper strand,
that's going to be joined to the triangle
in the lower strand after the flipping.
Okay.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this piece of DNA
and flipped over at this end.
Is intact, nothing has happened to it.
So that's the five prime end.
That's now the new upper DNA.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And now the lower DNA I'm going to draw in
here
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[INAUDIBLE]
Prime end and
here is the five prime end of the lower
DNA.
All right, remember, that's going to be
joined to the circle on the upper strands,
so I'm flip that over to the blue DNA.
So, I'm going to actually make a little
blue circle, so
you can see they came together.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
All right, and actually, let me draw it
just so you can see that there are two
triangles here and two circles on the
bottom.
So now you have two chromosomes that have
been restored, and
they've been separated by resolution of
the Holliday junction.
The resolution occurred because of a
longitudinal cut.
At this holiday junction, and a transverse
cut at this holiday junction, and
as a result of the combination of the
longitudinal cut and
the transverse cut, okay, what I end up
with is a chromosome,
an upper chromosome here that starts out
blue and ends up red, and
a lower chromosome, here, that starts out
red and ends up blue, and, so,
that is not an easy thing to draw, so we
have congratulate ourselves and say voila.
All right, what is this product called?
This product.
This method of, or this particular way of
resolving the two holiday junctions.
These products are now called a
cross-over.
So, I'll just write that, cross-over, from
homologous recombination.
Okay, that was very complicated, but if
you keep track of the five prime and
three prime ends of the DNA, you should be
fine.
So thank you very much.