[BLANK_AUDIO]
This video is going to review for you the
mechanism of homologous recombination.
Homologous recombination will actually
repair DNA double-strand breaks.
And here is a picture of a DNA
double-strand break.
And here is a picture of homologous DNA
that is
going to be used as the template for
repairing that double-strand break.
And I'm going to be very careful about how
I draw this diagram because I'm going to
put in the five prime and three prime ends
of the DNA, of every location.
And I've drawn the five prime and three
prime ends of the homologous DNA in
a way that will allow the diagram to be
very simple.
So, the first thing that happens after the
double-strand break is created,
to send this down the pathway of
homologous recombination, an exon
nucleus has to come along and remove some
of the DNA near the double-strand break.
Indeed, what the exon nucleus will do is
shoo back DNA to leave three prime
protruding ends.
So, I'm going to have my nucleus come in
and create three prime protruding ends.
Then, after the three prime protruding
ends are created, one of the two three
prime ends can then be used to hybridize
the DNA from the homogenous chromosome.
So, the homologous chromosome, which is
drawn in red,
then has to be partially denatured.
Let me draw it right here.
So, here's the five prime and three prime
ends.
Okay, and.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Some of the DNA here is displaced.
Okay, and there are proteins that allow
this to happen.
In fact, the protein that allows this to
happen is RAD51.
So here is the protruding, over here is
the protruding three prime overhang,
and it can do stra, what's called strand
invasion.
And, and it can invade the homologous
DNA duplex to displace one strand.
Now there is another strand of DNA from
the DNA double-strand break.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And that strand I'm drawing right here.
Again, I'm going to keep track of the five
prime and three prime overhangs.
All right.
So, now that strain invasion has occurred,
it has displaced
some of the homologous DNA, the intact,
from the intact chromosome.
And that is, that displacement forms a
structure that we call a D-loop.
And the reason it's called a D-loop is, if
you're falling asleep during this lecture,
your head will tilt to 90 degrees and
you'll suddenly wake up to see the letter
d.
Okay.
Now that we've formed a D-loop, DNA
polymerase can come along.
And at this point, at this three prime
overhang,
they can begin copying the homologous DNA.
Similarly, on the opposing strand, DNA
polymerase can copy the displaced DNA.
When this copying finishes,
ligase can bring the strands together on
the upper strand.
And when this copying gets to a certain
point, ligase can join.
And now, what you have here is the
formation of two Holliday junctions.
And these Holliday junctions then need to
be resolved.
The reason this pathway has become very
important recently
is because patients who have hereditary
breast cancer because
they have a mutation in either one of two
genes, BRCA1 or BRCA2.
BRCA1 or BRCA2.
If patients have, are carriers for
mutations in either of these genes,
they have a, a very high risk for getting
either breast or, or ovarian cancer.
Such patients have strong family histories
and
the syndrome is called Hereditary Breast
and Ovarian Cancer.
These genes are involved in homologous
recombination and their involvement
in homologous recombination is to load
RAD51 onto the protruding single strand.
Now I'm going to draw some RAD51
molecules.
Here's RAD51, and here's the molecule, the
little circle.
And these RAD51 molecules basically
facilitate the formation of, of the
D-loop.
They facilitate strand invasion and
formation of the D-loop.
BRCA1 and
BRCA2 work together to load RAD51 onto the
protruding three prime overhangs.
So, tumors that arise in patients who
have, who are carriers for
mutations in BRCA1 and BRCA2, all of those
tumors have
knocked out both alleles of BRCA1 or both
alleles of BRCA2.
And as a result, their tumors are
defective in homologous recombination.
And recent developments have now
introduced drugs that can potentially
be used to treat breast cancer because
they actually make cells defective,
that are defective in homologous
recombination particularly susceptible.
While leaving the patient's normal cells
alone because the patient is
heterozygous for permutation in BRCA1 and
BRCA2.
And so, those cells, those normal cells,
have normal homologous recombination.
Anyway, this is a very important pathway
and
I hope this has made the formation of
these Holliday junctions clear to you.
Thank you.