[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay this is chapter three of our series
on homologous recombination.
Here we're going to describe something
called unequal crossover.
So, in unequal crossover you can actually
get something called gene duplication.
And what I'm going to do is diagram for
you how this can happen.
The only way you can have unequal
crossover of
course is if you have crossover.
And in the last session we described how
crossover can occur if you resolve
the two holiday junctions with one
longitudinal cut and one transverse cut.
And so I've drawn for you or I've kept for
you here the diagram of
the cuts in the holiday junctions that
will lead to crossover.
And as a result of this you will have a
blue chromosome turning into
a red chromosome from here, this blue
chromosome.
Okay, on the other side off the holiday
junction will continue on as
a red chromosome.
And this red chromosome over here will
continue on as a blue chromosome.
Because the transverse cuts lead to
crossover.
So now imagine that you have a genome
where there are homologous sequences
scattered throughout.
Let me give you an example.
This, and this did happen to the
beta-globin gene.
Suppose you have beta-globin genes and one
beta-globin gene, and
it's surrounded by repeated sequences.
So I'm going to draw for you a beta-globin
gene.
Here is a beta-globin gene.
All right.
And it's surrounded by repeated sequences.
So, this beta-globin gene is surrounded by
repeated sequences.
And I'll draw for you a repeated sequence.
And in fact, lets call this repeated
sequence.
Lets just, in fact, it's true that there
are sequences called line
elements that actually could flank the
beta-globin genes, so
let me call this line element L1.
Okay?
L1 the end.
Again, this is the beta-globin gene.
And I'm going to describe to you how an
equal crossover can end
generate a duplication of the beta-globin
gene.
Imagine that the DNA undergoes hemologous
recombination, but
it undergoes homologous recomination by
winding up the homologous chromosomes,
but occasionally it can produce a
misalignment because of these,
the presence of these repeated sequences.
And as a result of that misalignment this
is what could happen.
So, let me draw the beta-globin gene over
here.
All right.
And, there's another line element.
I'm running out space but bear with me.
And over here, the other side of the
beta-globin gene
with the other line element that flanks
it.
So, so suppose during that homologous
recombination occurs by searching for
the hymology between the line element on
the upper chromosome and
the line element on the lower chromosome.
As a result of that, the hymologous
recombination if it
occurs between these two line elements
will lead to a misalignment of the DNA,
and that will result in what's called a
crossover, I'll use that as the notation.
And the way that would happen, of course,
is by homologous recombination up here,
because we're going to imagine that the
line element, L1, is here in this region.
L1.
Line.
Okay, so
the homologous recombination would be
occurring between two line elements so
I've drawn, say, a blow up of the line
element here
in the upper panel and and then you'll
have
resolution of the holiday junctions in a
way that leads to crossover.
So this, this X here indicates the
crossover.
As a result of that crossover you now have
a resolution into two
different chromosomes.
One chromosome will have, two B-globin
genes.
So the upper chromosome here, let's draw
that in.
We'll have one beta-globin gene.
Okay?
So you have one beta-globin gene along
with its line element, L1.
Okay?
And then you come over here to do this
downstream line element.
You have a homologous combination with a
crossover.
And so, you would end up with a line
element right.
Let's line them up.
Let's line up the line elements.
Oh boy.
Bad pun.
Okay, here we go with the second
beta-globin gene.
And it's downstream line element.
Okay, and the lower chromosome will start
over here.
Do the un, the crossover.
And come up here.
And as a result of that, you'll have this
kind of chromosome
with only a single line element and no
beta-globin genes.
So, as a result of this unequal crossover,
one chromosome now has two
beta-globin genes and the other chromosome
has no beta-globin genes.
And again, these are the products of what
we call unequal crossover.
So this is unequal.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Crossover.
And you can see that this type of unequal
crossover can now lead to
a chromosome with no beta-globin genes, or
think of another situation where you have
a primordial globin gene.
You may already know that there are many
different globin genes.
There's an alpha globin, there's a
beta-globin, and so on.
And what may have happened long ago was
that there was a single globin gene
flanked by repetitive sequences like this
line element L1.
That primordial globin gene could have
been duplicated into
two different primordial globin genes
which then could evolve separately.
One to eventually becoming the beta-globin
gene, and
the other eventually becoming the
alpha-globin gene.
So that's how unequal crossover works.
Thank you.