Hello students.
This is a quick tutorial on how to read a
paper.
Why learn how to read a paper?
Aren't review articles good enough?
Well you're an outstanding physician, and
want to see the real data.
A patient may ask you about a breakthrough
reported in the news.
You may want to screen many articles.
So you need to know how to get the key
points of each article in a few minutes.
You may want to focus on one article, so
you need to know how to read an article
with a critical eye.
Imagine you're a pulmonologist.
You see a patient with pulmonary fibrosis.
The disease runs in his family.
You find a paper by searching the
internet.
What should you do?
What you shouldn't do, is reading from the
beginning to the end.
You don't have the time, you don't have
the attention span,
you want the answers right away.
You're going to fall asleep, you just ate
lunch.
So, here's how to approach the paper.
First, you look at the title [SOUND].
If it's interesting, you look at the
abstract.
There may be words or concepts you don't
understand.
That will happen almost all the time.
So you'll go to Google for information.
And then, at that point.
You have enough information, so you can
look at the key data.
Now, if you want to dig deeper, you can
look at other stuff.
You can look at other figures, you can
look in the introduction, for
some more background, definition of terms.
You can look up key references.
You can scan the methods, to see if they
generally will give you reliable data.
You should look at the conflicts of
interests.
The prospect of getting rich can cloud an
author's judgment.
Then if you're really interested, you can
read the entire paper.
So, here's the paper we found by searching
the internet.
It links telomerase mutations, to a
disease, idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.
Well that looks very interesting,
completely unexpected.
And then you look at the authors.
And one of the authors here, you recognize
her name,
because she shared the Nobel prize in
discovering telomerase.
This is probably a solid group of
researchers.
You don't know much about idiopathic
pulmonary fibrosis, so
you do a Google search.
You type this into the search box, and
this is what you get.
And over here, on the right hand side,
is a definition for idiopathic pulmonary
fibrosis.
Idiopathic means without known cause.
Pulmonary fibrosis means scarring and
thickening of the lungs.
And look here, down here, pretty high on
the search, is an entry from Wikipedia.
I often go to Wikipedia sites, if I need
to get more information.
Now, we jump to the abstract.
You don't even read the abstract, from
beginning to end.
No, you look for the punchline, and the
punchline is down here in the conclusions.
And you see that mutations in the genes
encoding telomerase components,
can appear as familial idiopathic
pulmonary fibrosis.
That's the punchline.
Well, the connection between those two
things is completely unexpected, and so
you want to know, what's the background
behind that?
Well, it turns out that mutations in genes
including telomerase,
cause a different disease called
dyskeratosis congenita.
Well, it's a rare disease, but contained
in that disease, are other manifestations.
Aplastic anemia and in particular,
pulmonary fibrosis.
So you can immediately surmise that what
the authors did, was they decided to look
for germ line mutations, and the same
genes in patients who come from families
with pulmonary fibrosis without the other
manifestations of dyskerytosis congenita.
And you can immediately see how they did
this.
They screened 73 probands from a registry
of familial pulmonary fibrosis.
And of those 73 probands, six had
mutations in the telom,
telomerase genes, HTERT and HTR.
Okay, so now you know what the key
features of the paper are.
And you have enough information to jump to
the key data.
And here are the key data.
And you can tell, because it's labelled,
mutations in telomerase.
And you can see the six probands listed.
They came from six different families, A,
B, C, D, E, and F.
Okay, and each of them has a mutation in
one of the genes that encodes telomerase.
Five of them in the HTERT gene, and one of
them in the HTR gene.
And then the next question you have is,
do these mutations really cause shortened
telomeres.
And so you, you realize that this figure
here,
is going to be key because it shows
telomere length.
Here's telomere length.
In mutation carriers versus their
relatives.
So here are the carriers, in orange.
And here are their relatives, in blue.
And generally speaking, you can see.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That the orange dots, and squares.
Are, generally showing shorter telomeres,
than the blue dots and squares.
So, you have a pretty good idea of what
the data look like.
Now, you have a pretty, in the, in the
period of time that we've taken
you through this, you can see that we have
the general gist of the paper.
So in summary, what have I asked you to
do?
I've asked you to read, by jumping.
And then when, very early on,
you jump, to the key data.
[SOUND]
You understand very quickly what's new.
And if you've taken the trouble to read
the paper with a critical eye,
you can decide for yourself, if you
believe the conclusions.
Don't worry, you'll get better at this.
Your medical knowledge will grow so
that you can put things into context more
quickly.
You'll overcome your math phobia.
You better overcome it, and understand
some statistics.
You will acquire good judgment, and
will be able to apply what you find in the
medical literature to help your patient.
Thank you.