In this next module, I'm going to explain
the difference between modeling a variable
as a categorical variable versus an
ordinal variable And I'm also going to
talk about a test that's directly related
to that called the p value for trend test.
So if you have an ordinal variable, that
is a variable that's ordered category is
something like a Likert scale, you might
end up coding that variable as numeric.
So like code it 1 through 5 and
you could choose to analyze that data then
as a number that predictable variable but
could be treated as a number in the
regression model.
Now there are some assumptions if you do
this.
So, if you just throw that variable,
that number 1 through 5 into your model,
you are making an assumption.
So, in a logistic regression, you are
assuming that the logit of
the outcome has a linear relationship with
across the numbers, 1 through 5.
So literally that there would be a line.
You know, So if you plotted that, it would
something that was, roughly, on a line.
Now that's somewhat of an, of a big
assumption, right,
you're assuming that you're, as you go
from category one to two, that your,
your increase in risk, your jump in risk,
or your jump in the logit, of,
of the outcome, is equal across all of
these different levels.
And that may be true in some cases, but
you can imagine a lot of cases where those
categories aren't really evenly spaced,
and that your risk doesn't jump up evenly
across the categories.
You're assuming that when you just treat
that variable as a number.
You're only going to also get a single
estimate when you
put that variable into your logistic
regression model.
You're going to get a single beta and a
single odd ratio.
The reason being is that when you treat
this as a number you're
literally just getting one slope that's
the reason for that one.
You're going to get one p value.
Now that might be have some advantages.
If you have a small data set, the thing
about categorical variables is that if you
have a large number of categories, and you
dummy code them, that eats up a lot of,
you have to estimate a lot of betas.
That eats up a lot of degrees of freedom.
So if you're dealing with a small data
set, sometimes you might want to
treat something as an ordinal variable
just because you don't have enough degrees
of freedom to model it, to dummy code all
the categories.
Alternatively of course, you could just
take your ordinal variable and
treat it as categorical, treat it as dummy
coded.
In the way that we do with any categorical
variable.
This makes no assumptions about the
relationships between increasing
categories, because you're allowing every
category comp, you're comparing,
you're calculating a separate odds ratio
for
every category relative to the reference
group.
And so if one of the odds ratios is 3, and
the next category has an odds ratio you
know, of 2.9 and
there's really no increase, you'll you'll
capture all of that differences.
Of course it costs more degrees of freedom
you've gotta estimate all those betas and
all those odds ratios so that sometimes
can be an issue.
Now be very careful,
I just want to point out that sometimes
when you're coding data.
You take a categorical variable something
like the occupation and
just because it's easy to type it in, you
might end up coding it as a number.
Like one means teacher, two means social
worker, ectera.
That occupation variable is truly nominal
variable.
It is not ordered categories right now.
So just be careful that you don't
accidently dump that.
Variable into your regression model and
treat it as a number without even
realizing it.
You have to clearly, you cannot treat that
as a number.
It must be dummy coded.
Just to, illustrate all of this with an
examnple.
This was a study that was looking at
whether or not for men if they're
breastfed as infants are they more likely
to or less likely to be obese or
overweight later in life and I'm just
focusing here on the results for obesity.
So these are odds ratios this was a
logistic regression,
the outcome is obesity and breastfeeding
was measured in Five categories.
And now this probably has to do something
with how the questionnaire was set up.
Maybe there was a questionnaire where
people had to check off these categories.
So we ended up with five categories.
You could have measured breast feeding as
a continuous variable, but
I'm assuming here that it probably wasn't
measured as continuous and
that's why they're treating it as a
categorical variable.
But it clearly ordered categories, right?
So here's category one, two, three, four
and five.
So, the reference group are those who were
fed, breastfed for at least four months.
And then the, the,
the sort of, highest risk group is those
who were breastfed for less than a month.
And then we have categories in between.
But they're clearly ordered.
Okay, looking at the results, what do we
see here?
First of all, where do these ratios come
from?
The first row here is just a crude odds
ratio,
it means we haven't adjusted for
everything.
Notice the crude and the adjusted odds
ratios look awfully similar.
So the adjustment doesn't make a huge
difference here.
So where did the odds ratios come from?
Well, I fit a, or the authors here fit a
logit model for
obesity With an alpha that represents the
reference group and
then four betas for those four additional
categories.
Those translate therefore into four odds
ratios.
We calculated those odds ratios here's
what they come out to be
you can see that the first of the non
breastfed group essentially looks to
have somewhat of an elevated risk.
We also get a P value for linear trend
which is trying to summarize and
cross all those different categories.
That I will talk about in just a minute
but
again when I'm doing w coding my equation
is going to look like this.
I have to estimate four parameters.
Well we can also try to look at this
visually.
I did a plot of those odds ratios.
I can't do the log plot here cause I don't
have the original data but
I can take the odds ratios that were in
the paper.
And just for illustration's purposes just
plot them against these categories 1
through 5.
This is just show you that they kind of
jump around a little.
This is not certainly not a smooth curve
because odds ratio was
estimated separately.
Now what would happen though if I were to
model breast feeding as an ordinal
variable that is literally just.
Coded as one, two, three, four, five for
those five categories, and
dump it in the model at, treat it as a
number, the number 1 through 5.
I'm now only going to have a single beta,
because I'm, I'm treating it essentially
as a numeric or continuous variable.
I'm going to get out a single beta.
And I can kind of,
I can't actually run this on this data,
because I don't have it, but I can guess.
From the odds ratio published in the paper
that if I did that the betas going to come
out somewhere around lets say about -.08.
Then, I can then do both the logit plot
and the odds ratio plot.
The logit plot's going to be really easy,
assuming that I'm
pretty close on my estimate here is my
categories one, two, three, four, five.
My logit plot is again just going to be a
straight line so
I'm going to be going down across the
categories here and
my beta will be -.08 that's the slope of
that line.
So if my logit plot will just be a
straight line.
If I plot the odds ratios like I did in
the previous slide it'd
actually be a little bit curved cause we
don't have a linear relationship with
the odds ratios but with the beta.
The P value for this beta I know, comes
out to be .03 and the reason I
know that is because they told us that the
P value for linear trend is .03.
And all the P variable from the near trend
is, is when you put the variable in
as an ordinal variable, so I know that
beta is going to have a P value of .03.
And just to show you here is were we have
a single Beta.
This is ordinal graph.
Of the odds ratios.
You can see it's smooth, cause we only
estimated one beta,
essentially one odds ratio, one set of
odds ratios.
And then for when we treated it as
categorical, if you plot the odds ratios
it looks jagged, because we estimated
separate odds ratios for each category.
Now this P value for linear trend again
all it is, is if I take the model and
I do the logit of obesity [SOUND] and
I plug in a single data for breastfeeding,
that's the number 1 through 5.
That ordinal variable, I treat it as a
ordinal variable The p-value that's
associated with this beta, that is the
p-value for linear trend.
That's where it comes from, it came at
3.03 in this case.
Well, what does that really mean?
Well, all that really means is okay.
Again I don't know the exact logit plot
here but I can kind of guess
what the logit plot would look like if I
had the original raw data.
I can kind of guess about what it would
look like.
And you know it's going to be something
like, well clearly our
category one was elevated and then there
was you know some little bit of elevation.
Category four is actually lower than five.
So you know, its going to look something
like that and
I can fit a line to those points.
That's all I'm doing when I'm treating
this as an ordinal variable.
I'm fitting a line to those points.
So lets I fit the line to those points.
It comes out like that and
that slope is enough to trigger
statistical significance.
Well that comes out to be statistical
significance.
Therefore my p-value for linear trend is
signiificant.
What does that mean?
All it means is that if I fit a line to
those five points, and
five points isn't a lot, it, the slope is
significant.
Well how can I trigger a significant
p-value for a linear trend?
Well there's a lot of ways to do it.
You know, if I again, let's say I just had
the same kind of data set but
really there was no elevation.
And here's my reference group and then
there,
there was only one group, the most extreme
group from the reference group.
Category one versus category five that one
happened to be elevated well guess what I
can probably if I fit the line to those
data it's also probably going to
be a statistically significant slope.
Does that mean that I'm increasing
linearally as I go across the categories?
Clearly not it just means that you know,
the category one was elevated compared
with category five.
That could be enough.
To trigger a significant linear p-value
for linear trends.
You have to be a little careful.
It doesn't tell you about dose response.
It doesn't tell you a whole heck of a lot.
It's just one way though that you can
summarize across multiple
categories an overall p-value.
You can see that in the overall chart here
the p-values come out to be .03
for obesity.
I'm showing both the crude and adjusted
here.
That's largely triggered by the fact that
we have Elevation in
that first category and a little bit of
decrease as we go across
the categories towards the reference
group.
It does give you a single p value, though,
that you can point to, which is why people
use it.
If, you try to calculate a p value for
each of these separate categories, you do
get one when you dummy code.
But if people worry about,
well then, multiple testing because I'm
reporting so many p values.
They want one summary measure, so
this gives a summary measure that tells
you something across those categories.
Again, it doesn't tell you a whole heck of
a lot, though,
it just tells you that if you were to fit
a line to only those five points,
that at least the slope of that line would
be significant.
Just to show you one more example of a p
for trend, so we saw this example
earlier about dietary patterns and breast
cancer risk, they also reported a p for
trend, because they had the same kind of
thing, they had an ordinal variable.
Quin-tiles of dietary pattern they broken
up into quin-tiles for
whatever reason perhaps because they
didn't think it was linear,
well it's actually didn't have a [UNKNOWN]
it was,
it was contravention perhaps, it didn't
think it was linear in that model.
For some reason they've broken it up into
categories, so the reference could be
the lowest quin-tile, and what you can see
is the one that comes
really significant in the P value for
trend is this salad and wine diet.
That's really triggered by if you look,
you know, it's pretty much staying right
around 1.0.
And then suddenly in the fifth category,
it jumps up in risk.
So the logit plot here is going to look
something like [SOUND].
And basically, here is my reference group.
If you go up a little bit, maybe a little
bit in group three,
kind of sticking around one,
and then suddenly there's a big jump up in
group five.
Well, yeah, if I fit a,
a line to those five points, yeah, it'll,
it's going to trigger a significant.
It kind of came out to a highly
significant.
Slope there, so we do get a significant
slope but
its not based on a lot of points and
it just means that the highest category
was a lot higher then the lowest category.
So again, take the P value for
trend with a grain of salt, it is one way
though that you can summarize.
When you're doing, when you have ordered
categories it is one way that
you can get a single p value associated
with those ordered categories.