[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND]
So I've now talked about giving you an
overview of
three different ways to handle repeated
measures outcome data in SAS.
And I thought it might be helpful for
me to just put this together in an
organized fashion into a chart for you.
So you can run PROC GENMOD with a repeated
statement or
you could run PROC MIXED with a repeated
you could run PROC MIXED with a random
statement as I've alluded to.
What are the differences between those
three approaches?
So, first of all,
PROC GENMOD is a procedure in SAS that
handles any type of outcome variable.
It doesn't have to be continuous normally
distributed.
It can also handle binary outcomes, count
outcomes, negative binomial.
All of those different types of outcomes.
So, PROC GENMOD is general in that way.
However, PROC GENMOD does not allow for
the inclusion of random effects.
So we are fitting marginal models.
We cannot get subject specific effects.
When in the repeated statement in PROC
GENMOD, you're going to have to specify
a type equals where you tell SAS what type
of covariance structure you want.
Whatever you put here, exchangeable, for
example, unstructured.
You are specifying the covariance
structure that you want for
what SAS calls the R matrix.
This is the covariance structure for the
residuals.
The within subject correlation over time.
So just realize that that's the
correlation that structure that you're
specifying in PROC GENMOD.
When you do PROC MIXED with a repeated
statement,
you are really doing something very
similar to PROC GENMOD with
a repeated statement.
Couple of differences, so PROC MIXED with
a repeated statement,
PROC mixed in SAS only handles continuous
roughly normally distributed outcomes.
We can only do linear models.
There are procedures in SASS that handle
other types of outcome data,
such as binary outcomes.
But those are PROCs that are beyond the
scope of this course.
So, PROC MIXED itself cannot handle
anything other than
continuously normally distributed
outcomes.
But if you're using the repeated statement
and Proc mixed,
that is not including any random effects
so you are still fitting a marginal model.
You are not going to get subject-specific
effects, and you're still
focusing on the covariant structure of the
residuals, what SAS calls the R matrix.
So that's what you're specifying when you
put this type equals for
the covariant structure.
So those, the first two are very similar.
I'll, I'll notice that one other thing
that I've mentioned is that
PROC MIXED with a repeated statement has
more choices for
the covariance structure of the r matrix.
So that is one slight difference there.
PROC MIXED with a random statement is
actually doing something quite different.
So PROC MIXED again, can only handle
continuous normally distributed outcomes.
Although there are are procedures in SAS
that will do mixed models for
other types of outcomes such as binary.
however, PROC MIXED with a random
statement is now including allowing you
to include random effects.
So that's really quite different because
now you can fit these
subject specific intercepts and slope
subjects, specific effects.
So when you put the type equals, when you
specify the covariant structure,
the covariant structure that you have to
specify for
the random statement is not the covariant
structure for the R matrix.
It's the co-variant structure for what SAS
calls that G matrix.
This is just the co-variance matrix for
the random effects and
it usually involves very few parameters,
you might just have the,
correlation between the intercept and the
slope for
example, those random effects, so I
usually just set that to be unstructured.
So you have, you don't have to worry so
much about exactly the covariant structure
when you're including a random statement.
The other thing I want to point out is
that if you're in PROC MIXED,
you can included a random statement and
also include a repeated statement.
As I mentioned before, you usually don't
need to also include a repeated statement,
but SAS will allow you to do it.
You can also include multiple random
statements.
So for example you could include, if you
had a study where you had
repeated observations on subjects, and
then, but then the subjects were also
clustered in some way, so maybe clustered
within clinic or clustered within school,
you could include random effects for this
subject as well as random effects for
the clinic or random effects for the
school.
So you're allowed to include multiple
random statements in PROC Mixed.
With Proc GENMOD, you can only include one
repeated statement and
with PROC Mix, you can only include one
repeated statement.
So you can't include multiple repeated
statements.
So there tends to be some, some Datasets
that PROC MIXED with a random statement
will just handle more easily, because you,
the fact that you can include random
effects for multiple layers of clustering,
what we call multilevel models.
So that's just kind of to set up
the differences between those three PROCs
for you.
And then I thought it would be really
helpful for you to really understand
the difference between the marginal models
and the subject-specific models.
The easiest way to understand that is with
a picture.
So I thought it would be worth me drawing
some pictures here.
I'm going to go back to the same spine
bone density example that we've been
using because you're all very familiar
with this example by now.
So this is looking at three different
groups.
Their bone density changes over time.
I've shown you these pictures several
times.
I went ahead and took these data on these
41 women and
I fit the data in three different ways.
I used proc mix for the random statement,
proc mix for the repeated statement and
proc mixed, and proc/ gen mod with a
repeated statement - a GE model.
And I want to show you, I then asked SAS
to output for
me the predicted values for each person in
my data set, from each of those models.
Those predicted values, where,
you'll see, when we graft them, that they
are very informative.
So I'm going to start with the predicted
model,
when I did prop mixed with a random
statement.
I'm actually going to show you the code
here, just to show you what it looks like.
You can see I included a random statement.
I, I'm allowing random ess, effects for
subjects.
A random intercept, and random slopes.
And I haven't told you exactly what those
are yet.
But we're going to get to that in the next
module.
But the key is that if you look over at
the pic,
picture what I've graphed here are
predicted values for each subject.
So SAS calculates for me the predicted
spine bone density at each time point for
each subject based on this model, this
fitted model.
I went ahead and plotted those and you can
see that different subjects have
different intercepts and different
subjects have different changes over time.
There is a lot of subject-specific
variability here.
I then super-imposed linear regression
lines because we fit time is linear
here and we allowed the changes over time
to vary by which group you're in.
So we've got time group and group by time
in the model.
And there is three groups here.
The red and black groups you can see in
our fitted model have very similar slopes
and the control group has as we saw from
the observed values, it's pretty flat or
goes down a little bit over time.
So, this is the, the fitted model.
These are the predicted values.
This is the model that we just fit.
But see that subject specific variability.
I'm also showing you the code for
how to plot this in case you want to know
how to do it.
That's what it means to have a random
statement in the model.
Okay?
So contrast that to the following.
I then went ahead and
fit a proc mixed with a repeated statement
on this exact same data, exact same model.
Here are the predicted values from that
model.
So what do you notice?
These again are the predicted values for
each individual at each time point.
What you notice is there are no subject
specific variability.
If somebody is in the red group, they are
predicted to be right on that line for
the rate of change in the bone density
over time.
So we get the same general lines, I mean
the,
the scales are a little different here
because this is only showing .92 to 1.02.
Over here we're seeing a wider range
because it's showing you all
that individual variability, but
if you look just at those three lines, the
three lines look pretty much the same.
So, that's what we end up really caring
about is what is the slope for
each of the different groups and those are
basically the same.
Red and black are largely overlapping and
blue is lower than the other two.
However, what's different here is there is
no subject specific variability allowed,
so this is what we mean by a marginal
model or a population average model.
If you're the red group, you're predicted
to be on one line, and that's it.
And that's the difference between having a
random statement, and
having a repeated statement in proc mixed.
This is fitting a marginal model.
I went ahead and then chipped those same
data, and put them into proc genmod with
a repeated statement, essentially fit a
generalized estimating equation.
And when I did that, I get pretty much the
same model that I
got from PROC mixed with a repeated
statement.
So again, it's fitting a marginal model.
Everybody is forced to be on one of those
lines.
If you're in the red group, everybody in
the red group is on the same line.
Everybody on the black group is on the
same line.
So the only variation we're allowed is
because we have group in,
group by time in the, in the model.
We're not allowed any subject-specific
variation.
And that's the difference between the, the
picture really shows you
the difference between the marginal model
and the model with random effects in it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]