[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module I'm going to talk more
about how to interpret time
changing predictors.
So we saw in the last module that when you
have a time changing predictor in
your GEE module.
Interpreting the beta cooefficient can be
confusing because that beta
coefficient will encompass both within
subjects effects and between subjects
effects; you won't know just by looking at
the beta which of those you have.
Might have some of both and in the.
Previous example that I gave in the last
module these were made up data so
I happen to know that I built in a lot of
within subjects effects.
So I knew that the beta coefficient
largely represented within
subjects effects.
That is that if the chemical level went up
a person's depression level went down.
But what if you.
Of course most of the time you haven't
made up the data so
you don't know ahead of time.
Time.
So, I made a couple, I made up a couple of
data sets just so
we could explore this issue.
So here's the original data set that I
made up and, of course,
I specifically sat the base line value of
the chemical level to be the same for
everybody so that it did not correlate
with depression.
Scores had, base line.
So that most of what I have here are
within-subjects effects.
I then made up a second data set, where I
purposely built in
both between-subjects effects and
within-subjects effects.
So for example.
If you look at the base line chemical
level and the base line depression score
values, you'll notice that the people with
the highest depression scores,
levels of 50, had the lowest chemical
levels, 200 and 100.
The person with the highest chemical level
in their brain,
a thousand, had the lowest depression
score of 15.
So I built in some nice between subjects
effects here.
I also built in some within subject
effects.
So for example for
subject number one I made their chemical
level go up at time interval.
I also made their depression score go down
at every time interval.
So the change in chemical seems to also be
related to the change in depression score.
I then made a third example, where there
is only between subjects effects.
So in this example,
I made the base line chemical level highly
related to the base line depression score.
So very high scores.
Very, that, tended to go with low chemical
levels.
Very high chemical levels tended to go
with low depression scores.
However, I kept the chemical level in the
brain at about the same within a subject.
So you can see subject one hovered around
500, subject two hovered right around 700.
And I also didn't make the depression
scores change all
that much over time either.
So there's, there can't be really any
correlation between changes in
chemical levels and changes.
Which is in the depression score.
I then went ahead and graphed the last two
data sets.
I've already shown you the graph of the
first data set.
But just to show you this is example two.
This has both between subjects effects and
within subjects effects.
You can see that picture here.
So for example ID number one,
their depression score is in this blue
solid line.
Their chemical level is in the blue dotted
line.
ID number two is in red.
Their chemical level is in the dotted, red
dotted line there.
Depression score is the red, solid line.
And what you'll notice here.
Is that blue, the ID number one has a
pretty high depression level.
They also have a pretty low chemical
level.
Their dotted line is way down here.
On the other hand, ID two, person two
here, has a low depression score.
Their, the solid red line is down below
here.
And a higher chemical level.
Their chemical level is up on the top
here.
So that's representing cross sectional
between subjects effects.
One is high in depression score and, and
is low in chemical.
The other is high in chemical and low in
depression.
You do see some within subjects changes as
well.
So for example, ID number one, their
chemical level is going up over time and
their depression score is going down over
time.
And I've separated out each subject here,
so you can see that as this red
level line goes up, their depression score
does tend to go down for ID number one.
For subject number two, it just goes,
doesn't change too much over time.
For subject number three, their chemical
level experiences an upward lip here, and
their depression level correspondingly
goes down.
So I've built in some within subjects
effects as well.
You can see those here.
ID number five, there's not much change.
ID six, not much change.
And again, you can see the cross sectional
effects cause higher.
People with higher depression scores tend
to have lower chemical levels.
And then example three is the all
between-subject effects.
I've graphed the individual subjects so
you can see that the higher your blue
line, the lower your red line.
But not much going on over time.
Everybody staying pretty flat in both
their depression, and
especially in their chemical levels over
time.
So you can see all of that picture here.
So that's just showing it to you
graphically.
And then when I run GEE models for these
data,
what you'll notice is that, I get, so for
example, I get for
the example one, this all the, this is
mostly within-subjects effects.
[SOUND] I get a beta coefficient of
negative .017.
As we saw before, it's highly significant.
For a model two, this is both, within N
between subjects effects.
The beta coefficient changes, because it's
a different data set.
So they wouldn't be expected to be exactly
the same.
But it's negative, [INAUDIBLE], and, you
know, [INAUDIBLE].
In the same direction, also highly
significant.
And then when we had only between subjects
effects,
again, again I get a beta coefficient
that's negative, highly significant.
So, just by looking at those beta
coefficients and p values,
I can't distinguish which, whether or not
I have between versus subjects effects.
So what do you do to distinguish those
when you're dealing with data
tests that you didn't make up?
How do you differentiate?
So, there's a couple of different things
you can do.
So first of all, if you want to isolate,
are there a lot of between-subjects
effects, you need to graph things, examine
things, cross sectionally.
You're looking for cross sectional
relationships at specific time points.
So for example, you can graph.
The base line level of the chemicals
against the base line level of
the depression scores and
see if those are correlated cross
sectionally across different people.
To look for within-subjects effects,
there's a couple of different things you
can do.
So, one thing you could do.
Is to take say the base line level of the
chemical in the brain and
make an interaction with time.
And the reason you might want to interact
a variable with time is that, remember,
a predictor with time interaction,
assuming that we're now talking about
a time independent predictor like the base
line value that doesn't change over time.
If you interact that with time.
This will only be represent within
subjects effects.
So, a predictor times time only represents
within subjects effects.
So, that's going to all be the all within
subject effects and
there are occasions actually where I will
end up deciding in my final model.
To use the base line value and
interact it with time rather than the, use
the time changing value.
So for example I've done some, shown you
some data on calcium intake and
bone marrow content.
I could put those both into a model, and
have both calcium and
bone marrow content be changing.
Or what I might end up doing at the end of
the day is taking the base
line calcium level and interacting that
with time.
And using that in my final model because
then I know that somebody who is at
a high level of calcium that,
that's predicting their changes over time,
in in bone mineral content.
I've isolated the within-subjects effects,
so
sometimes you end up changing the model at
the end of the.
Of the day.
You can also examine correlations between
the change in
the time dependent predictor and the
change in the repeated measures outcome.
Within subjects effects we are talking
about changes, so
you can calculate the changes for the
predictors and the changes for
the outcome and try to correlate those,
you know, graphically for example.
So I went ahead and did some of these here
just to show you.
So I looked for cross sectional
relationships at base line.
So clearly for that first example one,
where I only had mostly within
subjects effects I gave everybody the same
chemical level at base line, so
we have no relationship between depression
score and chemical level at base line.
For the one where I had kind of both types
of effects, you can see that there is.
Some relationship cross-sectionally here
between Depression level, and
Chemical-scored base line.
And an even stronger relationship where,
for
the days that were ahead only between
subjects effects.
So that's telling me where there are,
at least where there are some between
subjects effects.
I could then also take the base line value
of Chemical Level, and
interact it with time.
Time, I actually can't do that with the
first data set because everybody has
exact same base line values so,
your base line value clearly doesn't
predict your changes over time.
However, when I did that with the second
data set that does have,
some within subjects, some between
subjects,
effects I take their base line chemical
level which is not changing over time.
I interacted with time.
This will all only represent
within-subjects effects, and indeed that
one comes out to be significant 'cause we
do have within-subjects effects there.
Whereas, for the second data set, sorry,
the third data set where
there's only between-subjects effects,
this comes out to be non-significant.
So that can help you again to, tease out
if it's within subjects effects and
you might end up choosing to model that
time changing predictor as
something static as just the base line
value at the end of the day.
And, then finally we can compare the
change in
depression scores to the change in
chemical levels.
So what I've done here.
Here's my first example data set though
within subjects.
Here is the second one which has both, and
this is the one that only has
between-subjects.
And so what I've done is I've taken
everybody's values between any two
time points.
And subtracted them.
So I calculated the change in chemical
level from time point one to
time point two for everybody and then from
time point two to time point three for
everybody, and then from time point three
to time point four.
I also calculated the change in depression
score for each of those time intervals.
And I'm just showing those graphically to
show if they correlate.
And indeed you can see that for
the data set where there's a lot of within
subjects effects, a big increase in
chemical level does correspond to a big
change in depression scores.
For this data set where there was some
within subjects effects.
Sort of both.
Some increase in chemical level
correspondent to some decrease in
depression score for the day.
But it's only between subjects effects,
they don't see much relationship between
the changes here.