[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to tell you
how we can use age as the time scale for
Cox regression, rather than time in the
study.
So, up until now,
we've been using time in the study as the
time scale for Cox regression.
So, what I mean by that, is when a person
joins the study, say subject one, joins
the study, the moment they join the study
a baseline, that's counted as time zero.
And we start the clock ticking from there.
So, if that person has an event three
years into the study, that's their time.
Another person joins the study,
maybe a year later we count from the time
they joined the study.
That becomes their zero time point and so
on and so forth.
That's the idea of time in this study.
However, there may be good reason to
instead choose age as your time scale.
And the main reason is that age is a
really important confounder in a lot of
the things that we want to look at in
survival analysis.
So, for example, age is obviously strongly
related to death.
It's strongly related to a lot of the
diseases that we, we may want to look at.
It's such an important confounder that we
want to treat it specially.
Now, if we're using time in the study as
our time scale, we can control for age
simply by adding age as a co-variant, as a
predictor in our Cox regression model.
So, we can add in baseline age.
So, somebody who's 30 years old at that
start of the study,
is obviously younger than somebody who is
60 years old at the start of the study.
And we can factor that in by controlling
for it, adjusting for it.
However, sometimes it's a better strategy
to actually choose age to
be the time scale.
When you choose age as the, as the time
scale, that means you're only going to be
comparing, 30 year olds to other 30 year
olds and 60 year olds to 60 years old.
So, somebody who has the event at age 60,
their only going to be compared to people
who are at risk at age 60.
When you use age as the time scale, you
may additionally need to control for
both birth cohort effects.
Because, obviously, somebody who could be
in your study who, w, is 30 but
[INAUDIBLE] you know, was born in 1960.
And you could have somebody who is 30 in
your study, who was born in, 1980.
You could have both in your study if you
were covering a wide range of,
of ages in your study and you're following
people for a long time.
Since people who were born in 1950 might
be very different, have different risks
than people who are born in, say, 1980, we
can adjust for both cohort.
One easy way to adjust for
it is to simply stratify on birth cohort,
like stratify on, say, decade of birth.
So, how we actually use as a time-scale.
The idea is this.
The risk that becomes everyone who is at
risk at a certain age rather than
everyone who was at risk at a certain time
in the study.
The risk set contains everyone who was
still event-free at
the age of the person who had the event.
So, the 60 year old has the event in your
study,
they're going to be compared to other 60
year olds who were at risk at age 60.
Obviously, this is going to require having
a relatively large dataset where you've
got enough people aty different ages.
If you, if your sample is spread out over
many different ages and you only have
one 60 year old in your study and nobody
else crossed 60 during your study.
Obviously this is not going to work, so
you need to have a relatively large sample
that ha, covers al,
has enough people at each of the different
ages, covers enough different ages.
the, to understand age as a time-scale
it's best for
me just to kind of draw some pictures out
and also to go through the likelihood.
So, I'm going to use just a simple little
data set for
illustration, it's just a made up data
set, for the purposes of this module.
So, you see that data set here has five
people in them.
I'd call them ID numbers, one, two, three,
four and
five just to distinguish the subjects.
You can see that the, they have a time in
the study.
So, for example person number one was in
the study for let's call this years so.
For three years before they had the event.
Whatever that event might be.
They were 28 when they joined the study
and 31 when they had the event.
And that's going to be, I'm going to be
using age or time here as the time scale.
And I want to have one predictor of
interest.
So, let's say the predictor of interest
here is pack years of smoking it,
I have put that in the last column.
If we were to use time in the study as the
time scale,
as we've been doing, here's what that
would look like.
So, everybody starts at time 0,
the time they joined the study, and so let
me put the ID numbers here, one, two,
three, four, five, and let me just draw a
picture of what this looks like.
So, for example, person number one, ID
number one, was in the study for
three years.
This is time in the study.
So, they were in the study for three years
until they had the event, and
I'll designate having an event with an X.
The second person was in the study for
five years before they had an event.
The third person was in the study for
seven years before they were censored.
I'll designate the censoring with a little
c.
And the fourth person was in the study for
12 years before they had the event.
And then the final person was in the study
for 13 years before being censored.
So, time is start in the study, we count
time in this way.
What, how does that affect things?
Well that affects the likelihood?
So, let me just start to draw the
likelihood a little bit for you.
You think about things in terms of the
likelihood, it will all make sense.
So, we're going to be drawing out a lot
likelihoods in this module.
So, if we're thinking about the likelihood
remember there's going to be one term in
the likelihood for every event in the
study.
There were three events here so there will
be three terms in the likelihood.
The first event happens three years into
the study, so
we can draw a little line down to see who
was at risk three years into the study.
Well, all five people were at risk three
years into the study, so I know
the denominator for this first term in the
likelihood is going to contain everybody.
And let's say I've got B smoking in my
model, so
I'm modelling the log hazard is equal to
some, this is Cox regression,
so baseline has it that we're not going to
be able to estimate, plus a beta for
smoking plus I'm also going to adjust for
age.
I'm going to adjust for baseline age, so
I'll throw in a beta for age.
So, the likelihood here would equal, well
who's the person who had the event.
The person who had the event is ID number
one.
They were 28 at baseline, and they had one
pack-year of smoking.
So, in the numerator their hazard is
going to be the beta for age times 28,
their baseline age, plus the beta for
smoking which was one pack-years.
And then everybody else is at risk.
So, I'm going to put all the other hazards
in the denominator.
So, that person who had the event, just
like that.
The, the second person, subject ID number
two, was 25 at baseline and
their 30 pack-years of smoking we're
going to need more room here.
The third person was 40 at their baseline
age and they were 0 pack
a year of smoking, the next person was 29
at baseline, and was also a non-smoker.
And then the final person was 30, at
baseline and 10 pack years of smoking.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, that would be first term in the
likelihood and
we could write out the other three terms,
I don't want to spend too much time on it.
I just want to show you what's going on
here is that everybody,
the first term in the likelihood is going
to include everybody.
The second term in the likelihood is
going to to include four people,
not including the one who already had the
event.
The last term in the likelihood will
happen here,
when there's two people left at risk.
There' s two who were still around at 12
years into the study.
We're going to make the likelihood a
function of the baseline age.
And in that way, we're adjusting for age.
And so that, you know, somebody who's
older, that's taken into account, or
somebody who is younger.
We also have a beta smoking in there.
We'll be estimating the beta for smoking.
And for the purposes of this example study
we're interested in the effect of smoking.
So that's the idea when we have, when we
want to look at time in the study.
Okay.
That's what we've been doing essentially
up until now.
Now, switching over here,
what if we wanted to use age as the time
scale instead?
How is that going to look different?
So, let me draw the little picture here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, when we use age as the time-scale
we're going to actually look at
a person's age rather than their time in
the study.
The ages here start at 25 so, I'll just
chart my age scale here at 25.
An excuse that this is not perfectly drawn
to scale and so person number one.
I'm going to put the pack years up here
cause that's going to help me to
remember when I'm writing the likelihood
of pack years for everybody.
So, person number one had one pack years
of smoking and they
joined the study at 28 years so that's
right about here, again, I apologize,
this isn't perfectly to scale, and they
were in the study until age 31,
and then had the event, so kind of a small
amount of time.
The second person was in the study from
ages 25, so let's say they had,
this person had 30 pack years of smoking,
they were in the study from age 25 until
age 30 and they have the event, again an x
designates the having the event here.
ID number three was at 0 pack years of
smoking.
They were in the study from ages 40 to 47
and
it was actually censored at the end of
that time period.
So, from age 40 to 47 and
they were censored and representing the
censored with a c here.
Notice that that person does not cross
over at all in ages with subject one or
subject two.
Therefore, they're never going to be in
the same term in the likelihood together.
ID number four was also a non-smoker.
They were in the study for a long time, so
from age 29 all the way up until age 41,
at which point they did have the event.
And then finally the fifth subject, who
had 10 pack-years of smoking,
was in the study from ages 30 all the way
up until age 43.
And they were centered at age 43.
So, now how would we actually write out
the likelihood for this little data set?
So, the likelihood here is going to be a
function of beta smoking.
Age is no longer going to be in the
likelihood because we're using age as
the time scale.
So, we're making the likelihood as a
function of beta smoking.
What's the first term in the likelihood
going to be?
Well, when does the, the first event
occur, so
remember the first event occurred three
years into the study for person one.
But if you use age as the time scale,
notice they're not the first person to
have the event.
The first person to have the event is the
second subject number two who had
the event at age 30.
So, she actually or he had the event
first, and at age 30,
there were four people who are age 30
during the time course of this study.
So, there's four people at risk at age 30.
The person who is in the study from 40 to
47 was not at risk at age 30.
So, what are we going to put into the
likelihood?
Well, the person who had the event is ID
number two,
subject number two, who had 30 pack years
of smoking.
So there, they go in the numerator, their
hazard goes in the numerator.
So, we're going to raise e, beta here is
beta smoking, e raised to beta times 30,
that's the hazard of having the event at
this time point, for the 30 year old, this
person who's 30 when he or she has the
event and has 30 pack years of smoking.
Now, I just realized that, that's well 30
pack years of smoking could mean she's
smoking 3 packs a day for 10 years and
then in the denominator, who is at risk?
So, ID subject number one is at risk,
they have a one, that person has one pack
year of smoking.
Obviously the one who had the event, the
30 pack year one is at risk, and
then subject number four is at risk, that
was a non-smoker, and then subject number
five was also at risk, that one had ten
pack years of smoking.
So, you notice right away that the
likelihood is different than what we
would use to time in the study as the time
scale.
What, when does the second event occur?
Well the second event occurs at age 31.
Subject one is age 31 when he or she has
the event.
There are three people at risk at that
time.
Subject two is already gone, they've
already had the event before he's 31,
and again subject three, is, doesn't join
the study until much later in, her life or
his life.
So the denominator here is going to be,
well the numerator first of all
is going to be the one who had the event,
that person has one pack year of smoking.
That person is also in the denominator.
Her or she is at risk.
Subject number four is also at risk,
that's a non-smoker.
And subject number five was also at risk
at that time.
So, that's the second term in the
likelihood.
The last event occurs at age 41.
That is in subject number four.
At that time there are also three people
at risk, because notice now subject number
three comes into play; because he or she
was in the study at age 41.
So, there are three people at risk at age
41, you have to squish this in here.
So, the person who had the event was a
non-smoker at age 41.
And then we had a, another non smoker at
risk.
So, the two non smokers at risk.
And that person who had ten pack years of
smoking.
So, there's three people at risk in the
risk set.
That would make up the entire likelihood,
for,
if you were using age as a time scale
here.
And then, of course, we would do maximum
likelihood estimation to solve for
the beta for smoking that made the most
sense.
But you can see that the likelihood comes
out differently meaning that
the beta coefficient is going to come out
differently for
smoking if we use age as the time scale
rather than time in the study.
And I went ahead and just wrote out that
likelihood again on a separate slide where
it's a little bit neater and I took a
little bit more room in writing it.
But that's just repeating what I did in
the last slide.
I've written out the entire likelihood for
you to see it written out.
I also want to show you that there are
slightly different ways that
you can model, that you can model age as
the time scale.
So, so
far we've been just choosing to look at
the ages in which a person was observed.
So, if we observe somebody from 28 to 31,
they are only at risk during those ages.
You could also start with time since
birth.
Their age since birth as the time stamp.
That makes a lot of sense if you're doing
a study on longevity obviously because if
a person joins your study at 28, we know
for sure that they didn't die before then.
So, there are cases where you'd rather use
the time since birth,
the age since birth as your time scale,
and then the people are at risk at
all ages up until the time that they had
the event or were censored.
So, let me just write up the corresponding
picture here,
and then I'll write out the likelihood, so
one, two, three, four, five subjects.
Here are the pack years, just so they're
handy when I'm writing out the likelihood.
So, the first person in the study, here's
the ages,
the first person in the study, subject
one, we know that they had the event,
let's say this, the outcome here is death.
They, they died at age 31.
So, they are at risk all the way, of
dying, all the way up until age 31.
Even though we only saw them from ages 28
to 31,
we're still going to count them at risk
all the way up until 31.
Subject two, if the outcome again here is
death, died at age 30, so, again,
at risk from birth though, subject three
is, had, was censored all the,
at age 47, so that person is at risk all
the way up to age 47.
Subject four died at age 41.
So, is at risk from birth until then.
And finally, subject five is censored at
age 43.
So, the picture looks like that.
The corresponding likelihood, it's
going to, again,
be a function of beta smoking.
Is now going to take everybody who's at
risk at a given age.
But there's going to be more people at
risk.
So, for example the event that happened at
age 30, subject two dying at age 30,
at that time everybody was at risk.
Everybody is now at risk at age 30.
So, the numerator is going to be E Raised
to beta three,
because that person at 30 pack years of
smoking.
That person is also in the denominator
there's their hazard.
He and everybody else is in that
denominator as well.
Everybody else is at risk.
So, if you're subject number one.
Here's, subject number three.
Here's subject number four, and here is
subject number five.
Everyone was at risk at that first event
time at age 30.
At age 31,
everybody is at risk except subject number
two who already died before age 31.
So, the likelihood would be the person who
died had one
pack year of smoking, so that's subject
one, this represents
subject three this is subject four and
this is subject five.
And finally the last event occurs when
there are still three people at risk.
Three people who crossed over age 41 and
that person,
the person who died was a non-smoker
that's subject number four but
also at risk was subject number three and
subject number five.
So, you can again see that the likelihood
looks slightly different if
we count the time since birth as the
time-scale.
You're going to be writing a lot of
likelihoods out this week and
so hopefully you'll get the hang of these.
Again, by looking at the likelihood,
you can really see what's going on in
terms of the model.
Just to give a quick example.
We've already seen an example where the
age was used as the time scale rather than
the time in the study and this was, they
used the age since birth.
This was the study looking at Academy
Award winners versus nominees.
They looked at actors and actresses.
As well as screen writers, I'm showing you
the Kaplan-Meier curve for
the screen writers here.
So, again in red, for screen writers, the
winners actually did worse than those
were only ever nominated, but you can see
on the Kaplan-Meier curve that the time
scale here is age and we start counting
from birth.
So, people are counted as at risk all the
way up through all of their ages,
and when somebody has an event, when
somebody dies here,
your counting a 50 year old; who might've
been born in the you know, 1920s.
We might be counting them against a 50
year old who was born in the 1940s,
in terms of the risk set, it's everybody
who has gone through the age 50 here.
And so this actually used age at the time
scale in
the Kaplan-Meier's here as well as in
their Cox regression.
So, this is an example of the use of age
as the time scale.