[BLANK_AUDIO]
Welcome to week four of the course.
This week, we're going to continue our
discussion of Cox regression, and
I'm going to tell you about some really
cool things that you can do with
a Cox regression model, including
incorporating time-changing predictors.
So this week we're going to talk more
about Cox regression.
I'm going to tell you about some
variations on Cox regression.
So, for one thing, last week we were
talking about using the time scale of
the time that you're in the study.
But we can actually switch the time scale
and
make the time scale age rather than time
in the study.
I'll show you how to do that.
We're also going to talk about
time-dependent predictors.
This is the first time that we've had a
model that incorporates time and therefore
that we are actually able to update
people's values for a given predictor.
That's really cool.
And I'll show you how that works this
week.
I'll also tell you some strategies for
dealing with repeated events.
So up until now, we've only been doing the
time until the first event occurs.
But what if you have an event, like a
heart attack or an episode of disability
that can happen, or a fracture, that can
happen multiple times during your study?
How do you deal with repeated events?
I'll also talk to you about how to deal
with clustered observations with
correlations in your data.
Most of what I'm going to be talking about
this week I'm going to have to present you
the likelihood function, go through how
things happen in the likelihood function.
For you to be able to really understand
what's going on,
you have to kind of dig into the
likelihood function.
So by the end of this week, you're going
to be dreaming in likelihood functions.
Just as a quick review, if you totally got
the likelihood function last week you
can fast forward this part, but let me
just give you a brief review of
the likelihood function for a Cox
regression so we're all on the same page.
So what I've done down here is I've drawn
out a very small simple little data set.
It's got four people in it.
Their ID numbers are one, two, three and
four.
And there's one predictor we're going to
look at, they're either in the treatment
group treatment equals one, or they're in
the control group treatment equals zero.
I've represented their data over time
here.
So for example subject one, it was in the
study for 12 months and
then the x means they had the event.
So they had the event.
Subject two was in the study for say,
about eight months.
And then the c represents the sensor.
How does this translate to a likelihood
function for Cox regression?
So remember that the likelihood function
for
Cox regression contains one term for every
event.
So, in this case we have two events.
Subject one and subjects three both have
the event so
we're going to have two terms in the
likelihood.
The terms and the likelihood again
represent the probability of your data.
For Cox regression, we're using a
conditional likelihood.
So we're looking at the probability of, if
we know.
We're conditioning on,
if we know that an event happened at five
months into the study.
We're conditioning on that fact.
If we know that an even happened at five
months into the study.
What's the probability that it happened to
subject three as opposed to
anybody else who was at risk?
That's what the term in a likelihood
represents.
So the denominator of the terms is going
to contain the probability of
anybody having the event at time two,
anybody who is at risk.
And we're going to be putting into that
denominator the hazard rate for
person, in this case subject one was at
risk at five months into the study.
Subject two was at risk, subject three was
at risk, and subject four was at risk.
So, the denominator contains the
probability of having the event at
exactly five months for any one of those
four people who were at risk.
Each of their hazard rates.
The numerator is going to contain the
hazard, the probability for the person who
actually did have the event, which happens
to be subject three here.
Remember, for Cox regression, the baseline
hazards, we're going to assume that
everybody has the same baseline hazard and
those are going to cancel out, so
we're not going to be estimating any
intercepts here.
And so, what is the hazard function
actually?
What does it boil down to?
It's going to be some e raised to data one
times x one times beta two times x two.
Whatever you have in your Cox regression
model for predictors.
Well, in this case, let's say we just have
one predictor which is treatment.
The person who had the event was person
three subject three.
They were not on treatment.
They have a value of zero for treatment.
We can also replace the hazard functions
in the denominator,
in terms of e raised to betas.
And so the person who had the event, they
had beta raised, times zero.
The person who, everybody else who was at
risk we had,
subject one who is in the treatment group
who is at risk.
That's their chance of having the event
right now as a function of beta.
Subject two was also in the treatment
group, and
then finally subject four was a control.
So that's what the first terminal
likelihood here is going to look like.
Again, representing the probability that
it was subject three as opposed to
anybody else who was at risk.
Conditioned on the fact we know we had an
event at five months into the study.
The second event happened at 12 months
into the study.
At that time period, there were only two
people at risk, subject one and
subject four.
So the only people who could've had the
event there is the subject four,
who was in the control group and subject
one, who was in the treatment group.
The one who actually had the event was
subject one who was
in the treatment group.
So that would be our likelihood function
for this simple data set.
If you understand the likelihood function,
that's going to allow you to do a lot of
cool things.
So one of the things that we're going to
grapple with this week is incorporating
time changing predictors into our model.
So, what do I mean by that?
Go back to this example I was talking
about last week
about Academy Award winners, and those who
are only ever nominated, and
I'm showing you the Kaplan–Meier curve
here for the screenwriters.
For the screenwriters, unlike for the
actors and actresses, those
who are ever only nominated actually did
better than those who were the winners.
But what's interesting if you think
carefully about this Kaplan–Meier curve,
there was a problem with this analysis, as
I mentioned.
Look, you can see that the time scale here
is age, so we're starting at age zero.
We are counting people is in the nominee
group on the red line, or
in the winners group on the blue line from
birth.
But that somehow seems wrong because
people were not
didn't win an Academy Award at birth, they
weren't nominated at birth.
Those events of being nominated or winning
an Academy Award happen much later in
life, and yet we're somehow assuming that
their status in one group or
the other translates and so, effects their
longevity their whole life.
So there's something quite wrong with
that.
With time-changing predictors what we're
going to be able to do is to correctly
count somebody as a control or a nominee
or as a winner for
the ages in which they were in one of
those groups.
So you can have the status of being a
nominee only for many,
many years before we switch you into the
winner's group.
That's going to be a much better way to
analyze these data.
I'm also going to tell you this week how
to deal with repeated events.
And so I'm just showing you an example
here of a study that has repeated events.
There are five subjects pictured here.
Every time you see a little black dot,
that's an episode of disability.
So what you'll notice is that some
subjects had many episodes of
disability over time.
Up until now I've only told you how to
deal with time to first event,
that would be the first dot you see on
each of these, but if you just look at
time the first event for data like this,
you'd be missing a lot of information, so
how we grapple with, how do we handle
repeated events?
I'll show you how to do that this week.