[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to talk
about statistical tests that simplify or
ignore the repeated measures outcome.
So there are a number of ways that you can
actually get around having to
handle the repeated measures at all.
So one option is to actually collapse that
repeated measurement into one value,
a single value for every person.
If every person only has one value, then
you don't have to handle any correlations.
So for example I'm going to show you in a
minute how to collapse all of
your measurements into a single slope for
every person.
Then you can use those slopes in
subsequent analysis.
You could also choose just to focus on one
time point.
Usually that would be the final time
point,
because presumably we care most about what
happened last.
So you could only compare groups with
respect to the final measurement
using something like an ANCOVA adjusting
for any baseline differences.
This is called an end-point analysis.
And, I'll show you how to run this one, as
well.
So, just to have some example data to play
with here,
I'm going to use that same dataset that I
showed you how to graph last week.
So, this was a dataset on 41 women
runners.
At the beginning of this study, they all
had irregular periods.
And women runners with irregular periods
tend to have low bone density.
So, we were following them over time to
see if their bone density would go up.
We identified three groups of women.
So, the group here in blue are women who
continue to
have irregular periods throughout the
study.
And you can see that their bone density
stayed pretty flat.
Then we had a group of women in red who
spontaneously regained their periods, and
you can see that their bone density went
up a couple of percentage points.
And we also had a group in black who took
hormones and
got their periods back that way, and also
had some increase in bone density.
I showed you how to graph those data last
week, now we want to attach some p
value to that to say whether or not our
groups are significantly different.
So, one strategy is to use this idea of a
slope analysis.
I talked a little bit about it slope
analyses last week as well.
What I'm doing here is I'm saying okay
I've got three spine bone
density measurements on each woman.
And rather than having to deal with those
three measurements,
I am going to calculate one slope for each
woman based on those three measurements.
So I'm literally going to be running a
linear regression model for each woman.
The slope that I'm trying to calculate
here is
going to represent the rate of change
[BLANK_AUDIO]
in spine bone density.
And, and time here is in years, so it's
going to be a rate of change in years.
I'm going to take say this woman over here
in the left.
She had bone density measurements of about
0.944, 0.938 and 0.948.
So, she's really staying rather constant.
But she goes up just a little bit over
time.
And so I'm going to take her three
measurements and
run the following linear regression.
The outcome is spine bone mineral density,
the predictor here is time.
And I do get to treat time as a continuous
variable here.
So the women were supposed to be measured
at one year and two year post-baseline.
But you can see she was a little bit
beyond a year and
little bit beyond two years.
So I'm going to just take these three data
points,
I'm fitting a linear regression line just
based on three data points.
I'm going to take these three data points.
I'm going to fit a linear regression line
to them.
You can see that line pictured here.
That line will have an intercept and a
beta.
The beta, that's slope represents sort of
an average rate of
change in spine bone density per year for
that woman.
I'm going to take that beta, I'm going to
save it for further analyses.
I'm then going to do that for the next
woman in my data set.
So, I'll run the same linear regression
model for
her, but I'll get a new beta for her.
I'll get a different beta.
So her beta, so the first woman's beta was
something positive,
the second woman's beta you can see is
going to be slightly negative,
because she's going down a little bit over
time.
So her rate of change is negative.
So I'll take her data coefficient, her
slope or rate of change, and
I'll save that into a dataset.
And then I'll do that for all 41 women.
I'll come up with 41 slopes.
I will then use those slopes as the
outcome variable in a,
another linear regression analysis.
Those slopes now become the outcome.
So I'm going to run another linear
regression where the slope,
the rate of change of bone density, is the
outcome.
because that's what we care about.
We care about how these women's bone
densities are changing over time.
So those rates of change, those slopes,
now become the outcome.
I only have one value per woman, so I can
just run a regular linear regression.
In this new linear regression, I'm
going to have an intercept of course, and
then my predictor here is the groups.
I, I'm calling them black, red, and blue
here just for simplicity.
I've gotta a categorical predictor, so I'm
going to have the dummy code.
So I will have a beta for the black group,
and I will have a beta for
the red group, and I'm making the blue
group my reference group just
because they're the ones that had the
least increase in bone density over time.
I fit that linear regression model as you
can see here.
And we can then figure out,
we actually are going to get an effect
size and a P value here.
So for example, for the red group, we get
a beta coefficient of 0.013.
The way would interpret that is, this is a
rate of change per year.
So, and we're comparing to the reference
group of the blue group.
So they have a 1.3% bigger change in bone
density per year than the blue group.
Their rate of change is 1.3% higher.
That is a statistically significant
difference, so the red group and the blue
group are significantly different in their
rate of change in bone density over time.
We get something very similar for the
black group.
Their data coefficient corresponds to that
their rate of change in
spine bone density is about 1.1, 1.2%
higher per year than the blue group.
And they also just make a statistical
significance there.
This slope analysis has a number of
advantages actually.
It notice that we got to treat time as
continuous, so that's nice.
We also, if we had some missing data like
if a woman was
missing just one measurement, we'd still
be able to calculate the slope on her,
because all we need is two time points to
be able to fit a slope, to fit a line.
So it actually handles missing data pretty
well.
We could also have continuous predictors
in this approach.
And so there is a number of advantages.
However, it does have some disadvantages.
Obviously we're reducing a lot of
information,
we're collapsing a lot of measurements
into a single measurement, and
thus we're losing information and
statistical power.
That's the main disadvantage.
It also doesn't handle time-changing
predictors at all.
But keep in mind that the slope analysis.
It, it is pretty elegant in, in some ways,
even though it's simple.
And in a way it's kind of a crude version
of what we're going to see when we
do mixed models.
Now turning to the end point analysis.
So the end point analysis is going to
focus on just the final time point.
So this corresponds to the graphic we had
where we were looking at
the absolute values of the spine bone
density.
We're going to compare among the three
groups the final value of spine bone
density, which for the red and black
groups was right around 0.98 or 0.99.
For the blue group it was somewhere about
0.93 or 0.94.
Now you'll notice that the, the groups
actually started a little bit different.
The, the blue group it was a little lower
at baseline.
A little bit lower to start with so we're
also going to adjust these analysis for
that difference at baseline.
So the ANCOVA analysis, it's just another
linear regression.
My outcome though is the final spine bone
density.
And my predictors are going to be, I'm
going to be putting in a predictor for
the initial bone density, so that we can
adjust for it.
That will take care of fact that the blue
group started a little bit lower.
Plus I'm going to have betas for the, for
the groups.
I'm dummy coding here, so I'm going to
have a beta for
the black group and I'm going to have a
beta for the red group.
And I'm going to leave the blue group as
the reference group, here again,
because they're, they're the ones who
stayed kind of flat.
So that going to be my model.
It's a linear regression.
We also can call it an ANCOVA,
an analysis of covariance because we have
a categorical predictor.
If we're thinking about it as an analysis
of covariance.
Then we can think about doing things like
calculating adjusted means or
least squares means, and that's kind of
useful.
So you can see here are the adjusted or
least squares means.
These means have been adjusted for the
base line difference in bone density.
You can see that the values are very
similar to the absolute values that you
can see on the graph.
However, the blue group,
the adjusted value is a little bit higher
than what you see on the graph.
The value on the graph is like 0.935.
After we adjust for
the fact that they started lower, that
brings them up a little bit closer.
So the adjusted value is 0.958.
But you can see that they are still a
little bit lower than the black and
red group, even after adjusting for that
initial difference.
So we can get those adjusted means, we can
also get p values
comparing the different groups, and that's
what you see over on the right here.
The one, two, and three, correspond to
black, red, and blue.
And there are three p values here that are
repeated in this table.
But if we compare the red group to the
black group,
clearly those are very similar, and so the
p value is totally non-significant.
If we compare the blue group to the black
group,
that one just makes statistical
significance, and
these p values are adjusted for multiple
comparisons with a 2D adjustment.
Because we are now doing multiple
comparisons by com,
doing three comparisons here.
If you compare the blue and the red group
after adjusting for
multiple comparisons, that one is also
statistically significant.
Those two groups have the biggest
difference, so
not surprisingly, they also have the
smallest p value.
So again, we are able to detect a
significant difference here,
using this endpoint analysis.
The endpoint analysis is nice and simple
but it does have a number of limitations.
So again, we're reducing a lot of
information and
thus we're losing a lot of statistical
power.
We're actually throwing out all interim
measurements, so,
it's kind of a waste of data.
If you're missing data on that very last
time point,
since that's the only time point we're
looking at.
If somebody had, wasn't measured, they're
going to be thrown out unless you
impute their values, so you're going to be
needing to be doing some imputation here.
The end point analysis also doesn't handle
time-changing predictors in any way.
So the end point analysis has a number of
limitations.
However, it is simple and easy to
interpret.