[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about some of the math that
underlies the Cox regression model.
Specifically, we're going to talk about
the likelihood function.
I'm not expecting you to be able to
maximize any likelihood functions or
take any derivatives or anything like
that.
But I do want you to have a basic
understanding of what the likelihood
function looks like.
That's going to be especially important
when we start talking about time
changing predictors.
So the likelihood function, when we talk
about parametric regression had
one term in the likelihood for every
observation, every person in the study.
The likelihood function for Cox
regression, which is sometimes called
a partial likelihood function, is going to
have one term in the likelihood for
every event time, so every unique time
when events occurred.
So just like Kaplan–Meier is pegged on
those event times,
the partial likelihood is pegged on those
event times.
I just want to point out that Kaplan–Meier
methods,
we call those non-parametric because we
estimated no parameters.
The parametric regression methods, we
called those parametric because we
estimated all the parameters, all the
alphas and the betas.
The Cox regression method is sometimes
called semi-parametric because we're
going to estimate some of the parameters,
but not others.
We're not going to bother to estimate the
intercepts, but
we are going to estimate the betas.
So this is called, also, a partial
likelihood.
Just to set up with the likelihood
function is going to be here.
The likelihood function again is the
probability of our data, and
it's going to be a conditional likelihood,
kind of similar to
conditional logistic regression, the
likelihood that we saw there.
The likelihood function is going to have
one term in the likelihood for
every event time.
And basically, it's going to be a
conditional probability.
So we're going to have a term, say, at a
particular event time in the study,
I don't know, event time equals 4,
whatever it might be.
There are a certain number of people who
are still at risk of
having the event at time four.
Those are the people who have some
probability of having the event at
four months into the study.
What's going to go in the denominator is
that for
everybody at risk we're going to put their
probability of having the event, of dying,
or having whatever the event is, at that
exact time, at time is equal to four.
And every person may have a different
hazard rate depending on their
risk factors.
So let's make this really simple and say
that there
are only four people that are still at
risk in our study at event time 4,
we're calling them subjects one through
four.
I'm writing down their hazard function
here,
because remember the hazard function is a
person's probability of having the event
at exactly that time, at exactly event
time four.
So the denominator represents the
probability of somebody,
anyone who's at risk.
[NOISE].
Having the event.
And let's just call the event time, the
event here,
dying just to make it easier for me to
write.
So just imagine the event is dying, so
it's the probability that
the denominator represents that the
probability that anybody in
the risk set whose still at risk, dies at
that time, timing equal to four.
Well, what actually happened in our data?
Somebody died.
So we're conditioning on the fact that
somebody died at time four.
And who was it that died?
Let's say that it happens to be person
two, who happened to be the one who died.
So the probability of this event,
the given that we know that somebody died
at event time four,
what is the probability that it's person
two who died as opposed to anybody else?
That's what this conditional probability
represents.
So we put the hazard, the probability of
the person who did die,
what actually happened in our data, we put
their hazard in the numerator.
So you can imagine then of course these
hazard functions are going to be
a function of your risk factor.
So maybe person two is a smoker and
has all these other bad risk factors, and
that will mean that the betas for
smoking and things will reflect the fact
that they died early in the study.
But we get these conditional probability
terms in likelihood.
That's what the likelihood function looks
like.
This is going to be nice, because we're
going to be able to cancel some
things out as we did with conditional
logistic regression.
I think it would actually be helpful to
just make this really simple by
writing out a likelihood for a very simple
data set.
So, I'm going to kind of lead you through
how you'd write out the likelihood for
this small little data set.
And I think that will help you to
understand that,
once you've seen one written out.
So we've got a data set here with just six
people in it.
Five of them died, so there are five event
times, so
that likelihood function is going to have
five terms in it.
The only thing, we're going to do a Cox
regression model.
Let me just write out the Cox model first.
So the Cox regression model is going to
say that the log of our hazard rate is
equal to the some, log of the, some
baseline hazard rate.
Of course, we're not going to want to have
to specify that, but that's in the model.
plus, a beta for age, we're only going to
have age in the model, and nothing else.
And just to make this easy to write out,
I'm going to say that beta, I'm going to
write the word beta.
And what I mean by beta, here, is beta
age, so
that I don't have to keep writing out age
every time.
So there's only one beta in the model, the
beta here is beta age.
If that's the Cox regression model, that
means that the hazard rate for
a given person, we have to exponentiate
both sides to get the hazard rates.
So if I exponentiate both sides with the
hazard rate for
a person is equal to the baseline hazard
rate,
exponentiate it, so e raised to some
baseline hazard rate at a given time,
times e raised to beta age, times their
age, whatever their age might be.
So that's going to be the hazard rate at a
given time for a given person.
So now, let me write out the likelihood.
So the first thing that happens in my data
as at time equals 1, we have an event.
So we're going to get a term in the
likelihood, where time is equal to 1 and
actually, I'm going to write this out for
you.
It's going to be pretty long.
For the first event time, we have
everybody still at risk.
So what's going to go in the numerator
here the hazard for the person who died.
So, the hazard for the person who died is
this base line hazard for t is equal to 1.
Whatever that might be,
which we're eventually not going to bother
to estimate, but
rather we're going to cancel out, times e
raised to beta, the beta for
age, times this person's age.
The person age who died was 60 years old.
So they, we're plugging in their age.
That's the person who died, who is at
risk.
So everybody at risk includes everybody in
the set here.
So the person who died, that's they're
risk of dying at exactly one month
into the study plus the second person, the
65-year old, their hazard looks like this.
[NOISE].
Plus, the third person, their hazard,
everybody's at risk still,
looks like this.
[NOISE].
And you can see this is going to be very
long.
Then the fourth person, their hazard looks
like that.
And, I'm going to add to that the
probability of the fifth person dying,
their hazard, their chance of dying right
then is equal to that.
And then finally the 40 year old, their
hazard, their chance of dying,
their probability of dying at one month
into the study is equal to that.
Notice that these are all,
these probabilities are all a function of
this unknown beta.
Well, that's what we're going to try to
solve when we maximize this function.
We're going to solve for this beta for
age.
Alright, this looks rather cumbersome.
It's tedious to write out, but I want you
to notice something that everybody has
the same baseline hazard, because the
numerate, we have a numerator and
a denominator here, all the baseline
hazards can cancel.
We're assuming everybody has the same
baseline hazard, and, at time equals 1,
and we are just going to cancel them out.
Whatever the hazard rate is at time equals
1 doesn't matter,
because everybody has the same one, that
same baseline hazard.
We're just going to cancel those out, so
that's a nice thing about a conditional
likelihood, we just get to cancel out that
intercept, we do not have to estimate it,
and I'm going to just erase it here to
make this easier to read.
So we've now cancelled those out,
we no longer have to worry about
estimating an alpha here an intercept.
It means we don't have to specify what
that baseline hazard function looks like.
It doesn't have to follow a particular
mathematical function.
We are not committed to anything.
So that's what the terminal likelihood now
looks like for time is equal to 1.
How about for time equals 2?
So at time equals, well time equals 2
nothing happens, so
at time equals 3 that's when we have our
next event.
So we get a terminal likelihood for time
equals 3.
Alright, so that's going to look like, who
is at risk?
Well, the person who died at time 1 is no
longer at risk, so
we're just going to have the rest of them
at risk.
[NOISE].
And the person who died was the
65-year-old, so they're in the numerator.
And, and so on and so forth, we're
going to keep going.
Notice that the denominator shrinks every
time you lose people and
the person who was censored will be in the
first three terms in the likelihood, but
they won't be in the likelihood after
that, because they'll be censored.
They never get to be in the numerator, but
they're in the denominator a few times.
And so on, so we could write this whole
thing out and then we'd have a function.
Take the log of that function, maximize
it, and so I'll take the derivative, and
solve, you know, solve for beta there.
Obviously if people with the higher ages
are dying early that's going to lead to us
estimating that beta is associated with
dying early.
I stopped writing out this,
it takes a while to write out, but I went
ahead and you can pause the video if you
want to see that you agree with the full
likelihood that I've written out here.
Make sure that you can follow how the full
This is very, this likelihood is very
interesting,
it's going to come back again when we talk
about time changing predictors,
because I want you to notice something,
that every person,
every time they're at risk, I'm writing
their age in to determine the likelihood.
So for example, the 60-year old,
well let's not do the 60-year old because
he drops out after, but
the 40-year old, that 40-year old is in
the denominator of the first term.
He's in the denominator, he or she is in
the denominator for
the second term, the third term, the
fourth term, and the fifth term.
Now they're in each one of those.
Why that's important is I've written the
age 40 five different times.
But what if we had a predictor that could
change over time.
Because I have to re-enter the value every
time there's an event for a person, that
leaves open the possibility that I don't
have to write the same value every time.
Now, age of course, is not a good example,
but what if we had something like weight,
and somebody was, weighed a 100 pounds at
time point one, but
then at three months they weighed 120
pounds.
You would put in a 100 in the first
terminal likelihood, and
then you'd just put in 120 in the second
term.
So all of a sudden, this likelihood
function suddenly allows us
to update people's values for the
predictors.
This is the first time we've had that
flexibility.
So I'm going to be talking about that next
week, but
it's just kind of built into the
likelihood function.
So that's really cool.
Tuck that into the back of your mind, and
we'll get back to that next week.
After you've written out the likelihood
function, which,
again, I'm not going to make you write
out, but
I just want you to understand what it
looks like.
Once you've written out the likelihood
function,
then you're just going to maximize it.
So that means you take the log of the
likelihood function with respect to beta,
take the derivative, set it equal to zero,
find, solve for beta.
And that's going to be the value of beta
that makes your data the most likely.
And of course, we want to make our data
the most likely.
That's the maximum likelihood estimates.
So just the same as when we did maximum
likelihood estimation for
logistic regression or any other
generalized linear model.
Out of maximum likelihood estimation you
also, the variance, or
the standard error of beta also falls out
of that method.
So the variance actually turns out be
related to the second derivative of
the likelihood function.
So we can get a standard error for beta.
And that's nice because that allows us to
do hypothesis testing, so you don't have
to do any of this, but the computer will
give you the standard error for
beta and a p-value that goes with beta.
The p-value that goes with the beta for a
particular predictor is just,
you take the estimate for beta and divide
it by the standard error.
You get what we call the asymptotic
standard error because again,
that came out of maximum likelihood
estimation.
So beta divided by it's standard error
will follow a z-distribution.
So it will come with a p-value to tell you
whether or
not beta is significantly different from
zero.
A beta of zero of course would mean the
slope of zero,
no relationship between the predictor and
the hazard function.
Just to give an example, remember we had
some data last week on a hepatitis trial.
People with active hepatitis were given
either a treatment, a steroid, or
were in the control group.
I ran these data in a Cox regression
model.
Out come our maximum likelihood estimates,
we get a parameter, we get a beta, we get
a standard error for beta.
If you divide beta by it's standard error
you get a z-value which is
a little bit more than two.
You can square that to get a chi-square
with one degree of freedom that
corresponds to a p-value of just under
0.05.
So this p-value just comes out of dividing
beta by it's standard error,
as we did with logistic regression.
Also, what,
what else do you get out of maximum
likelihood, the maximum likelihood method?
Well you get the negative 2 log
likelihoods, and
you can do global tests of whether any of
the betas in the model are significant.
The one we've talked most about is the
likelihood ratio test.
So if you take the negative 2 log
likelihood from one model and
subtract it from the negative 2 log
likelihood from a nested model,
you get a chi-square with degrees of
freedom equal to the number of parameters
different between the two models and you
can get a p-value with that.
So this will tell you in, in this
particular example I
only have one beta in the model, but if
you have multiple betas in the model,
the null hypothesis here is that all of
the betas are equal to zero.
So if that rejects,
that tells you that something in the model
is predictive an overall global test.
We can also get statistics about model
fit.
So, again, the negative 2 log likelihood
if I do the model without any covariates,
I subtract from that the model with the
covariates.
The one that has more covariates is always
going to be smaller.
You subtract those, that's going to have a
chi-square in this case with one degree of
freedom because there's only one covariate
in the model.
That in this case comes out to be a little
over four, and
does come out to be statistically
significant, so
that's that likelihood ratio statistic
that we just talked about.
You also get something called the AIC
criteria,
which I have talked about a little
earlier.
All this is is you take the negative 2 log
likelihood value and
you add 2 times the number of parameters
in your model.
In this case we only have one parameter in
our model, one beta, so
I'm just going to add 2, so 173 plus 2
gives me 175.
With the AIC, smaller is better, so
if you wanted to compare different models,
they don't even have to be nested models.
Different models on the same data, if,
the one with the smaller AIC is going to
be considered the better fit model,
because the AIC has a penalty built in for
the number of parameters.
So you've been essentially controlled for
The negative 2 log likelihood is always
going to be
smaller when you put more parameters in
the model, so we need to correct for
that, that's what the AIC does.
So that's a statistic you can use to
compare different models.