[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to give you
several different strategies, for
plotting repeated measures data.
So, it's always important to plot your
data, but
it becomes even more important when we're
dealing with repeated measures.
Because there's an additional layer of
complexity to the data, and
sometimes when you just throw things into
the black box of regression, it's hard to,
get the right answer, but if you look at
the picture,
you're always going to get the right
answers.
So, it's really, it's really important to
plot.
The data that I'm going to use as an
example for
this module is the same runner's data.
I've got longitudinal data on, bone
density in women runners, and
women runners are at risk for having low
bone density.
So, we measure their bone density at
baseline, about a year later and
about two years later.
And for the purposes of this module, just
have some groups to compare.
I'm going to compare three groups.
So, there was a subset of women.
Who, had irregular periods at, baseline
and
that puts you at risk of having low bone
density, and
some of those women went on to a
spontaneously regain their periods.
Some of the women went on to take oral
contraceptives to get their periods back,
and other women still had, irregular
periods at the end of the study and
we can compare, the trajectory of changes
in bone density in those three groups, so
the first type of plot I'm going to talk
about is, what we call a mean plot or
a profile plot, and I already showed you
several examples of these.
When I, showed you the examples of
repeated measures from
the medical literature.
This is typically the way people will
plot, repeated measures data.
Now, the key is that we, are going to
assume,
that there are some regular follow-up
times so that, everybody in
our study comes back kind of at the same
time for their follow-up measurements.
We're going to set esssence treating time
as discrete.
At each of those, regular follow-up times.
We're going to calculate the mean value of
the outcome for, everybody or
you know, broken down by different groups
for
different groups, and we're just going to
plot those means against time so,
here's you know the mean for one group at
time one, and a time two and a time three.
We're going to connect those means, with
some lines and
typically we'll also add like some like
standard deviation or standard error bars.
[SOUND].
Now, one of the key things that you have
to keep in mind when doing these
mean plots is that, often with follow up
data.
With longitudinal data, our sample size
sort of shrinks over time.
So, maybe the first, at the first
follow-up time.
That baseline there's 105 people in our
study.
But then, by the second measurement
[INAUDIBLE] the first follow-up time.
Maybe we're down to 105.
And then, maybe by the third measurement
we're down to like 90, and
it keeps shrinking from there.
So, as you lose people over time, you're
essentially changing the groups, so
it's going to be very important that you
impute missing values,
because we don't want to compare our, one
group of people at time one bear mean,
to a totally different group of people at
time two.
The 20 people that we lose between,
between the first time and
the second time, might be the 20 who have
the highest values.
And so, it might look like we're having a
decrease in the outcome simply because of,
who we lost.
So, we want to be comparing apples to
apples, so
we need to make sure, that our ends remain
constant.
And the way that you can do that is by
imputing missing values.
A simple way to impute,
the missing values is something called
last observation carried forward.
That's what I've done for the plots I'm
going to show you on the next page.
What that does is, if a woman is missing a
follow-up value,
you take the last value that you saw on
her.
And you, carry it forward.
So, you fill in her value at say time two,
with her value from time one.
What that does is if, if a person if you
know, for
the example of bone density if a woman
happens to have really high bone density.
And she drops out, you're at least
carrying forward her high value, so
that there isn't an artificial drop in the
mean, at time two,
just due to the fact that we've lost her.
So, that's going to be important to keep
in mind.
There's kind of two ways you can do these
plots.
You can plot the, absolute value in the
outcome variable.
The, the absolute mean.
Value or, the mean percent change since
baseline I'll show you both of those, so
now, I'm just showing you the plots two
different ways of plotting, the outcome
here is spine bone density and again I'm
looking at these three groups of women
runners in my study, I'm going to start
with the graph on the left hand side.
This is plotting the mean, percent change
from baseline.
So, what you'll notice is that, everybody
starts at 0 because at baseline your
mean percent change, your percent change
since baseline, at baseline is 0.
So, everybody starts at 0.
And then, we're going to calculate for
every person in my data set, their percent
change, from baseline to Year 1.
So, imagine that I've got a woman,
who has a spine bone density at baseline
of 1.0 [SOUND] and then,
at one year into the study, [SOUND]
she has a value of 1.03.
And then let's say, at two years into the
study, she has a value of, 1.05.
So, her percent changes.
Are going to be, well 0 at baseline.
And then, 3% at Year 1.
She went up, 3% from baseline to Year 1.
And then, 5% at Year 2.
From baseline to Year 2 she went up 5%.
We're going to calculate these percent
change values for Year 1 and for
Year 2 for every person in the data set.
And then, we'll calculate the average for
each group.
So, for example, this blue group here,
these are the women, who had irregular
periods throughout this study.
You can see that on average, they went
down about .5% from baseline to Year 1.
And they were basically stable.
They didn't change much by the end of the
study.
By Year 2 is about, a 0% change.
In contrast, the red group which were
those who,
spontaneously regained their periods, and
the black group, which were those who
started taking oral contraceptives, and
got their periods back that way.
They went up about 1% in the first year of
the study and about, you know,
2+ percent in the second year of the
study.
So, that's the graph on the left hand
side.
The graph on the right hand side is very
similar except rather than, plotting these
percent changes in space line we're just
going to, plot the actual absolute values.
So, you can see that, spine bone density
is measured in grams per
centimeters squared and a typical value is
1.0.
These women were all a little low to begin
with because of
the fact that they were having irregular
periods at baseline.
So, they're a little below 1.
But, what's interesting is you can see
that the blue group,
they were even kind of a riskier group,
because they started with a lower,
baseline value than the other two groups.
So, that's something that the, the
baseline differences don't show up on
the percent change graph, that you do see
them on the absolute value graph.
And then, we're just going to calculate
the,
mean value of spine bone density for each
of those groups of baseline.
We do those mean values at Year 1 and at
Year two.
And again, connect them with some dots.
And, you can see that the base, the same
basic, general pattern emerges from
this plot, but you get the additional
information, on the opposite plot of
whether or not there were any, baseline
differences, as you can see here.
And, the other thing, as you can see,
that the percent change graph, well, it's
maybe a little bit.
Prettier.
Those tend to be a little bit neater.
It may be a little bit easier to
interpret.
So, depending on, the problem,
depending on what you're trying to show,
one of these graphs might be preferable.
But those are both, they're, they're
going to give you basically the same,
general pattern.
I also went ahead, and did the same plots
for
plots for whole body bone mineral content,
which is just the total amount of calcium
in your skeleton, just as another example.
You can see again, same, same general
idea.
There's the group, group in blue is kind
of going down over time.
The other two groups are going up over
time.
One is displayed as the percent change
since baseline,
which gives you a little bit more you
know, you can, the x axis, or
the y axis can be stretched out a little
bit more so you can.
You know, it gives you a little more
distinction.
But the absolute values,
actually tell you what the absolute values
were on the right-hand side.
So, those are the mean plots.
A second type of plot you can do is
actually,
rather than calculating the averages at
the discrete time points,
which assumes that everybody was measured
at the same follow-up time points,.
Another option is that,
there is a way to do the graph, where you
can treat time as continuous.
And this is important if you've got data,
where not everybody was measured,
at the same follow-up time points,
especially if there's a lot of variability
in those follow-up times.
When you do this graph, it's important
that, you have to have some way to
account for the fact that it's the same
person over time.
So, we're really only going to be able to
do the percent change since baseline,
that's the only way to.
Account for the correlation over time.
You're not going to be able to do the
absolute value graph, in this one,
because that won't account for, the fact
that it's the same person over time.
We're going to plot each subject's percent
change since baseline,
against their actual follow-up time,
whatever that follow-up time is.
We're not going to be calculating any
means here.
We're just going to be doing a scatter
plot,
of the percent change since baseline
against the follow-up time.
Then we'll superimpose a smoothing line
for
each of the different groups to figure out
what the patterns are over time.
Notice that, we're not calculating any
means here.
So, we don't have to impute the missing
values.
If a, person doesn't come back for their
follow up value, you know,
maybe they're only going to contribute
only one or
two dots, to the follow up to the scatter
plot.
So, maybe here's a woman who comes back,
the first time, but maybe she doesn't come
back at Year 1 like she was supposed to,
but she comes back at Year 2.
We can still, fit the smoothing line to
those data.
We don't have to do anything about.
Filling in, the values that are missing.
A person contributes, just when they were
measured.
Let me just show you some examples.
This will become clearer with an actual
example.
So, what I've done here is on the same,
same data as before,
the outcome here is this spine bone
density, it's the,
I've done the percent change since
baseline in, spine bone density.
Again you need to do percent change here.
And, I'm plotting that against the years,
since the baseline DXA.
Now, you can see that time is continuous,
there's some variability in
when women actually came back, for these
follow up measurements.
Women were asked to come back at one year,
and then at two years.
But here's what actually happened.
So, here's one year.
You can see that, women did come back, by
and large right around one year.
But there's some variability.
Not everybody came back right at one year,
some people were a little late, in coming
back.
If you go to two years, there's even more,
variability, right.
Women were supposed to come back at two
years.
But there's a huge amount of variability
in.
When people actually, came for those
measurements, the end of a study you know
people get busy, we had to chase people
down a little bit to get them in, and
sometimes took longer than, the two years
that it was supposed to take [SOUND].
[COUGH] Let me just tell you, what, you
know, is actually being plotted here so
let me give you an example, so this person
right here this little dot right here,
what is this represent so this is saying
that this.
This person had, was measured, they came
back for
their one year follow-up visit right about
one year, just a little after one year.
At that time point compared with baseline,
they had a, about a,
negative three and one half percent
decrease in their spine bone density.
I don't know, which other dot represents
that person, but
that's okay since, everything is.
Calculated as the percent change this
baseline sort of accounted, for
the within subject correlation.
Then I super imposed for each of the
different groups,
these smoothing lines to get the pattern
over time, and
you can see the general pattern that
emerges is very similar.
To the pattern, that we saw with the,
profile plots, with the mean plots.
However, there's a little more subtlety,
on where we treat time as continuous.
It's accounting for the, variation in
time, and
that can make, some difference in the
trajectory over time as you can see here,
especially with so much variation at Year
2.
You also, as I mentioned, [SOUND] do not
have to impute, the missing data for
this, left-hand graph because, if a person
didn't come back,
they just don't get a dot for Year 2 or
for Year 1 or around that time point.
Whenever they come back they get a dot,
and that's it.
And you see the general pattern is, the
same.
There's certain advantages again of the,
left hand plot here.
I went ahead did the same plot with whole
body bone mineral content.
Again, you can see that the general
pattern that emerges is very similar to
what we saw, for the mean plots.
You get a little bit more going on at the
end here, so, you know,
we were definitely decreasing, in the blue
group.
You know, with the, full body bone mineral
content.
And that pattern is borne out to about two
years.
And then, you can see though, there's a
few people who came back after that, and
that drags the, this line a little bit up.
So, you get slightly different patterns.
But generally it looks.
Pretty similar, but this can make a
difference, depending on the data set that
you have, if you have a lot of variation
in follow up times.
[SOUND] So, those are just a couple of
different ways,
that you can plot repeated measures data.
[BLANK_AUDIO]