In this next module I'll just walk you
through an example of the use of
time dependent predictors in the
literature.
Just to get some practice with the idea of
using time dependent predictors.
I'm going to show you a study from the
literature that was looking at whether or
not antidepressant use, women who take
antidepressants during pregnancy,
does that prevent major episodes of
depression?
So you can imagine that a woman who has
depression may have to wrestle with
the question of, should I continue taking
my antidepressants during pregnancy.
Obviously, you know, we generally, caution
women against taking too
many drugs during pregnancy because of
potential impacts on the fetus.
And but, if the antidepressants can
prevent a major episode of depression,
then there might be reason for some women
to actually take them.
The risks the benefits would outweigh the
risks in that case.
So, trying to get at that question there
was some authors who had data from from
a large cohort study,
they did an analysis of 778 pregnant women
who all had a history of depression.
And the predictor of interest here with
the use of antidepressants, but you can
imagine something like antidepressants is
going to change over time.
Some women may start or stop taking them
during their pregnancy.
So, they're going to, we're going to model
this as a time-dependent predictor.
The outcome here was the time to the first
major depressive episode,
if a woman had one.
You can imagine that one way that the
others could've looked at
this data is they could have just said,
did the women ever take antidepressants
during the study or not?
That's going to be a problem, as you'll
see.
Because you can imagine that if you just
use the ever never variable, women who
have a major episode of depression during
pregnancy may then get on,
may start taking an antidepressant.
So you'd have some kind of reverse
causality.
So it's a really good use of
time-dependent predictors here
to allow antidepressant use to change over
time.
Baseline use of antidepressant also may
not be a very good measure here.
Because some women may choose to go on
antidepressants, but
may not be on them right at the beginning
of the study.
And just to get some practice reading
statistical method sections a lot of
you are going to have to go on to write
these eventually.
So I am just going to show you what they
wrote about their predictor from their
statistical methods section.
So, we use cost regression to model risk
for a major depressive episode.
That's the their outcome variable.
And major depressive episodes hat to last
at least two weeks,
that's part of definition of the outcome
here.
What was the risk period they were looking
at?
So, the risk period that they were looking
at was from the second month of
pregnancy to two months postpartum.
So, women were followed for those time
periods.
They were at risk of getting a major
episode of depression.
From two months into the pregnancy to two
months post partum.
Now interestingly they, there was some
missing data so some of
the women they didn't actually know if
they had a major depressive episode.
Some of them maybe, you know,
lost, were, they lost them or they just
didn't have that data.
So those missing data were treated as
censored for the primary model.
They also just to see what would happen.
They did what's called a sensitivity
analysis where they also said everybody
who we don't really know, we didn't follow
them for the entire period of the study.
What if all of them went on and actually
did have a major depressive episode?
How could that affect the results?
So they tried treating all of them as
having the event rather than being
censored just to see how it affected the
results.
So, that's called a sensitivity analysis.
You'll see that sometimes when people have
missing data.
And another interesting point on this, in
this method section, for
each model, we used the exact method of
computation to account for
a large number of ties in times to event.
So, last week we talked about the issue of
ties.
And in this particular study they were
looking on a monthly basis.
They were updating antidepressant use and
outcomes every month.
So, there's only you know nine months,
only kind of nine time points here in this
study.
So there's an awful lot of ties.
A lot of women could have depressive
episode in the same month of pregnancy.
Large number of ties therefore they
decided to go with the exact method to
get it, you know, as precise as possible.
And again the exact method computationally
is, is, probably, you know,
most computers can handle it.
Even for 778 women.
All right.
So then the primary exposure of
interest was antidepressant treatment, a
time-dependent variable.
Okay.
So they were allowing this to
change over time.
We examine models comparing treatment with
onset of major depressive episode during
the corresponding months.
So we also created models for time-lagged
antidepressant indicators so they
could just put it in you're either not on
antidepressants or not in a given month.
However, the potential problem with that
is since time
isn't measured very precisely here you can
imagine if
a woman has a major depressive episode in
a given month.
She may then as a result of that start
taking antidepressants.
And so if you don't look, you know, you
know, if you don't put a time lag in,
you may catch some women who are on
antidepressants at
the time of major depressive episodes
simply because you haven't measured time
finally enough to realize that she got on
them after.
So, they did some time lag models.
They said,
you have to have been on antidepressants
at least a month before the event time.
Or at least two months, or
at least three months, to resolve this
issue of causal ordering.
In the end, they chose a lag of two
months.
So, you were only counted us on, as being
on antidepressants,
if you were on them for at least two
months.
Just to make sure that there was none, you
know, reverse causality here.
So that was their model.
Here is the results from the study of this
slide.
You can't really see to much so I'm
going to zoom in now on the results.
So this is from their multi-variant Cox
regression model.
They're presenting the unadjusted and
adjusted hazard ratios.
They adjusted for a lot of things because
this was an observational study.
You can imagine there are a lot of
potential confounders here.
Of course, the variable we care about is
this time-dependent antidepressant use.
And so when they look at antidepressant
use in the un-adjusted model the hazard
ratio was 0.85.
It's slightly protected but certainly not
statistically significant.
In the adjusted model it's 0.88.
So there's really no evidence that being
on antidepressants during pregnancy,
at least in this data set,
seems to prevent, it doesn't seem to
prevent a major episodes of depression.
It's trending a little bit in the
protective range, but
clearly very close to one there.
So that's the answer from the study, and
you would interpret as that, you know,
being on antidepressents at a given time
doesn't seemed to
prevent against depression in pregnancy.
They also looked at some, you know, they
also adjusted for all of these other
factors so just to practice interpreting
Cox regression results something that
was a pretty good predictor is if you'd
had a major depressive episode in
the six months before pregnancy, it was
almost a threefold increase in risk of
depression during pregnancy, major
depressive episode during pregnancy.
After adjustment, that got attenuated, but
it was still elevated.
An 84% higher rate or risk of having a
major depressive episode during pregnancy.
There was some elevation in risk if you'd
had a lot,
larger number of depressive episodes
before pregnancy.
Looked like, if your age at your first
depressive episode was below 14.
With some elevation of risk,
although again that went away in the
adjusted model.
The races other than white appear to have
an elevated risk.
And this is one of the few cases where
being young seems to be worse and
being old seems to be protective.
So if you look at age, at least in the
un-adjusted models,
the younger women had a higher risk.
Of course when you adjust for things that
gets attenuated as closer to one.
Still a trend towards the older women
having a little protection there.
Education in the adjusted models doesn't
look all that interesting.
Diabetes looks a little bit interesting,
although the confidence intervals are
wide.
Probably not a lot of women have diabetes
at, in this age group.
So, that's just some practice in
interpreting the results of
Cox regression with time-dependent
predictors.
[BLANK_AUDIO]