[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module, I just wanted to show
you that, even though we're focusing on
continuous outcomes in this class,
generalized estimating equations can
handle other types of repeated-measures
outcomes data, including binary outcomes.
So, just for the purposes of illustration,
I made up a simple,
little data set where we can run GE on
this data set.
So, imagine we had 20 teenagers, some of
whom were smokers,
some of whom were not smokers.
We randomized them to an anti-smoking
intervention.
Smoking status, which is a binary outcome,
is allowed to change over time, and
we measured that smoking status at four
time points after baseline.
So, the data now looks something like
this.
I, I'm showing you the data in the long
form.
We've got an ID number to identify the
subjects.
Every subject is measured at four time
points.
Their smoking status, which is the
repeated-measures outcome here.
you, you can have a subject go, so like,
subject number one was a smoker to start,
then they became a non-smoker, then they
were a smoker again for
the last two time periods.
So, that's allowed to change.
That might, that's my repeated-measures
outcome.
Here's my time variable.
I have a time-independent predictor, which
is,
you're either in the treatment group or
the control group.
That does not change over time.
It's always the same within a, a given
subject.
So, we're sticking with the
time-independent predictors for
a little bit longer, here.
I went ahead and graphed these data
because, of course,
the graph is most important in
understanding what you have.
So, what I'm graphing here is, my outcome
is binary, you're either a smoker or
you're not a smoker, but I'm graphing the
means for the sample.
So, this represents the percent of each
sample,
the percent of people who are smokers at a
given time point.
So, for example, at baseline, both of the
groups had about 60%,
were already smoking, and there's some
change in the smoking status over time.
You can see that the treatment group stays
pretty flat in their
smoking status over time.
They even go down, maybe just a little,
little bit.
Whereas, the control group gets higher and
they're, more of them become smokers over
time.
So, it looks like the treatment is doing
something but
we need to attach to this graphic some
effect sizes and p-value.
So, if I were just to hand you this data
set and you didn't know anything about GE
models, your first instinct would probably
be to run a logistic regression, right?
You have a binary outcome, so you would
say, okay,
I'm going to run a logistic regression
where my outcome is the logit of smoking.
And, the simplest model you could think of
was just to put a beta in for
treatment to say whether or not treatment
is related to a lower risk of smoking.
Now, obviously, this would be incorrect
because it completely ignores the repeated
measures, but I went ahead and did that
just to show you what happens.
And, when you run that model, you get a
negative beta coefficient.
That indicates that, indeed, the treatment
group is associated with
a lower likelihood of smoking, as we saw
in the graphic.
The p-value that's attached to that,
however, it looks statistically
significant, but,
in fact, that's overly optimistic, that is
too small.
And, the reason being is that, if you
think about the data set,
we have 20 individuals, but they're all
measured at four time points.
So, we actually have 80 observations, and
we are over-counting people by allowing
somebody who was in the treatment groups,
so essentially four times in the data set,
to be counted four times.
That's going to make our p-values here too
small.
Treatment is a between-subjects
comparison.
Failing to account for correlations will
make our p-values too small.
We're over-counting people.
So, I then went ahead and ran one other
logistic regression model, just for
illustration purposes.
This is closer to what we're actually
going to be running in the GE model.
So, in a GE model, we're going to want to
put in a beta for time, a beta for
treatment, and a beta for time by
treatment.
Now, this logistic model has not yet
accounted for
the correlation within subjects, but
otherwise, it's similar to what we're
going to be running for the GE model.
And what you'll notice is, when I run
this, I actually don't get anything to be
statistically significant, so all my
p-values are non-significant.
Some of those p-values are going to change
when we, now, correctly account for
the correlation within subject.
So, here's the empirical correlation
matrix.
A binary outcome can have correlation
across time periods.
If you were a smoker in one time period,
you're more likely to be a smoker in
another time period.
And I went ahead and just run it, ran
piercing correlation coefficients be,
between those ones and zeros at different
time periods.
What you'll notice is that between
adjacent time periods,
the correlations are the highest: 0.83,
point, almost 0.6, 0.75.
If you go two time points apart, the
correlations are a little bit lower,
as you would expect with repeated-measures
data.
If you go three time points apart, the
correlations are even smaller.
So, probably, something like an
autoregressive would be a good choice for
the correlation matrix here.
Indeed, that's what I ended up choosing.
So then, I went ahead and ran the GE
model.
It looks exactly like the logistic
regression model, except that now
we're adding this correlation factor, this
correction for the correlation within
subjects, the correlation matrix that we
just saw on the previous page.
Running logistic regression model just
means that our errors were say, saying our
errors follow a binomial distribution,
rather than a normal distribution.
Our outcome, we're going to model as a
logit of the outcome because, again,
we have a binary outcome.
So, it's just like a logistic regression
with this additional correction
for correlation.
I went ahead and ran that model, and
here's what I got for my output.
So, a couple of things to pay attention
to.
So, first of all, I want you pay attention
to the p-values over here.
The p-value for treatment, when I ran the
regular logistic regression, was 0.7.
That went up when I ran the correct model.
So, treatment is a between-subjects
comparison.
So, for between-subjects comparisons, the
p-values are too small.
When you fail to correct for
correlations, they going to go up when you
correct for correlations.
However, the treatment by time, and time
effects are within-subjects effects,
when we correctly account for correlation,
these p-values go down.
Now, they're starting to approach
statistical significance,
which they weren't before.
Remember, in the picture,
it did look like the treatment group did
somewhat better than the control group.
How would I interpret the beta
coefficients here?
Well, the effect for treatment here if I
were to exponentiate these beta
coefficients I would get odds ratios, but
basically, a negative beta coefficient for
treatment means that at baseline, so
the main effect for treatment is the
affected baseline.
At baseline, the treatment group actually
had slightly fewer smokers in it
than the control group, even though this
is a randomized trial, but
that difference was not statistically
significant.
The main effect for
time represents the change in the risk of
smoking over time for the control group.
And so, that's positive,
seeing that the control group was going up
in their smoking over time, as we
saw in the picture that didn't quite reach
statistical significance, but almost.
And then finally, the treatment by time
effect is negative,
saying that the treatment group does
better over time than the control group.
They're, they don't go up as much as the
control group in their smoking status.
In fact, they stayed pretty flat or even
went down a little.
The difference between the control and
treatment over time did not
quite reach statistical significance, but
it was approaching it.
So you can see that the interpretation's
actually very similar to
the interpretation when we had a
continuous outcome.
The model looks very similar.
GE can handle other types of outcome data,
like binary outcomes.