[BLANK_AUDIO].
Welcome to unit eight.
This week we're going to start our
discussion of regression methods that
handle repeated measures outcome.
So this week we're going to be talking
about generalized estimating equations,
which is one of the regression methods
that handles repeated measures data.
And there are many benefits of using a
regression method for
handling repeated measures data.
We saw last week that if we wanted to use
repeated measures ANOVA or
repeated measures MANOVA that there were a
number of limitations to those methods.
So for one thing they assume that time is
categorical.
Everybody has to be measured at the same
time point and
forMANOVA those time points had to be sort
of equally spaced time intervals.
With regression, with generalized
estimating equations and
next week we'll see with mixed models you
can treat time as continuous.
Everybody can have different time points
that they're measured at.
Also the ANOVA methods don't handle time
dependent covariants.
And as you all learned on the midterm, the
time changing predictors are very,
very important.
And the regression methods will
incorporate and handle.
these.
For ANOVA you have to impute missing data,
or
anybody who's missing even one time point
will be thrown out of the analysis.
With the regression methods, you don't
necessarily have to
impute the missing data because people
will only be thrown out.
At the time points that they missed.
The ANOVA methods have some more
restrictive assumptions.
Particularly uni-variant repeated
measures,
ANOVA had a restrictive assumption about
the correlation structure.
The regression methods don't necessarily
require such restrictive assumptions.
And if you notice when we did a NOVA, we
didn't get any parameters estimates.
We didn't get any measures of effect size,
for example.
We just got p values.
We'd also like to be able to get some beta
coefficients,
some estimates of effect size and
regression.
We'll bias that as well.
[BLANK_AUDIO]