[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to walk you
through a real data analysis experience,
to help you synthesize all of the things
that you've learned in this course.
And, as the example data, I'm going to use
the data set from the final exam,
since you've all just had to grapple with
that data.
I've laid out a series of steps here that
I think you should take,
when you're doing a real data analysis.
And these are really just guidelines, but
you'll see that the emphasis, is to make
sure, that you spend ample time
doing things like checking your data set,
understanding your variables,
thinking about missing data, exploring
simple relationships, graphing, graphing,
graphing and just really understanding
what you've got in your data.
You really need to do all of that before
you jump to the model building.
So that's the emphasis of this list.
I also want to remind you, that we always
want to document all of our steps.
We're striving for a reproducible
research.
Which means that I could hand my code to
somebody else, and
they would be able to recreate the steps
that I used in my analysis, and
also reproduce the tables and figures in
my paper.
So now, I'm going to walk you through,
each of these steps in turn,
as applied to this example data set.
So, first thing we're going to do is
going to prep the data set, just make sure
we've got the variable names that we want
formatting the variables correctly,
importing the data set into SASS or
whatever statistical program that
you're using, making any new variables
that we need.
I asked the authors of this original
paper, this was a data set from a cluster,
randomized trial, and I this was a paper
that was published in BMJ open.
I asked the authors to send me the data.
They had indicated that the data were
available.
They sent it to me in the long format.
It was also sent to me with variable names
that were in Italian.
So first thing I went through and did, was
fortunately the data dictionary was in
English, so I was able to go through and
rename all of my variable names into
something in English to make it easier for
myself.
These data were collected as part of a
cluster randomized trial, so
there were six pregnancy clinics, three
were randomized to
be intervention clinics, three were
randomized to be control clinics.
They enrolled women from within each of
those clinics, a total of 89 women women
enrolled into the in, intervention clinics
received lifestyle counseling to
help them lose their pregnancy weight
faster after the birth of their babies.
And women in the control groups didn't get
anything.
And the primary outcome of that trial was
the mother's weight loss postpartum.
However the authors went back, and they
did a secondary analysis.
These data set represent that secondary
analysis.
They were able to get data on the birth on
the weights of the babies up until
four years of age, on 64 of the original
89 infants from the original trial.
I went ahead and took this data set, and
also converted it into the broad form of
the data, so it was sent to me in the long
form, I used a proc transpose in SASS.
When you use proc transpose, you can
change one outcome variable,
one repeated measures outcome variable at
a time into the broad form, and
then you have to merge the data sets.
But I went ahead and did that, because
there are a few things, like, I want to
get correlation matrices where I'm
going to need the broad form of the data.
I also went through, and
there were a few binary variables that
were coded as 1,2 rather than 1, 0.
I prefer them as 1,0, so I recoded those.
But the data set was pretty clean.
There wasn't a huge amount to do in terms
of prep.
The next thing we're going to do, is we're
going to check the data set for
data errors and also if there are
outliers, extreme values, we want to
learn about those early, even if those are
not errors, if those are real values.
It turns out that, that, the these data
again were from a published paper, so
as you might expect or you would hope.
The data set when the author sent it to
me, was quite clean.
So you'll see that I didnt' have to spend
a lot of time on checking the data set
here, though I didn't find anything that
was worrisome,
it looked like a nice clean data set.
If you're dealing with your own real data,
it's probably not going to be this clean.
These have sort of been pre-cleaned for
us.
So I went ahead and
just got basic statistics, like the number
max and min, for all of the variables.
I'm looking to see if there's anything
outside of the range that I would expect.
I'm looking to see how many babies have
these values.
For each of these variables.
Again, everything looks pretty clean,
I didn't find anything that looks
worrisome here.
There's a lot of variables here,
I'm using the broad form of the data to
generate these statistics.
So there's a lot of variables because I've
got the variable for
each one of the time points.
The babies were measured about ten times
in the first year of life they had
their weights and heights measured, and
they were measured also at their
second birthday, at the third birthday,
and at their fourth birthdays for
a total of about 13 weight length
measurements per baby.
What you can see is that the birth weight
is we, weight length z
one of the outcomes was to translate that
weight into a z score that adjusted the,
you know, the z score takes into account
how long or how tall the baby is.
So, that's, that's sort of like a baby
BMI, and into a z score.
You can see that at the, at birth we had
63 measurements out of 64 so
one baby was actually missing the birth
weight.
You can see there's a lot of the interim
measurements are missing small amounts of
data, because not every baby had every
measurement, so just keep that in the back
of your mind, but again, I won't spend a
lot of time on checking the data here,
because everything looks pretty clean.
They also had, so there were three outcome
variables that I looked at.
So the weight for length z-score, that's a
z-score, adjusted for height.
The authors also had provided a BMI
z-score.
But that was only available for the
infants after they turned two years of
age, and that's because this conversion to
a z-score is based on population norms,
and they only, there is only a conversion
after the babies are older than two.
So they are, there's not a calculation for
it prior to two years of age.
So we only have that available for three
time points,
the 11th, 12th and 13th measurements in
this data set.
And I also looked at weight in kilograms
as an outcome.
Again that was measured at all 13 time
points.
Few things to notice, the the max of 24.3
kilograms, this is at the fourth birthday,
that, that's a little high but it's
probably a real baby.
But we'll see when we graph it that, that
baby actually stands out a little bit as
having a little bit higher then everybody
else.
But again, I don't think it's an error,
I think it's just an extreme value that
we'll need to consider.
So, data set looks pretty clean.
I then went ahead and went through each
variable, and asked for
univariate statistics and histograms on
each variable separately.
So that I could just understand the
variables in my data set.
I also examined correlation structures,
using, using the broad form of the data.
Because I know we're going to be doing
dealing with repeated measures
outcome here.
we, it's important to understand the
correlation or
covariant structure of those repeated
measures outcomes.
Now at the end of the day, we ended up
using a random effects.
I ended up using a random effects model
for this data, and
you don't actually have to do much in
terms of specifying the, within
subject correlation across time points,
when you do the random effects model.
But if we were doing a generalized
estimating equation, or
a proc mixed with a repeated statement,
we would really need to understand those
correlation structures.
So they were important enough that I
tackled them early.
So first of all I went through and took,
for all my variables that are not my
repeated measures variables I went ahead
and asked for my simple statistics.
Yeah, in SASS, you can do that with a proc
univariate.
I'm just, going to go through these
quickly.
So one thing to notice is that on the
group variable.
The original trial enrolled 89 women, but
only 64 women provided data about their,
their infant's weight trajectory over time
because, again,
this is a second-degree analysis.
So it turned out that the women who had
been in the intervention group,
that's group equals one is the
intervention.
You know, they're probably a little bit
more motivated, because more of
them provided that follow up data on their
infants than women from the control group.
So we have slightly more women from the
intervention group here,
and you just going to keep that in mind.
There was about half of them had smoked at
some time during their lives.
They exclusively breast fed for an average
of three months.
They introduced solids at almost five
months.
Most of them, 89% were employed.
About 3% had an abnormally high birth
weight.
And about 17 to 18% had a low birth
There's only 42% girls so slightly fewer
girls in this data set than boys.
The average maternal age was about 29.
The, the pre-pregnancy BMI was about 22.
So this is a relatively light group of
women.
They're not on average overweight.
About 12% would be considered having a,
not a, a high birth weight, but
sort of being bigger than normal at birth.
The average maternal weight gain was about
15 kilograms, just you know,
30, 35 pounds, and so on and so forth.
So I went ahead and just looked at the
simple variables, then I went and
looked at the covariance and correlation
structures of my three outcome variables,
my weight for length z-score which was
measured at 13 time points.
My weight in kilograms also mentioned at
13 time points, and
my BMI z-score which is only measured at
three time points.
So you can see this is a little unwieldy,
this is the weight for length z-score.
So they've been adjusted for how big, how
long the baby or tall the baby is,
as well as converted into a z-score, into
a standard deviation unit.
The pattern's a little bit harder to see
with the z-scores,
than it will be with the weights in
kilograms.
But you can see, for example the weight
for length z-score at time point one,
that's the birth weight, birth weight for
length z-score.
It has some correlation with the next time
they were measured, and
then some correlation with the third time
they were measured, but
pretty much falls off after there.
So just because you started a little above
average at birth,
doesn't mean you're going to be above
average forever.
And you can see the general pattern is
that, you know,
adjacent time points tend to be more
correlated to one another, and
then there's some drop off as you get
farther in time, and
sometimes even the correlations are
negative as you get further in time.
Remember that these time points are not
evenly spaced.
The first ten measurements are all within
the first year, so
they were measured quite frequently.
Measurements measurement ten corresponds
to the first birthday.
Measurement 11 corresponds to the second
birthday.
Measurement 12 corresponds to the third
birthday, and
measurement 13 corresponds to the, around
the fourth birthday.
So you'll notice there's a,
kind of a high amount of correlation once
you get past the first year.
There's a fair amount of correlation
between, say you know, ten, 11 and 12.
As we get over here this is the
correlations between weights ten,
11, and 12.
So by the time you're one years old,
you're, it's pretty, if you're a big
baby at one you're might, more likely to
be a big baby at two, three, and four so.
You can see some correlations there.
So, the adjacent high points tend to be
more correlated.
Maybe stronger correlations after the
first year of birth.
There's no clear correlation structure
here, although maybe something like
an autoregressive or an independent would
be appropriate.
Unstructured's probably not going to work
here,
because we have far too many time points.
Exchangeable seems wrong as well, because
it doesn't look exchangeable to me.
The weights, if you just look at the
weights in kilograms,
the correlation structure is a little bit
easier to discern.
I think this one looks nice and
autoaggressive, because you can see this
clear pattern, that if you weighed a lot
at time point one, the correlation with
time point 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, it kind of
nicely goes down overtime.
You can kind of see that, and if you look
at week two the correlations again also go
down over time, and you'll see this
general pattern, so something like, again,
like an autoregressive or independent
would be most appropriate here.
The BMIs, these scores, there's only a few
of those,
you could model that one as an
unstructured.
Or maybe an,
again, an autoregressive further of apart
time points seem to be less correlated.
As you might expect with repeated measures
data.
I looked at histograms.
Again, this is the group variable.
You can that there's more intervention
women who provided these data than
control women.
So we need to at least think about that in
our interpretation of the findings.
just, you know, few things for fun, so,
about more than half the women had smoked
sometime in their life, the maternal age
was centered around 29, these are first
time mothers, and most of the women were
employed, a lot were edu, highly educated.
The maternal weight kind of centered
around 60 kilograms.
There's a few heavier women out to the
tail here for maternal BMI.
Maternal weight gain during pregnancy
follows a nice normal distribution.
They also, the author's also provided that
as a categorical variable.
Most women exclusively breast fed their
babies for about five months.
There's some variation on that.
Partial breastfeeding went up to 30
months,
that's continuing to breast feed after
you've introduced solid foods.
Birth weight looks nice and normal,
gestational age has
a left tail because some of the weight
babies were born a little early.
And then I went ahead and
graphed all of the outcome variables at
each time point, in separate histograms.
What I'm looking for
here is, we're going to be running linear
models, linear mixed models.
And so we want the outcome variable to be
at least reasonably normally distributed,
and you can see that this is for weight,
so the weights,
it doesn't look like a perfect normal
distribution, I've shown you a,
a sampling of the different time points
here.
But looks probably close enough, good
enough for running linear models.
Here's weights at the first birthday, the
second, third, and fourth birthdays.
It's not perfectly normally distributed,
but good enough to run our linear models.
And here's the one baby who had a little
bit of a higher weight.
At the fourth birthday, it's a little bit
of an outlier there,
that we need to think about.
The weight for life z-scores, I also
looked at those,
they also look reasonably, normally
distributed, good enough to,
to be able to run linear models.
So, after you kind of get a feel for all
the different variables in your data set,
then, we need to think about missing data.
So, I just wanted to just first quantify
the missing data.
So, I ran a little macro.
And all that macro is doing is, it's
identifying for each measurement,
there's different missing data at
different measurements for these babies.
At each different measurement for the
weight for life z-score, I asked for
SASS just to to save the, the number of,
to save a new data set with all the babies
who were missing data, for
that outcome for that time point, and then
just to print them out to me.
It's just a quick way to get a sense of
how many babies are missing data at
each time point, missing outcome data at
each time point.
And so, this is just a sampling of what I
came up with.
So this is the first time point.
One maybe was missing a weight for length
z-score score at birth.
You would hope you could get that data
point but for
whatever reason they didn't have it, but
that baby did have it for
the second measurement so their only
missing that first one.
There was actually 21 babies who
were missing that second week for length
z-score.
Well, probably not every baby comes in
right after they're born for
another checkup, or somehow that data, the
mothers didn't collect that data.
So we're missing the most number of babies
for that second time point,
but remember these babies were measured up
to ten times in the first year of life.
So it's probably okay if there a few of
babies here and
there are missing various of these interim
measurements.
I went through and counted how many babies
were missing weight for
length z-scores at each one of these time
periods, and I've written them out here.
It's good that the later time points,
which represent the older ages, there
aren't that many missing data points.
Because almost everybody, well everybody,
probably goes in for
their first birthday checkup, their second
birthday checkup and so on.
They may not get all of their checkups
within the first year.
So it's just good to know the pattern of
missing data to have an understanding of
what's there.
And then we have to think about how we're
going to handle missing data for
this particular example.
So first of all, the more important
missing data are actually not available to
us in this data set.
So remember that the original randomized
trial had 89 women in it.
Only 64 of those women were able to
provide data on their babies.
So we actually had, essentially, 25
dropouts.
And that could have a lot of influence
because you can imagine that perhaps
the mothers who were most embarrassed
about by their baby's weight gains or,
you know, were most,
were least concerned about their baby's
weight gains, or something.
There's something, there could be some
bias,
in terms of who actually provides that
followup data.
The fact that the women weren't willing to
provide it, or
didn't have it, might say something.
So we need to consider that.
This is a secondary end point from the
clinical trial.
Therefore we're not going to be using
intention to treat analysis, so
we don't necessarily need to include those
dropouts in any way in some kind of
intention to treat analysis.
However we should explore what's different
about the dropouts,
try to do, if we had these data, we could
try to do some sensitivity analyses,
where we said if everybody that dropped
out, you know,
their babies had abnormally high weight
gain, how would that affect the results?
We could do some kind of sensitivity
analysis if we had those data,
we actually don't have them, so we're
really not going to be able to do
much here, although ideally if this was
our data set, we would be able to.
On the other hand, the missing interim
data, the fact that at a given time point,
some babies are missing data for given
measurement.
That actually I'm not going to worry so
much about for this dataset.
All of the babies have a large number of
weight measurements.
And just if there missing one or two
during their first year of life,
that doesn't in all impede my ability to
draw a growth curve for them.
They can measure one baby, you know?
Was supposed to be measured here, here and
maybe missed the third measurement and
then, you know, missed the fifth
measurement and so
on, but, you know, has the majority of the
measurements, I'm going to be able to
draw a nice growth curve for that baby
even missing a few interim measurements.
So it's not going to be a big deal,
I'm not going to actually try to fill in
that missing data in any way.
And remember the mixed models handle the
missing data just fine.
Again, it's just going to, if the baby
doesn't have data for
that time point, it's just going to leave
it out.
But the babies, doesn't,
you don't need to have complete data in
order to be included in those models.
So we're not going to worry too much about
the missing interim data,
although it's important to understand how
much of that missing data we have.
The next thing I did was to explore simple
relationships,
simple bivariate relationships between the
different variables in my data set
relationships between the variables in my
data set and the outcome variables.
As well as to start thinking about some of
the assumption that
we're going to have here.
Among the assumptions we have,
we need a normally distributed outcome, we
already kind of looked at that.
We also need to think about what is the
shape of the growth curve over time?
It's probably not going to be linear, so
we can't just throw time into our model
and and that's good enough.
We don't want to fit straight lines here.
We're probably going to need to fit either
something quadratic or
cubic, something more complicated.
So we really need to think about the shape
of that growth trajectory for these data.
So I went ahead and ran some correlation
matrices
between the variables that are not
repeated measures variables.
Just of interest to see what variables
tend to go together.
So some interesting things.
If you look the luckily there's not too
much going on with group,
we're hoping the two groups are relatively
balanced.
It looks like they are reasonably
balanced,
there's not huge correlations with any
confounders in our data set.
What's interesting to me is that if you
look at the ever smoking variable,
women who have ever smoked gained more
weight during pregnancy.
They were higher in their weights before
pregnancy.
And again, gained more weight during
They were less likely to breastfeed, they
introduced solids earlier.
So even though you tend to think of women
wanting to smoke to
keep their weight down, in fact, that
correlated with higher weight and
probably ever smoking is some kind of
proxy here for socioeconomic status.
So the women who have ever smoke generally
tend to be less healthy in general.
More educated women, exclusively breastfed
for longer.
They also tended to be a little bit older,
as you might expect.
Partial and exclusive breastfeeding tend
to go together, you know,
there's a lot of things we can look at
here.
employment, you're more likely to be a
little bit older if you were employed.
And so on.
We can look at, you know this is an
interesting pattern.
So ever smoking seems to correlate with
some kind of worse health habits.
Being more educated tends to correlate
with better things, as you might expect.
The, maternal age again correlates with
the education and
employment, as you might expect.
The ever smoking again correlates with
maternal weight, so
you can see all kinds of these patterns.
So it's just good to get a sense of how
the variables go together in
this data set.
I then went ahead and
graphed the growth trajectory for each
baby individually over time.
And I've done this separately for girls
and
boys, this is equivalent to figure two of
the BMJ open paper,
the authors actually showed this graph
because I think it is important.
It gives you the shape of the growth
trajectories over time.
What's interesting is that, you'll notice
that the girls have more variation in
their growth over time than the boys for
whatever reason in this data set.
You'll also notice that there is this one
baby,
this one girl who had a little bit of a
higher, weight gain over time.
She is in the control group.
So that could artificially make the
control group look like they're having,
you know, more weight gain over time.
So we will need to consider that.
The shape of the growth curves over time
is clearly not linear, right?
It is not a straight line.
As you would expect, that baby growth
would not follow a straight line.
So we're going to need to consider that in
the modeling.
When we're building our models,
we're not going to just be putting age in
as a linear term.
We are probably going to need to consider
cubics and quadratics here.
The other thing that you might do is, you
might say well, if you kind of look,
there's this high growth rate up until the
first year of age and
you know, that looks like a little bit of
a complicated shape.
It might be okay to model it as linear,
you can see after the first year of age,
it looks more linear, maybe not perfectly
linear.
Same thing over here.
So you could also think about breaking up
the data set into two time periods and
modeling those time periods separately.
That might be another way to handle the
data.
The fact that there are definitely not
linear.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That was the weights.
The weights makes the prettiest graphic.
The weight for length Z score.
Remember this is a Z score.
And so it has a little bit funnier pattern
every time.
It's really hard to discern for these
individual growth lines.
Exactly what's going on with the Z score.
So you could easily be a standard
deviation above
average at birth, that doesn't necessarily
mean you're going to be
a standard deviation above average by the
time you're one years old.
And you can see there's a lot of kind of
going back and
forth, a lot of variation here.
So it's messy in the first year of life,
you can see a lot more kind of going back
and forth in the first year of life.
The BMI Z scores were only available after
the kids turned two, and so
you can see we only have it measured at
three time points but again it's
hard just in this individual growth line
to see exactly what the pattern is there.
We're probably going to need to do some
mean plot to get a sense of the pattern.
So I went ahead and did some mean plots,
and
so I'm actually going to show you here.
I'm plotting, this is, what you see on
this screen are the girls only.
So I did girls and boys separately, just
to start with.
I plotted the mean, weight for lengths, Z
score the means, BMI Z score and
the mean weight at every visit.
And I"m treating time as categorical here.
But the blue line is the control group.
Then the red line is the intervention.
And interestingly enough, we do seem to
see some separation between the control
group and the intervention group.
Even in some of the earlier time points,
and
then especially at the later time points
by the time they are four.
You see that also for the BMI's, and
you see that also for the weeks in
absolute values.
So, little bit of a separation here and
here.
So it does look like the control group
seems to be gaining a little bit more
weight over time than the intervention
group, at least for the girls.
Interestingly if you look at the boys, we
don't see as strong of a pattern for
the boys.
In fact you can see that the intervention
group was a little heavier than
the control group at the early time
points, although it switches over by
the end, but those are really highly
overlapping graphs.
So, you, it makes you wonder these are,
there's very, this is
only 64 babies though, and there's, you
know, more boys than girls here.
So, there's not a huge number of boys and
girls.
The numbers are small, but it does make
you wonder if there's maybe some gender
interaction where the women who get the
intervention,
the counseling, somehow we're more worried
about their girl's growth trajectories or
it could just be chance that it happened
to show up in the girls but not the boys.
You see a little bit of separation on the
weight where the control group is
a little bit higher but again those lines
are highly overlapping, so it doesn't look
as like there's as much going on with the
boys but this could just be chance.
I will later consider a gender
interaction.
I then combine the boys and
the girls together to get enough, and here
to see what's really going on.
Then you do see that it doesn't look like
there's much difference between
the control, and the intervention group at
the early time points.
But again at the end at, at the second,
third, and
fourth birthday, you do start to see some
separation for
the Z scores, for the weight, and also for
the BMI Z scores.
And it, in, you know in fact the authors
did
find a statistically significant
difference at the later time points.
So we're seeing a little something here,
it's not a huge effect, but a little bit
of separation.
And just to contrast it,
I went ahead and ran the same, graphic for
height just to show you.
Here's the graphic for height.
And you'll see that the two groups are
really overlapping for height.
So the separation you're seeing for weight
might actually mean something you know,
real clinically here.
The other thing to consider is what's the
shape of the curves.
It looks like, you know, again you're
probably getting, certainly not linear.
You're probably even for the Z score is
going to need quadratic, at least, and
maybe a cubic.
I then went ahead and did scatter plots
rather than mean plots.
I think the scatter plots are actually a
little bit nicer.
You can really see the shape of things.
So, what I'm graphing here is, here's age,
in months, on my x-axis.
This is the weight in kilograms, on my
y-axis.
And I'm graphing a separate line for each
clinic because one of
the the things that we're going to need to
worry about for
this data set, is the fact that we have a
cluster randomized trial.
And we had reanimization by clinic rather
than by individual.
So there's some potential that different
clinics have different road
trajectories because maybe their serving
slightly different populations.
So we needed to keep that in mind, we need
to look for clinic effects here.
So, I've done this graph.
And what I did was to go ahead, the blue
lines represent the control clinics,
that was clinics three, four and six.
And the red lines represent the
intervention clinics,
which is one, two and five.
And interestingly, you can see that there
doesn't appear to be a huge amount of
variation between the different clinics,
but the blue lines do tend to be a little
bit higher on weight, especially at the
later time points and the red clinics,
which are the intervention ones do tend to
be a little bit lower.
And there seems to be most of the
variation between different clinics seems
to correlate with whether or not you're in
the intervention or the control.
Again, you're going to look at the shape
of that graphic.
I would say that that looks like a cubic
shape to me.
It's not linear, clearly.
It's not quadratic.
It's probably cubic, it's kind of going
like this, so it's more of a cubic.
I then went ahead and did the same scatter
plots for the three outputs.
This is girls and boys combined, and I
graphed a red line for
the intervention group, a blue line for
the control group again.
And you can see again that there seems to
be some separation at
these later time points where the control
were beginning a little bit more of
a time in the red group seems to be going
down.
Now you can see that for weight, for
length Z score this is for
the BMI Z scores and this is for weight
overall.
It's not a huge effect, but
there does seem to be something, a little
something going on.
Some separation at the later time points.
Notice that on the weight graph,
we've got this one girl, who was in the
control group, who is a little bit higher.
You can imagine that she could potentially
be pull, pulling this blue line up,
she could be having a lot of influence on
that line.
So we're going to need to consider how
much influence she's having on
the estimates, and we'll do that later on.
All right, so
I looked at all the shapes of the growth
trajectories over time, by clinic.
My intervention group, my individual, and
then just for
fun, I'll also went through and try to see
is there anything else,
is there any other predictors in my
variable obese,
in my data set besides intervention group
that correlate with baby weight gain?
And this is data from a randomized trial.
Actually, the groups ended up being fairly
balanced on all the covariants.
So we're probably not going to have to
adjust for any confounding here.
So this is just out of curiosity, to see,
is there anything else that predicts baby
weight gain over time?
I looked at the early time periods, this
is using the broad from the data set,
I looked just at the early time periods.
If you look at the early time periods, the
things that correlate with the baby's
weight tends to be how much weight the
mother's gained during pregnancy and
how big the babies were at birth, that
makes sense.
The later time periods, so when the baby
was one, she was three and four.
Interestingly it does appear that there is
some correlation with the age
at which solid foods are introduced.
So, introducing your solid food later is
correlated with having being
a little bit of a light baby, you know,
at least up until the second year, second
or third year of age.
So that's interesting, when you introduce
solid foods might have some effect.
So in the exclusive breastfeeding assuming
to have some correlation whereas
the babies that were exclusively breastfed
for longer tend to be a little bit
lighter at least into their, you know,
again, third or fourth year of life.
I went ahead and did some graphs just for
fun.
So this was looking at the early solids.
So if you were in the green line they
introduced the solids the earliest age.
The blue line represents introduced the
solids at the latest age.
And you can see there does seem to be
something going on,
although the lines are converging a little
bit by the fourth year of age.
So at least in the second and
third year of life it seems to have some
influence on the weight gain.
I'll show you later this actually does
turn out to be a statistically
significant difference.
I also look at maternal weight gain
because that seems to correlate,
at least with the earlier time points, and
interestingly you do see some separation
where the women who gained the most
weight during pregnancy, their babies do
seem to be a little bit bigger,
at least in weight overall across time
periods, so we can look at that as well.
Again we're probably not going to have to
adjust for
these things because they're well-balanced
between the two groups.
The next thing we'd want to do is make our
formal descriptive table one for our
paper and any descriptive graphics that
we're going to want to make for our paper.
You, we've already made the graphics, so
I'll just show you the table one.
I got lazy here and the authors had
actually prepared a table one already so
I didn't bother to recreate it.
I trust that they've done a good job in
compiling these data.
The things to pay attention to is that we
do have slightly more numbers,
37 in the intervention group and 27 in the
control group.
However, if you look across at the
different, potential confounders,
it really does look like it's still fairly
well balanced between the two groups.
So there's probably not a lot we're going
to have to do in terms of worrying about
adjusting for confounding in our final
models.
And that's the nice thing about randomized
trials, you often get things that are very
nice and balanced, and you don't have to
worry about adjusting for confounding.
We can also prepare some formal graphics
here as well.
For this is on paper obviously lends
itself to graphing so
we'd prepare some formal graphics as the
authors did to present in the paper.
The next thing we're going to do is test
the main hypotheses.
Step seven and eight are kind of very
similar here because again,
I don't think we're going to be doing much
in the way of adjusting for confounding.
So I'm just going to reiterate here to
test the main hypothesis, for
repeated measures data I'm really going to
want to look at graphics.
So I've already shown you these graphics.
I'll just remind you then before we jump
to building the final models,
the shape of the graphics does not look
linear.
Girls look to have a little bit of a
bigger effect than boys,
I'm going to look at that in my final
models.
Here's the overall, it does appear that
there is some benefit for the control for
the intervention group at the later time
points compared with the control group.
I am going to have to worry about
within-clinic effects, that,
if there's any correlation within clinic.
But as I showed you already it doesn't
look like there's a huge amount of
variation between the different clinics
and most of the variation seems to be
explained by whether or not you're an
intervention clinic or a control clinic,
so it may turn out that there's not a lot
we have to worry about there.
And then I already showed you these
graphics as well.
All of these graphics are setting me up
for being able to build my final models.
So now we'll jump into building the final
models.
We're normally going to have to worry
about confounders, but
again, the covariates were well balanced
between the two groups,
even in the secondary data analysis, so
I'm actually not going to bother to try
adjusting for any confounders.
I also have explored the data enough to
know that none of
the covariates are terribly great
predictors of weight gain over time.
I'm going to look for an interaction with
gender,
just because in the pictures it did look
like the effect was bigger in girls.
I am at least going to test that.
And I'm going to need to think about in my
building these models here,
the main thing I'm going to need to be
thinking about is how am I modeling,
how am I dealing with the repeated
measures, and
how am I dealing with the within-clinic
correlation?
So it's really about dealing with the
correlations.
Do I need to have a random intercept and a
random slope?
I'm going to be looking at models that
sometimes include a random slope,
sometimes don't include a random slope,
and
those are the things that I'm going to be
comparing here.
So I'm going to start, remember I had
three outcomes here.
I'm going to mostly focus on the
weight-for-length Z score,
my general process for the BMI Z score and
the weight, or
is, is pretty much the same.
So rather than show all of that, I'm just
going to show the process for
the weight-for-length Z score.
Here is the picture that corresponds to
the model that I am about to build.
Okay, so I'm going to build a model for
this data set.
You can see weight-for-length Z score
because of the Z score is not
necessarily going to increase over time.
However, it doesn't look like it's flat
over time.
Babies do seem to go up or down in their Z
scores.
And you do see at the later, the earlier
time points,
you're not seeing much difference between
the control and the intervention group,
but in the later time points you certainly
are.
I went ahead and ran a mixed model and I,
the authors of
this paper chose to use random effects
rather than a repeated statement.
I think that's a good choice because of
the fact that we have two sources of
correlation here, our observations are
clustered within
individuals, and the individuals are then
clustered within clinics because this
is a cluster randomized trial.
And so we would call this a multi-level, a
three-level model essentially,
because we've got repeated measurements on
the same subject but
then we also have individuals clustered
within clinics.
So this is well-handled by a random
effects model because we can put in
random effects for the individual subject
specific slopes and
intercepts, as well as random effects for
the clinics.
So we could also test if we need to put in
clinic specific intercepts and slopes.
So that's what I'm doing here.
I already know that I'm going to need by
the,
just by the picture that I'm going to need
quadratic and
cubic terms if I'm modeling all the time
periods from zero to four years.
I'm going to need to put in a group by age
term.
I also did consider putting in a group by,
I also tried group by age by
age because maybe the quadratic function
might be different between the groups.
That turns out to be not significant and
the group by age cubed also turns out to
be non-significant, so I ended up with as
the authors did,
just ending up with a group by age term to
quantify the effect of the intervention.
Of course I'll need mean effects for those
as well.
I asked for confidence limits, I'm setting
my degrees of freedom at
this particular method of doing it, and
then I'm putting in a random statement for
clinic as well as a random statement for
individual.
And I'm starting by allowing there to be
subject-specific intercepts,
subject-specific slopes and
clinic-specific intercepts and
clinic-specific slopes.
And when I run that model I get an AIC of
1692.
And you can see, however, when you look at
the covariance parameter estimates for
clinic they are all very, very close to
zero.
So what this is telling you is that there
isn't a lot of variation within clinic
between the different clinics.
So there probably isn't a lot of the,
the correlations within clinics are
probably really, really small.
There isn't a lot of difference between
the different clinics.
So that might suggest to us that we don't
need clinic-specific effects.
So I went ahead and I dropped the random
slope for clinic.
I left in the, random intercept for
clinic, but
I took out the random slope for clinic.
And when I did that, my AIC did get
slightly better at 1690.2,
and this was actually the best model that
I found.
So this is that final model that I ended
up going with.
I allowed there to be a, intercept, random
intercept for
clinic, but not a random slope for clinic.
I then went ahead and said do we need the
random slope for individual.
And, and you can see that even here we
probably don't even need
the random intercept for clinic,
because again, that variation between
clinics is almost zero at baseline.
I left it in anyway, it doesn't make a
huge difference here.
I went ahead then, however, and dropped,
the random effect for slope for
the subject, the subject-specific slopes.
That turns out to be a bad idea, because
the AIC goes way up.
And the reason is that there really is a
lot of variation in
the growth trajectories over time for
different individuals.
So we really want to keep that random
slope in the model.
And that's, this is just the results from
that model,
you can see it has a really high AIC, so
probably not the best model here.
So here's my final model for the weight
for length Z score.
So you can see that indeed there's a
significant, here's the p value,
there's a significant effect for time,
there's a significant quadratic effect for
time, and a significant cubic effect for
time.
So we're going to keep all of those in.
However, the group by age term, which is
what we really care about,
that p value is not significant.
It does favor the intervention group, it's
negative,
saying that the intervention group has
less weight gain over time,
however it's not statistically
significant.
Well, this probably has to do with the
fact that the majority of the time points
are early, and at those time points,
it doesn't look to be a huge difference
between the groups.
I then went ahead and did test for
a gender interaction to see if the girls
whose mothers had the intervention did
better than the boys and so I put a group
by age by gender term in the model.
But however it came out to be totally
non-significant.
So even though it,
there is some suggestion that the girls
did better if their mothers were the,
in the intervention group, I didn't see
anything in modeling.
We have very low statistical power here to
detect the generate, gender interaction.
So what we saw could have just been
chance,
and I'm certainly not going to factor it
into my final model.
So then I went ahead and put together a
table two, similar to what the authors
have in the paper that reports the beta
coefficients for my weight-for-length
Z score model, for my weight in kilograms
model, and my BMI Z score model.
And you can see that the weight in
kilograms, the group
by age term approaches statistical
significance but doesn't quite make it.
The BMI Z scores, which were only measured
in those later time points,
does make statistical significance because
again,
we did see some separation between the two
groups at the later time points.
And just for fun, I thought it would be
very useful for your understanding of
what these models are doing to go ahead
and generate some graphics that
actually graph the predicted values for
the individuals in the data set.
So if you take, if you fit a model, you
can ask your computer to calculate
predicted values for everybody in the data
set and output them and then graph those.
And that's really, that picture will show
you what,
what we've modeled, what the model looks
like.
So I went ahead and did this.
So here on the left-hand side, this is the
observed weight growth trajectories for
the, for the girls.
And then I went and got the predicted
values for the girls out of my model,
the model that I just showed you on for,
where the outcome was weight.
This had a cubic term in it as well as a
quadratic.
And you can see that indeed, and
then I just went ahead and got the
predictive values at each time point for
each woman, for each girl, and I just
connected those lines here.
And you can see that it indeed does appear
to have a nice cubic shape to it.
And it's basically a smoothed-over version
of the observed data.
And then, just to show you, in fact,
what we modeled was we modeled each growth
trajectory as a nice smooth cubic.
So I also went ahead and, rather than just
connecting the dots for each girl, I just,
you know, connected them as a cubic, which
is essentially what the model is.
So this is really kind of the model
picture.
This is, this picture corresponds to the
model.
This is what we've modeled, here with this
next model, with this cubic term in it.
Let's just help you understand what's the
difference between putting a linear term
in, a quadratic term, cubic term.
What does that really mean when we're
putting those complicated terms in the
model?
I went ahead and got the pre-, I fit new
models.
So I fit a new model where I only put in
an age term, so
I only modeled ages linear.
And these are the predicted values from
them all.
Well, you can see what we did was we fit a
line for each person.
And then I also did the same thing where I
only put a linear term in a quadratic, but
not a cubic term into the model and
you can see what we get is a quadratic
shape at the end of the day, and
here's the smooth quadratic shape, which
is really what the model fits.
Those clearly don't match the picture of
the observed data, so
we definitely need that cubic term.
And I did the same thing just to show you,
observed and
predicted for weight for boys, you get the
same idea.
We, we model the cubic.
I think these predicted graphics are
really helpful.
I also did an observed versus a predicted,
by clinic.
So here's the observed values, when I
graphed by clinic, blue lines for
the control clinics, red lines for the
intervention clinics.
Here's the fitted model, the predicted
values for my fitted model and
you can see that clear cubic shape.
And, the, blue clinics are predicted to
have little bit higher weight gain over
time.
And then again, just to kind of get to the
sense of what we mean by quadratic and
cubic, I took out the cubic term and what
you can see is that if I take out
the cubic term, then my model is actually
fit a quadratic function, not a cubic.
And if I take out the quadratic term you
can see that my model has fit
just a line for each clinic, which is
clearly not the right shape, but
that's what the quadratic, cubic and
linear terms all mean.
We're of course going to want to do some
model checks on our models, so
I went ahead and asked for the residuals
for my models.
You can get that even out of proc mixed.
You can see that we want the residuals to
be reasonably, normally distributed.
That looks pretty good.
You can plot the residuals and, you know
across time and things, and look for
any patterns.
It looks like we're, we're meeting the
assumptions pretty well here.
I then went ahead and limited the analysis
just to the later time points when
the babies were two, three, and four.
We already saw that there seems to be more
separation at those time points.
And so here's the picture that goes with
that, here's the observed data,
which I've, this graph I've already showed
you.
I then went ahead and fit a model.
So in this model, for weight-for-length Z
score, I took the same basic model but
cut the only model for the later time
points after the second,
including the second, third, and fourth
birthday visits.
And when you do that, you do see that as
we saw with the BMI Z scores,
the BMI Z scores were only available for
the later time.
We did have a separation between the
groups.
We see the same thing when we look at the
weight-for-length Z scores,
limited to the second, third, and fourth
birthdays.
We do get a significant result here as the
authors reported in the paper.
Now interestingly, if we're only looking
at these last three time points,
we probably don't need this age cubed term
anymore.
You know, you look at that, well, maybe
it's a little bit cubic,
but we may not need to actually fully
model that as a cubic.
So I went ahead and dropped the cubic
term, from the model.
So here is my observed and my predicted
when I include the cubic term.
This is the predicted on the right here.
This is the observed.
I actually then went ahead, and this is a
you know, if I really show you it,
here is if I just grab a smoothing line on
the predicted values.
Here is if I actually graft that cubic one
on the predicted values.
As you can see maybe we don't need that
much curvature.
And I went ahead and dropped the cubic
term, and so
the quadratic term, the AIC turned out to
be sufficient.
We didn't really need that quadra, the
cubic term anymore.
But you can see it didn't make a huge
difference on the P value for
the group by age term.
It's still statistically significant.
Here's the observed versus.
I predicted, when I have the quadratic
term.
So, I'm showing you now this is the
predictive where I'm just fitting
a smoothing line to the predicted values,
and if I actually fit the quadratic to
those predicted values you can see that
nice quadratic shape there.
That sufficient to capture, the content of
the data here.
I also limited the weight outcome to 24 to
48 months.
Again, the group by age is also
statistically significant.
I only went up to the quadratic for
weight, as well.
So, we do get a nice separation at these
later time points.
Just for fun, I also looked at some other
predictors of weight gain over time.
So this is looking at the BMI Z scores.
These are again, only two, three, and four
years of age.
We already saw that maybe the age at which
you introduce solids to
the baby might have an influence on their
weight gain trajectory over time.
And, indeed, if you look at SolidAge.
Now this is, SolidAge is the age at which,
the month at which the baby was introduced
to solid foods, which is usually somewhere
around 4, 5, 6, 7 months.
And you can see now that the main effect
for
solid age is, solid age is statistically
significant.
because remember, that this were starting
baseline here, is two years of age, so
this is way after SolidAge.
The SolidAge foods have been introduced
but the baseline of this analysis,
which is at three years of age, the babies
who were fed solid foods back
earlier or later when, at a later age when
they were
young they are tracking about a half
standard deviation less in BMI Z score.
Or and it is statistically significant at
two years of age.
Some solid food interdiction seems to have
some influence here.
And then they continued, there continued
to be some significant effect here.
So, what's interesting is that the babies
who, had gotten their solids at a later
age they at two years they are lighter by
about half a standard deviation.
But they are actually catching up with the
other babies a little bit over time.
So, what you can see is that the SolidAge
by age.
This interaction, i, what's happening is
thats positive, so
the later you were introduced to solids as
your goal for
being two years old, to three years old
[INAUDIBLE] to four years old.
You are actually catching up for
gaining a little bit more weight relative
to the ones who got solid at younger age,
but you started at two years at being, as
being quite a bit lighter.
So, there's a little bit of the curves
coming together there.
All right, so the other thing that I just
wanted to throw in for learning purposes
here, was we have modeled this, we had a
proc mixed with random statements.
That actually handles the data really well
here,
because you can put in two random
statements, one for
clinic and one for subject.
But, I also wanted to illustrate, the fact
that you could also model these data with
a generalized estimating equation or with
a proc mixed with a repeated statement.
And I wanted to try to,
again, say what difference between those
three approaches are.
So, I went ahead and re-ran the exact same
model,
except I did it in proc mixed with a
repeated statement.
And then I asked [INAUDIBLE] to generate
the predicted values from those models.
And they're very informative, to look at
these graphics.
This is the predicted values, and I'm
graphing here by clinic,
so predicted values by clinic.
And this is from my proc mixed with the
random statement.
So, what you can see is, well gee, each
clinic is allowed,
all the clinics have different
trajectories of growth over time.
All the individuals are predicted to have
different growth trajectories over time.
There is variation, so a specific
individual has a different predicted
value even two individuals who are, are
from the same intervention group,
they 're predicted to have different
values over time.
So, you get variation, you get scatter.
Now look over here.
Here, is the predicted values by clinic
from a proc mixed with a repeated
statement.
Might use I think an autoregressive
correlation structure.
And, what do you see here.
These are the predicted values.
So, there is no subject specific
variability, that's the whole point.
That the random effect builds in the
subject specific variability.
There's no variation.
So, from the proc mix with the repeated
statement,
you're getting a marginal model.
So every, anybody who's in the, any of the
intervention clinics is,
projected to have a specific value at each
of the time points.
And everybody who is in
the intervention clinics is projected to
have a specific value.
At specific time points and there's no
variation built into that.
We're not allowing subjects to vary from
that.
So, you can pictorially see the difference
between those two models.
You can clearly see that the proc mix or
the repeated statement is a marginal
model.
And then I also ran a generalized
estimating equation which is basically
doing the same thing as the proc mixed
with the repeated statement.
It's also fitting a marginal model.
So, you don't get any subject specific
effects.
Everybody is predicted to lie right on
that line.
And I just did it as again, looking at the
weights.
So, here's the predictive value of the
weights on the left hand side,
from the proc mixed with the repeated
statement.
Again, it's a marginal model, we're
predicting.
Two lines, your getting two lines here,
because remember my model has intervention
group and control group in it.
So you're clearing seeing some difference.
For the this is with the intervention
group.
This would be the control group.
But everybody's projected to lie on that
line.
Only, the only thing you're allowed to
vary on is.
Whether you're intervention or control.
On the right side, here's the proc mixed
with the random statement.
And again, you can see that we're allowing
subject specific growth curve.
So, that's the difference between proc
mixed with the repeated statement, and
proc mixed with a random statement.
And the generalized estimating equation,
again, it's marginal model, so
it looks just like the proc mixed with the
repeated statement.
So, the next thing we'd want to do is to
do some sensitivity analyses.
The real sensitivity analyses that would
be best for
this data set would be to probe those 25
dropouts, and
see what influence those might have had on
the analysis.
We don't have those data.
So, the only sensitivity analysis I went
ahead and
did was to just notice that there was this
one baby in the control group, this girl,
who was quite a bit heavier and could be
pulling the blue line up.
It might be having a lot of influence on
our estimates.
So, I went ahead and ran the model with
her and then ran the model without her
just to see how much influence she might
be having on the estimates.
We wouldn't want one baby to be completely
pulling that line up.
So, when I ran the model with her, you've
already seen these estimates.
The group by age term had a P value of
0.005.
So, fairly statistically significant.
When I remove that outlier, it still
remains statistically significant, but
you can see that some of the effect is a
little bit less.
So my data coefficient was negative .035.
And this for weight so that corresponds to
.035 kilograms less per ages and months,
for months.
The effect size is a little bit lower when
we take that girl out,
and also the p-value is still significant,
but you know, a little bit higher.
So, she is having some influence on the
estimates,
although taking her out doesn't completely
we don't completely lose the effect.
We still seem to have the effect even if
she's not in there.
So, you want to do some analysis like that
to probe potentially influential values.
And then, finally,
we're going to want to create some formal
graphics that summarize the findings.
I've already shown you a ton of graphics
and easily, a lot of,
a number of those graphics could be
formalized to include in the paper.
I'll just show you the graphic that the
authors actually chose to include in
their paper.
Here is the observe that I like to show
observe along with projected, predicted.
So, here is my observed graphs that I
already showed you for the week.
For length score, and for the BMI Z score,
what the authors showed in their paper was
the fitted curves from their mixed models.
For this is the, control group in the
dotted line.
And this is the intervention group in the
smooth line.
This is for the weight for length z-score.
And this is for the BMI Z score.
So these are kind of the [INAUDIBLE] the
smooth version of the observed graphs.
And, this is exactly what the model fits,
the model fits for weight length score,
we fit cubits, as you can see,
those are cleric cubits with the control
grouping a little higher.
The Z score for
BMI, we fit a quadratic, and the control
group ends up a little bit higher.
So, those are just their, they're showing
the fit graph, they're showing.
That the model projects the control group
to be a little bit higher than
the intervention group.
The dots you're seeing on these graphics,
I think, are not the prettiest thing, but
they're showing the mean value for all,
for the weight for
length score or the BMI Z score in the
intervention and control groups.
So, those are the observed values, the
lines are the fitted values.
So, that's one possible graphic that you
could present, and again,
I've shown you a number of other graphics.
That would make nice pictures for the
paper.
[BLANK_AUDIO]