[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module,
I'm going to give you some introductory
examples to repeated measures data.
Just to give you some examples from the
literature of the kinds of
things that we're talking about when we're
talking about repeated measures outcomes.
So here's an example that was in the
British Medical Journal a number of
years ago.
This was looking at comparing homeopathy
versus a placebo pill in
treating pain after surgery.
And the homeopathy group is in the filled
in circles,
the placebo group is in the open circles,
and you can see just by looking at
this visual that homeopathy really doesn't
do so well in terms of treating pain.
It doesn't do anything better than a
placebo at least.
The outcome here is a continuous outcome
which is your mean pain scores,
assessed by this visual analog scale.
You basically, you ask people to rate
their pain on a scale from
zero to something, and you can see that
right after surgery they
are probably on the sedatives and the
drugs from surgery.
So as they come off of those their pain
slowly goes up,
then they start this homeopathy or placebo
but the pain goes up and
the homeopathy group doesn't really do any
better than the placebo group.
Yeah, and what you can see though is that
pain was measured multiple times over
the course of after surgery, so these are
hours after surgery.
So every hour after surgery the
researchers here
were measuring this pain on this visual
analog scale.
And they've plotted it here and the plot
tells you a lot of information,
because clearly you can see there's not
much difference between the groups.
So this would be a type of repeated
measured outcomes,
it's the same people having their pain
measured over time.
Just another example, this was a study
comparing a antidepressant divalproex,
to a placebo pill for the treatment of
depression.
And so what we're seeing is the mean
change in the depression score, so
you want to go down because these are
people with depression, they want,
you want to lower their depression scores.
What you can see that's interesting they
measured the depression scores at
multiple time points, after randomization,
after they started taking the pills.
And you can see,
you can see a clear placebo effect because
the placebo group, that's the group in
red actually does have quite a drop in
their depression scores initially.
So reflecting some kind of placebo effect
that
they think that they're getting something
that will help.
But then it sort of plateaus out and
you can see there's an additional drop in
the the antidepressant group here.
This does turn out to be statistically
significant by something
called repeating measures.
So NOVO which we'll talk about next week.
But again another example of they've
measured depression scores at
multiple time points, on the same people.
You're starting to get the idea here, just
a few more examples, so
this one was looking at acute mountain
sickness,
it was treated with something called a
simulated descent.
One hour of treatment in a hyperbaric
chamber.
Or a kind of a steroid.
And so you can see that the steroid group
is in the open circles.
This pressurization group is in the closed
circles.
They are measuring their mean score on
some kind of measure of mountain sickness.
If, again, a continuous measure, and
you can see that they're both going down
over time.
It looks like the pressurization maybe has
a quicker resolution of the acute
mountain sickness.
So another example of multiple
measurements on the same groups of people.
Another one, so we're going to be talking
about milk and calcium in bone density.
This was a randomized trial, where they,
women at adolescence were randomized to
drink a pint of milk extra a day versus
being in a control group.
And they followed their total bone mineral
content,
this is the total amount of calcium in
your skeleton over time.
And the milk and calcium intake does
matter for adolescents.
So you can see that there's a small
separation between these groups.
This is graphing the percentage increase
in his bone mineral content over time.
And you can see it's not a huge difference
between the groups, but
definitely getting some advantage if
you're drinking that extra milk.
And finally one more, so this is looking
another randomized trial looking at
counseling and smoking in pregnancy.
This is the number of cigarettes smoked
per week so another continuous outcome.
We have the counseling group in red and
the control group in blue.
So the counseling group is doing somewhat
better on reducing their
cigarette intake during pregnancy than the
control group.
But again, we're measuring, [UNKNOWN] it's
number of cigarettes per week,
that continuous outcome multiple, at
multiple time points.
You can see that graphing these types of
data is going to be very important,
because it really gives you a lot of
insight into what's happening in the data.
[BLANK_AUDIO]