[BLANK_AUDIO]
Welcome to week five of the course.
This week we're going to wrap up our
discussion of survival analysis.
So, I've tried to keep the material in
this unit fairly light because you're
all working hard on your mid-term data
analysis and
there is no homework set specifically for
this unit.
I'm going to cover a couple of topics, so
first of all, the idea of competing risks.
You've actually seen a data set that had
competing risks in it
already,so that melanoma data set that you
dealt with in the first couple of
homework's actually had a competing risk.
There was variable that told you, did
somebody die of melanoma specifically, or
did they die of other courses.
For the purposes of those homework's, to
keep it simple,
we just want those together and we look at
overall mortality,but what if
you specifically wanted to look at risk
factors for death from melanoma.
How would you isolate that from death for
other causes.
This is the idea of competing risks and
it's a little bit tricky and
we'll see how to handle it this week.
Secondly, I'm going to talk about
something called the intention to
treat principle.
This is not specific to survival analysis,
but
is a principle that's used whenever you
have randomized clinical trial data,so,
because a lot of the times in randomized
trials we have survival data, we're often
implied applying this intention to treat
principle,so we'll go over that this week.
Just an introductory example along the
ideas of competing risks, what you're
looking at here are two Kaplan-Meier
curves from the same data set.
So on the left hand side you're seeing
cardiovascular mortality is
the outcome and on the right hand side
you're seeing deaths from other
causes that are not heart disease related.
What's interesting if you look carefully
at these Kaplan–Meier curves,lets just,
for the purposes of illustration, focus on
just this low group the people in
this study were classified according to
levels of a particular blood biomarker.
Those in the low group, if you look
carefully and
see the total number that died of
cardiovascular disease.
You can kind of scroll over and you can
see that by the end of the study,
about seven or eight years in,there was
about a 50% survival probability which
means that there was a 50% chance of dying
from cardiovascular
heart disease related causes,so 50% chance
of dying from,
from that but, what's interesting is if
you go over here and
look at the low group, over again the
whole course of this study for
non-cardiovascular mortality, the survival
probabilities may be only 44 or 45%.
That means the chances of dying from other
causes besides CVD,
cardiovascular disease, was 55%,so
in other words, people in this study had a
50% chance of dying from heart disease,
and they had a 55% chance of dying from
things other than heart disease.
Well, we should be able to add those up
and
get the total probability of dying from,of
dying in this study.
Notice that if we add those up, it turns
out that people in the study had
a 105% chance of dying, and obviously
that's
impossible,so there's something wrong with
the way the data is presented here.
We'll get to this idea when we get to the
topic of competing risks.