I just want to quickly point out that the
partial likelihood, when I was
describing that partial likelihood for
you, I didn't say what you did about ties.
So every term in the likelihood, I said
you get the person who died or
had the event in the numerator and the
risk set in the denominator, but
what if more than one person had the event
at a particular time, say time equals one.
So in the pregnancy data, for example, we
had several women getting pregnant in
the first month of their first cycle,
essentially, of the study.
The partial likelihood actually assumes no
tied values amongst
the observed survival times, and that is
not often the case with real data.
In other words, with real data, like the
pregnancy data, you'll often see ties.
A lot of times the reason you have ties is
not because people had the event at
the exact same moment in time, which is
very unlikely.
But because, when we do a study, we don't
measure time very precisely.
So you might only know the month when
people had an event,
when a person had an event.
So several people might have the event
three months into the study,
because that's as fine as you've measured
time.
And that's usually what we assume.
We assume that the ties result from, that
the ties in your data set, that is,
having multiple people with the same event
time in your data set,
we usually assume that that just results
from the imprecise measurement of time.
So, in other words, we think if we, there
is some true order of
events that people don't die at the exact,
exact moment, but that if you
could measure time more finely you would
be able to know exactly who died first or
had the event first, so there is some true
order of events, we just don't know it.
And so, if you assume that, then you can
calculate the partial likelihood.
You can deal with the ties based on
something called an exact method.
And the exact method, as all exact methods
we've seen,
it calculates the exact probability of all
possible orderings of events.
So, in other words we said that they're,
if five people all have these
same event time in your data set, you can
calculate the probability that, you know,
the order was one, two, three, four, five,
if we call them subjects one through five.
Or that it was five, four,
three, two, one or all possible five
factorial possible orderings.
You could calculate the probabilities of
all of those.
Now this can be very calculation
intensive, as you can imagine,
especially if you have a lot of ties.
because it's literally calculating all the
possible ways it could have happened.
So since the exact method, especially in
the past, it's so
computationally intensive.
Back in the 70s, when we didn't have as
much computing power,
people came up with approximations to the
exact methods.
They went, rather than doing out this
exact probability, which can be,
if there a huge data set with lots of
ties,
which might hang your computer, there are
available approximations to it.
Bres, the Breslow approximation and
the Efron approximation are most commonly
used.
And I'm not going to go into the
mathematical details, but
they're just trying to do the exact method
without having so much computation.
kind of getting at it without being
totally exact.
So, the Breslow approximation is actually
the default in SASS although,
statisticians will generally tell you that
the Efron approximation is
better in some situations.
In fact, if you take some real data and
try all of these different methods for
dealing with ties, even if you have a lot
of ties,
a lot of times it doesn't make a huge
difference in the estimate.
The only place that it really makes a
difference is if time is
actually not continuous, but time is
actually truly discrete.
And so one other way to handle the ties is
to, is called the discrete method, and
this is actually conceptually different,
because this is,
you might choose the discrete method when
time actually is truly discrete.
In other words, when the ties are real,
and
people actually have the event at the
exact same times.
And the way that might happen is if events
can only happen at certain discrete times.
So if time is truly discrete, you know,
the events are somehow periodic and
can only happen at certain times.
So maybe like winning an Olympic medal can
only happen every four years or voting for
President can only happen every four
years.
There's just some things that can only
happen at a given time.
Those ties are then real, and so
the method for handling with the ties then
is somewhat different.
Now, the discrete method actually does
something a little bit different.
So if you choose the discrete method for
handling ties, you're actually modeling
proportional odds.
And what you get out at the end of the day
are odds ratios, and not hazard ratios.
So that's a key distinction,
you have to know that those effects that
you're getting out are then odds ratios.
And just briefly, I don't want to go into
a lot of detail here, but briefly how it
works is, if, for example, you have a
hundred people at risk at a certain time
and 15 have the event at the exact same
time, what we're going to model
therefore is, what's the chance that, that
given that we know, condition that we
know that 15 events occurred, what's the
probability that the events happened to
this particular set of 15 people, out of
all possible sets of 15?
So in your denominator,
you are going to sort of have all possible
sets of 15 that could have happened.
You are going to have the probabilities
for all of those, and there are 100,
choose 15 of them if you have a hundred
people at risk.
And then you'll put in the numerator, the
probability for this specific 15,
the ones who actually did have the event
at that time, the actual set of 15.
So you're going to have a conditional
probability in your likelihood that
looks like that.
This does give you, because we've taken
out time now,
we're just saying groups of people, what
group of people had the events,
this does now go back to odds ratios,
rather than hazard ratios.
And if you think about it, if you remember
back to when we talked about conditional
logistic regression, the likelihood here
is actually very similar to the one we
had for conditional logistic regression,
which also gave you odds ratios.