This next module is actually going to
serve two purposes.
So I want to do a little bit more practice
and enforcement of linear regression.
But I also want to just slip two tools or
tricks into your tool box.
These are some statistical tricks that you
may have occasion to
use in the future when you're analyzing
your own data.
Now they happen to involve linear
regression, and will help reinforce your
understanding of linear regression, so I'm
going to slip these in now.
So the first tool that you may end up
wanting to use someday is something I'm
calling residual analysis.
And basically the idea is that the
residuals from
a linear regression can sometimes be
useful in and of themselves.
They can be analyzed as a new variable.
And this is really just best illustrated
with me giving you some examples.
Basically, if you have a really key
covariate,
like a covariate that's going to be a
major, major confounder.
And you actually want to know whether a
person's value is higher or
lower than expected, given their level of
this key confounder, this key covariate.
What you might be after is these
residuals.
So let me just give you some examples
here.
So, for example, if we're talking about
nutrition data, this is often used for
analyzing nutrition data by the way.
So, imagine you've collected some
nutrition data and nutrition variables,
nutrient variables are highly, highly
related to total caloric intake.
If you're somebody who just eats a lot of
food,
you're going to have high levels of all
the nutrients you can think of, but
that's partly mediated through caloric
intake.
So what if you just wanted to know
specifically about, say,
their calcium intake.
How do you untangle that from the total
caloric intake?
One way to do that is to use the residuals
from a linear regression that regresses
the, their calcium, a person's calcium
intake against their caloric intake.
So you would regress calcium on calories
for that linear regression, and
there's definitely going to be a positive
association there.
because the more you eat, the more calcium
you're going to take in.
But the residual analysis will focus on is
a person's value for calcium higher or
lower than expected, given the amount of
calories they eat.
So if you're somebody who eats a high
amount of calories but
your calcium is way above the line.
This is the residual, remember is the
difference between an observed value and
a value on the line.
This person is a person who for the, the
calories they eat,
eats an unexpectedly high amount of
calcium for that level of calories.
Where as if I had somebody over here,
who's kind of in the middle range for
calories, their expected value for calcium
is on the line here, but
they are lower than average for their
caloric intake.
So their residual would be negative.
That would be somebody who ate kind of a
lower than expected calcium intake for
the, the cal, their calorie levels.
So we can take these residuals, run this
linear regression,
take these residuals and store those
residuals as a new variable and
use those residuals for further analysis.
Just to, to have another example, I'm
going to go through this specific example
with calcium in more detail in just a
second.
But just to show you that that has more
uses than just nutrition,
let me present one other example to you.
So imagine you're doing a study that's
looking at weight loss.
And we know that if you lose weight, so
here's weight lost in the study.
We know if you lose weight, that generally
it improves your lipid profile.
So maybe like you're LDL cholesterol which
you want to be low,
may be that as you lose weight that
generally will go down.
So more weight lost, the more your LDL
will decrease.
However, there may be individual
variability again.
So here's a person right here, this dot,
who their LDL went
down a lot more than expected for the low
amount of weight loss that they had.
Where as maybe, here's a person who lost a
lot of weight, but
didn't lose as much LDL as expected.
So again, we can store those residuals as
a new variable if what
we care about is trying to figure out
where,
why is there variability in the amount of
LDL improvement after accounting for
the amount of weight loss in this weight
loss study, for example.
So this has all sorts of uses.
Let me zoom in on the nutrition one,
because that's one that you'll see a lot
in the literature.
So I have some actual data from women
runners that I have from a number of
years back.
This particular dataset I was looking at
has 125 women runners in it.
We gave them all a food frequency
questionnaire,
I'm just looking here at the baseline
data.
Food frequency questionnaires are
notorious for
the fact that you know, you basically are
checking off boxes about how much you eat.
Some people will be really lenient in
checking off those boxes and
will end up having high estimated caloric
intake, and
therefore, everything will kind of be
high.
Other people are very stringent in which
boxes they check and may come out with
something as you know, low just because
they, they tend to check less.
So calories and nutrients are going to be
strongly related, and
of course just for real reasons the more
calories you eat,
the more you're going to take in of all
the nutrients.
And you can see that reflected here.
This is the Pearson's Correlation
Coefficient Matrix for,
this is calories, calcium, fat, iron,
vitamin D, and vitamin C.
These are all baseline values.
So what you'll notice is that first of
all, calories is just really key here.
More calories means more overall intake.
So, calories has a, a correlation with
calcium intake of 0.66, with fat of 0.79,
iron 0.74, Vitamin D 0.47, Vitamin C 0.46.
The more you eat, the more you're going to
take in of everything.
And so automatically all of your nutrient
values are going to look high if your
calories are high.
Even beyond that, if you look at
correlations between individual nutrients,
so for example, if I look at vitamin D and
fat, for example, that has a positive
correlation.
All of the correlations in this matrix are
positive.
So, because, if you're a person who eats
more fat, you'll,
you probably eat more calories and if
you're a person who eats more Vitamin D,
you'll probably also eat more calories.
It's going to look like all the nutrients
are highly correlated because again
somebody who just eats more is going to be
high on everything.
And so, we'd like to somehow adjust for
calories.
You can of course put calories in as a
co-variant in your
regression model that's one way to adjust
for it.
But it's slightly better to use this
residual method.
It's going to reveal more things.
it's going to help with answering the
question of is vitamin D,
do vitamin D and fat really go together?
Or is it just that this is reflecting the
fact that more calories mean
more of both of these?
We can tease that apart.
So I'm going to just concentrate on
calcium to have on nutrient to look at it.
This was a study on bone density, so
of course calcium is important for bone
destiny.
So here is the plot I'm plotting.
This is just a baseline values of calories
for
the women in my study, these 125 women.
This is calories per day.
Again, you can see since it's from a food
frequency questionnaire,
some people just check off a lot of boxes
and
they end up with much higher you know,
values and
calories, probably more than they actually
eat, and some people are a little low.
They're probably not really only eating
800 calories a day, but
they just you know, tended to be a little
conservative on checking off the boxes in
the food frequency questionnaire.
This is calcium in milligrams per day.
And what I did here is to fit a regression
line.
So as calories go up, we are expecting
calcium to go up.
What we're interested in though, is for a
given caloric intake,
how far, how much higher or
lower is a person that expected for their
choleric intake, that's the residual.
So, for example, this person right here is
you know, reported on
the food frequency questionnaire eating
more than 4,000 calories a day.
For that level of calories,
we're expecting them to consume 2,000
milligrams of calcium.
In fact they were reported consuming more
than about 3500.
So their residual is going to be something
here like positive 1500.
On the other hand,
this person right here who reported also
eating a lot of calories, but
close to 4,000, they're predicted to have
a value of about 2,000 per calcium intake.
But they're little bit lower than that,
they're closer to maybe 1300, so they may
get a residual of like negative 700.
So for every person, every person is
going to get this residual calculation,
this person you know, maybe is positive
1,000 or so.
We're going to take these residuals,
we're going to store them in a new
variable called calcium residuals.
So everybody, here's my ID number, so
person one will have a value,
let's say this was person, subject one,
and subject two might have this value.
And subject three might have this value.
So, it just becomes a new variable.
This variable reflects whether a person is
high or
low in calcium for a given caloric intake.
We can do this with all the nutrients.
And this is just showing you the
distribution of the absolute value of
calcium on the left.
So this is just the calcium and the
milligrams per day.
This on the right is the calcium
residuals.
So this now you can see is whether or not
they're, how, how much higher or
lower they are than expected for a given
caloric intake.
What you'll notice is that the calcium
residuals have a much more normally,
a much more normal distribution.
So now this is untangled, on the
right-hand side,
these values are untangled from calories,
they're corrected for calories, and
they have a much nicer distribution, much
more normally distributed.
So that has advantages.
We can now look at the correlation matrix
and as expected.
Now the correlation with calories for all
these nutrients is exactly zero,
that's what the residual method will, will
do for you.
Another thing that is very useful here is
that now if you
look at the pair wise comparisons between
the individual nutrients,
they're now no longer all positive.
So now you get a better sense of how
actual nutrients go together.
So, for example, here's a good one.
If you look at vitamin C and fat intake,
these are the residuals for vitamin C and
fat, you'll notice that this was, vitamin
C and fat had a slight positive
correlation in the original correlation
matrix before we accounted for calories.
But now it's highly negative.
This makes sense because people who eat a
lot of fruits and vegetables are going to
have a high vitamin C intake, but might
also have a very low fat intake.
So now you're getting real patterns and
you're picking out these real patterns,
these real relationships in the individual
nutrients untangled from calories.
You can take these residuals and use them
in further analyses.
So what I did here was I took the calcium
residuals as my predictor, and
my outcome for this is the spine bone
density at baseline for this data set, and
I put in, I set a model with an intercept
plus a beta set for the calcium residuals.
So now rather than putting calcium as an
absolute value,
let's see if that correlates with spine
strength,
bone strength, I've put in the calcium
residuals.
Now, it turns out that you know, the spine
bone density and
the calcium residuals, if you plot them
there's really no relationship.
This is a cross-sectional look, so you're,
your calcium intake now may, and just
looking cross sectionally may not have a
lot to do with your current bone density.
And we will see that calcium does is
important at, if you look longitudinally,
but at a cross section it will look, it
sometimes isn't correlated.
So what we found here is just that the
beta is close to zero and
it's not statistically significant.
But that used the calcium residuals in
further analysis.
The second little trick that I want to put
in your toolkit that also involves linear
regression is what I'm calling an
individual slope analysis.
And the idea is this.
Sometimes, we may have a situation where
we want to
actually run a separate linear regression
on each person and
to store those slopes, and those slopes
become a new variable.
And this can be useful for, this will be
our segue into repeated measures data
because this can be useful for a simple
way to analyze repeated measures data.
So, imagine that I've got people measured
over time and
I'm looking at say the spine bone density.
This is again a measure of bone strength.
What if I have measured women, say I've
measured them six times.
So here's just a plot for one woman.
So I measured her time point one, a second
time, a third time,
a fourth time, a fifth time, and a sixth
time.
And maybe her data looks like that.
It's only six points, but it's enough to
fit a line.
So, what you could do is actually fit a
linear regression line just for
this one individual woman.
And why would you want to do that?
Well, it simplifies the data.
You've got a, an outcome variable that is
six data points to it.
You can simplify it into a single summary
measure which is the slope of this line.
You can see that there's a lot of
assumptions here.
You're assuming that there's sort of a
linear change over time, and
that change over time is constant.
But that might be reasonable for a lot of
cases.
You will fit a linear regression line for
every person in your data set separately.
You will store those slopes as a new
variable.
And that's perfectly valid to do.
But yet slope will, could be interpreted
as then, as a rate of change
in bone density for a given woman.
So you get a rate of change value.
Now you could of course just you know,
another way to summarize these data would
be to take the first and
last measurement, and say like how much
did she change from first to last.
But that would ignore the intron
measurements that you made, so
this is a way of capturing sort of all
these measurements that you've made
into one summary measurement.
Now next week, subsequent weeks I'm
going to tell you how to actually analyze
all six of those data points and not have
to summarize them into one, but
there may be occasion where you want to
get that summary measure.
So I went ahead and did that.
Now I've got in my example data set of
women runners,
I actually only have three time points, so
it doesn't make the most precise slope.
You know, it's only based on three points.
But you can fit a line to three points
which I've done here.
So this represents on women on the the
left and
then a different women on the right.
The women on the left her slope is
positive the women on the right her
slope is negative.
So her you know, her spine bone density
was going down over time.
These are not big slopes but we can, they
represent the rate of change over time for
bone destiny for these women.
I went and got these slopes for
all 125 women in my data set, and I've
plotted them here in a histogram.
So you can see that bone density wasn't
changing a lot.
These were women who were already adults,
and
you don't change bone density very rapidly
after you've passed adolescence.
But you can see that,
you know, the average rate of change was
somewhere around zero or positive one.
Spine bone density, the average is around
1.0.
And the standard deviation for spine bone
density is about 0.1.
So, women are going up like 0.01, 0.02,
maybe as much as 0.03 or
0.04 in bone density.
This is their average rate of change per
year.
I got these just from storing those slopes
as a new variable.
We can then use those slopes as variable,
as a new variable further analysis.
So I went ahead used the slopes as an
outcome variable.
So I said my slopes are my rate of change.
And in this slide, I'm actually looking at
the rate of change in
bone mineral content which is just the
total amount of calcium in your skeleton.
I've stored those [UNKNOWN], and I'm
looking to see whether or
not a woman's calcium intake or the
calcium in her diet measured as residuals.
The calcium residuals that we just did a
few minutes ago, whether or
not that predicts her rate of change in
bone mineral content,
the amount of calcium in her skeleton over
time.
And it's not quite statistically
significant but it's bordering on it and
it's positive, because it kind of makes
sense if you're somebody who is
eating a lot of calcium in your diet that,
that would predict that
you would be depositing more calcium in
your skeleton over time.
And we do see that, although it doesn't
quite reach statistical significance here.
But those slopes then can be useful for
further analysis.
[BLANK_AUDIO]