[BLANK_AUDIO]
Since we're not having an official class
meeting after the,
final exam is slated to be released, I
thought it would be worth me taping just
a short video to say a few words about the
final exam.
So, the data for the final exam come from
a BMJ Open paper.
The authors were kind enough to share
their data with us.
The authors had run a cluster randomized
trial.
So, they had randomly assigned six
pregnancy clinics.
They assigned three of them to be the
intervention clinics and
three to be the control clinics.
And women were enrolled from within those
clinics.
Women rolled into the, enrolled into the
intervention clinics received some
lifestyle counseling about diet and
exercise to help them lose
their pregnancy weight faster after the
birth of their babies.
The control clinics didn't receive
anything.
And the primary outcome of this trial was
the mother's weight loss postpartum.
Those data are in a different paper and
that's not the focus of this analysis.
So, this paper is actually looking at a
secondary outcome.
The authors went back and collected data
about the weight gain of the infants and
toddlers over time.
And their thought was that if the mothers
received some training about
eating better, that that somehow might rub
off on their children and
that the children might have a slower
trajectory of weight gain over time,
which would be valuable for preventing
things like childhood obesity.
So, they were able to collect, the
original trial had 89 women in it.
They were able to go back and collect this
weight gain data on the infants for
64 out of the original 89 infants.
And the infants had their weights measured
about ten times during their
first year of life.
Infants go in frequently to the doctor to
be checked.
And then had their weights measured and
heights measured at their second, third
and fourth birthdays.
The authors provided me the data.
Here's the final exam shown here.
The authors provided me the data in the
long form the variables also had Italian
names which I went through and changed for
you into something English, but
the data dictionary is there for available
in the long form of the data.
In that Excel file, there's a tab that
says labels and
values, you can click on that, you'll see
the full data dictionary in English.
I also turned the data into the broad form
just in case there are some analyses that
are easier to do with the broad form and
you want the broad form in the data.
For the exam I'm asking you to look at
three outcomes,
the two outcomes that the authors look for
in their paper, the weight for
length z scores which was measured at
every time point.
The BMI z score, which is only available
after the infants turn two
because the standardization to calculate
those z scores is only available.
It's based on population norms and
it's only available for infants who are
older than two.
So there's most of the infants only have
two or three values for that BMI z score.
Those are the two outcomes that the
authors looked at in the paper.
I am additionally asking you to look at
the absolute value of
weight in kilograms to give you a third
variable that isn't in the paper, for
you to grapple with for your final exam.
I'm leading you through a series of
questions,
there's a couple of questions that ask you
to think about missing data.
And then I'm leading you through a series
of plots that you need to do and
it's going to be really important to
understand these data.
You really need to do a lot of plotting.
The first plot you're going to have to do
is just to reproduce figure two
which you see here, these growth
trajectories.
I just let you know that you do not have
to make all of
the formatting identical to what is in the
paper here.
It should look professional and the
trajectory should look the same but
you don't have to match exactly the
legends and things.
I'm leading you through a series of other
graphics that will help you to
understand the data.
In question seven here, I'm then asking
you to basically recreate
the statistical models that the author's
themselves ran in their paper.
And there's a nice description if
you scroll down into the statistical
methods section.
It starts mixed effects linear regression
models.
It tells you exactly what those what, what
they put in those models, and
you're welcome to run very similar models,
to what the authors ran here,
of course, you want to think about it.
Think carefully about it.
I want to just point out that there is a
layer of complexity here that we
haven't dealt with in the homeworks so far
for this class.
And, what we have here, is we have two
sources of clustering.
So we have been dealing with observations
that are clustered within
an individual because we have repeated
measures within the same individual.
We've dealt with that so far and I told
you how to deal with that.
There's an additional source of
correlation here, however, because this is
a cluster randomized trial and so that
means that we may have some correlation
among the women within a given clinic and
so we at least have to consider that.
We at least have to try to build that into
our models to
test whether there's any correlation there
that we need to worry about.
The nice thing is that if you use a random
effects model,
you can actually have it in the code two
random line,
more than one line where you can ask for
not only randomized effects for
subjects, so subject specific intercept
and subject specific slopes.
But you can also ask for clinic specific
intercepts and
clinic specific slopes and I've given you
the code under question seven here that
you would need in order to be able to do
this kind of model.
So, that should be enough to set you up to
do those models.
It may turn out that the random effects
for
clinic may not add much to the model fit.
It may be that there isn't a lot of
correlation within class, within clinic.
And if that's the case, you know then
it'll be up to you whether or
not you keep those in the model.
But we at least need to think about the
effect of clinic here,
because it is a cluster randomized trial.
So, I think I've given you enough
instruction there, to be able to do that.
I'm asking you to recreate the,
basically, the analyses that are presented
in table two.
So, you're going to make something similar
to what you see here in table two.
I'll point out that, even if you run the
exact same models,
you think you're running the exact same
models as what the authors describe in
their paper you may get slightly, slightly
different estimates.
They used a different program than SAS and
there may be slightly different things
about how we're modeling degrees of
freedom so, I didn't get identical values
to what's in the table so don't expect to.
I'm also asking you to additionally, get
the values to build a model for
weight in kilograms.
Of course that's so that I can make sure
that you're actually building these models
correctly and not just copying the values
that are presented in the table here.
And so that's just basically the final
exam.
I'm leaving you through a series of
questions.
There's probably going to be a lot more
you do to look at these data than
than our just, then just the questions I'm
asking you on the final exam.
I'll point out that there is a, an age
cube.
There's a cubic term in the weight for
length z score model.
To get that it's very similar to dealing
with a quadratic instead of doing age
star age, you would do age star age star
age and that would give you in cubic term.
That just means that the weight growth
trajectories over
time are cubic rather than quadratic.
And as you might expect the growth
trajectories as you can see in the picture
from figure two, the growth trajectories
don't look perfectly linear or
quadratic over time there's actually a
cubic there.
So hopefully that's enough to get you
started and good luck with the exam.
I will be providing a solutions video at,
after you've
finished the exam that will again walk you
through the steps of a real data analysis.