In this next module we are going to do a
little practice on
repeated measures A.N.O.V.A. to make sure
that you understand the difference between
the group effect, the time effect and the
time by group interaction.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So what I'm going to have you do in this
module is I'm going to show you a couple
of pictures and I'm going to ask you to
pause the video in just a second here.
Which of these do you think, which of
these effects do you think?
Would be statistically significant
assuming that we kind of have
reasonable sample sizes in you know, sort
of a moderate sample size in each group,
we do expect the time effect to be
significant and
what I'm showing you here is that the
black line is group A, one group,
the red line is group B, and you can
assume that we have more than you know,
three people in each of these groups,
again a reasonable sample size.
Do you think that the time effect is going
to be significant for this data set?
Do you think the group effect is going to
be significant and
do you think the time by group effect is
going to be significant?
So I actually want you to pause the video
and figure out your answer on all of
those and then restart the video and then
I'll walk you through it.
So, hopefully on this one, you said that
the time effect would be significant.
So if you average over groups, over the
red and the blue groups, it does seem that
even averaging in the grou the b group,
which doesn't change that much over time,
that you would still have some downward
trend here.
So the time effect is going to be
significant here, you know,
assuming a reasonable sample size.
Is there any significant difference
between group?
Interestingly on this one, if you average
all four time points for
group A and all four time points for group
B, the.
They're going to be about the same.
So group A on average because it started
higher but
ended lower, is not going to be on average
different than group B.
So there will not be a significant group
effect here.
There will be a significant time by group
effect,
because clearly group B seems to stay flat
over time, whereas group A goes down.
So there will be a significant group by
time.
Effect.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Alright.
Again, I want you to do the same thing.
Black line is group A.
Red line is group B.
Same thing.
Pause the video and see which one of these
you think would
be statistically significant with a
reasonable sample size.
Alright, so with this one,
hopefully you realize that the time effect
is not going to be significant because it
doesn't look like either group is really
changing much over time.
However, the group effect is going to be
significant because
the red group is clearly, group B is
clearly higher than group A throughout.
And then finally the time by group effect
is going to
be nonsignificant because they're again
both, they're both flat over time.
So essentially the changes over time are
the same pattern in group A and group B.
So finally I want you to pause the video
one more time and.
See if you can figure out which of these
effects is going to be significant for
this graphic, for these data.
So, for this one hopefully you realize
that the time effect is
clearly significant because if you average
over the two groups they're
definitely going down on average.
The group effect here is not going to be
significant because, you know,
if you were averaging all the red time
points and
all the black time points, it looks like
they're going to be fairly similar.
And the time by group effect is also not
going to
be statistically significant here.
The black group does go down just.
Slightly more than the red group.
But unless we have a huge sample size
since they're both generally going
down over time, we'd have to have a really
big sample size for that time by group,
that little difference to come out to be
statistically significant.
So hopefully you were able to get all of
those without too much trouble.
[BLANK_AUDIO]