[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module, I'm going to show you
how the Cox regression model can
actually handle time changing predictors.
So up until now, all the statistical tests
and
models that we've dealt with, like linear
regression, logistic regression,
there was no way to allow an individual's
predictor to change over time.
Those models didn't account for
time, or take into time in any account
time in any way.
However, when we do studies where we
follow people over time,
we tend to make multiple measurements over
them.
And we allow, in at least in our data set,
we allow the covariate values,
the predictor values, for an individual to
change.
We might measure their blood pressure, or
their weight, their height, many times
over the study.
Up until now, we've kind of been throwing
that data out.
Or, you might be able to do something like
take their average weight through
the study, or their average blood
pressure.
But that's a big amount of lost
information.
There's all sorts of time dependent
predictors that you can imagine.
So you, if you're following subjects over
a time, looking at a certain
drug used the subjects may start and stop
a drug multiple times during the study.
The subjects may gain and lose large
amounts of weight.
So if you were to just put in one
measurement for
their weight, like their baseline weight
as the predictor in your regression model,
that's losing a lot of information.
Subjects may change their smoking habits.
They may start and stop smoking.
They may smoke less and smoke more.
So, there's so many ways in which
predictors could change over time and
we sort of, up until now, haven't really
had any good tools to deal with that.
The great thing about Cox regression is
that it can totally
handle time changing predictors.
And, that's wonderful because now this is
opening up a whole new tool kit for
us, where we can accommodate time changing
predictors into our model.
If you, you have to think about the
likelihood to,
to figure out exactly how this works.
But just think back for a minute to the
likelihood for logistic regressions.
There's a likelihood for logistic
regression, if you recall,
had one term in the likelihood for every
person.
You either had the disease, the outcome,
or
you didn't and the likelihood term looked
something like this.
And so let's say we were looking at
smoking as a predictor.
You've got to enter one value for smoking
per person in the study.
They, they get one term in the likelihood.
Their value, their x value for smoking,
gets entered in once in the study.
That is not allowed to change in any way.
Now you could capture smoking in multiple
variables.
You could have a variable for, they're a
smoker yes or
no, and then also a variable for the dose
of smoking or something like that.
But those variables are not allowed to
change.
You enter them once into the likelihood
and you're done.
Now, think about the likelihood for Cox
regression.
This is why the understanding, the
likelihood is so
important, because this allows you to
understand time changing covariates.
So the likelihood for Cox regression,
remember, has a term in the likelihood for
every event time.
So, maybe there's an event at time one,
and
there's an event at time three in the
study.
There's a subject who say was at risk at
time one and
their value, for let's say we are looking
at weight, so maybe their value for
weight at the first time point where there
was an event in the study was 200 pounds.
They are entered into the denominator
because they were at risk at
event time one.
But, that person, say they're still at
risk at event time three.
They get entered a second time,
they get entered into the denominator for
the term for event time three.
Well now we don't, we're not forced to
re-enter the same weight of 200.
Maybe their weight went down and maybe
they're, they're now 180 pounds.
We can now update their weight.
Every time an event occurs, there is a new
term added to the likelihood and
we get to re-enter all of, every, for
everybody who is at risk,
we get to re-enter all of their values for
the predictors, so we can change them.
In this way,
Cox regression can handle time-changing
predictors, which is really, really cool.
I'm going to go through a full example
with the likelihood you're going to have
had your fill of likelihoods by the end of
this unit, but
I'm going to go through a full example of
the likelihood in just a minute.
But I just wanted to let you know that
we've actually seen an example where time
dependent covariates were used and
actually make a lot of sense.
So I'm going back now to this example
about looking at
survival in Academy Award-winning actors
and actresses.
And this is the one, I am taking the table
for the one that was looking at actors and
actresses and comparing those who actually
won an Academy Award,
to those who were ever only nominated.
So if you recall, looking at the winners
compared with nominees only,
there did appear to be some survival
advantage for the winners.
Unadjusted it was a hazard ratio of 0.75,
indicating
a 25% relative reduction in the mortality
rate for winners versus nominees.
If you adjusted for
some other factors, it went down just
slightly to a hazard ratio of 0.78,
about a 22% reduction in the mortality
rate for winners versus nominees.
I've mentioned this study several times
and I alluded to the fact that
there is a problem with the way that the
authors originally did their analysis.
So, if you think about the Kaplan-Meier
curve for this data set, so
here are the say, here are the winners and
here are the nominees only.
It looks something like that, making that
up.
It actually probably doesn't diverge until
they hit about 50 but something like that.
Here's the problem with the original
analysis.
So notice we've got a curve that's winners
and we've got a curve that's nominees.
And what they're doing is they're saying
hey,
you were always a winner since birth,
right?
They're counting that the winners are
being counted as winners since the,
the day they were born.
This is, this analysis was done from time
of birth.
So you're being counted in the winner
group from the day you're born or
you're being counted,
you're being counted in the nominated only
group from the day that you're born.
Well obviously, if winning actually has
some effect on longevity,
it can't have that effect on longevity
until after you've actually won the award.
That winning can't retroactively somehow
increase your longevity.
So this analysis had, had this problem,
this bias in it,
which we talked about a little bit before.
A natural way to solve, to deal with that
problem, would be to say well, I, you know
in the Kaplan-Meier curve I kind of have
to group one group and another group and
it's hard to incorporate time changing
predictors into that graphic.
But the Cox regression model can
completely handle time
changing predictors.
So in fact, the authors of that original
paper did do an analysis where they used
a time-dependent covariate for winning
and, and only being nominated.
So you can read from their text, this was
buried a little bit in the text, but
it says analyses using time-dependent
covariates,
in which winners were counted as controls,
until the time of first victory.
So they were accounted as controls or only
nominated,
until the time of first victory, yielded a
relative reduction of 20%.
So this is a more correct analysis because
it,
what they're doing is they're saying okay,
up until the age at which you
actually won the award, you are counted as
in the control group.
Again, this works fine in the likelihood,
because imagine the first death happens,
you know, maybe around 50.
So event that happens at 50.
If a person who is at risk at 50 has not
yet won their Academy Award, then they're
going to get a zero for winner versus
nominee in that model at that event time.
And then, maybe at when another event
occurs at age 60, and
maybe they are still at risk, but by now
they won the award, say at 55 years old,
now we count them as a winner only in that
term in the likelihood and
not in any terms before they won.
So we are able to now make sure that we're
not counting somebody as,
as the the effect of winning, we're not
having it kind of act retroactively.
So this is a great way to analyze these
data.
It did yield a smaller effect size.
It yielded an effect size of a relative
reduction of 20%.
And they don't tell us in the paper is
that adjusted for any covariance or not.
I'm kind of guessing that it's probably
just a basic analysis.
An additional adjustment may attenuate
this even a little bit further.
Notice it's starting to boarder on being
nonsignificant here.
So one of the criticisms of that paper,
you know, later on, is people said,
well, that more proper analysis was buried
in the paper and the,
the authors chose to highlight kind of
the, the less good analysis.
And indeed, when a few years later, some
other authors did
a reanalysis of the original data, this is
a kind of a busy table, but
I'll just want to highlight one thing, in
their new analysis,
they didn't do time-dependent covariance,
they did something slightly different.
But notice that the hazard ratio that they
came out with their new analysis
accounting for this immortal time bias,
trying to avoid that bias.
They came out with a relative risk
reduction of about 18%, so it's very close
to what the original authors got with
their time-dependent covariant mode.
So they probably, those original authors
should have reported and
highlighted that time-dependent model from
the start.
All right, so now let me just kind of
delve in with a very simple data set how
this actually works in the likelihood.
And I'm going to use a simple data set, I
just made up these data, but
I'm basing it off some real data that I
was analyzing many years back, looking at
the effect of oral contraceptives on
stress fracture risk in women runners.
There is some thought that if you're
taking exogenous hormones, there have been
some studies that have linked that to a
reduced risk of stress fractures.
The exogenous hormones may suppress your
bone turnover and
therefore make you a little bit less at
risk of fracturing.
The problem is, if you wanted to, if
you're doing a cohort study, where you're
following women over time and you're
measuring time to fracture, which is the,
the outcome here, you could imagine doing
an analysis where you just put in
a single variable for oral contraceptive
risk that doesn't change over time.
Like they never used oral contraceptives
is a common way of looking at
oral contraceptives.
You ever took them or you didn't take
them.
Or, you could say whether or not they are
taking them at baseline.
Or you could, have some measure of the
cumulative amount of
total time a woman has taken them, you
know, in her life or something like that.
There's a lot of ways you can force that
variable,
that predictor oral contraceptive you sent
to something static, but
in fact, again with Cox regression we're
not forced to do that.
We could instead say, well, if a woman
stops or
starts taking oral contraceptives, we can
accommodate that in our model.
So again, there's a lot of different ways
you can look at oral contraceptive use.
This comes up with a lot of different
exposures.
How am I actually going to measure that
and report that in my model?
So the non time-dependent ways of looking
at this,
which is sort of what we were stuck with,
for logistic regression and so on,
was things like did a women ever use them
was she using them yes or no at baseline.
Some kind of simple binary variables or
something like the total months of
use during the study or the total months
of use in the lifetime.
Those are all a single static variable
that could be entered into say,
a logistic regression model.
However, we're no longer stuck just
forcing our oral contraceptive use
measurement, exposure measurement into one
of those.
We could, with Cox regression, now look at
time-dependent predictors.
So we could have a model that incorporates
oral contraceptive use as a,
you are either on it or
off it at a given time and that's allowed
to change during the course of the study.
That's the one I'm actually going to look
at because it's a little bit simpler.
We could even do something even a little
more fancy, like say,
how many months has someone used the oral
contraceptives up until each event time or
something like that.
We'll stick with the binary one.
Allow, a woman here is allowed to on them
or off them and switch on and off.
And again, these are just some made up
data, but, you know,
based on some real data I was looking at.
And I had just done this for seven
subjects to keep it really simple, so
we can write out the whole likelihood.
So we have an ID number identifying the
subject,
a time that each woman was in the study,
time to event or sensory, whether or
not she fractured, 1 is fractured, 0 is
censored, and then the time at
which she start and, started and stopped
oral contraceptives within the study.
So if it's time 0 for starting OC's, that
means that she was on them at baseline, or
she started them at baseline, and this
woman, for example, the first woman here,
was on oral contraceptives at baseline,
started them at baseline, and
stopped them 12 months into the study.
There are one, two, three, four events,
four fractures that occurred in the study.
So there's going to be four terms in our
likelihood and
the rest of the women were censored.
I went ahead and drew out already a little
picture representing these data just so
we don't have to, spend time, you don't
have to spend time sitting and
watching me draw.
So but let me just show you what this
little picture shows.
So again our, in our time here is time in
the study from zero up to
the study went as long as two years.
The first woman for example, was in the
study for 12 months before she
fractured and I'm representing a fracture
with an x and a c represents censored.
So I have her in the study from 0 to 12
months and she fractures at 12 months and
then she's no longer at risk for first
fracture.
I represented the time at which a woman is
on OCs, the time period where
she's actually taking the pill, the oral
contraceptives, with a little blue line.
So I, for example, this first woman was on
oral contraceptives from month 0 to
month 12 in the study.
So her whole line is covered with a blue
line here,
indicating she was on the drug at all the
times of the study.
The second woman was only taking oral
contraceptives from month 10 to month 11.
So that's represented here as a teeny blue
line on her graph and so on.
And subjects three and six never took oral
contraceptives during this
study represented as that there was no
starting and stop time for them.
So that's just to,
a pictorial representation of the data,
which is a little bit easier to deal with.
So now I'm going to show you a couple of
time-independent predictors,
what the likelihood would look like if we
were doing time-independent predictors.
So let's start with a very simple one.
You were on oral contraceptives at
baseline, yes or no.
A lot of times we end up using the
baseline exposure.
And so, let's say we chose to use the
A woman was taking oral contraceptives at
start of the study or not.
That's our predictor in our model.
So our Cox regression model, would be the
log hazard is equal to,
we would have just a beta for yes, no
baseline use.
And a woman would just get a yes or no, a
one or a zero in there.
So, what would this actually look like in
terms of the likelihood, okay?
So the likelihood is a function of this
beta of yes, no use.
It starts with the first event.
So the first event, if you look over here
on my little graphic,
at six months into the study, subject
number 6 fractures, okay?
So, we look at subject to six months into
the study, everybody is still at risk, so
everybody's going to be in the denominator
here.
And our predictor here is baseline use of
oral contraceptive.
So, subject one was on OC's at baseline.
She's going to have a value of one for
that variable, subject four was also on
OC's baseline and subject five was.
So, those three will have ones, for
the variable baseline oc use, and
everybody else will have zero.
So then we can just write out the
likelihood.
So, the person who fractured was not a
baseline user of oral contraceptives.
So this is event time, the event that
occurred at six months.
And she was, the one who fractured was not
a user at baseline and
then we had I'm just going to this is a
yes, no variable.
So I'm just going to count up the number
of risk, women at risk with ones for
this variable and the number of risk,
women at risk with zeroes.
So at six months into the study, subject
one was at risk, subject four was at risk,
and subject five was at risk.
So there were three women who had a value
of one for
this variable of OC use at baseline.
There were four women,
everybody else, who had a value of zero,
including the one who fractured.
So that would be the first terminal
likelihood.
The second term in the likelihood occurs
at 12 months into the study.
There is another fracture.
A second woman fractures 12 months into
the study.
At that time point, so she is going to be
the numerator, she was,
the one who fractured, was a baseline user
of oral contraceptives.
So she gets a one value for this variable.
And everybody else is at risk, except
there was one woman who was
censored at 11 months and there was one
woman who had the fracture at six months.
Those two are no longer at risk.
So there are five women at risk.
Of the ones at risk, there's one, two,
three for baseline OC users.
And their are two who were not.
Subjects three and seven were not.
So we have three baseline OC users at risk
and two not at risk.
And then we can keep going.
You get the idea.
We can keep going and do this for
the fracture that happened at month 17,
and then for the final fracture.
I'm going to just leave that on the next
slide.
If you want to see the whole thing written
out, it's going to look like that.
So, again, these two terms I just did out,
if you wanted to keep going, make sure,
test yourself, make sure you can get these
two terms as well.
That's what the likelihood looks like.
The key, though, is that you're going to
see that this likelihood looks
different than when we treat oral
contraceptive use in different ways.
I'm going to just do one quickly, one more
time-independent predictor, because just
to show you there's even lots of choices
of how you could model this exposure.
What if we instead chose ever/never used
during the study rather than baseline use?
So we looked at women across the study and
said if you ever used it, you get a value
for this variable of one.
So who's going to get a value of one for
this variable?
So, subject one, subject two, subject
four, subject five and subject seven, all
five of them used the oral contraceptives
at least sometime during this study.
Only Subjects three and six never used it.
So, the likelihood then, is going to be,
for
this variable, again, six months into the
study, everybody's at risk.
The one who has the fracture was a never
user of oral contraceptives.
There are actually five women, one, two,
three, four, five, who ever
used oral contraceptives, who are still at
risk at six months into the study.
And there were two who never used it.
And we could keep going.
We could do the likelihood for 12 months
and 17 months and so on.
There's going to be four terms in the
likelihood.
Again, I'll leave that to you to finish
that one up.
But I've written it out here.
You can again test yourself to make sure
you're getting the right likelihood.
That's another time-independent predictor,
because we're not allowing women to change
over time.
Now let's move to what's really important
here, is the time-dependent predictors.
So, the time-dependent predictor that I'm
going to use here,
there's more than one we can come up with,
but the simplest one is just to say,
is a woman on oral contraceptives at a
given event time.
She is either on them at that time when an
event occurs or she's not.
So lets look at how that's going to be
reflected in the likelihood.
So, again, first event happens at six
months into the study.
Subject six has a fracture six months into
the study.
Everybody else is still at risk at that
event time.
What's, what are we going to represent in
the likelihood, okay?
So first of all, we are now counting a
woman as being on OC's.
If she's on OC's at that time, so anybody
who has a blue over her at, over her
line at six months, those are the ones who
are on oral contraceptives at six months.
So at six months, subject one is on oral
contraceptives, subject four is,
subject five is, subject six is not, and
subject seven is.
So the, this is again a binary predictor,
but
we're allowing it to change now in
different event times.
The one who had the fracture here was not
on oral contraceptives at that time.
There were one, two, three, four, who were
on oral contraceptives at six months
into the study, so they each get a value
of 1 in their terms, in the likelihood.
There were three, who at six months were
not on oral contraceptives.
All right, so that's the first term in the
likelihood.
The second term in the likelihood happens
at 12 months into the study.
At 12 months into the study, there are
still five women at risk.
Subjects one, three, four, five and seven
are still at risk.
Subject two has dropped out and subject
six already had a fracture.
At that time, the one who fractures,
subject number one,
is at that time taking oral
contraceptives.
She is on or, oral contraceptives at 12
months.
However, subject three is not on oral
contraceptives at that time.
Subject four is on oral contraceptives at
that time and
subject five is not on oral contraceptives
at that time.
So we have one, two women who are taking
oral contraceptives at that time.
Now notice, subject seven is the one to
focus on here.
Subject seven, in the first term in the
likelihood, she got a value of one for
this variable, because she was on oral
contraceptives at that time.
Now she's switching over.
In the second term in the likelihood
subject seven is getting a value of zero.
So she is, has switched.
If we were to write out an individual
hazard term for
her, for the first term in the likelihood,
in the second, you'll notice that her
value went from one to zero.
She was allowed to switch.
All right, now how about the third term in
the likelihood?
So the third event happens at 17 months
into the study,and at that time,
the one who fractures is subject seven.
At that time, she is not on oral
contraceptives.
So in the first term in the likelihood she
had a one,
every other term she's had a zero.
Then at that time, there were four woman
at risk.
Three were not on oral contraceptives at
that time and one was.
And then the final event happens at 20
months into this study.
At that time there's only two women left
at risk.
One of them, subject four, is on oral
contraceptives and one is not.
So the one who fractures is not taking
oral contraceptives at that time, and
there's one who is taking them and one who
is not taking them at that time.
So again, the likelihood function now
looks different because of
the fact that we're allowing women to
change their value.
Women have different values in different
terms in the likelihood.
So that's what the likelihood is going to
look like for
this time-dependent predictor.
And so you'll notice that the likelihoods
look different for
the time-dependent predictor versus the
ever, never use versus the baseline use
and so that means the beta coefficients
are going to come out slightly different,
depending on which of these models you
choose.
What's it actually going to mean if we put
a time-dependent predictor in the model?
And let's say we put a time-dependent
predictor in the model and
we have a bigger data set and oral
contraceptive use does indeed come out to
be a significantly protective factor
against stress fractures.
What that's going to mean is that, at the
moment, the way we've modeled it here,
is that at the moment that you're taking
oral contraceptives,
you get some protection from them.
And the interpretations of those betas are
going to be different.
So one says, if you're taking a, you know,
an oral contraceptive ever,
that that's somehow going to protect you
against fractures, having ever taken it.
That seems like a less, you know, that's
going to be a less good measure here.
The time-dependent OC use tells us that,
if you're on oral contraceptives, that,
when you're on them you are, have some
protection against stress fractures, if
this were to come out as a statistically
significant protective effect.
So the interpretation of the betas changes
as well.