So now I'm just going to walk you through
a quick review of linear regression.
So what we're dealing with linear
regression,
the picture is that we've got a continuous
outcome variable, call it y.
And then we've got predictors that could
be continuous, or could be binary, or
categorical variables chopped into binary
variables, dummy coded.
But for now, let's imagine that we've got
an x variable,
a predictor that's continuous.
If you got two continuous variables you
can draw some kind of scatter plot.
And the idea of linear regression is that
we're just going to fit the best fit line
to those points that you see there.
Something like that.
Linear regression is the easiest because
unlike all the other types of
regression we've dealt with.
Where you had to do some kind of
transformation of the outcome Y,
we don't have to do any transformation
here.
We're just modeling Y as itself, so that
makes life a lot easier.
We're fitting a line, so
that means that we're going to have,
there's two things that define this line.
We're going to have an intercept which we
usually call alpha.
That's just the point at which x is equal
to 0.
Where are we on the y axis?
So that's the intercept, that's the value
of y when x is equal to 0.
And then, of course, the other thing that
defines a line is the slope.
Which is just, how much does y change as x
goes up one unit?
So, then y is defined by an intercept in
the slope.
In linear regression we usually call the
slope a beta and the beta
coefficient tells us about whether or not
x is significantly related to y.
So, the null hypothesis for linear
regression is that beta is equal to 0.
If the slope is equal to 0.
That means we would have a horizontal line
and
there was no relationship between the
predictor x and the outcome y.
If we reject the null hypothesis and say
that beta is different than zero,
that would tell us that there is some
relationship between x and y.
Notice that we are assuming a straight
line, we're fitting a straight line here.
So if we had some kind of relationship
ship between x and
y that wasn't a straight line, something
like a quadratic,
well clearly if we try to fit a straight
line here we might end up with.
Beta equals 0, but
haven't fit the right relationship, this
is not, x is not linearly related to Y, so
of course we're always going to want to
plot things and evaluate that.
Because, perhaps we need to put an x
squared in the model, or
somehow model the predictor or the outcome
differently.
But that's just the basics of linear
regression, of course it get's more
complicated if you put more things in to
the model, so our basic model.
Is just to say that the, the average value
of y,
the expected value of y, is equal to some
alpha plus beta x.
But we could add another, you know, that
could,
we could have a beta 1, and then we could
put in another variable x2.
This gets hard to draw because what we're
doing is we have two predictors in
the model.
We're fitting a plane rather than a line,
so we have to kind of come out from the,
out from the screen here and to into the
three dimensions.
So imagine here's x 2 here's x 1.
We can then fit a plane into the scatter
plot,
it gets a little hard to draw and if we
add another beta to the model,
we're now instead of on a plane we're on
some kind of three dimensional cube.
And you know, it gets hard to draw after
that.
But basically it's the same idea.
If these betas are equal to 0, that would
say there's no
relationship between the predictor and the
outcome, at least no linear relationship.
And if they're significantly different
than zero, that would say that these
predictors have a significant relationship
with the outcome, adjusted for
everything else in the model.
We've dealt with regression before, so
in a way linear regression is sort of the
easiest of all of the regression again.
Since Y is not transformed in any way.
So now I made up some data just to
illustrate linear regression here.
I'm using that same, those same test
scores, exact same test scores as before.
But I've made up a new predictor variable.
So imagine we didn't have some group, some
intervention here, but
imagine we were looking at parental
education.
And I've just defined that as the average
total number of years of school,
averaged between the mother and the
father.
Again, these are just made-up data.
All right, I've got a couple of scores on
the test.
And now, we've just got 24 kids.
These are independent kids, so they're not
siblings.
Yeah, and they have some average parental
education and
then they take the test, they get some
score on it.
We're going to see if those are
correlated.
The outcome variable here is the same
scores as before, so it's still looks and
nice and normally distributed, nothing has
changed on the scores.
So that says it's okay to use linear
regression, we're going to want to of
course plot our data so we've got our
continuous predictor, average parental
education, our test score is our outcome
variable here, and I do a scatter plot.
I actually like to fit a smooth line to
those points just to see if there is
any curvature to see whether or not this
is really well modeled as a straight line.
When I do that here it looks pretty good.
I mean, it's never going to be a perfect
straight line, but
as real data goes that looks pretty nice
and, and straight.
We, of course, have also assumed that the
average scatter around the line,
that the homogeneity of variances of the
is about equal.
I mean.
It looks like, there's maybe, just a
little bit more variability at
the higher ends of parental education than
at the lower ends but
it generally looks pretty balanced, pretty
constant.
So, the homogeneity of variances looks
okay here as well.
So now, we have independent kids that I
would say that it is okay to fit a.
Linear regression line.
So I went ahead and actually fit a linear
regression line, so
when we do the linear regression line,
we're forcing a straight line.
Keep that in mind.
Again, we're going to end up with a
y-intercept, which here, I'm sorry,
this is really small.
I can't really see that.
The units on the y-axis here.
But the intercept comes out to be about 6.
So when parental education is 0, if you
project this line out,
it would say that the average score would
be predicted to be 6.
And then you can see clearly that there's
a, you know,
a positive, pretty big positive slope
here.
The slope, as I'll show you in the next
slide, comes out to be about 1.3.
So every one year extra of parental
education.
Corresponds to about a 1.3%, 1.3 unit
increase in this test score.
And it is statistically significant.
So let me just show you.
I went ahead and ran the regression in the
computer to actually get out
the parameter estimates, the alpha and the
beta.
So the intercept here is about 6.2.
The beta, the slope here, is 1.349.
And that does turn out to be statistically
significant.
So that really does, and I made up these
data, so
of course I made there be a significant
relationship.
So there really does appear to be a
significant increase in the score,
the test scores, as parental education
goes up.
I'll just point out one other thing in the
output here.
There's something called the root mean
squared error.
Which is just a fancy name, for, the
standard error.
This is the average variability, around
the line.
The average residuals essentially.
And this, this root mean squared error is
what we.
Minimize when this line is fit, so when
the computer runs the algorithm to,
to actually get out the alpha and the
beta,
what it's doing is finding the line that
minimizes this root mean squared error.
So, this line here gives us the smallest
possible root mean squared error.
This root mean squared error just reflects
the average variability around the line.
The standard error of Y given X is another
way to write that.
So this is saying that, if we're on our.
Here's our Y, there's some scatter around
the line.
So this, this scatter around the line,
that's standard error at any given value
for X.
That variability, that's the root mean
squared error.
And that factors into calculating the
standard errors for alpha and
beta, which then determines whether or not
we reach statistical significance.
So I want to just focus for a minute.
When, usually when we're doing real linear
regression.
Problems in medicine.
We, of course, we care about the alpha and
the beta.
We, we're, that's usually what gets
reported in the paper.
And we kind of ignore the fact that
there's something else in the model.
But we're going to, I want to focus on it
for a minute.
Because it's going to be important when we
talk about how to account for
correlations in the data, such as repeated
measures.
So our linear regression line basically
says that the expected value of y.
Is alpha plus beta x is just very simple
single line.
This is the expected value so this is the
actual line value, the average value or
the expected value for any given value of
x.
But in, of course any given individual Yi,
everybody will have points that are not
exactly on the line.
Some people might rie, lie right on the
line.
But most people are going to lie somewhere
around the line, but
not right on the line.
The distance between a person's actual
value and
the line is called their residual.
That's the observed minus the expected
value.
We also call that the error.
So every person, their value is the, the
predicted value on the line plus, or
minus some error.
Some distance from the line.
We these error terms are what we're this
is related to the root mean square error,
this is what we're minimizing, we're
minimizing the square error terms.
When we fit this line, we find the line
that minimizes the square errors.
The square distances from the line that's
the best fit line.
That represents the unexplained
variability in y, once I've accounted for
x how much variability is there still left
over in y?
Couple of things to keep in mind about
these errors.
So what are the assumptions that we are
making about the errors?
So the actual assumptions of linear
regression.
They actually revolve around the error.
So the error terms are assumed to be
normally distributed.
They are also assumed to have equal
variance, so at any given value of x,
those, that, those errors around the line
are assumed to be equal.
That's that homogeneity of variances
assumption.
And they're also assumed to be
independent.
So one observation doesn't have any
correlation.
Their error doesn't have any particular
correlation with another person's,
another observation's error.
Those are the basic assumptions of linear
regression.
Somewhat easier to illustrate those with a
picture.
So now I've got some x variable, some y
variable.
And what I'm assuming is that we can fit.
A line.
And the line tells us the expected value
for y, for every given value of x.
But, of course, not everybody's going to
lie right on the line.
There's going to be some variability
around the line.
We're assuming, scatter around the line
falls in normal distribution.
That all the observations.
They're normally distributed around the
line.
And that, that, that standard error for
that normal distribution is the same at
every different value of x and that's also
called the root mean squared error.
This is what I've written here.
That's what we minimize when we fit a
linear regression line.
So we're assuming that's homogenous.
We are also assuming that if I pick you
know, this particular person here, and
this particular person here, that their
errors are in no way correlated.
Now that's the part that's going to be
violated.
When we have repeated measures data.
So imagine for a minute that my predictor
now is time.
And these dots represent the same people
at different times.
And imagine I'm, I'm going to give some
examples with my outcome is bone destiny.
Basically reflecting your bone strength.
In the units and modules this week.
So imagine my outcome variable is some
kind of bone strength,
which is bone density.
Imagine that I have a person here whose
bone density was measured at baseline and
then this is the corresponding to one year
in the study and
this is corresponding to two years in the
study.
I'm just making up the units of time.
But imagine that this person.
Is measured at baseline.
And then they're measured again a year
later.
And then they're measured again two years
And because they started low,
they had lower than average bone density,
they remained low.
So their residuals are always low.
Of course, that person may change over
time.
They may go up a little or down a little.
But, the, the fact that they started low
means that the residual for
this guy and this one and this one are all
correlated, they're related to
one another because it's the same person,
that residual is low to begin with,
it's going to be low at every subsequent
time point most likely.
So there's some correlation there and
that violates this assumption of the
errors being independent.
That's what we're going to need to deal
with when we
talk about having repeated measures data.
So a lot of our discussion on dealing with
repeated measures data will focus on what
to do with those error terms.
[BLANK_AUDIO]