Up until now we have been implicitly
assuming that change over time was linear.
Of course, there's no reason it has to be
linear.
You can imagine that there may be cases
where you have non linear time effects and
I'm going to show you an example of that
in this module.
So just to have some data here, I made up
some data.
This is similar to data that you're
analyzing in your homework.
So imagine that 50 patients are randomized
to an exercise intervention, these are all
elderly patients, and 50 patients are
randomized to a control group.
The outcome here is the mini mental state
exam score, this is a continuous variable
and it measures cognitive function and
higher scores are better.
The blue group is the exercise group, the
red group is the control group.
And what you can see that is,
that it indeed looks like the exercise
group did better over time.
They had less of a declining cognitive
function over time.
But what's also interesting in this
graphic is that you'll notice that
the trajectory over time doesn't look like
a straight line.
It looks more curved, more like a
quadratic.
And you can see that even better if you
graph using a scatter plot like
I've shown you how to do.
You can definitely see that there appears
to be a quadratic element to the rate of
change in depression scores over time.
So that means we're probably going to have
to include a time squared term in
our regression models.
So I went ahead and ran a series of models
here, so
all of the models contain a cognitive
square as the outcome, a main effect for
time, a main effect for group, the
interaction of time by group, but
I also included this quadratic effect for
time.
And then I ran three different models.
I ran a model with only a random
intercept.
We've seen in some cases that's
sufficient.
I ran a model with a random intercept and
a random time slope and
I ran a model with a random effect for the
intercept for the linear time as well as
for the quadratic time because that also
may vary between different subjects.
I'll just show you the results of those
three models.
Here's the random intercept model only.
Pay attention to the AIC.
It turns out to be 1639 here.
If we look at the results we see that the
intercept here represents at baseline
the average for the control group, the
average cognitive score was about 23.
The main effect for time is 0.58 and that
is highly statistically significant.
This would say that well, you have to be
careful here because we also have a,
a time squared so, so I'll look at both of
these.
There's also a highly significant time
squared term here.
Both of these belong to the control group.
But what this is saying is that there,
appears to be sort of an initial
positive increase but then as you saw,
that this, that this is kind of fits that
quadratic term, where we're going up a
little and then down quite a bit.
So, that corresponds to the control
group's trajectory over time.
It is highly significant saying that the
cognitive score is really changing over
time in both a linear and quadratic
fashion.
The mean effect for group is not
significant.
Well, this is supposed to be a randomized
trial, so
we would hope that at base line, they
didn't differ in cognitive score.
And, but the interaction between time and
the treatment group, that is highly
significant, and it's positive, indicating
that the treated group, the exercise group
had higher cognitive scores over time, as
we saw in the picture.
Now when I fit a model with a random
intercept and a random effect for time,
actually the AIC went up quite a bit, so
this was not as good of a model, and
what you'll notice also is that a lot of
things that came out significant in
the previous model don't come out
significant here.
So, a year is no longer significant the
year by treated effect is
no longer significant, so made a pretty
big difference.
We definitely didn't do as well for
whatever reason.
The quadratic effect's still significant
because that definitely is a nice curve.
I then went ahead and fit it with a random
intercept, a random effect for
time, and a random effect for the time
squared, because that's another within
subject element that we can put as a
random effect.
You'll notice that the AIC is actually the
best from this model.
So this is the model that I'm going to end
up reporting.
And in this model it looks very similar to
the results that I got when I
had the random intercept only.
I'm getting a significant effect for time,
a significant effect for
time by group, and a significant effect
for the quadratic shape of time.
So that seems to be the best model here.
Now the other thing that we need to
consider in adding is that, we also want
to consider whether we want to put a year
squared terms times treatment group.
What that would indicate if we put it in
the model is
that there was a difference in the
quadratic shape between the two groups.
And actually the picture doesn't seem to
indicate that.
If you look at the picture carefully,
the blue group definitely looks higher
than the red group over time.
They're, so the linear affect over time
for, looks different but the, the shape of
the quadratic, the shape of the curve kind
of looks similar over time and indeed when
I went ahead and set a model adding this
year squared times group effect it
didn't come out to be statistically
significant and the AIC went up.
So we probably wouldn't end up including
that in the model.
But this is just to show you that
sometimes we don't want to necessarily
that rates of change are linear over time
because sometimes they're not.