So finally I thought it would be useful to
actually look at some real data,
rather than some made up data.
So going back to the data set I have on
runners, the larger data set.
I measured bone mineral density on those
runners at three time points.
And we also measured their weight.
And so for example, if you wanted to know
whether or
not increases in weight, correlated with
increases in bone mineral density.
You might run a generalized estimating
equation.
And my outcome here would be bone marrow
density, measured at three time points.
So you can kind of think of it again as a
vector of bone marrow
density measurements.
And, so I'm writing a GEE model.
And I'll have time in the model.
And I'll also have this vector of weights.
If I enter weight in as a time changing
predictor,
I've got the centralist vector of weights.
And I've got a single beta for weight.
When I went ahead and ran that model with
these data, I'll show you what I get.
So you'll see that my weight was in
pounds.
I get a highly significant coefficient for
weight.
So weight across time does seem to be
correlated to bone mineral density.
I also get a significant effect for time,
saying that as we know in these women the
bone density was going up over time.
But how do I interpret this beta
coefficient for weight here?
It's highly significant.
But it could be that I'm getting a
significant coefficient here,
because people who are heavier have
stronger skeletons.
Or, it could be that women who increase
their weight also increase their bone
mineral density.
Or it could be some combination of both of
those.
How am I going to tease that out?
So, one way to do it is just graphically.
And so, what I did here is I went ahead,
and
I graphed the cross sectional relationship
at base line.
Between weight and spine bone density.
To look for between subjects effects.
And we have, clearly, very strong between
subjects effects here at baseline.
The higher your weight was at baseline,
the higher your spine bone density tended
to be.
So strong between-subjects effects for
sure.
To look for within-subjects effects,
I then calculated the change in spine bone
density from time period one to two.
And from time period two to three.
And I graphed that against the change in
weight for those same time periods.
So every woman will have two dots on here
representing her two
different time periods.
And you can see that there are some
within-subjects effect here, but
they're much, much weaker.
There's a lot of women who didn't change
much in their weight.
So we get this kind of, line of women
around zero.
If you superimpose a regression line here,
it certainly does look positive.
But be careful because your eye is sort of
being drawn by a few people who happen to
have very large weight gains.
And also happen to gain spine bone
density.
So if you deleted these two subjects over
here, it wouldn't be a very strong effect.
So, probably we have, very strong between
subjects effects here,
that are driving that significant beta co
efficient for weight.
We probably have some weak within subjects
effects that are also contributing, but
that are much weaker.