In this next module,
I'm going to talk about the two ways that
we typically store repeated measures data.
So there's two ways to represent, repeated
measures data.
You can put it in what is called the broad
form, and
often when we're doing data entry, it's
easier to enter it in the broad form.
So the broad form is going to be just what
it sounds like,
it's going to be broad so every person is
going to
have only one row in the data set as we
normally do one observation, one row.
And the multiple measures that you've made
over time are going to
be stored as separate variables.
So here I've got, say these are some
scores on a depression questionnaire.
I've got other person who had a value on
that questionnaire at time 1 of 31.
At time 2 it went down to 29, and then 15
and then 26.
Person 2 had a depression score at time
point 1,
F24 that went to 28 at time point 2 and
then 20 and then 32 and so on.
This is the broad form of the data,
because it's broad every person will have
a lot of observations along the row.
That's one way to store the data.
However, sometimes we need the data in
what's called the long form.
So again, the long form's just what it
sounds like.
It's long, so
there are going to be multiple rows now
per observation, per person.
So you can see, for
example, subject number one had four
measurements of this depression score.
What we're now going to do, is we're
going to have only two variables.
That stores those depression scores,
one to indicate the time and one to
indicate the actual score at that time.
So for example, person number 1, ID number
1 at time point 1,
their depression score is 31 and at time
point two it was 29,
at time point 3 it was 15, at time point
four it was 26.
Person number 2 had a depression score of
24 at time point one,
28 at time point two, and so on.
Now, converting between these two forms,
can involve a little bit of trickery
having to do this in a computer.
Sometimes it's hard to go from one form to
the other.
I'll try to give you some tricks in the
computer for doing that.
But you can see why there might be
advantages of one form or the other.
So one place that we might use the broad
form, is if I wanted to
get the correlations in depression scores
between different time points.
And we need the broad form of the data.
Because my correlation matrix would be
time one.
Time two, time three, and time four and
I would want to get the correlations
between all of those time points.
So we, I need them in the broad form.
However, if I wanted to plot,
the depression scores over time to do a
plot over time of these depression scores.
I'm going to need the data in the long
form because I want to have one
x variable and one y variable to plot that
over time.
So for plotting over time, I'm going to
need it in the long form.
So different analyses will require the
data in different forms.
Now I went ahead just to show you, I
plotted these six individuals.
I did some what we call profile plots.
So this is just one individual at a time.
Every rep, line represents one individual.
I've plotted over time the scores, but
you can see that in order to make that
plot I needed the long form of the data.
This is showing you all six individuals.
We can also just plot the mean, at each
time point for the six individuals.
And then I have superimposed those two
plots.
In the next module I'm going to be showing
you a lot of different plots,
we can do for these type of, of data.
Those are usually done on the long form of
the data.
Just to put a real data example now to
this,
I have some data longitudinal data on bone
density in women runners who tend,
who can be at risk for having low bone
density.
This was a two year study.
And bone density was measured at baseline
one year into the study and
two years into the study.
You measure bone density with a machine
called a DEXA machine.
And I've modified the data just slightly
to meet all the HIPAA rules.
I've jiggered some dates and changed
values a little bit and rounded things.
But just to show you some real data or
something that's very close to real data,
this is the broad form of the data.
So the women, so for example, subject
number id number one,
she came in April of 1999, that's a pretty
old data set.
For her first measurement, and then again
in April of 2000 for
her next measurement, and then in May of
2001 for her next measurement.
Her spine bone densities were 0.93, 0.93,
and
0.93 beyond, so she didn't change at all
over time.
And her bone mineral content total calcium
in her skeleton.
Went down slightly at measurement two, but
didn't, was pretty stable.
You can see there wasn't much change for
that person there.
That's the broad form of the data.
If I want to translate this into the long
form of the data,
there might be two ways I can represent
time now.
So I can represent time as just time 0.1,
time 0.2, and time 0.3.
However, if you look closely, you'll
notice that there was some variation in.
Women were supposed to come back every
year, but
there was some considerable variation in
when women actually came back for
their subsequent, their follow-up
measurements.
So I could also, since I've got actual
dates,
I could take these dates, and I could
subtract them, and
I could get the actual amount of time
between measurements.
For a given woman, so I've done both of
those.
So I've now turned this into the long form
of the data.
So every woman had three measurements so
she's going to get three rows in the long
form of the data set.
I can represent time as just this one,
two, three, which measurement was it.
Or I can represent it more precisely.
So for example person number one, baseline
would be zero years into the study.
She came back nice and close to one year
into the study and, and
2.1 years into the study.
Not everybody did so well in being so
precise.
So like subject number seven came back at
one year, but
then not until 2.7 years into the study.
Then the spine bone densities for each of
those time period,
points is represented next as well as the
bone mineral content.
So we have one variable now storing the
spine bone density, and
one variable storing the bone mineral
content,
which again will allow us to do plots in
certain types of analyses.
Just to give you a quick overview of where
you'd want to use one versus the other.
So for you, if you want to calculate
correlations between different time
points you actually need the broad form of
the data.
If you took HRP 261 there were a couple of
situations where I gave you both forms
of the data set because you needed the
broad form for doing correlations.
Between time points.
With actually correlations between time
points then, but
between physician practices, if I'm
remembering that correctly.
You'll also need the broad form if you
want to calculate the change
between time points for a given woman.
It's actually easier to subtract within a
row than to,
to subtract across different rows.
So, it's usually easier to calculate the
change scores from the broad form.
When we do repeated measures in Nova next
week we'll be using the broad form
of the data.
However, you're going to need the long
form for
kind of all the really cool things you
want to do with the data.
So if we want to make plots you need the
long form of the data and
when we get to mixed models and GE models,
you'll be using the long form of the data.