[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to talk
about what to do,
when you have competing risks.
So, first of all, what is a competing
risk?
A competing risk is an event that either
precludes the event of interest, or
alters its probability.
So, up until now,
we've been talking about, you either have
the event of interest, or you're censored.
And there's the no, nothing else in that.
And we've actually been assuming
implicitly,
that the censoring was independent of the
event of interest.
Didn't influence your chance of having the
But what if there's something else that
can happen in your data set?
You can have something happen that
actually changes your probability of
having the event of interest, or prevents
it all together.
So, as a couple of examples, imagine that
what you
care about in a particular data set is
death from melanoma, a specific cancer.
But, some of the people in your data set,
this you know,
this people tend to be older.
So some of these patients actually die
from other causes.
Well if you die from something else, then
clearly, you are no longer at
risk of dying from melanoma, so that would
be a competing risk.
Or as another example, imagine that what
you cared about,
your event of interest was death while on
dialysis, in a kidney patients.
But some kidney patients,
who are having kidney failure, will go
onto get a kidney transplant.
And once you get a kidney transplant,
you're removed from dialysis.
So you can no longer die while on
dialysis.
So that also, the kidney transplant in
that case, would also be a competing risk.
What do you do in that situation, when you
have such a competing risk?
So, if competing risks are present, we
now, instead of having sort of
two possibilities, event or censored, we
have a third possibility.
So, we could have the event of interest.
You could be censored.
And again, up until now, we've only been
considering those two possibilities.
But now there's a third thing that could
happen.
You could have a competing risk,
which changes your probability of having
the event of interest.
And this is a little tricky.
You have to think about it carefully, but,
competing risk is distinct from censoring.
So if you think carefully,
if you ask the question, who failed from
the event of interest?
What do we know?
So, if somebody has had the event of
interest, so somebody, say, died from
melanoma, we can say for sure that yes,
they have had the event of interest.
We observed that for them.
If somebody was censored, all we know is
that up until the last time we saw them,
they had not have, had yet the event of
interest.
But, there's still, we've left of it,
open the possibility that sometime after
the study ended or, after we
lost them to follow up, they could have
gone on to have the event of interest.
So, the answer to this question for people
who are censored, is maybe.
Maybe they went on to fail from the event
of interest later.
That possibility is still open.
However, imagine you've got a competing
risk that precludes the event of interest,
like dying from other causes.
If they died from other causes, then
clearly we know for
sure that they certainly did not die from
melanoma.
So, censoring and the competing risk have
a different answer to this question.
The censoring, they could have gone on to
have the event, but
the competing risk, they could not have.
One of the ways that people typically
we'll handle competing risks,
is just to treat them as censored values.
To lump them together with the censored
individuals.
The problem with this, is it can run into
some trouble.
Especially when calculating probabilities.
Because what you're essentially doing,
is you're treating these nos, you're
treating them as maybes.
You're glossing over that distinction.
If you treat the nos as maybes, you're
factoring into your estimate of
probability, that it's possible that some
of the people who got censored,
could have gone on to have the risk.
You're factoring that in, in some way in
your probabilities.
Because you're treating some of the nos,
who couldn't have gone on to have that
event of interest, as maybes, you're
actually going to end up overestimating
your risk of having the event of interest,
or equivalently underestimating your
survival probabilities.
And it's easiest just to illustrate this
with a few examples.
So, think about this melanoma data set
that you dealt with for
the first couple of homeworks.
That had actually two competing risks in
it.
You could die of other causes, or you
could die of melanoma.
And, for the purposes of the homework, to
make sure we got everything correct and
it was simple, I had you lump those two
causes of death together, and
just look at the overall probability of
survival.
And that's what's represented here on the
left-hand side.
This is just the Kaplan-Meier curve, for
the overall cohort, for overall survival.
So, about something like maybe 55% of the
cohort,
had the probability of survival somewhere
around 55% for the entire cohort.
This is a perfectly valid analysis, but
it doesn't allow you to isolate different
causes of death.
We also sometimes call this, event-free
survival, or overall mortality.
Because we're indicating that you didn't
have.
This is the probability of having none of
the events available.
None of the competing risks in the data
set.
Now, look over on the right-hand side.
Here's the Kaplan-Meier curve that I've
drawn specifically on the top here,
is specifically for death from other
causes.
[SOUND]
And I've lumped together people who
died of melanoma, in the censored people,
for this Kaplan-Meier curve.
So, everybody who died of melanoma is
counted as censored for
this Kaplan-Meier curve.
And on the bottom here, I'm showing the
Kaplan-Meier curve from,
for death from melanoma specifically.
And in that cure, I've treated people who
died of other causes as censored.
And let's just look actually at the five
year survival probabilities.
A lot of times with cancer,
we're very interested in the five year
survival probabilities,
those are often what people will cite.
So, if you look at the survival
probability for the overall survival,
it's about, somewhere around 75%, and I've
specifically gotten the actual numbers.
It was exactly a 26.8% chance of dying.
That's the overall failure probability.
So I'm going to talk now about the failure
probabilities.
Your chances of dying in five years was
26.8%.
Chances of survival, of course, would be 1
minus that.
That's, and this is the valid analysis on
the, on the left-hand side.
When we do the Kaplan-Meier, when we're
censoring the competing event [INAUDIBLE]
you're going to see that something funny
happens.
So, if we look at the five year survival
on death from other causes, it was,
only a low number of people had died, but
there was a 4.7% chance of dying,
from other causes according to this
Kaplan-Meier curve.
And then, if you looked specifically at
the melanoma-specific five year
survival rates, the chances of dying,
the survival probability's about 77% and
the chance of dying specifically from
melanoma as projected on this Kaplan-Meier
curve was 23.1%, but
you'll notice something interesting,
there's two ways to die in this data set.
You can die from other causes, or you can
die from melanoma,
those are mutually exclusive, and it
covers all possible ways of dying.
So it should be case that if we add up the
probability of dying from other causes,
plus the probability of dying from
melanoma,
that should equal the total probability of
dying.
But notice that it doesn't add up here.
So if I do 4.7% plus 23.1%, I actually get
a, a total probability of 27.8%.
It's slightly different, than the 26.8%
that we got for the overall survival.
So, something's funny here,
because they're not adding up in the way
that they should.
And this difference isn't so huge, but
it's, I mean it should add up exactly, and
so that the fact that there's any
difference is problematic.
But yeah, just to give you an even more
humorous example or
more kind of dramatic example here is an
example from the literature, and
if you look at the overall serv the, this
is the cardiovascular mortalities.
So if you look at just Kaplan, this, this
is a Kaplan-Meier curve on the left-hand
side for cardiovascular mortality dying
from some heart disease related cause.
The survival probability is estimated for
the whole study is estimated to be about
50% in this low group.
And the low group is just, they divided
the study subjects into three groups based
on a blood biomarker, if we just look
specifically at the low group,
then the chances of dying in that low
group of heart disease was about 50%.
But what's interesting if you go on and
look at the low group, for
non-cardiovascular mortality on the right
here,
it turns out that this is somewhere around
44 or 45% survival probability.
So, one minus that will give you the
probability of death,
which turns out to be about 55% or 56%
chance of dying From non-cardiovascular,
and from, from something other than heart
disease.
Now, again you should be able to add these
up and
get the total probability of dying at all.
And if you have a 50% chance of dying of
heart disease, and
a 50% chance of dying of things that
aren't heart disease.
That should sum up, but that would say
that you have a 105% chance of dying,
which of course is clearly impossible.
So, something is wrong with treating the
competing risk as censored.
You get the wrong probabilities.
[SOUND]
And in fact, here is the overall all cause
mortality graph.
And what you'll notice,
is that in fact in the low group, in fact
they had about a 15% chance of surviving.
So they had about an 85% chance of dying.
So certainly, that's very different than
105 or 106% chance.
And obviously, anything above 100% is, is
impossible.
So this is just a really extreme example.
And you can see that some other authors
kind of pointed out this error.
And they actually did a nice little table
here, which shows you at the one year,
the three year, and the five year
follow-ups.
The all cause mortality values are valid,
from the Kaplan-Meier curves.
But if you calculate separately, using
Kaplan-Meier methods.
With the competing risk treated as
censored.
You'll notice that if I get the heart
disease mortality, and
the non-heart disease mortality, and I add
those up.
Those ought to su, sum up to the total
mortality.
But they don't, in any of these cases.
And in some of these cases, you can see
that the gap is quite large.
Obviously, again, you can't have more than
100% chance of dying either.