[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module,
I'm going to show you how to fit a mixed
model with random effects.
So I'm just going to use that mock data
set on depression scores that we
used last week.
I had six subjects and they had their
depression scores measured over time and
I plotted each individual subject on the
graph you see here.
I went ahead and took those data and put
them into a mixed model.
And here's the predicted values from that
mixed model.
And what you can see is that we've
essentially fit a linear regression line
for each person.
What this model includes is both a random
intercept and a random slope.
And by including random intercept and a
random slope,
I am able to get subject specific
intercepts and subject specific slopes.
Now you might wonder how that's possible
because if you thought about how you
would do that, you might think well then
I'm going to need to
put a beta coefficient in the model for
each subject for
their intercept as well as a, a beta
coefficient for their slope and
that's going to obviously eat up all of
our degrees of freedom.
But what mixed models cleverly do is they
actually say,
we're going to get subject specific
intercepts by assuming that the intercepts
follow a normal distribution with some
mean, and some variance.
Remember, normal distributions have just
two parameters, so
we can get a whole distribution of
intercepts by estimating only just
those two parameters, the mean and the
variance of these intercepts.
That allows us to get this whole
distribution of intercepts.
And that's what we mean by a random
intercept.
So when I put a random intercept in the
model, I am estimating the mean and
the variance for this whole distribution
of intercepts.
And the same with the slopes.
To get such x specific slopes, I'm
going to assume that
those slopes following normal distribution
with some mean and some variance.
And all I have to estimate therefore is
the mean and
the variance of that normal distribution.
So, that's called adding a random slope to
the model.
And that allows us to get the picture you
see here.
And, of course at the end of the day we're
going to get
some overall regression lines.
So we have a mean intercept and we have a
mean beta and so, here's the mean of
the intercept and the mean beta as
represented by the slope of that line.
And that, this alpha and
this beta is probably what we're going to
end up reporting in our paper.
But by explicitly modeling the variance in
the intercepts and
the variance of this flows, that's going
to allow us
to get our standard errors correct and our
p values correct.
It essentially accounts for the
correlation within subject here.
Alright, so again, what's a random effect?
A random effect is we're assuming that
there is a distribution.
If I had add a random intercept into the
model,
we're assuming that there's a distribution
of intercepts, and
every person's intercept is a random
variable from that distribution.
So what I'm estimating, and
I'm going to be using the in this module,
beta not rather than alpha for
the intercept so by data not here I'm, I'm
referring to the intercept.
So I'm assuming that the intercepts,
following normal distribution, and
I just have to estimate these two
parameters,
the mean of that distribution and the
variability.
This variability essentially represents
the variation in
depression score between subjects at base
line.
And that sounds a lot like the between
subject variance that we estimated when we
did a univariate repeated measures ANOVA,
and it, it essentially is.
So, just estimating that between subjects
variance will go a long way in
accounting for the women subject
correlation.
Now generally this, we're going to have to
estimate this between subjects variants
but generally it's considered a nuisance
variable.
So we're not necessarily going to report
it in our paper or make any story out of
it but it will allow us to get our
standard errors and our p values correct.
Now to start here, what I thought I would
do is to just start with a model that had
only fixed effects and build from there.
So if the model has only fixed effects,
I'm fitting just a regular ordinary least
squares regression.
And so you can see the model contains only
fixed effects so
this is a regular linear regression.
We get our standard error term.
And the outcome here is depression for at
different time points.
The error terms are assumed as with
regular linear regression assumed to be
normally distributed with a mean of zero
and some variance for the error terms.
We always have to estimate that in linear
regression.
That's assumed to be homogenous and
independent, and all, and all of that.
But that is what we call the mean squared
error.
That's the unexplained variance after we
fit this linear regression model.
That's what we try to minimize when we fit
the regression line.
And then we're going to have to estimate
also we have to estimate that
error variance that goes into calculating
our standard errors and p values.
We also have to estimate the intercept and
the beta for time.
And just to recall the picture of linear
regression,
regular linear regression, that error
variance that we’re estimating essentially
represents the average scatter around the
line at any given value for, for time.
And that's called the mean squared error
and we're trying to minimize that.
So I went ahead and sent just a regular
linear regression.
And, you can see that there were three
parameters that I had to estimate.
This residual error term and then the
intercept and the beta for time.
Just went ahead and, and applied this
model to our depression data and
fit it in SAS and here's the result I got.
So the value for
the unexplained variability, the variance
of the error, was 59.4.
The value for the intercept comes out to
be 24.9.
All that means is that in these six
subjectsm on average of base line,
their average value for depression score
is about 24.9, and
the beta coefficient for time is negative
.557 meaning that they're going down
every month about a half point in their
depression scores.
Where would I find all of this in just the
output from SAS
from a regular linear regression so you
know where to find the intercept and
the beta for time, those are down there,
but where do
you find that residual error term which we
don't usually pay that close attention to?
That you can find under the analysis of
variance table,
that is the mean squared errors.
So here's the mean squared error,
again that represents the unexplained
variability.
Notice that our standard error at this
point is too high, it's .727.
That's going to obviously going to shrink
once we account for the within
subject correlation, and the p value is
obviously also going to be too high.
Pay attention to that as we start adding
random things to the model.
I'm going to start by adding a random
intercept into the model but
keeping time as a fixed term for now.
So, my mixed models have both fixed and
random effects.
So, now we have a mixed model because we
have a random effect and
we have a fixed effect and we still have
the error term as always.
My residual variance is still going to be
assumed to be normally distributed with
mean of zero and some unexplained
variability that I have to estimate.
But now, for my intercept, I'm going to
actually have to estimate two parameters.
The mean for the population and the
variance.
I'm treating the intercept as a random
variable with a probability distribution
which means I have two parameters to
estimate instead of one.
again, this variance that we're estimating
here is very comparable to the between
subjects variance that we estimated in
univariate repeated measures ANOVA.
And of course we have to estimate the data
for time as well.
I went ahead and
fit this in a mixed model and I'm showing
you the predicted values here because I
think the picture just kind of says it all
about what a random intercept means.
So what you can see here is that we have a
random intercept, but
we have a fixed slope.
Everybody has the exact same slope but the
intercepts vary.
So the mean population intercept gets
estimated again at 24.9 but
then we're also estimating the variation
in those intercepts and
we're allowing there to be the variability
there.
Again, I think this picture just really
sort of captures the whole concept.
Let me show you the numbers now that go
with the model that I fit.
So here's the model that I fit.
I had four parameters to estimate.
I went ahead and estimated those and got
some numbers out of SAS.
So, the residual variance, which before
was about 59, is now reduced to 18.9.
So that's gone down a huge amount because
a lot of the variability in
depression score just had to do with the
fact that we had different subjects.
Once I account for
the subjects, the unexplained variability
is greatly reduced.
Very akin to what we did in repeated
measures univariate ANOVA.
The variability in the intercepts turned
out to have a value of 44.6.
So that captured, sort of, subsumed, most
of
the unexplained variability got subsumed
into the variability for the intercepts.
The average intercept, the mean for the
intercept doesn't change.
It's the same as what we got out of linear
regression.
It's still exactly 24.9, so that doesn't
change at all.
And the beta for time also doesn't change
at all.
It's still negative .557.
Let me just show you where to find these
things in the output from
PROP MIXED in SAS.
So the variance for the intercepts is up
here.
You can see that.
And this is the between subject
variability at baseline.
The residual variance is here, 18.9.
Now, you'll notice that a lot of the
variability in depressions courses is
explained by the differences between
subjects making calculating how much of
it, it's about 69% of that variability and
depression scores was actually explained
by the differences between subjects.
Because prop MIXED mixed models actually
use
a maximum likelihood estimation method.
We are going to get AIC fit statistics as
before, so that's nice.
I'll show you that in the model.
We get the exact same intercept in beta as
in the regular linear regression, so
that didn't change.
However, if you look carefully at the
standard error,
the standard error from regular linear
regression was .72.
It's gone down a huge amount here because
our residual error has gone down.
And as a result, of course,
our p value also went down although it's
still not statistically significant.
Now I went ahead and fit a model where I
made the intercepts fixed again but
this time made a random effect for time.
I just want to show you what that means
conceptually.
This is not a typical model that we'd run
but I can run this model and
show you conceptually what, what it's
going to look like.
So this is going to have I'm going to have
to estimate a variance for
the slopes and an average for the slopes.
So I went ahead and did that on this
depression score data.
I'm going to show you the predicted
values,
because I think again the picture is
really helpful here.
So here's the predicted values, so what
you can see is that it's clear.
That I have a fixed effect for
the intercept because there's only a
single intercept.
Everybody shares one single intercept.
However, you can see that there's
variation in the slopes.
And it's even really clear from this
picture that the variance,
that the slopes you know, follow a normal
distribution.
It looks like they follow kind of a nice,
normal distribution here.
It wasn't a huge amount of variability in
the slopes between different subjects but
some variability is estimated here.
And again, the picture just kind of shows
it,
this is what it means to have a random
effect for time.
And then I went ahead and actually put
numbers, fit that in SAS and
actually get numbers out just to show you.
So the residual variance now bounced back
up to 40, because actually a lot of,
it was really important to have the random
effect for the intercept in here.
I've taken that out now and so some of my
unexplained variability has come back in.
The variability in time slopes between
subjects actually turns out to
be relatively small.
We kind of saw that in the original
picture that I showed you of the subjects,
and it looks like most of them are kind of
drifting a little bit downward over time.
So there's not a huge amount of
variability in the pattern of changes and
depression scores over time between the
different subjects.
The intercept here is still stays at 24.9,
the beta for
time still stays at negative .557, those
don't change.
Alright, so that model's clearly not a
great model but again it makes a good
picture and then I went ahead and fit the
model with both of those being random.
A random intercept and a random time
slope.
So now we've got some additional
parameters that we have to fit but
before I show you the numbers there, I
again want to show you the picture because
I think the picture is very helpful.
So now you can see that I clearly have
variability of the intercepts here but
I also am allowing some variability in the
slopes.
You'll notice that there isnt a huge
amount of variability in the slopes.
So there's a big amount of variability at
base line in terms of the baseline
depression score in terms of the
intercept.
But most people are following a fairly
simple trajectory with the exception of
this one purple line, that person felt
followed a more steep trajectory, but
the slopes are pretty close.
You can see there isn't a heck of a lot of
variability in the slopes in,
in this data set.
Alright, so I went ahead and actually fit
the model and
I just want to show you the numbers that
came out.
So first of all, the error term, the error
variance is now down to 16.6.
We've explained away a lot of that
unexplained variability.
The variance for the intercepts is at 53,
so
again a very big variability in the
intercepts.
The variance for the time slopes is pretty
small, is only 0.41, so
that's also matching the picture and
showing you that there wasn't a heck of
a lot of variability in people's slopes
over time.
Everybody was kind of staying very
flattered with just going down a little.
The beta for the intercept, and for time,
don't change at all as before.
And then there's one other additional
parameter that we have to estimate here.
So we have to estimate the covariance now
that we have a random effect for
the intercept and a random effect for
time, we have to actually estimate the
covariance between those.
And that here comes out to be 1.99.
I'll show you where to find that in SAS
[UNKNOWN] in just a second here.
But I'll just remind you that as I
mentioned in an earlier module,
the matrix for
the random effects, that will also have a
covariance matrix that goes with it.
And we have to specify that covariant
structure, that's called the g matrix.
So, I'll show you when I show you how to
program this in SAS that we do have to
specify that covariance matrix structure,
I usually set it unstructured.
But we do to get this additional
covariance and
this is one additional parameter we're
estimating here.
Where do I actually find these things in
SAS?
So the variance for the intercept, the one
here's representing the intercept.
The two is representing the time effects.
So the variance for the intercept turns
out to be 53.
The covariance between the intercept and
the time slope is the negative 1.99.
The variance for the time slope again is
very small.
And then the residual variance is 16.63.
We're getting AIC Fit Statistics as
before, and
then we get our same intercept and data
coefficient as before.
The Standard Error's actually gone up a
little bit compared with
when we had just a random intercept
because it turns out
here that the model with the only the
random intercept is
only slightly better than the model that
also includes the random effect for time.
I'm going to show you that in a minute.
So how do we choose between all these
different models?
So clearly the model with all fixed
effects,
which is just a regular linear regression,
and
doesn't handle the correlation within
subjects, clearly that's not a good model.
We can all agree on that.
But then, how do I know, should I include
the random intercept?
Should I include the random time slope?
Should I include both?
How do I know that?
Well one of the ways to choose the model,
is to look at the AIC statistic.
So now that we're doing maximum
likelihood,
actually restricted maximum likelihood
estimation,
we're going to get likelihood statistics
in AIC statistics again.
So just to remind you, the AIC, is it just
it takes the negative 2
log likelihood value and it penalizes it
for the number of parameters in the model.
Values that are smaller indicate better
fit, and greater parsimony.
But I shouldn't know that sometimes we're
going to see AIC values that actually turn
out to be negative.
We want values that are closer to zero.
So we want the absolute value of the AIC
to be smallest.
So just remember that when we get to those
negative values.
So values closer to zero are better,
better fit.
So what, I went ahead and compared the AIC
from our four models.
Where we had all fixed, this was a regular
linear regression,
doesn't do anything to account for the
correlation within subjects.
Clearly that's a bad model.
That's, that's the worst AIC of all of
them.
Then I have the only the random intercept,
the random intercept only model,
that one actually had the best AIC.
When I had only time effect random and
intercept fixed, I didn't do very well at
all because it really didn't account for
the between subject variability very well
at all.
When I put both random in I actually
didn't do as well as
with just the random intercept.
And you'll see that sometimes, that
sometimes it's sufficient to just put
the random intercept and then you actually
get a better model fit that way.
So the best model turned out to be this
one,
where we allowed a random intercept which
accounted for
the fact that different subjects have
different depression scores.
But it turned out that it looks like the
pattern, the trajectory of changes in
depression scores over time was fairly
similar among the different subjects here.
And I actually do want to show you the
code so
you know exactly where what I'm talking
about how I got these models.
So, in proc mixed, we would be adding a
random statement.
And if I only want the random intercept, I
would just put random and
then an int for intercept.
If I want to get the random intercept and
the random slope for
time, I would put int and then whatever my
time variable is,
I would name that here, that's the same
variable I named in the model.
Now because we've got more than one random
effect in the model,
we do now have to specify the covariance
matrix for
the random effects which in SAS is called
the G matrix.
I will typically set this to be
unstructured because, you know,
there's very few parameters to estimate
here so,
the unstructure doesn't really cost you
too much.
So I will usually set that as
unstructured.
[BLANK_AUDIO]