[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module I'm going to introduce
you to Cox regression.
So in this module we're going to get to
the multivariate regression technique
called Cox regression.
So Cox regression is sometimes also called
proportional hazards regression, and
that's because inherent in Cox regression
is this
assumption called the proportional hazard
assumption that's very essential.
And we'll talk about what that is, so
you'll sometime see it called that.
It's a multivariate regression technique
that you use when you
have time-to-event outcomes.
And it's the most commonly used regression
technique for this type of outcome data.
What do you get out of Cox regression?
What you get out of Cox regression is
simply adjusted hazard ratios.
You actually don't get anything else,
there's no intercept,
you're not going to get an estimate of the
underlying hazard function or
the underlying survival function, you're
just going to get the hazard ratios.
But that's often okay, because often all
we care about is what is
the effect of age, or treatment, or
smoking on the outcome, and
we don't care so much about what the
underlying function looks like.
Just to compare with parametric
regression, which we did last week,
here's some results from an exponential
regression that we ran on data that were
comparing people with active hepatitis.
Some received steroids and some were in a
control group, and
it was comparing time to death.
When we fit an exponential model,
we're assuming that the hazard rate is
constant over time.
So that model, for the control here, which
is in red, the hazard rate was
about 1.1% up per month of time, 1.1%
chance of death every month.
So that was quite high compared with the
steroid treated group,
which had a much lower hazard rate every
month of about .5%.
That corresponded to, that we could
actually draw out these
nice smooth survival curves that you see
on the right hand side here.
What cause regression does is it says,
well what if I don't care exactly what the
absolute value for the hazard rates is,
and what if I don't care to actually draw
out these smooth survival curves?
What if what I care about from this study
is just what's
the difference between the treatment group
and the control group?
What's the relative difference in
mortality rates?
A lot of times that's all I'm after, and
that's what Cox regression does.
It says let's not bother to estimate this
hazard, this underlying hazard function,
let's just estimate the difference between
these two lines,
the relative difference in the hazard
rates.
The assumption here, of course, is that
there is a single relative difference.
Since the hazard rate can change over
time,
it could be the case that the hazard ratio
could also change over time.
If the hazard rate went up in one group
but
down in another over time, then there
wouldn't be a single hazard ratio.
But what we're going to try to do in Cox
regression is say,
well, if the relative difference between
the two groups is constant over time,
as it is if we're assuming an exponential
here,
then we can estimate the relative
difference between those groups.
We can estimate that hazard ratio and we
won't bother to estimate anything else.
So, in this case, you can see we were, you
know,
again, the, the rate in the control group
was somewhere around 1.1% versus
about 0.5% in the treated group, so that
would translate to a hazard ratio for
treatment versus control that's some where
around 0.4 or 0.5.
And maybe that's all we'll estimate.
And in fact, when we ran a Cox regression
on these data I showed you briefly last
week, that if you run a Cox regression on
these data,
in fact, all you get out is a hazard
ratio.
The hazard ratio comparing treatment
versus control was about 0.43,
saying that the treated group had about a
57% decrease in their mortality rate.
And this was statistically significant.
Notice the output from our maximum
likelihood estimation in SAS for
Cox regression has no intercept.
This is it.
Just the treatment versus control.
That was the only predictor in the model.
No intercept here, we're not bothering to
estimate the intercept.
But we can still get that hazard ratio,
which is what we care about in this case.
So what does the model actually look like?
It's the same basic model as we used for
parametric regression.
We're modeling the log hazard.
We're modeling the log hazard as a
function of some baseline hazard,
which may change over time, plus some
increase or
decrease in that baseline hazard function,
depending on your risk factors.
The key to Cox regression, however, is we
are not going to commit ourselves to
any particular form for the underlying
baseline hazard function.
We're going to end up canceling it out in
the likelihood, and
not bothering to estimate it.
So that means that it would be perfectly
fine if your log hazard for
a particular group looks something like
this.
So maybe this is you know, some weird
function.
So maybe this is my reference group, this
is the log reference for
my reference group.
And then maybe my smoking group looks
something like this, it's kind of similar,
weird function over time, no easy
mathematical function to describe that.
But as long as the difference between my
smoking group and
my control group is roughly kind of the
same at all different time points,
then we can estimate the difference
between those curves,
the relative difference, and that is the
hazard ratio.
And we're just going to estimate that.
And the hazard ratio will be represented
by the betas in the model, betas for
all of our risk factors, such as smoking
and age and so on.
So what we're going to get out of the
model is we're going to cancel out those
baseline hazard functions and only
estimate the betas.
And if you exponentiate the betas, you get
hazard ratio.
So let me show you that now.
If you take the betas for, from the Cox
regression model and
you just directly exponentiate them, you
will get the adjusted hazard ratio for
that particular predictor, and that's just
shown here.
So imagine that we've got a Cox regression
model that we fit and
we have smoking and age in the model.
I've got, say in my, I want to do the
hazard ratio for a smoker versus
a non-smoker, so I'm going to take the
hazard ratio estimate from the model for
the smoker versus the non-smoker.
But I'm not going to fill in anything
particular for
the baseline hazard function, which again,
is allowed to change over time.
But I'm going to assume that they both
have the same underlying kind of bate,
shape of that baseline hazard function.
I'm going to assume it's the same for
both, but that the smoker gets additional,
gets an additional increase in
the hazard at all times because of the
fact that they're smoking.
I also have beta age, I have age in the
model here.
And I'm just going to hold age fixed,
because that's what it needs to adjust in
the regression model.
So as long as we're holding age fixed,
those are going to cancel,
the underlying baseline hazard functions
are going to cancel.
And all we're going to be left with is
that the smoker compared to
the non-smoker, if we have a binary
variable for smoking,
if I exponentiate that beta for smoking,
that will give me the hazard ratios for
say, the outcome here being lung cancer,
for smokers versus non-smokers.
Adjusted for everything else in the model,
and notice that I never had
to specify the baseline hazard function in
order to get the hazard ratio.
I can just cancel it out.
So this would represent, if I take the
beta for smoking and exponentiate it,
I get the hazard ratio for smoking, in
this case adjusted for age.
Just to remind you that we can get hazard
ratios for continuous predictors, as well.
So, if I wanted to look at the hazard
ratio for age, adjusted for
smoking, so from that same model, how
would I get the hazard ratio for age?
Well, I'm going to say, again,
I want to to compare somebody who's older
to somebody who's younger.
So this would be the hazard for somebody
who's older divided by the hazard for
somebody who's younger.
If I assume that they have the same
underlying baseline hazard function,
I can cancel them out, I don't need to
bother to estimate them.
I'm going to fix smoking, say they're both
non-smokers, or
I could have said that they're both
smokers, so that those will cancel out.
So all I'm left with here is e raised to
beta age.
And let's say I want to compare somebody
who's ten years older to somebody who's
ten years younger, then it would just be
beta age times 10.
I would then exponentiate, that would give
me the hazard ratio for
a ten unit jump in age.
It works exactly the same as when we
exponentiated‎ betas from a logistic
regression model, except now we're getting
hazard ratios instead of odds ratios.
Now the key assumption here is that we
have proportional hazards.
What I mean by proportional hazards is, is
that the hazard ratio is
constant over time, that the, the, those
two hazard curves are parallel over time.
Otherwise, that hazard ratio would be
changing over time.
There are many ways that
we're going to learn to test the
proportional hazard assumption.
One of the simplest ways is to generate
this log-log plot that we
talked about last week.
If the log-log plot is parallel, then that
would tell you
that the underlined hazard functions were
also parallel, and
therefore that the proportional hazards
assumption was met.
So we're looking for parallel lines here.
This is the log, log plot for the steroid
data.
And so this will show you well,
it's not a perfectly parallel set of lines
between the two groups.
You can see that it's a little bit
narrower,
closer together at the beginning and a
little bit further apart at the end.
But as real data go, this isn't terrible.
These lines look reasonably parallel as,
you know, as real data go, so
probably proportional hazards assumption
would be close enough here.
That's one way to test, to test that
proportional hazards assumption,
we're going to talk about a whole bunch of
other ways.