Just to give some examples of the use of
Cox regression in the literature,
here's a study that I talked about in an
earlier module,
one of my favorite studies, it really
illustrates the idea of publication bias.
So I'm showing you the Kaplan-Meier Curve
from that study here.
This study tracked people who were funded,
got grant money,
from the time they were funded until they
had their first major publication that
actually addressed the main question that
the grant was set up to answer.
And they wanted to know does it matter in
terms of how fast you get published,
whether you found something significant or
you got a null result.
And in fact, the black line here, this is
time to publication.
So the outcome here is a good thing, you
want to be published.
So, the falling, the quickly falling line
here,
the black line, are the ones who actually
had a significant result.
You know, something like P is less than
0.05, or whatever.
The cut off they used.
Those were published much faster than
people who got a null-result,
non-significant result.
It took longer to publish null-results.
Even more interesting that there was this
in-between group,
where they had what people sometimes would
call a non-significant trend often,
that something like P was greater than
0.05, but less than 0.1.
And people say well, looks like something
maybe is there, and if I had a bigger
sample size That was even harder to get
published, and that took even more time.
So this gets at the idea of publication
bias,
that we rush things to publication because
it get a significant result even though
a null result may be just as important as
a significant one.
Well, that was the Kaplan-Meier Curve, and
that tells a lot of the story from this
data, but, again, it's not adjusted for
anything and we haven't
quantified the magnitude of this effect in
any way, other than just visually.
So they then, the authors then ran a Cox
regression on the same data.
So here's the corresponding Cox regression
to those data.
This is just a univariate Cox regression
so
they actually haven't even adjusted for
anything yet, but they could.
But even running a Cox regression buys us
that we get some estimates of effect here,
the effects size.
So the Null group, those who came out with
null results,
was chosen as the reference groups so it's
set to 1.00.
The non-significant trend group was had a
decreased rate of publication so
the hez, the hazard ratio's below 1.
It does cross one here,
it's not a statistically significant
difference from the null group but you
can see there's some suggestion of that
group having a worse publication rate.
And finally, the significant group,
the ones who actually found significant
results, did have a statistically
significant increase in the publication
rate compared with the null group.
And we can interpret this hazard ratio as
basically having about
a twofold higher incidence of publication
compared to those will null results.
So it gives us an effect size we can
measure.
Second example a, of a use of Cox
regression in a literature
has to do with a series of studies that
were published that were looking at
Academy Award winners versus nominees, and
trying to get at this question,
people always say, well, it was just an
honor to be nominated.
Is it really as good to just be nominated
as it is to actually win,
at least for the outcome of longevity?
Researchers thought that there might be
some survival advantage if you
actually won versus only being nominated.
So there's actually more than one study
published on these data.
But the, I'm going to start with the study
that was published on the screenwriters.
I think it's interesting that the
screenwriters got a different result than
the actors and actresses.
So it's just fun to kind of show and
illustrate an example of Cox regression.
So this was the Kaplan Meier curve from
looking at the screenwriters and the blue
curve here is people who, actually screen
writers who actually won an Academy Award.
And the red are screenwriters who are only
nominated but never won.
And interestingly, it's the opposite of
what the authors found for actors and
actresses, the winners did worse, in terms
of longevity, than the nominees.
And, it's just interesting that it kind
of, it,
it reverses itself for the writers.
You can kind of think of some potential
reasons why.
Obviously I can't name too many
screenwriters who were,
won Academy Awards whereas I can probably
name a few actors and actresses.
That's probably winning an Academy Award
for
screenwriting doesn't give you the same
kind of social status and
visibility that an actor does for an actor
or an actress.
And maybe you know people who are really
great screenwriters, they drink more and
do more drugs, who knows, I, I'm just
making things up but,
in any case it was sort of interesting
that it turned out that way.
But that's the Kaplan-Meier curve.
Then you want to adjust for confounders,
get effect sizes so
you can run a Cox regression and that's
what the authors did next, they ran
a Cox regression on the screenwriter data,
that's what's shown here.
What you're seeing, are the results of
that regression.
They're showing you, they're not showing
you exactly the hazard ratios.
They're showing you the relative increase
in the death rate.
So they're directly related to the hazard
ratios, but
they're doing a little bit of translation
of the hazard ratios for you.
They think it, perhaps, makes it easier to
understand.
But basically, in their basic analysis,
when they didn't adjust for
anything, they got a hazard ratio of 1.37.
And they were interpreting that for the
reader as a 37% increase
in the mortality rate for winners compared
with nominees.
This was done, the data were collected
just on the internet, so
they didn't really have a ton of potential
confounders.
They had sort of things that you could
look up on the internet, but
they tried to adjust for those confounders
that they did have.
Adjusting for all of these nine factors
that changed into a hazard ratio of 1.35.
Essentially there was no change, so
nothing that they adjusted for really
accounted for this higher death rate in
the winners group for screen writers.
And again that's just a hazard ratio of
1.35.
So just an example of the use of Cox
regression.
This example has a lot of interesting
pieces to it.
However, it's just an interesting topic.
As I, alluded to in the overview for this
week, the,
they also looked, of course, at Academy
Award Winners for actors and actresses.
And for actors and actresses, they did
find a survival advantage in
the direction of the winners doing better
than the nominees only.
They looked at it with Kaplan-Meier as
well as with a Cox regression.
In the Cox regression, winners versus
nominees, the hazard ratio was 0.75.
So, winners being less likely to die
quickly.
And when they adjusted it went to, it
attenuated a little bit.
The hazard ratio was 0.78.
Again, proportional hazard regressions
also sometimes called Cox regressions.
So that, this is from a Cox regression.
Now what's interesting is if you think
carefully about what's going on with
these data.
You can probably think of a bias that's
going on here.
And indeed, some people reanalyze this
data worried about this particular bias,
and the bias is something called the
immortal time bias,
and rather than give it a fancy name, we
can just kind of describe it.
What's going on here is, if you look at
the Kaplan–Meier curve.
Think about the following.
There's a, a line for nominees and there's
a line for winners.
Drawing the line that way, and with
starting with time, you know,
this is time in age.
That so their age from birth to death.
So what's happening here is that we're
classifying people as winners and
nominees right from the moment they're
born.
But that's not quite right, right?
Some of the people in the winners group
were actually only ever nominated or
were in the control group before they were
ever winners.
So, it doesn't seem quite fair to count
them as winners from birth.
The problem is that living longer
increases your chances of being a winner.
Right.
If you die early in your life for
whatever reason, you then have no chance
of going on to
make an Academy Award winning movie
afterwards.
So, rather than winning, increasing your
chance of living longer,
it could be the case that the fact that
you live longer gave you more chance to
win an Academy Award so the causality
could be reversed here.
And because we just grouped people
statically that's not captured in
this analysis.
So, actually, some other authors went back
and tried to account for this immortal
time bias and tried to analyze the data in
different ways to account for this bias.
And so it's very interesting.
This generated a lot of debate in the
literature.
They're showing a bunch of things that
stated here, but in the re-analysis paper,
what they're showing you here is that, the
survival advantage that was
originally estimated from the original
authors was somewhere around four years.
And that was widely reported in the media
that the winners live about almost four
years longer than the nominees only group.
The reduction in mortality as we saw on a
previous slide, winners versus
nominated was about 25% corresponding to a
hazard ratio about 0.75.
When the authors of the reanalysis paper
relooked at that data,
they came out with reduced effects.
So when they reanalyzed their data using
proportional hazard regression but
accounting for the fact that people
weren't always winners,
they're hazard ratio was now 0.7, 0.82 an
18% reduction in mortality.
So the winners did still have some
advantage but
notice that it was no longer statistically
significant that confidence in
one year crosses, zero, 0% reduction in
mortality rate.
So it attenuated the affect, not
completely to one but
now it's no longer significant and is a
smaller affect.
Showing that perhaps a lot of the original
affect that was found was due to
this particular bias and they estimated
the survival advantage for
winners versus nominees to be more on the
order of a year, and
again, not statistically significant.
And so, perhaps a lot of the original
finding had to
do with this particular bias.