[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module I'm going to talk
about time-changing predictors in
mixed models.
And the interpretation is actually
going to be very similar to when we
had time-changing predictors in
generalized estimating equations.
So, this module should be largely review.
So we're going to use this same old data
set that I used last week.
This had six subjects.
And they all were given a drug that's
supposed to make a happy chemical in,
in their brain go up.
And you can see that's what's happening.
And then they had their depression scores
measured over time.
They were all depressed subjects.
I graphed this data for you last week.
The overall graphic look like this.
Indeed, it look like on average, people's
happy chemical level was indeed going up,
and on average, the depression scores were
going down somewhat.
So I'll show you here the SAS code.
So, this was I fit first a model with just
a random intercept in it.
And here is the results from that model in
SAS.
So just to go through the output,
you can see that I got my variants for the
intercepts.
That's 35.3.
That's my between subject variability at
baseline, my residual variance.
My AIC here is 147.2, just keep that in
mind.
And then you get down to the actual model,
the parameter estimates.
And you'll see that it's very similar to
what we got when we
did this with a generalized estimating
equation.
So the time effect is not statistically
significant.
The chemical effect is highly
statistically significant, and
as before, since chemical is a time
changing predictor,
we do not put in a chemical by time
interaction.
Time is already inherent in chemical
because it's a time changing predictor.
The beta coefficient for chemical is
negative 0.129.
So almost exactly the same a what we got
out of
the generalized estimating equation.
It's highly statistically significant.
The interpretation of that beta
coefficient is tricky,
as we talked about last week, because it
encompasses both within subject's effects,
and between subjects effects.
So I can't tell you just by looking at
that beta coefficient whether or
not any two people who differ in their
chemical level will also be predicted to
differ in the depression level.
Or, whether a person whose individual
chemical level goes up
whether that will correlate to their, you
know,
whether they will be predicted to have
their individual depression score go down.
It could be both of those or some
combination of those.
We saw last week that with this particular
data set, which is made up,
that mostly this was within, due to within
subjects' effects.
But, again, the interpretation than no
different than, than we did last week.
I'll also note that the estimates here of
the beta coefficient and the P-values
are really similar to what we got out of
the generalized estimating equation.
I also ran this model with both a random
intercept and
a random time slope just to see if there
is if one model was better than the other.
So here's the output from that model.
You'll see that the AIC is 149.5.
So a, we actually did a little worse by
including the random time slope here.
So we would probably just choose the model
that had the random intercept only.
And we've seen that that often is a good
fit for these types of data.
I do want to point out one thing here that
I haven't mentioned.
Which is that if you're running a mixed
model with a random intercept
only [SOUND] that is sort of conceptually
equivalent to running a marginal model,
either a GE model or, a mixed model with a
repeated statement a marginal
model where you choose the exchangeable
correlation matrix or
the compound symmetry covariance
structure,
[SOUND] as your correlation structure for
the residuals.
So those are actually, those actually
converge on one another.
You should get very similar results if you
run those two models.