[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module I'm going to be giving
you sort of the 30,000 foot overview of
mixed models.
So before I delve into any of the
mathematical details I
just want to tell you how mixed models fit
in with generalized estimating equations.
And also, I want to point out that there
are actually two different ways to
handle repeated measures data from within
a mixed model.
So what's the difference between a
generalized estimating equation and
a mixed model?
So first of all, obviously both of them
can handle correlated data such as
repeated measures data.
The key difference is that mixed models
can incorporate what
are called random effects whereas GEE
models cannot.
So mixed models are actually called mixed.
Because they include both what are called
fixed effects and random effects.
Fixed effects are our normal effects that
we've been dealing up with until now.
Random effects allow you to do things like
have
subject specific intercepts in slopes.
So we are going to be handling repeated
measures data
with subject specific effects.
GEE models cannot handle those, so they
are only estimating
population-average effects rather than
subject-specific effects.
And for that reason they're sometimes also
called marginal models.
So that's the major difference between
mixed models and GEE.
Another major difference is that GEE and
mixed models actually use different
estimation techniques.
So, as we saw last week, GEE uses what's
called quasi-likelihood estimation,
that's the reason that for our fifth
statistics we got QICs rather than AICs.
In contrast mixed models uses maximum
likelihood estimation actually.
Restricted maximum likelihood estimation
but
that's very similar to maximum likelihood
estimation.
And we will be getting out our normal AIC
model fit statistics.
Because these two modeling techniques use
slightly different estimation methods.
We will get slightly different parameter
estimates and P-values and such.
The other thing I want to point out is
that for when I'm dealing with
continuous outcomes, I tend to choose
mixed models for various reasons.
And there's some advantages when I have
discrete outcomes of picking
the generalized estimating equations.
So often, the choice of which model that
you're going to use may be related to
what type of outcome you have.
Now, I just want to give you a broad
overview of what a mixed model looks like.
So first of all,
we are going to be focusing exclusively
this week on continuous outcomes.
As I mentioned, I actually kind of prefer
to use GE models when I,
have discrete outcomes.
The other major reason we're going to
focus on continuous outcomes is
that we're going to be using the procedure
PROC MIXED in SAS.
And PROC MIXED only handles continuous
outcomes.
So we're going to be dealing with
continuous outcomes,
presumably, roughly normally distributed.
The right hand side of the equation here
looks
an awful lot like all regression models
we've seen before.
The only thing that's new and
different here is the inclusion of these
random effects.
So the fixed effects would correspond to
our normal alphas and
betas in our normal regression models.
And the error term is exactly the same
error term that we've seen in
all the regression models up until now of
the residuals.
The only difference here, the only thing
that's new is the random effects.
Now there are actually two ways to handle
repeated measures data from within
a fixed model.
So let me go over the first of those now.
So the first strategy actually does not
include any random effects in the model.
Instead it handles the within subject
correlation by
focusing on the error return, and
this is very similar to what we did when
we fit generalized estimating equations.
So remember, with generalized estimating
equation, what we did is to say,
well, normal linear regression assumes
that these errors are independent of
one another.
Clearly that's violated when we have
repeated measures data.
And the way that we handle that with
generalized estimating equations was to
allow the correlation structure to be
something other than independent.
To make it be exchangeable or auto
regressive to
explicitly estimate the correlations
between different time points.
Well we're going to do basically the same
thing as strategy one in our mixed model.
So if your in SAS and you're using PROC
MIXED.
If you want to fit a correlation matrix
for
the errors, we're going to be including
what's called a repeated statement.
So you would be including a repeated
statement.
And that repeated statement is going to
look very similar to
the repeated statement that we saw in PROC
GENMOD.
You're going to be specifying type equals
where you
specify a particular covariance structure.
We're actually going to be specifying the
covariance structure rather than
the correlation structure but same idea.
So you might specify for
example that you want a compound symmetry
covariance structure.
By explicitly estimating the within
subject correlation,
we are in that way correcting for it.
And so that would involve the repeated
statement in PROC MIXED.
The, we are estimating essentially the
co-variance matrix variance for
the residuals.
And for that reason it is sometimes called
the R matrix.
Or at least in SAS that is called the R
matrix, so
just that you know the terminology in SAS.
So that is one way of dealing with a
repeated measures data, and
it's very akin to what we did in a
generalized estimating equation.
In fact, because we're not fitting any
random effects,
I would call this a marginal model, same
as a GEE model.
All right, so that's one strategy.
The only advantage of PROC MIXED to GE to
PROC GENMOD there are more choices for
the types of correlation, covariance
structure that you can specify there.
All right.
So that's started our strategy one.
The second strategy is actually to include
random effects in the model.
To include a random effect for subject,
and allow us to
estimate subject specific intercepts and
sometimes subject specific slopes.
To do that in PROC MIXED in SAS what you'd
be including is a random statement.
And on that random statement you would
specify things like I
want a random intercept would be and I
want subject-specific intercepts.
If I want a random slope I always specify
that I want subject specific slopes.
So along with that you also do have to
specify a covariance matrix and
I just want to point out that this is a
different covariance matrix than the one
we specify for the error terms.
So just to avoid any confusion here
there's a covariance matrix you have to
specify for the random effects because the
random effects themselves will
have a covariance matrix.
That is, in SAS, called the G matrix and
I will just usually set that as an
unstructured covariance structure.
Usually there aren't too many parameters
that have to be estimated for
the random effects matrix, and therefore I
would just usually set it
as unstructured so I don't have to worry
too much about it.
But I just want to point out that that's
a, you're going to see that on
the random line you have to do a type
equals and specify covariance structure.
That's a different covariance structure,
that's for the random effects, not for
the residuals.
So, different things here.
Now, if you put a random effect for
subject into the model, if you include
that, it turns out that you
are actually redefining changing what a
residual, what this error term means.
So, once you have put a random effect in
the model.
You have most likely taken care of the
issue of within subject correlation.
That's probably sufficient.
You probably don't have to additionally
put in a repeated statement.
So, once I have a random effect for
subject in the model, then the error
terms are no longer the distance between
an observation and the population average.
These residuals are redefined now and they
become
the distance between an observation and
the mean for a specific subject.
And so, what that usually means is that
these errors are now
reasonably modeled as independent.
And so we don't have to do anything with
them.
Practically what that means is that I do
not need to include in my PROC MIXED,
a repeated statement.
Once I have a random statement, usually
that's sufficient.
If I put a repeated statement, I usually
don't have to include a random statement.
In other words, I'm only probably going to
be including either a random
statement to account for the repeated
measures data,
or a repeated statement, and usually I'm
not going to be including both.
Now if you get to more complicated data
sets that are beyond the scope of
this course, there may be occasions where
in fact there is
some additional correlation in the error
term that needs to be accounted for.
And then you would have to have both a
random statement and
a repeated statement in the model,
where you would specify the correlation
matrix again of the aura matrix.
But again those examples are beyond the
scope of this course so for
our purposes, it's going to be sufficient
to have one or the other of those.
Since we already fit GE models which is
essentially are very similar to
using the repeated statement in PROC
MIXED, I am going to focus this week on
adding the random effects rather than
focusing on the repeated statement.
So I'll be ref, focusing on the random
statement in PROC MIXED.
So again in this module, I just want to go
over how to fit
those marginal models with PROC MIXED and
then after this module,
I'll be focusing on that random statement
I'm putting in the random effects.
So PROC MIXED has a repeated statement
similar to PROC GENMOD, which allows you
to specify a covariance structure for the
within-person correlation.
It allows you to specify the covariance
matrix for the residuals for
the R this is what SAS calls the R matrix.
If you use PROC MIXED with a repeated
statement you're actually going to
get very similar results.
To when you use PROC GENMOD with a
repeated statement,
they are both fitting marginal models.
There are no random effects.
So therefore, you know, they're kind of
doing the same thing.
Now, if you do with the same data set you
fit those two models in MIXED and
GENMOD and you choose the same correlation
structure,
you will actually get slightly different
answers.
Because, as I pointed out before,
the two modeling techniques are using
different estimation methods.
One is using quasi-likelihood, the other
is using maximum likelihood.
And then the other reason, at least off
the bat you're going to
get slightly different answers is that the
default is to give you
the robust standard errors in generalized
estimating equations.
In PROC GENMOD and SAS you get the robust
standard error is by default.
Whereas, in PROC MIXED, the default is to
give you the model-based standard error,
so since you're getting slightly different
standard errors, at least if you don't ask
for them in PROC MIXED, again you're
going to get slightly different answers.
If you want to fit a marginal model
however, and
you have a continuous outcome, even though
GEE is doing something similar,
I would actually recommend that you use
PROC MIXED to fit the marginal model.
And the reason is, is that PROC MIXED
offers many more choices for
the covariance, the structure of the
covariance matrix.
There's very limited choices in your
generalized estimating equations.
So for example PROC MIXED gives you the
power, in generalized estimating equations
we were actually talking about the
correlation structure.
We never did anything with the variances
with for each time point.
We did PROC MIXED, so the variance is
like, image you have three time points.
Make this a little bigger.
So imagine that I've got three time
points.
Time one, time two, and time three.
When we're estimating the covariance and
the correlation.
We have correlation between every two time
points.
So, you know, if I have an exchangeable
correlation matrix that looks like that.
But I also have the variance at each time
point.
And one of the assumption,
one of the things we've been assuming is
that variance is equal.
So the variance of the outcome at time one
is equal to the variance of the outcome at
time two, is equal to the variance of the
outcome at time three.
That's that homogeneity of variances
assumption.
Well, we didn't have a way to deal with
that in PROC GENMOD but
actually in PROC MIXED, you can choose to
make those variances heterogeneous and
actually to fit three separate variances,
you have that option.
Another additional option that you have in
PROC MIXED, is
you can actually allow different groups,
like the treated and the control group,
to actually have different values for
their covariance structures their, so
for their correlation coefficients and
their variances.
And so, there's some flexibility there
that doesn't exist in PROC GENMOD.
So, generally again if,
even if you want to fit a marginal model,
I would do it from within PROC MIXED if
you've got a continuous outcome rather
than from PROC GENMOD.
But just to show you that you get very
similar results last week we fit a GEE
model for the spine bone density data with
these three groups, black, red and blue.
And here are the results.
We went over these results last week.
We saw that the time by group interaction
was significant for
both of the, the black and the red group
compared with the blue group,
saying that they do have a higher rate of
change of,
of spine bone density over time than the
blue group as we can see in the picture.
I'll just point out the P-values here are
0.0456, 0.0057.
The point estimates are 0.0108, 0.0140.
If you scroll across, you can see you can,
there's a lot of different estimates here.
But I went ahead and fit that same data in
a PROC MIXED, but for
the, asking for the marginal model, using
the repeated statement.
And in this, these results, I had chosen
an exchangeable correlation matrix.
So for PROC MIXED, I went ahead and chose
compound symmetry.
Compound symmetry means exchangeable
correlation plus, that the same,
the variance is, at different time points
are all the same homogeneity of variances.
So I went ahead and chose compound
symmetry.
I also, specifically requested a robust
standard error just to
get these as similar as possible.
I just want to show you that you get
pretty much the same results.
So, the P-values are 0.4, 0.0491, rather
than 0.0456,
0.007 rather than 0.0057, 0.01079 rather
than 0.0108.
I mean these are really, really close.
We are in the third decimal place before
you see any difference.
So these models are very much essentially
doing the same thing.
Again, I slightly prefer PROC MIXED here
because you have more flexibility for
that correlation covariance structure.
I am actually going to show you some SAS
code this week, just because there's a lot
of different ways of modelling these
things, and it can be a little confusing.
And sometimes just seeing the code can
help clarify what we're talking about.
So again, last week we did generalized
estimating equations, with PROC GENMOD.
Using the repeated statement to specify
the structure of the correlation matrix.
We can do a similar marginal model in PROC
MIXED,
by using the repeated statement in PROC
MIXED.
The syntax looks very similar to PROC
GENMOD, a few differences in the syntax.
And we can there specify again, the core,
same correlation matrix, and
we are getting a mixed a marginal model
out this way.
We're going to get similar results.
Again with, with some slight advantages
for PROC MIXED in terms of choices for
your covariance structure.
[BLANK_AUDIO]