In this next module,
I'm going to introduce you to generalized
estimating equations.
For those of you who had HRP 261 in the
winter,
you've actually already seen these models
before, but,
what's new here is their application to
repeated-measures data.
So generalized estimating equations are
used to analyze correlated data,
including but not limited to,
repeated-measures.
They're basically an extension of our
generalized linear models, but
they estimate and explicitly account for
the correlations,
whether those correlations are within
cluster or pairs of subjects or
within the same subject over time, as in
repeated-measures.
So take this data set that I've got
displayed up here, for example.
Imagine that I give you this data set.
It's in the long form.
And this corresponds to, similar to the
data sets we've been talking about.
I've got subjects who have had their bone
density measured at three
time points about at baseline and about at
a year later and about two years later.
If you didn't know anything about how to
account for correlation and
I were to hand you this data set and say,
can you tell me whether or
not the bone density changes significantly
over time, you might look at
these data and say, well, okay, I have my
outcome variable is bone density.
That's continuous and normally
distributed.
Therefore, I'm going to be running a
linear regression model and
my predictor will be time.
And actually that's almost it.
That's very close to what we are going to
be doing when we do a DE model,
with one exception.
We have to do something to account for
the correlation, but it's going to look an
awful lot like this model.
So I'm just going to start with just this
simple linear regression model run on
the long form of the data.
So if I run this linear regression model,
it corresponds to the picture on the left
here, where I've graphed the spine bone
density of these women against time.
This data set has 41 women in it.
There's a lot of dots because women are
measured multiple times and
notice that there's no way to connect
which dots go with themselves.
You don't know which dots are connected by
being the same woman.
However, you can fit a line to this
scatter plot, which I've done here.
And you can see that there is a slight
positive slope here.
So this spine bone density seems to be
going up a little bit over time.
The equation of that line, we can get that
by fitting a linear regression model,
which is what I've done.
We can see the results over here.
So the beta coefficient for time is indeed
positive.
It comes out to be .005 spine bone density
on average is about a value of 1.0.
So this corresponds to about a 0.5%
increase in spine bone density per year.
Small, but important.
And, however the P value is totally not
significant here.
I want you to pay attention to the
standard error.
The standard error is 0.01.
So what's happening here is that our
standard error is too high.
If you'll look at the picture here,
you'll notice that there's a huge amount
of variability in spine bone density, but
most of that variability doesn't have to
do with what's happening over time.
It has to do with the fact that we have
different subjects and
different people have vastly different
bone strength.
You can see there's one person up here
this,
you can imagine that probably this is the
same person over time.
This person just genetically has really,
really high bone density.
There's other people who tend to be very
low.
The bulk of the variability in bone
density has to do which subject you are.
And, this is going to be analogous to last
week in repeated-measures,
univariate anova, we calculated the
between subject variation.
Once we've accounted for that between
subject variation, our standard errors,
our unexplained variability shrank a huge
deal.
Well, we're going to basically do the same
thing here.
If we can account for which, which of the
part of the variability is just due to
the fact that we have different subjects,
we can greatly shrink our standard errors,
that means our P values are also going to
get smaller.
So that's all that GE does.
It connects which of these dots goes with
which of
the other dots which is the same person
over time.
And the model doesn't look that different
from a regular linear regression.
The only difference is that we have this
correction factor for correlation.
So essentially, this is a nuisance
variable.
We're going to be estimating a correlation
matrix.
If you don't explicitly ask for it,
you won't even see it in your SAS output,
for example.
But we need to estimate that in order to
be able to correct for
the between subject variability.
So I went ahead and ran the correct model
now, just to show you the difference.
So the picture is still the same.
We've still got spine bone density over
time.
It's the overall increase is a slight
positive increase.
But when I correct for this correlation
within subject,
what you'll notice is that the beta
coefficient for time doesn't change much.
It's still positive.
It's now a little bit higher, about a 0.8,
0.9% increase per year.
But, what really changes here the, the
effect of accounting for
a correlation, what affect that has is to
hugely effect the standard errors.
So, remember our standard errors before
were 0.01.
Our standard error goes from 0.01 down to
0.002, so
it's, we've actually cut our standard
error by five fold.
So the bulk of the variation here was just
due to the different subjects.
And once we've accounted for that our
standard errors are much, much smaller and
notice now that our P value is highly
significant.
So this is a true increase over time.
It's a small increase, but
it is a statistically significant increase
in bone density over time within women.
Notice that when we're asking about
changes over time we're
talking about within subjects comparisons.
When we fail to account for correlations
for
within subjects comparisons, as I've told
you before, then our P values and
our standard errors are too high as you
see here.
When we correctly account for
those correlations then those p values and
standard errors come down.
So that's the idea of generalizing
estimating equations.
We're essentially going to be changing
those standard errors
adjusting the standard error based on the
correlation within subject.
Let me go now into a little bit more about
the mechanics of
generalized estimating equations.
So, what's actually happening behind the
scenes in the computer?
So, as I've mentioned,
it's not really that different than
fitting a regular linear regression.
What the computer is actually doing is it,
in fact, first fits a regular old linear
regression,
assuming that the observations within
subjects are completely independent.
It then calculates the residuals from that
linear regression.
So the observed minus predicted values for
everybody.
Those residuals are going to reflect the
pattern of correlations in the data.
It takes those residuals and
uses them to estimate what's called a
working correlation matrix.
And the one constraint is that you do have
to a priory specify a structure for
that correlation matrix.
I'm going to show you the different
choices in a few minutes here.
It's going to then refit that linear
regression model but
now correcting for the correlation.
And it's going to calculate the residuals
from that new model and
then estimate a new working correlation
matrix and it's iterative process.
So it's going to keep going through this
over and again until it can,
until the model converges.
And essentially we're estimating this
working correlation matrix,
this within correlate subject correlation
structure.
We're estimating it so
that we can get the correct standard
errors but it's a nuisance variable.
If you don't explicitly ask for it in the
outputting staff, you won't even see it.
It's not what we care about,
it's just that we care about getting the
standard errors correct.
I just want to point out quickly here that
we've
talked a lot about maximum likelihood
estimation and about likelihood functions.
You've all thought about likelihood
functions in
the concept of survival analysis.
I want to point out that, in fact, when
you have correlated data it's
very difficult to correctly specify the
entire likelihood function,
because it's complicated by the fact that
we don't have independent observations.
So we don't actually do maximum likelihood
estimation methods.
We do what are called quasi-likelihood
methods for
generalized estimating equations.
I'm not going to go in to any of the
details on that, but
basically it saves you having to specify
the likelihood function exactly,
which is beneficial when you have this
complication of correlation.
But it has a lot of the advantages of
maximum likelihood estimation.
And, as a result of the fact that we're
doing quasi-likelihood rather than
maximum likelihood methods, what you'll
notice in your output,
is that you're going to get a QIC instead
of an AIC.
So remember that we use the AIC previously
to as a measurable of model fit and
that comes directly from the likelihood
function.
Since we do have a likely hood function
here, we have a quasi-likelihood function,
we're instead going to get a QIC, Q coming
from the word quasi.
It's essentially analogous to the AIC but
it's based on the quasi-likelihood rather
than the maximum likelihood function.
So, we're going to treat it as we would
the AIC.
The smaller values indicate a better model
fit.
The QIC is very useful for
helping you to select the best working
correlation structure.
So again, when you're asking the computer
to run your
generalized estimating equations you do
have to specify up front what type of
correlation structure you want.
GEE luckily is fairly robust against the
wrong choice of correlation matrix.
Particularly if you've got a large sample
size.
So if you get it wrong,
you're going to see that it's not going to
necessarily make a huge difference.
But obviously we'd like to spend some time
thinking about what is
the best correlation structure for our
data.
I'm going to give you some different
examples of correlation structures that
you have as choices at your disposal.
So, I'll go through each one of these in
turn to say exactly what
that structure looks like.
But basically we're looking for simplest
structure, the one that uses up the fewest
degrees of freedom, the simplest structure
that fits the data well.
And again, you can use this QIC to help
you decide which one is the best one.
So let me just show you what all these
correlation structures look like.
So first of all, the, an independent
correlation structure is when you're
assuming that all of the time points are
independent of one another.
This is clearly probably not going to be
the correct correlation structure if you
have repeated measures data.
If you have correlations, you don't have
independence.
But I'm just showing you this is the one
that we're,
we're assuming independence when we fit a
regular linear regression and
this what I'm showing you here is a
correlation matrix.
Imagine we've got a data set that has four
time points and I ask for
the correlation between any two time
points.
If they're zero, if a person isn't
correlated to themselves at
different time points again, unrealistic,
that would, be then you would be on,
on an independent correlation structure.
That's usually not the right choice.
The simplest correlation structure that
actually has correlation between different
time points is what was called the
exchangeable,
this is we talked about compound symmetry
last week so.
So this is the same as compound symmetry.
This is saying that any, the correlation
between any two time points is equal.
So for example, the correlation between
time one and
time two is the same as the correlation
between time one and time three, and
is the same as the correlation between
time one and time four.
Now you can imagine that the advantage of
the exchangeable correlation matrix is
that you actually are modelling and
accounting for correlation.
However you only had to estimate one
parameter.
There's one correlation parameter to
estimate so
it doesn't cost you a lot of degrees of
freedom, so that's an advantage.
The disadvantage is that, especially for
repeated-measures outcomes, you can
imagine as you get further and
further apart in time, probably the
correlations are going to go down.
People as you drift in time, you're likely
to drift in your values and
therefore, you would expect that if you're
three time points away rather
than one time point away that you might
have a smaller correlation.
So the exchangeable isn't always the right
choice for repeated measures for
that reason.
Another choice you have is the
unstructured correlation matrix.
The issue with the unstructured is that it
uses up a lot of degrees of freedom.
So unstructured just says for
every possible correlation coefficient,
estimate a new one.
So, if there are six pairs of time points,
estimate for
me six correlation coefficients.
Obviously, that's going to be very
precise, but
it eats up a lot of degrees of freedom.
If you have four time points, you're going
to have four choose two, which is
six correlations to estimate, If you have
five you will have five choose two,
which is ten correlations to estimate, and
so on.
So you can see that this can get untenable
rather quickly.
However, if you've got a situation where
you've got a large number of subjects and
a, only a small number of time periods you
have sort of unlimited degrees of
freedom and, you know, you're not going to
eat up too many of those degrees of
freedom if you only have, say, three time
periods.
Then, the unstructured might be a good
choice in that situation.
The autoregressive is kind of a compromise
between exchangeable and unstructured.
So, there's only one parameter to
estimate, as in the exchangeable, but
it's allowing some flexibility, so that
you actually have different
correlations across different time
periods.
So the way the autoregressive works is,
this works well for repeated measures
data, is that it starts with estimating a
correlation between adjacent time periods.
So it's saying that there's a,
one correlation that describes all of the
adjacent time periods.
And then if we're two time periods away,
the correlations is going to be a little
bit smaller.
And if we're three time periods away,
the correlation is going to be even a
little bit smaller.
This often describe repeated-measures
data.
And the way we can get away with only
estimating a single parameter here is
a little tricky, if you've noticed what
they done,
is you take the correlation from one time
period away and you square it.
Well, if you square a number that less
than one it's going to
be a little bit smaller.
And then you can cube it for three time
periods away and so on.
So this way you get diminishing
correlation as you go further and
further apart in time, but it only costs
you one degree of freedom.
So very useful in repeated-measures data,
often.
The independent correlation structure is
trying to do the same sort of thing,
which is to recognize that often for
repeated method data, if you're one time
point away, you have a different
correlation than say if you're two times
points away, or three time periods away.
So what it does is it allows you to
estimate one correlation width for
one time period away but then it doesn't
assume that you
can just square that one to get to two
time periods away.
It estimates a whole separate correlation
for two time periods away.
And then you can do, if you did three
dependent here we could
estimate a whole separate correlation for
three time periods away or at some point,
you might say that we're far enough away
that they're no longer correlated,
you just set them equal to zero.
So we could do two-dependent or
three-dependent here.
Another one that is often useful for
repeated-measures data costs you a few
more degrees of freedom, but
certainly not as many degrees of freedom
in an unstructured matrix.
So how do you chose the working
correlation structure?
Again, generalized estimating equations
are fairly robust against the choice of
correlation structure, so you don't have
to stress about it too much.
But often the nature of the problem
suggests the choice of structure.
So, for example, for repeated-measures
data, autoregressive or
m-dependent are often appropriate for the
reasons I've talked about.
Exchangeable will also if the changes over
time aren't too big.
If you have clusters in your data that
don't have any natural orderling,
ordering like time then the exchangeable
would be recommended.
If you have a situation where you have a
huge number of clusters and not so
many measurements within clusters,
sometimes even the independent structure
may suffice.
But you can use again the QIC to help
guide this, the choice.
And I'll give you an example in a minute.
You're looking for the lowest QIC.
So take this example data on bone density
that we've been using.
I went ahead and just asked for the
empirical correlation matrix.
So what are the correlations between each
time period?
So I took, I'm getting, showing you here
there's only three time periods for
this data set.
So I'm getting the correlation between the
second spine measurement and
the first spine measurement.
That was actually the highest at .979.
The correlation between the second and
the third, which are only one time point
adjacent, was 0.974, so pretty close.
And then the correlation between the first
and
the last was just a teeny bit smaller at
0.966.
You can see that they're all very similar,
because the bone density wasn't changing a
huge amount over time.
It takes your skeleton quite a bit of time
to change,
especially when you're already an adult.
So which correlation matrix would this
correspond to?
Well, we could choose the exchangeable,
because they're all right around 0.96,
0.97, 0.98.
Probably exchangeable would be just fine.
The when I showed you the run of GEE
before.
I actually for these data, I just chose
the exchangeable.
You could also argue that maybe
autoregressive would be appropriate,
because you can see that the correlation
between the first two and
the second two time periods,
those are a little bit higher than the
correlation from the first to the last.
So, maybe autoregressive would work here
as well.
You could also choose unstructured because
we only have
three correlations to estimate.
Although this data set only has 41 women
in it, so
we're limited on degrees of freedom.
I went ahead and
fit all of these different correlation
structures just to compare them.
See what happens.
So I started with the exchangeable
correlation matrix.
I've already showed you these results
before.
So the beta coefficient was 0.0088.
My P value is highly significant.
My standard error is about 0.002.
The exchangeable working correlation is
0.974.
There it estimated for all of the
correlations about 0.974.
That seems like a good compromise, because
they were all right around 0.96,
0.97, 0.98.
I then want to have them fit the
autoregressive, oh so
the the, the QIC from the exchangeable is
126.88.
I went ahead and fit the autoregressive.
You'll notice that the QIC was just teeny,
teeny bit better from the auto regressive.
Although I would consider these models to
be equally good.
They're, that QIC isn't very different.
But it is a little bit better from the
autoregressive.
So maybe the autoregressive is just
slightly better here.
For the autoregressive you can see that it
says 0.9975 for one time-point adjacent
and 0.9949 for two time-points adjacent,
which is just the square of 0.9975.
It doesn't affect the model much at all.
The beta coefficient is0 .0098, so
just slightly higher than with the
exchangeable, basically the same.
The standard error is pretty close 0.0024,
rather than .0021, so pretty similar.
The P value is still highly significant.
So it doesn't change things a whole heck
of a lot.
Either of those would be a good choice
here.
I then went ahead and fit the
unstructured.
Now again, there's only three time periods
here.
So, you know, when you only have three
time periods and
unstructured might normally do pretty well
but
because there's only 41 people in my data
set it really blew up the QIC.
There's something funny going on when the
QIC gets that big.
If you can see that it's at 0.9956, 0
.9876, and
0.9690, all different correlations.
It didn't really impact the outcomes so
much.
The beta estimate's a little bit higher
now and
the standard error is actually almost
double.
So that made our P value a little bit
higher, but
it still came out to be statistically
significant.
This probably would not be the best choice
here.
Although again, if we had a bigger data
set, the unstructured might do fine.
I also went ahead and fit the independent
correlation matrix.
This is where all of the correlations get
set to zero.
So the correlation matrix would look like
this.
Now, of course, that's totally the wrong
correlation.
We certainly have correlation here.
But what I want to point out to you is
that the QIC is higher than for
the exchangeable or the autoregressive, as
it should be,
because it's certainly not as good as a
choice.
However, it didn't make, it does make some
impact here,
but we still do a lot better then when we
just ran a regular old linear regression.
So the point estimate turns out to be
0.005.
The standard error is pretty big.
The P value is no longer significant, but
this is still better.
Remember, the standard error when we get a
regular linear regression was 0.01,
so we've still done a lot better than
that.
And the reason that the independent, if
you choose independent,
you still don't do too badly especially if
you've got a bigger sample size,
is that you're using what I'm showing you
here are the empirical or
robust standard errors, which I've talked
about before.
If you ask for the robust standard errors
or the empirical standard errors, then
the estimates are fairly robust against
the choice of correlation structure.
So we even don't do too badly if we choose
the independent correlation structure,
which is obviously wrong.
So again, there's two types of
standard errors that you can get out of
the generalized estimating equations.
You're mostly always going to want to
choose the robust standard errors.
There may be a few exceptions to that,
but,
in general, the robust standard errors are
preferred,
because they are robust against the
incorrect choice of correlation structure.
It's not going to make a huge difference
which correlation structure you choose for
the most part, especially if the sample
size is large.
If you're doing this in SAS, it just gives
you the robust or
empirical errors without you asking.
However, there are another type of
standard errors called the model-based
standard errors.These are very sensitive
to the choice of correlation structure.
And there may be a few instances when you
want to use these,
specifically if you have a very low number
of clusters then the model based
standard errors may be preferred.
This is not generally be the case when you
have repeated-measures data, because for
repeated-measures data the cluster is the
subject and you know it's
very aware that you'd have a data set with
less than 20 subjects measured over time.
That certainly could happen but for the
most case, for repeated-measures data,
usually we're going to have a large enough
number of clusters.
So but you may get a situation where
you've got cluster data where people are,
say, clustered by school or something and
you only have ten schools in the data set.
Then you would want to consider the
model-based standard errors.
But, in general, we're going to be using
those robust standard errors,
which helps us,
because it guards us against any problems
in our choice of correlation structure.
And I just want to show you the
model-based standard errors,
when I choose the independence correlation
structure and
I then choose the model-based standard
errors, I really get things wrong.
I actually back to the just the original
linear regression that I showed you at
the beginning of this module where I did
nothing to account for the correlations.
I get back at standard error of 0.01 and
the non-significant P value.
So clearly, we don't want to use
independence correlation structure.
And again, this is just to show you that
the model-based standard errors are really
sensitive to that choice of correlation
structure.
[BLANK_AUDIO]