[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module,
I'm going to introduce you to Univariate
repeated-measures ANOVA.
And, in this module, we're only going to
look at the time effect.
So we're not going to complicate the
picture by comparing groups quite yet.
So I've got here a very simple example
data set with only six subjects in it.
I'm choosing a very simple data set,
because I actually want to do out all of
the sum of squares, all the math on this
to illustrate how it works.
So we're going to keep it small.
And, again, for
this module, we're going to be ignoring
the distinction of what group you're in.
So, we're only going to be comparing,
whether or
not, there's any differences over time.
That is time point 1, time point 2, time
point 3, and time point 4.
So, this is six subjects and they've had
something measured.
Let's say it's a score on a depression
questionnaire.
They've had that measured at four time
points.
And for a, an ANOVA analysis, what we're
asking is whether or
not the mean depression score differs
across the different time point periods.
It's a simple dataset, and of course we're
going to want to plot it.
And since I only have six subjects, I
might as well plot an individual line for
each subject, and that's what I've done
here.
So this is the depression score over time
for the six subjects.
And you can see,
well, they seem to be going down a little
bit towards time point three.
And then, rebounding a little bit at time
point four.
But there is some individual variability
there.
Before we jump into actually how to
calculate repeated measures ANOVA,
I just want to point out that there are
some assumptions.
So, as with any linear model,
we are assuming that we have a normally
distributed outcome.
So I'm going to assume that this
depression score is reasonably normally
distributed here.
The other assumption of repeated measures
ANOVA is analogous to
the homogeneity of variance assumption.
That we had when we did regular ANOVA.
Remember, that assumption was that the
variances for each group were equal.
It gets a little more complicated, when,
when we jump to repeated measures, in
ANOVA.
Because now, not only do the variances at
each time point have to be equal.
But, we also,
because we've got correlation across the
different time points,.
The other assumption is that we have equal
correlation across the different
time points.
That's the same as an exchangeable
correlation matrix.
So this is sometimes called Compound
Symmetry.
But again, sort of analogous,
a more complicated version of
homogeneative variances.
So let me spend just a little bit of time
on that.
There are ways to correct for violations
of this assumption as I'll show you.
But compound symmetry requires that the
variances of
the outcome variable ought be the same at
each time point.
Maybe that's, that's essentially
homogenially the variances.
But it has this additional assumption that
now that we have correlation across
time points.
We're assuming that the correlation
between repeated measurements
are equal across different time points.
Regardless of the time interval between
measurements.
And this often doesn't make sense because
we're saying that time one and
time four are just as correlated as time
three and time four.
When oftentimes, closer, measurements are
going to be
more correlated with another than farther
measurements.
But this is one of the assumptions of
repeated measures ANOVA.
So how do we test those assumptions?
So we can look at the variances at each
time point just visually.
So you can see that he variance in
depressions course seems to be
a little bit bigger at time point one than
at time point four, just visually.
So if I'm just looking at the variance at
a given time point.
And we can also calculate those variances,
now are facing these various calculations
on just six data points.
But we can calculate a variance with six
data points.
So we can see that indeed we calculate the
variances that indeed the variance at
time four was quite a bit smaller than the
variance at time one.
So we're probably somewhat violating this
compound symmetry assumption.
We also need to look at the correlation
matrix.
To look at the correlation between
depression scores across
different time points.
You could look at the covariance matrix
but covariance is
somewhat dependent on unit, so I find it
easier to look at the correlation matrix.
These are just Pearson correlation
coefficients.
So you can see that time point one and
time point two are very highly correlated.
However, time point one and
time point three are actually inversely
correlated, and it.
So on.
You could see that we're looking for
these all to be equal.
Clearly these are not equal here.
So we're probably violating compound
symmetry.
An exchangeable correlation matrix,
compound symmetry would look like the
following.
You would have basically had the same
correlation between all pairs of
time points.
Again, somewhat unrealistic with real
repeated measures data.
So those are the assumptions of repeated
measures ANOVA.
Now let me jump into how it actually
works.
Essentially, it's just like a regular
ANOVA but there is one little twist.
There is the twist that you have to
account for
the fact that you have different subjects,
measured over time.
So it's accounting for a between subject
difference and
I'll show you that in a minute.
But we're going to start with the null
hypothesis here.
The null hypothesis is that the mean
depression for
a time point one is equal to the mean
depression for a time point two.
Is equal to the mean depression for
at times three and is equal to a mean
depression four at times four.
And if you had more time points this would
keep going.
So it's just like regular ANOVA in that we
are assuming that the means of
all the different groups.
Are equal except group here is time point
rather than,
you know different treatment groups.
So we're assuming that the means at all
the different times are equal.
Now I'm going to start by actually
analyzing these data with
a regular old ANOVA, not yet doing the
repeated measures ANOVA.
To show you where the difference lies.
So imagine that you didn't know anything
about reputed measures ANOVA, but
I gave you these data.
And I said, well just count times, the
times as different groups and
run a regular ANOVA.
How would you do it?
So, this is sort of a nani, a naive or
incorrect analysis.
But here's what it would look like.
I would have to use the long form of the
data because I'm going to
be pretending for the moment that I have
24 independent observations.
I am not accounting for
the fact that person one was measured at
multiple time points.
So I'm just saying, well imagine I've got
24 independent people.
And they're each measured at a different
time point.
So I'm going to run this.
And the long form of the data to achieve
that, I'll just show you the code here so
you can see what the model is.
I am putting in time as my categorical
predictor, my outcome variable is score.
And I have no you know again, I am
assuming 24 independent observations here.
This is going to compare the means from
each time point as if they
were independent samples, so this is
analogous to using a two sample t-test.
When a paired t-test would have been
appropriate.
It's going to result in a loss of power.
So here's the, the incorrect, the one-way,
incorrect one-way ANOVA.
And let me show you what we would do.
So again, this just, is just doing an
ANOVA like we reviewed last week.
So I've got my four time points.
And I would calculate the mean for each
time point.
And I've calculated the overall mean,
okay?
So if I add up 31 plus 24 plus 14 plus 38
plus 25 plus 30 divide by 6 I get 27.
If I add up all 24 observations and divide
by 24, I get 27, and so on.
I would then calculate the sum of squares
between time and
the sum of squares within time.
And the way we would do in an, a regular
ANOVA.
So I calculated this sum of squares
between times.
So, for example, the mean for the first
time but it was actually 27.
That's equal to the mean for the overall.
So, 27 minus 27 squared would be the first
element of the between time variance.
Then I would calculate, I would subtract
the 28 from time point 2,
minus the 27 overall.
Then I take the 22.33 that's the average
for
time point 3, subtract the mean overall.
And finally, the 30.83 minus 27, square
that.
So this would give me the sum of squares
between times.
That when you calculate it out comes out
to be 224.79.
How would I calculate the sum of squares
within?
This is a good review.
So the sum of squares within.
Again, think of the times just as groups
here.
So I would take each individual.
I would compare their value at time point
one to the overall mean for
time point one.
So for example, 31 minus 27 squared.
24 minus 27 squared.
14 minus 27 squared.
And so on.
I'm going to add up all of those squared
differences, and
we're comparing each person to and each
time point to the, the time point mean.
So 29 minus 28 etc.,
The way you would normally calculate a sum
of squares within.
So that represents the unexplained
variability, and
that comes out to be in this problem
676.17.
If I add those up, I get the total
variability here which is
about the total sum of squares, which is
about 900.
So when I ran this in the computer I
actually get my ANOVA tables out and
we can look at the results.
So my total sum of squares is about 900.
My sum of squares error, unexplained
variability is 676.
My sum of squares due to different time
points is 224.
I can then calculate an F statistic and a
P value.
The P value comes out to be out 0.117.
All right so that's the incorrect way.
There's something we haven't accounted for
here, which is the fact that we have
different subjects in the dataset.
So there is.
I'm now going to do this the correct way,
running a repeated measures ANOVA.
And basically what's going to happen here
is that we're going to explain away some
of this unaccounted for, this error
variability.
This sum of squares error or sum of
squares within.
Which was 700 and, 676.
That's going to be reduced by accounting
for
the fact that we have the same subjects.
We're going to account for the differences
between different subjects.
Almost as, as if subject was itself a
grouping variable.
So we're going to end up reducing some of
this variance.
If you reduce the unexplained variability,
your P values are going to get smaller,
right?
So we, we can explain some of the
variability by just the fact that we
have different subjects in the data set.
So let me now show you how you would
incorporate that,
here's the fast code to do this.
So how do we now do this if we're actually
doing this out by hand?
So the sum of squares between time stays
the the same.
We already calculated that.
That's where you compare the mean for each
time point to the overall mean.
But now we are going to additionally add a
sum of squares between subject.
So how do we do that?
What you can recognize is that you can
calculate a mean value for
each subject and I've done that already.
For example, subject one, over all four
time periods,
averaged over all four time periods, their
depression scored was 25.25.
Subject two's average was 26.
Subject three's average was 23, and so on.
We can calculate a sum of squares between
subject then.
Again, kind of think of subject as being
its own grouping.
A lot is explained by which subject you
are.
So I'm going to take the mean for subject
one, and
I'm going to subtract it from the overall
mean, square that.
And then I'm going to do the same thing
for
subject two and subject three, and so on.
So I've done that down here.
So, subtract each subject's individual
mean from the overall mean, square those,
and add them up.
And then I have to multiply by 4 because
again I need to end up with
the total number of sum of squares being
24.
When I add that up I get a value of 276.
So, 276 out of that original 676
unexplained sum of
squares was actually due to the fact that
we have different subjects.
So my sum of squares within is going to
get reduced.
Remember, the sum of squares always totals
up to the same 900.
So now that I've explained some of the
explained, unexplained variability.
I've now explained it by which subject you
are.
I get to subtract that away.
So the unexplained variability has now
gone down from about 676 to below 400.
So much less background noise.
Much less background variability.
So when we then get the results of this
repeated measures ANOVA,
what you'll see is that you've got the
224, that's the between time.
But we're going to only compare that to
the error of 399.
The rest is a, is the between subjects
difference.
I don't have that shown on this slide.
But the between subjects, we saw, was
about 276.
So the total is still about 900.
But when I compare the between time sum of
squares,
now to the background variability.
And I calculate my mean sum of squares by
dividing by the degrees of freedom and
then calculating my F value,.
My P value gets smaller.
And that's what we would expect when we
properly account for the correlation here.
With a time comparison is a within person
comparison.
So when we properly account for
the correlation, we would expect the P
values to get better to get smaller.
Now there's a little complication with
this particular data set.
In that I've already alluded to the fact
that,
we seem to violate compound symmetry here,
that assumption of compound symmetry.
And at least in SAS, you get a, a measure
that helps you to evaluate whether or
not you've met compound symmetry.
You get two, what are called epsilon's
here.
Slightly different versions of this test.
So you get a value, and
if this value is equal to 1.0 that would
mean compound symmetry is met.
If these values are very far from one that
would indicate that you
have some violation of compound symmetry.
We kind of already know that we violated
compound symmetry here because we looked
at the correlation matrix and the
variances.
At different time points and
we looked pretty much like we violated
them, that assumption.
If you violate the assumption of compound
symmetry, there are ways to correct for
that, so these two additional P values you
see pictured here.
Are difference statisticians ways of
adjusting the P values for
that violation of compound symmetry.
And you can see that it makes the P values
get higher.
And this is sort of analogous to, if you
remember back to when we did t-tests.
We had the choice of using the unpooled
variants or using the pooled variance.
The assumption for the pooled variance is
that we had homogenized variances.
If the, the variances in the two groups
were similar,
it is okay to pool them and the advantage
was we got more statistical power.
Because we got to use all of the
observations to estimate a single variant,
so it improved our degrees of freedom
therefore decreases our P value.
If we had variances that differed between
the two groups we had to
use the unpooled variance.
And the cost of that was that the number
of people being used to
estimate either one of those variances was
smaller.
So we had less degrees of freedom, and
therefore you know we
have less statistical power, our P values
tended to be bigger.
So same idea here.
The compound symmetry is kind of like
assuming, using a pooled variance.
If we violate compound symmetry,
then we need to estimate individual
variances in correlations.
And that's going to cost us some degrees
of freedom,
it's going to make the P values go up.
So in this case I'm probably going to
choose this G-G value.
It turns out to be 0.13 at the end of the
day.
So for this data set, this small data set
of just six people.
There does seem to be some difference in
time point three compared to
the rest of the time points.
But it wasn't quite enough to trigger,
statistical significance here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]