In this next module, I'm going to tell you
how to test the linearity assumption for
continuous predictors in Cox regression.
When we talk about logistic regression, we
spend an awful lot of time talking
about testing, whether or not continuous
predictors were linear in the low jet.
And this is exactly analogous to that.
We're going to have a linearity assumption
in the log hazard that we have to test for
continuous predictors.
Why is that?
Remember, what is our model here?
We're modeling the log of the hazard rate
is equal to the log of
some baseline hazard rate, which we're not
bothering to estimate.
Plus, betas and predictors.
Some combination of betas and predictors.
We are assuming a linear relationship
between x and the log hazard,
just by modeling it this way.
So, for example, if I was to put age in my
model and I fit a beta for age,
I am then assuming that age actually has a
linear relationship with the log hazard.
I've modeled age as a linear term in the
model here.
If I find that age doesn't have a linear
relationship,
I might need to do a quadratic term for
age or something like that.
We need to somehow be able to determine
whether or
not age has a linear relationship with the
log hazard.
Of course, if you've got categorical
predictors or binary predictors,
you're not going to have to worry about
this because binary predictors and
dummy-coded categorical predictors always
hit a straight line because two
points always make a line.
This is only for continuous predictors.
We can't directly plot the log hazard
against age, however.
So we're going to have to get at it with
some other types of plots.
So just to give sa,some data, example data
to work with here.
I've got some data from early in the AIDS
epidemic.
A 100 people, the outcome was time to
death.
The continuous predictor here is age.
There was also a binary predictor we
talked about in an earlier module,
IV drug use.
But of course, we don't have to test
linearity for IV drug use.
Only for age here.
So, one of the ways to test linearity in
the log hazard is to do a Martingale
residual plot.
So, you can take your continuous predictor
and
you plot it against the Martingale
residuals, but you want to plot it
against the Martingale residuals from a
model that actually doesn't include age.
That includes any other predictors that
you're going to include in
your final model, but excludes the
predictor that you're testing.
That's probably the preferred way to do
this.
So you plot age against these residuals
which your computer easily calculates for
you and will spit out for you.
I'm going to put on superimposed some kind
of smoothing line here to
see what's the functional form here.
And for age here, it looks pretty good.
It's not a perfectly straight line.
It's just teeny bit of curvy curviness to
this line.
But it's pretty close as real data go.
It would probably be just fine to model
age here as a linear term in the model.
By leaving out age out of the model, we
also can see that the risk,
the rate of death goes up here with age.
That tells us something about the
relationship between age and our outcome.
So that's the Martingale residual plot,
it's super easy to do and you're looking
for, to see whether or not there were
actually is a straight line relationship.
A second option that you have for
testing the, the linearity assumption is
to do some kind of a dummy plot.
And so what this is, is you're going to
take your continuous predictor and
split it into even-sized categories.
So like, quartiles, or quintiles, or
deciles, depending on how big your sample
is.
You're going to calculate the mean value
of your continuous predictor for
each one of those categories, you're
going to need those later for graphing.
Then you take the, that new categorical
predictor,
those categories, you enter them into a
Cox regression.
Cox regression dummy code it.
So a binary indicator variable for each
category.
You then are going to plot the betas that
result from those,
from that Cox regression model,
plot those betas against the mean value of
your continuous predictor for each bin.
This should roughly be a straight line.
If that's a straight line,
that would indicate that you've met the
linearity assumption.
If it's not a straight line, it tells you
that you may have to
model a continuous predictor as something
other than linear.
And so I went ahead and
did that with the data for age from this
sample of a 100 people.
So what I did here was I divided age up
into six categories.
You know I could have done ten here,
I could have done eight, I could have done
five.
I, I just choose, I just chose six
arbitrarily for illustration purposes.
So I took my, my 100 observations and
divided up, them up into roughly even
categories of six.
Of course, they're not going to be exactly
even, and for
each of those categories I calculated the
mean age for the category.
So for example, the youngest category for
age at a mean age of around, somewhere
around 28.
The second category for age had a mean age
rate around about 31 or 32, and so on.
I then set up a Cox regression model,
which contained in it a beta for age
group.
I set age group one as the reference group
here.
So, a beta for age group two, a beta for
age group three.
And these are, again, dummy coded
variables.
Beta for age group four, beta for age
group five and a beta for age group six.
In my model I can also include any other
ah,predictors that I
might be adjusting for in that model.
I then took those betas and plotted them
against the mean age for each category.
And that's all I've done here.
You can actually do this one by hand.
And it looks pretty good.
It looks like a reasonably straight line
fit here.
So again, it looks like age,
it's reasonable to model age as a linear
predictor in this model.
So for any continuous predictors,
you're going to want to check the
linearity assumption.
[BLANK_AUDIO]