So I've told you what can go wrong if you
treat competing risks as censored in the
Kaplan Meyer analysis.
But what's the correct thing to do?
When you want to do unadjusted analyses
like Kaplan Meyer and
you have competing risks how can you
handle it correctly?
So one very simple thing you can do is
just to do the Kaplan Meyer estimate but
focus only on event free survival and
what this means is you treat all the
competing risks as events.
So you're essentially modeling the
probability of having any of the events as
opposed to being censored.
And this would be something like, rather
than looking at cause specific mortality,
you just look at overall mortality.
You'll get the correct and valid estimate
that way.
The problem with that, of course, is it's
very limited.
There are cases where you really want to
know about a particular event
within that group.
So for example if you're looking at a new
cancer drug, you will want to,
may want to know specifically about the
effect, of of the drug on progression of
the cancer, and you may care less about
some of these other competing risks.
So what if you want to look at specific
risks?
Then you have to use something called a
cumulative incidence analysis.
And what this does essentially is Kaplan
Meier estimates the probability
of survivals.
The cumul, cumulative incidence analysis
instead looks at
the probability of failure, and by turning
it around like that
we'll actually be able to get the correct
estimates.
We're going to look at the cumulative risk
of failure for
each of the competing events separately.
But let me just do a little review of what
event-free survival would look like.
What do we mean by the Kaplan–Meier
estimate of event-free survival?
It's quite straightforward.
What we're going to do is just count all
of the competing risks as events.
And everything else is censored.
And do normal Kaplan–Meier estimates.
So let me review that here.
Because we're going to need the estimates
of event-free survival in
the calculation of the cumulative
incidences.
So it's worth me walking you through how
you calculate this.
This is also a good review of
Kaplan–Meier.
So what I've got here is I've got a simple
little data set, a made up data set.
And I've got six people in the data set
who had things happen at various times.
There are two outcomes, death from
melanoma and death from other causes, and
then of course some people are censored.
Let me just show you how we would
calculate the Kaplan-Meier estimate of
event-free survival.
So of course at time zero, everybody is
still alive, nobody has died.
So our Kaplan-Meier estimate of survival
probability is 100%.
Our cumulative incidence are, which is one
minus the Kaplan-Meier estimate of,
survival, is going to be zero.
0%.
So nobody has died yet.
So we don't have any, deaths yet.
At ten minutes into the study we had a
death from melanoma.
There were six people at risk at that
time.
One of them died from melanoma.
Five out of six remained alive.
So the Kaplan-Meier survival probability
at time ten is going to be five six.
Meaning the cumulative, the cumulative
chance of dying is one sixth,
one minus that.
At 20 months into the study, we have a
death from a different cause
other than melanoma, but again, all the
deaths are being lumped together here.
So, there were five people at risk at that
time.
Four out of five survived without dying,
in that interval.
So we are going to be multiplying four
fifths,
that's the chance of surviving that
particular time period.
But remember Kaplan-Meier estimates are
cumulative so we also have to multiply by
the chance of surviving up until then so
we are going to take the previous estimate
of survival five-sixths and multiply it
times this four out of five.
When we do that, we see that we get a
value of two-thirds.
Two-thirds probability of surviving.
The chance, the cumulative risk of dying,
that is one-third.
30 Months into this study, we are going
to,
we have at that point, We still have four
people at risk.
Three out of four survived that interval,
one dies from melanoma.
And we have to multiply that by the
previous estimate,
Kaplan-Meier estimate of survival, which
was two-thirds.
So take the three-fourths times the
two-thirds.
The threes will cancel, and we come up
with a value of one half probability of
survival up until 30 months, half chance
of dying.
At 40 months into the study somebody is
censored so
our probabilities do not change.
At fifty months into the study somebody
dies from other causes.
That's at depth, at that point, there were
two people left at risk.
One of them dies, one of them survives.
So the survival probability for that
interval is one out of two.
We multiply that with our probability of
our survival, up until now,
which was one half, we get a cumulative
probability of survival of one-fourth, so
the chance of dying up until then is
three-fourth.
The last thing that happens is a censoring
so none of our probabilities change.
So that's what our Kaplan-Meier
probabilities look like.
We can draw them on our typical
Kaplan-Meier curve.
See how that curve drops if you're doing
it in terms of survival.
Drops to five-sixths at ten and then drops
again to two-thirds at 20.
And this is not well drawn to scale but,
you get the idea.
Drops at 30.
Stays.
And drops again at 50 down to one quarter.
And then it looks something like that.
So not well drawn to scale, but it's going
to look something like that.
The cumulative incidents is just one minus
the survival curve.
That's going to start at zero percent.
And it leaps up to one sixth at ten months
into the study.
And then up to a third.
And then up to a half.
And again not well drawn to scale.
Scale but you get the idea, stays at a
half until we get to fifty months, and
then that jumps up to three quarters.
So something like that, again, not, not
well drawn, but you get the idea.
So three quarters, three quarters chance
of dying by the end of the study.
That's the Event-Free Survival.
And again, we're going to be using these
estimates in just a minute
in the Cumulative Incidence calculation.
So how do I do the cumulative incidence
calculation?
So first of all, the cumulative incidence
analysis separates the competing risks
from the event of interest.
So we're going to look at them separately.
We're going to calculate cumulative
incidence curve separately for each.
If there are no competing risks,
it turns out that this will be equivalent
to Kaplan-Meier methods.
We're going to focus on the failure
probabilities rather than
the survival probabilities.
That will allow us to get the math right
here.
And each event goes into a separate bin.
We're going to calculate a separate curve
for each event.
The reason that we can do the cumulative
incidence analysis, why this works, is we
have a property, which we had something we
learned about which said that the hazard
function, the hazard rate is equal to the
density divided by the survival.
So remember, all this means is that to get
the chance of dying in
a particular instance or in a particular
interval of time.
That's the probability of dying in that
interval,
divided by the probability of surviving up
until then.
We had this mathematical relationship
before.
So it's also true that the chance of dying
in any particular interval, that's
the density, the probability density, is
equal to the hazard times the survival.
Essentially, that's what we're going to be
using,
this little relationship, in calculating
the cumulative incident
We're going to calculate the chances of
surviving up until a certain time.
We're going to calculate the hazard of
dying within a given interval.
We're going to multiply those together.
That will give us the overall probability
of dying within a particular interval
We can take those probability densities
and
just add them up, and that will give us
the cumulative incidents.
Accumulative risk of dying.
So that's the general idea.
Let me just walk you through an example.
So using the same data, I've laid out the
chart already here.
What we're going to do we're going to look
at melanoma and
death from other causes separately.
So, we just calculated the event-free
survival probabilities.
So, let me fill those in now.
We just calculated these, so they should
be fresh on your mind.
We're going to need those in order to be
able to
calculate the cumulative incidences.
Then we're going to focus on melanoma to
start with.
So we're going to ask, what's the hazard
of melanoma?
So what is the change of getting a
melanoma death
if you've already survived up until now
out of everybody who's still surviving,
what's the chance that you die of melanoma
in the next interval.
So obviously that won't pertain to time
point zero, but
at time point ten we have indeed have a
death from melanoma.
There were six people at risk.
One out of six of them, had a death from
melanoma.
So the hazard out of everybody that was
still alive at that time The hazard of
dying form melanoma was one out of six.
The density therefore is we're going to
multiply the chance of
surviving the previous interval, so
we're actually going to be multiplying the
hazard times the probability of sur,
the event free survival probability from
the previous interval.
So we'll be multiplying the 1.0 times the
1 sixth here, so
the density here turns out to be 1 sixth.
The cummulative incidences were just
summing up the density.
So that's still 1/6.
We got to time point 20.
So now, we are going to say, alright.
In that interval, there was nobody who
died from melanoma.
So the hazard for melanoma in that
interval was actually zero.
So the melanoma density is also zero.
So we'd multiply zero times 5/6.
But that's just zero.
The cumulative incidence is we're adding
up the density so
that remains at 1/6 at 30 months of the
study we have another death of melanoma.
And so at that point there were one, two,
three, four people at risk.
One of them developed or died from
melanoma So
one out of four is the hazard, the chance
that if you made it up until now,
you're going to now die from melanoma in
this time interval.
The density therefore would be the
probability, the ongoing survival
probability previously, which was two
thirds times the hazard,
which is one fourth, we multiply those
together to get the density.
That's going to give us a probability of,
a density of one-sixth.
So a one-sixth chance that the, a person
would die in this interval, overall.
Kind of a marginal probability.
We can then sum that to the cumulative
incidence, which was that 1 sixth,
we add another one-sixth, we get
two-sixth.
So there was a two-sixth cumulative chance
of getting, of dying from melanoma.
Right here.
And now everything else doesn't involve
melanoma.
So the hazard of melanoma for the rest of
this is just zero.
So we just, the cumulative incidence
remains at two-sixth.
So that's for melanoma.
We then turn to death from other causes.
So the first thing that that happens is
the death from melanoma.
So there's no hazard of dying of other
causes.
So all of that remains at zero.
Then we can adjust from other causes at 20
month.
So at the point there were one, two,
three, four, five people at risk.
One out of five had died of other causes,
in that interval.
So those are out of everybody who survived
up until then,
that's the hazard of dying in that
interval.
We're going to multiply the hazard times
the previous the event
free survival probability from the
previous time interval.
So that's 5/6 times 1/5th which will give
us a value also of 1/6th.
So our cumulative incidents is now 1/6th.
We're adding up the densities to get the
cumulative of incidents.
Now we're going to go next thing that
happens is there is a death from melanoma,
so that doesn't change anything here, and
then the censored, that doesn't change
anything.
And, then we get another death from other
causes at the point at which there's two
people left at risk, so 1/2 would
be the hazard there out of two people who
survived up until now, one of them died.
so the hazard is 1/2.
We're multiplying.
By the event free survival probability
from the previous interval which was
also one half, so one half times one half
would give us one quarter.
And now we add our density.
We add that to the cumulative incidence.
So one-sixth, plus one-fourth.
Well, that's the same as 2 12ths plus 3
12ths, or 5 12ths.
And then, the censoring, of course, don't
change anything.
So, we end up with a cumulative
probability of dying of other causes
of 5 12ths.
Now, what's important here, is that the
overall probability of dying from
melanoma is 2 6th, the overall probability
of dying from other things is 5 12ths,
if you add that up, that's 4 12ths plus 5
12ths.
Which equals 9 twelfths which is also
equal to 3 quarters,
that's exactly the total probability of
dying from anything that we've got from
the event free survival analysis.
So this all adds up as it should.
Now let me just show you that if we did it
the wrong way things will not add up.
So now we're going to do it the wrong way.
That was the right way to do cumulative
incidence.
Now I'll just show you the wrong way to do
it just to show you
things don't add up if we do it the wrong
way.
So we do it the wrong way.
The wrong way of course is treating the
competing risks as censored and
just running regular old Kaplan–Meier.
So, I've done this here for the
Kaplan-Meier for melanoma specific death.
So, we start at 100%.
But somebody dies of melanoma at ten
months.
So, their Kaplan-Meier survival estimate
here would be 5/6.
One minus the Kaplan-Meier would
supposedly give us
the cumulative incidents.
But it's not going to be the right
cumalative incidents, as we'll see.
At 20 months, somebody dies from other
causes.
We're counting that as a censoring now.
So that doesn't change anything.
Thirty months, we get another death from
melanoma, so at that point,
there are four people at risk, so
three out of four survive without dying
from melanoma in that interval.
We multiply that by the 5 6ths.
We get a value of 5 8ths.
And then the one minus that is 3/8 and
then everything else stays the same
because there are no more melanoma events.
If we do the same thing for other death
The first death is a melanoma death, so
that doesn't change for other deaths.
That person just is counted as censored,
but at 20 months into the study,
then one there's five people at risk, four
out of five don't die from other causes,
one out of five dies from other causes.
So now 1 5th chance if we minus from the
Kaplan-Meier.
At 40 months, now it's a death from
melanoma, so we treat that as a censoring.
Nothing changes.
The censoring itself doesn't change
anything.
Then finally, at 50 months, we get another
death from other causes.
At that point,
there is one out of two people at who has
the death and one out of two who survives.
We're going to multiply that by our
previous Kaplan-Meier survivor probability
of 4 5ths This gives us a probability if
we multiply these together of 2 5ths.
And so, one minus that would be 3 5ths,
and that will continue until the end.
We could plot these in little Kaplan-Meier
curves.
We can plot those cumulative incidences,
and if we do that,
we'll see that we end up with something
that's a little funny.
Because it doesn't match the cumulative
incidence calculations that we just,
just calculated.
And you can see that if we add up the 3
8ths plus the 3 5ths,
that is going to give us something that is
not equal to 3 4ths.
That's going to give us 15 40ths plus 24
40ths which is 39 40ths,
so that's going to mean that the
probability of dying is almost a 100%.
That seems wrong because actually two of
the people here were censored And
clearly does not match the 75% that we got
from the event-free survival analysis.
And we can, you can, if you actually draw
this on a little graphic, so for
melanoma, I start at zero percent.
I go up to 1 6th.
And then I go up to 3/8ths.
If we compared that with the correct
calculation,
what you'll see is that the correct
calculation is in fact lower than that.
That was an over estimate of the
cumulative incidence.
And same thing if we look at the incidence
from other deaths.
It jumps up here to 1 5th and
then jumps up here to 3 5ths, and that
also is
an over estimate of the cumulative
incidents.
So if you compare that to the, the
cumulative incidence that
we calculated the proper way, you'll see
that that's, that, you know,
the proper curve is going to be lower than
that.
So that would be the wrong way to do it
and it shows you why you get the different
estimates and why the cumulative incidence
is the correct way to do it.
And just one more example,
this was another paperwork Somebody was
kind of illustrating this point.
So they're showing you here the
Kaplan-Meier method.
The incorrect method versus the correct
cumulative incidence method.
And this is the people who had kidney
disease.
They could either die while on dialysis or
they could get a transplant and
then they weren't at risk of dying from
dialysis, or
they could survive this is the event for
your survival meeting.
Neither of those things happened.
And you can see that the Kaplan–Meiers are
clearly wrong,
because, those three things have to add up
to a 100,
you know, 100% and two of the
Kaplan–Meiers add up to more than a 100%.
Well, obviously we can't have higher than
100% here.
So the correct analysis is the cumulative
incidence.
And you can see how off the Kaplan–Meier
estimates can be, as is illustrated here.
Now what about the multivariate situation?
I basically just set you up for the
univariate, the unadjusted situation,
we just want to look at basic
Kaplan-Meiers.
When we get to the multivariate case,
it kind of depends on what the point of
your analysis is.
If you care about absolute probability,
you are going to
get things wrong if you treat the
competing risks as censored values.
However, there's a lot of situations where
we're doing some kind of
explanatory analysis, and we don't really
care about the absolute probabilities.
We just want to compare, say the treatment
group to the control group.
It turns out that it's probably fine if
the absolute probabilities don't matter.
To just treat the competing events as
censored values in a Cox regression.
And the hazard ratios will probably be
reasonable.
But, keep in mind that if you're doing
some kind of predictive or
prognostic study and you're trying to
actually get those absolute probabilities,
treating the competing events as censored
will give you the wrong probability.
So if that's your goal, you need some kind
of more sophisticated model that is
going to take into account the different
competing risks.
One example of that is something called
the sub, subdistribution hazards model.
There are a couple of different ways of
handling that.
But you do need to think carefully if you
care about those absolute probabilities to
make sure that you get them right.
[BLANK_AUDIO]