[BLANK_AUDIO].
Welcome to Unit 9.
This is the final unit of the course, so
after this all you have left is the final
exam.
This week I'm going to introduce you to
the use of mixed models for
analyzing repeated measures data.
Last week we talked about the use of
generalized estimating equations for
analyzing repeated measures data.
This week, I'm going to take those same
data, and show you
how analyze them using a different
technique, called the mixed model.
The good news is that whether or
not you choose to analyze your data with a
generalized estimating equation, or
a mixed model, for most cases, you're
going to get fairly similar results.
The answer ought to be the same, even if
there are slight differences in,
say, the point apex, and the P values.
I tend to, if I've got a continuous
outcome, I tend to prefer the mixed model.
If I've got a discreet outcome,
I tend to prefer the generalized
estimating equations.
There are slight advantages to each of
those, for each of those cases.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Before we jump into the discussion of
mixed models,
I just wanted to point one thing out.
We have been mostly focusing on,
all of our examples have centered on
repeated-measures over time.
So, longitudinal data.
That's the focus of this course.
I wanted to point out,
however, that if you had a different kind
of repeated measure.
Where you had repeated measures over
conditions, rather than time,
that the general approaches to analyzing
the data would be the same.
So again, we've been focusing on you've
got the same subject
measurement measured at different time
points, like in a cohort study.
But what if you had a situation where you
had the same subject measured not over
time, but in different, say, experimental
conditions.
So imagine you did a study where you were
measuring people's brain activity in
the laboratory.
When you have them exercise, and maybe
when you have them drink alcohol, and
when you have them listen to music.
There is no time element there, but it's
the same person at different,
under different conditions rather than at
different times.
All the things we have talked about, where
we were talking about time,
can be easily adapted to the case where we
have different conditions.
And so what, how you would do that is that
rather than having a mean effect for
timing the model,
wherever we've been seeing time in our
models you replace that with a condition.
The condition will act sort of like the
time effect.
If you have different groups you'd have a
group effect, and you would also have
a group by condition interaction rather
than a group by time interaction.
So, you can just kind of go through the
code, and
replace wherever you see time, replace
with condition.
The only slight difference that your
going to have is that the correlation
structures may be different.
So when you have correlations over time,
it tends to be that the further and
further apart you get in time, the less
and less correlated observations are.
With conditions, there usually isn't some
odd priority structure that you'd expect,
some operating pattern that you'd expect
for the correlations.
So for that reason you're probably
going to end up choosing something like
an exchangeable, or an unstructured
correlation matrix rather than something
that you might choose when you were doing
time, like an auto-regressive one.
All right, now let me just give you a very
brief introduction to mixed models just to
set up the picture for you.
So recall that a couple of weeks ago we
talked about something called
a slope analysis.
So this is where we fit separate linear
regression lines for
each person based on their repeated
measurements.
And it was a two step process, so
we took each person's individual slope
from those individual linear regressions.
We stored those slopes, and then we used
those slopes for further analyses.
Well, in a way, the slope analysis is kind
of a poor man's mixed model.
So if you understood the slope analysis,
you're going to understand, the mixed
models.
the, drawback of the slope analysis is
that we
had to do it as a two step process.
But what if you could actually, in one
single linear regression model,
fit a separate linear regression line for
each subject?
That's essentially what a mixed model
does, and
I'm showing you the picture of that here.
So we had some data last week where I had
just six subjects, and
they had depression scores measured over
time.
I am showing you here the predictive
values from the mixed model for
those subjects.
And what you'll see, is that each subject
has their own,
linear regression lines, so there's a
predicted intercept, and
a predicted slope that's different for
each subject.
So we're getting subject specific linear
regression line.
Which is great, because this controls for
the, within subject correlation.
Now, if I were actually to ask you to go
out, and, accomplish this,
to fit subject specific linear regression
lines, your first instinct,
might be to say, okay, well, I guess I
could run a linear regression,
with my continuous outcome at my
intercept, and
then I could actually fit separate
coefficients for each subject, right?
If I want a subject specific intercept for
subject one, I would have to fit a beta
for subject one.
And then if I wanted a, a slope for
subject one, I could fit a subject one
times time interaction.
And then same thing if I wanted to fit one
for subject two.
And the slope for subject two, and I would
literally have to do this in the model for
every person in my data set.
Well, that would control for subject, and
give me subject specific effects.
However, of course there's an obvious
problem with this,
which is that you can see clearly that we
don't have enough degrees of freedom.
This model's just going to blow up,
because there's no way we can fit so
many parameters.
However, a mixed model kind of
accomplishes this in a clever way.
So rather than fitting a specific
parameter for each subject, or
two parameters for
each subject, which is clearly, we don't
have enough degrees of freedom for.
What our next model does instead is very
clever.
It says well, we can fit subject specific
intercepts simply by
assuming that those intercepts follow a
particular distribution.
We are going to assume that they follow a
normal distribution, and
normal distributions have only two
parameters, a mean, and a variance, so
we can estimate a whole set of
subject-specific intercepts simply by
estimating just the two parameters of that
normal distribution.
There'll be a mean intercept, which in
this case is going to fall
somewhere around here, and then there'll
be a variance for
the intercept, which will help us to
define, the subject's specific intercepts.
That's if the variance is represented by
the, different values at baseline here.
And we can do the same things for the
slopes.
We can define a distribution of slopes,
that again depends on only two parameters,
a mean and a variance.
If we fit that mean in the variance,
then we've got a whole set of subject
specific slopes.
And in this way, with very few degrees of
freedom is used,
we are able to fit subject specific
regression lines.
And therefore, account for the within
subject variability.
That's the general idea of mixed models.
[BLANK_AUDIO]