[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, I've been thinking that
it would be really useful, to walk you
through a real data analysis experience,
to show you how I would approach real data
from start to finish.
What are the steps you need to take?
What are things you need to think about
while looking at real data?
This module will obviously be, a
condensed.
The version of a real data analysis which
would take you a lot longer in real time.
And I thought it would be fun, to use as
the basis of this exercise,
the midterm dataset because you've all
just finished grappling with that data.
So, I've tried to layout all the steps
that you should take.
When approaching a real, data analysis.
I'm going to go through each of these
steps in turn as applied,
to the Academy Award winners data set that
you had for your midterm.
One thing that's really important to keep
in mind,
is that you need to document all of these
steps.
You need to document any changes you make
to the variables, any new variables you
create, any participants that you exclude,
even when you reformat variables.
What we're striving for here, is what's
called reproducible research.
This is the idea that, you should be able
to hand me the data set that you used,
to produce your paper as well as a piece
of code, and somebody else.
Should be able to run that code on that
data set and
come up with the, same numbers that you
have in your tables and figures.
And that's, kind of sounds like it should
be trivial, right?
If you have the data set it should be easy
to reproduce those numbers, but
in fact there are so many small decision
points and
steps that go into a data analysis it
turns out that that's not trivial at all.
You really need to precisely document that
step, so
that somebody could reproduce those
numbers.
So, I'm going to go again through, each of
these steps in turn.
I just want to point out that, [SOUND] the
analysis for the Academy Award winner data
set is an explanatory analysis, our goal
is to answer questions about etiology.
Does being a winner, have an effect on,
mortality rates.
Does winning an Academy Award have an
effect, on mortality rates.
This is not a predictive goal.
And, so, all of the steps that I have laid
out here, are specific to, when you
have explanatory [INAUDIBLE] analysis, if
you are doing a predictive analyses
trying to build a predictive model, a lot
of the steps would be the same.
But I will just point out that, the way
that you would build the final model
would be different, because the goal would
be to kind of find the model that was,
the most predictive so you wouldn't be
worrying.
So much about confounders and things like
that.
You would also be, performing some kind of
validation.
And we don't have to do that for an
explanatory model.
So, step 7, 8, and 9 would be different.
I just want to point that out.
[SOUND] The other thing I want to point
out is that I'm not going to spend so
much time, on steps 4, 9, or 10 in this
module.
That's because the midterm dataset didnt
have any missing data, as we'll see.
So you don't really have to do anything to
deal with it.
And you, therefore, it did not, it also
didn't have any outliers to speak of so,
we didn't need to do any sensitivity
analyses.
I also did not ask you, for the midterm to
create any professional looking graphics.
Which is because it's pretty hard to,
graphically display the time changing
groups.
[SOUND] So I will, not do much on 4, 9,
and 10 here.
But I'll just let you know that, for your
final exam, I will make sure to
have a data set that has missing data, and
I will be, sure to be sure asking you for
informative graphics, so that you will get
experience with those steps as well.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So the first thing you need to do when you
get a real data set,
is just to get the data set ready for
analysis.
And this is very basic.
You need to, make sure everything is
formatted and named appropriately.
You need to import the dataset into your
com, statistical analysis program.
Create any new variables that are just
basic derivations of other variables.
So, I gave you the dataset for, for this.
Exercise, as I just downloaded it right
from, the website.
The authors, who published the real
analysis of this data,
had provided the data all as in, in the
appendix of their paper, and
I just downloaded it and handed it to you.
I didn't, clean it up at all for you.
So this, represents kind of the thing that
you might get from somebody.
The, data dictionary, is very condensed
but, you know, the variables are mostly.
Self explanatory but,
they've stuck it in the dictionary right
at the top of this Excel file.
So, one of things you're going to have to
do,
is you're going to have to delete all of
this, before you load it
into your statistical analysis program or
you'll end up with all this garbage.
Also, notice that the way that they've
named variables, they have a lot of.
Question marks and equal signs.
I don't like those in my variable names
so, I'm going to get rid of those.
I'm just going to rename them in the Excel
file before I load, things into SAS.
And, so a little bit of clean up needs to
be done before I even input the data.
So, before I imported the data I, my file
looked like this.
I, didn't do anything other than, delete
that garbage at the top,
the data dictionary.
And, I changed a few of the variable names
to get rid of things like, equal signs and
question marks, so you'll notice that some
of the names here are different from
what we started with, tried to make the
data a little more informative.
I then imported, the data into SAS and
of course, you would import into whatever,
statistical package you were working in.
Once I had things in SASS I did a few
other steps.
A few other basic steps to get ready for
my analysis.
So, one of the things is that there were
four variables.
Born in the USA, born white, name change
and
genre drama, that were, originally coded
as yes, no variables.
They're character variables.
And that's perfectly fine to leave them as
yes, no character variables.
I just happen to prefer, when I deal with
binary variables,
I prefer them to be coded as 1,
0 so that I can treat them as numbers,
rather than as character variables.
I find that a little bit easier.
So, what I went ahead and did with code,
was to re-code all the yeses to 1s and
all the nos to 0s for these four
variables.
And also to change it from a character.
To a numeric variable.
I also, as I was, bothering to do that
with code.
I thought, well, I might as well change
the variable names.
I got rid of the underscores.
I don't really like, underscores in my
variable name.
So, they're slightly renamed.
I then had to think about, since we're
doing a survival analysis.
What am I going to do, in terms of the
time variable?
How am I going to treat dates, and things
like that?
So, what I decided, for
the time variable for this data set, was,
everything was given in years.
And so, I decided to keep it in years, and
treat the years as numbers.
It was, would have been harder to treat
the year variable as a date/time variable.
Because we don't, w, date time variables
are in days, and
we don't really want things in days, we
can just keep it in years.
It's perfectly fine to subtract 1960,
subtract 1900 and
get that somebody was 60 years old and
just keep everything in, in numbers.
So, I've just kept the years in numbers.
I then, realized that I'm going to need to
use age since birth, as my time scale, so
this is looking at.
You know, total life time.
So, I'm going to be using age since birth
as the time-scale here.
And, that's actually an easy variable to
create, because time,
what I'm going to be calling my time
variable here,
is just going to be the age at either
censoring or at death.
So to create the time variable, I'm
calling it time,
because in survival analysis I'm thinking
of this as my time variable.
You could have named the variable age,
because it's equivalent to age.
So, to get this new time variable, all I
did was I subtracted the final year,
which was the year they were censored or
died.
I subtracted the, from that the birth
year, the year they were born.
That's going to give me their age in
years, and that is my time scale.
So, I just have to call that variable
time.
You could have also called it a.
Age.
I also, decided to create some other new
variables that I knew I was
going to need for this analysis.
So, the point of this analysis was to
compare people who won academy awards,
to people who were only ever nominated, to
people who were never even nominated.
So we call those groups the winner group,
the nominee group and the control group.
So, I thought right from the onset I knew
I was going to have,
to have a variable that denoted those
groups.
In the original data set.
The, authors had recorded the number of
wins.
I don't really care how many times you
won,
that wasn't, important to this particular
question that we were asking.
I really just need to know if you were a
winner at all, or not.
So, I just changed, I made new variable,
winner.
And I said if your wins, if your number of
wins are greater than 0,
then you are a winner, you won an Academy
Award.
If you number of wins was 0, then you are
not in the winner category.
I created another variable with that
whether or
not you were ever nominated at all.
And so, I said, if your nominations,
again, was more than 1.
1 or more, more than 0.
Then you're a nominee.
If it's, if you were never nominated, then
you're not a nominee.
I made another category that was, only
nominated,
which separates, the winners out of those
who were nominated, but never won.
So, if your nominations was greater than 0
but,
your wins was equal to 0, then you're in
that nomination only category.
I know I'm going to need that group
separated as well.
And, then finally I, defined a control
group which is if you're not a nominee and
you were not a winner.
If you never were a nominee, you never
won, then you're in the control group.
So, I made those new variables because I
knew I was going to need those for
a lot of the analysis.
So, once you've prepped you data set got
it ready for analyses, then you are going
to go through and check the data set,
check all of your variables to check for
errors, outliers, extreme values and for
missing data.
So, I just did a simple thing for this one
I used the proc,
means option which just asks for summary
statistics, I specifically, wanted to see
the sample size for each variable, because
that will tell me about missing data.
As well as the minimum and the maximum to
make sure, to see whether or
not I have any outliers.
By the way, in SAS, if you do variable
_all_ SAS, will just do this for
all your variables and you don't need to
write them out separately.
So, this was a pretty small dataset.
There's not so many variables.
So, I just used that all command.
So, here is all of my variables, in this
dataset.
It's going to give me statistics on the ID
number because I asked for
all the variables, that's not really very
important.
But, we can kind of go through each one of
these variables, and
first thing you notice is that, there's no
missing data in this dataset.
So the, authors who prepared the dataset
filled in all of the values.
So, for example, you see that for every
variable there's 1670,
so that means that, that none of those
variables are missing anything.
There's two variables that have, 239 and
768, those are the ones that
only apply to the winners or to the
nominees, so that's why those have fewer.
That's not missing data.
But, you see that, there's no missing data
on it.
Any of the variables.
So, that's nice to know.
That means we're not going to have to work
too hard in terms of missing data.
I then went through and looked at all the
minimums and the maximums.
So, I'll just point out a few here.
So, the birth year, the earliest birth
year was 1858.
The latest birth year is 1988.
That's very important to know, and
understanding these data.
The, final, the last possible time to
event was 2001.
That's because these data were collected,
in 2001.
They were collected or at least updated in
2001,
that's the last year we have information
for.
It's probably great for somebody, time for
somebody to update this data set again.
So we can reanalyze these, but that was
the last data set that we have available.
So that everything ends at 2001 and
you are censored there if you haven't died
by then.
You can see that all the binary variables
go from 0 to 1 there's no weird,
values in here.
If you go down to time, this is, their
ages at death or
censoring, and they range from 13 to 104
those are reasonable ages.
We can also look at the, years in which
people were nominated and
won Academy awards, those ranges look
reasonable.
All of these look, reasonable.
Somebody ac, actually was in 290 films.
That's not unreasonable over a career.
You could be in 290 films.
So, everything looks pretty good there.
I then, went through and checked, the
variables for consistencies.
This is checking one variable against
another.
To see if there are things that are, that
just don't make sense.
And so, for example, there's a lot of
years here.
If somebody was you know,
died before they were born, that would be
an example of an inconsistency.
I went through and found [INAUDIBLE]
inconsistencies I could think of and
went through and flag, any person who had.
A yes on any of these if statements.
So, for example, if there's a variable
fourstar films, if you made more fourstar
fil-, more fourstar films, than you made
films overall, that would be impossible.
If you were born after you died or
after you were censored, that would be
impossible.
If you, had won an Academy Award but never
been nominated, that would be impossible.
I, I'll kind of go through just some of
these.
If you were a control, but you have a year
for your no, first nomination or
first win, that would be impossible.
If you, made your first film after you
won,
after you won your first Academy Award,
that would be impossible.
If you made your first film after the
first you,
after you were, you were nominated, that
would be impossible.
If you were nominated after your first win
that would be impossible.
So, all of these are the sort of things
that would make, not make sense.
If something's going wrong, there's at
least some error in the data, for
all of these, if these, if these are
flagged.
If you have more wins than you have
nominations,
all of these kind of inconsistencies.
So, I just made one variable called a flag
variable.
I set it equal to 1 if any of these came
out true for for
an observation in the data set.
And then, I printed out everybody who had
[SOUND] flag equals 1.
So, when I did this,
I came out with six people, where the flag
variable was equal to 1.
[SOUND] And I just printed these out.
These are the ones that meet, any of those
inconsistencies on the previous slide.
I came out with six.
Great example, person with ID 908 if you
look, their first film was made in 1989.
But they were first nominated, for an
Academy Award in 1985.
Well obviously, one of those dates is
wrong.
If we were, doing a real data analysis, we
might go back and
try to figure out, for 908, where the
error lies, and to fix the error.
We can go back and do that.
I don't know who person 908 is, so for
the purposes of the midterm, I just said
to exclude these kinds of inconsistencies.
1192 was again, the first film occurred
after they were first nominated.
There's some error in there.
1430.
Let's see, there were, they, their first
win year was in 1952, so they first one
an Academy Award in 1952, but they weren't
first nominated until 1960, so
that's an inconsistency, and 1521 they had
their first, film was made, in 1988,
but they were nominated first way back in
1971, so those are all inconsistencies.
Now one of them, one of the instances,
inconsistency, that came up 1075,
if you look in the fine print of, the
paper that was published in 2006 where
the authors reanalysed, this data set,
they actually said they excluded this
person and the reason is if you look at
the date of death they died in 1994 but
they were first nominated for an Oscar in
1995,
when I found that inconsistency i thought
to myself that it might be possible.
For somebody to die between the time that
a film is made and
before they are nominated because you can
be nominated posthumously after you die.
So I went and googled it just for fun, I
actually googled you know,
deaths after being nominated for an Oscar
after death, and you
can find a Wikipedia page which lists the
people who were nominated after they died.
There aren't that many, and
I was actually able to find that there
indeed was a person who died in 1994 and
was nominated in 1995 after they died and
who had been born in 1953.
So I am pretty certain, that this
represents Massimo Troisi who was in
Il Postino, and therefore that that's a
real data, that all that data is real, and
there's nothing wrong with it and
therefore, I did not exclude that, that
person.
All right, the next thing you're going to
want to do,
in your data analysis is to spend a lot of
thing studying your variables.
And you can see that in this whole
process,
we are spending a lot of time on very
basic things about the data.
I haven't gotten at all yet
to the question of you know, do winners
live longer than nominees.
So I'm going to ask for univariate
statistics and
histogram and explore those for all the
variables in my dataset so
that I have a firm understanding of what
these variables look like.
again, you can insass, you can do
histograms and
basic statistics with proc univariate if
you ask for underscore all underscore,
you get all the variables, and since there
aren't that many here.
I went ahead and got all of the
histograms.
This is the histogram for ID.
It automatically comes up, because I've
asked for all.
But it is interesting to just note that
the ID numbers get restarted at 2,000 and
at 3,000.
That probably has something to do with the
fact that this data set was
updated at one point.
Those may be the, the updates.
So, even there there's something
interesting.
Here are some histograms for those binary
variables.
This was country of birth, whether or not
you where born in the U.S.A or not.
And what you can see is that,
interestingly, I mean a,
about 70% of people where born in the
coun, in the U.S.A, but there
are almost 30% of actors and actresses who
where born in another country.
We're tracing, you know, Back to the 1800s
and things.
So that's very interesting.
And that might affect the mortality.
In terms of race however.
That they're almost all were white.
There's only a very small percentage of
people who were races other than whites,
who were nominated or actors and actresses
in that time.
So, the variable, born white.
Whether or not you were, of white race.
It might be interesting.
It might be related to longevity.
But, you have to keep in mind that the non
white group is very small here.
gender.
So this is the males, and this is the
females.
You'll notice it's fairly well balanced.
But there were, in general more men in
films.
Especially, in the early days.
And then we have this variable, name
change.
Actors and actresses sometimes change
their names.
I didn't do a heck of a lot with this
variable.
There was a fair number of people who
changed their names.
I don't think that that would be related
to mortality, however.
Then this is, these are the, this is the
distribution of the birth years.
So, again, we went from 1858 to 1988,
where the birth years,.
And everything in between.
Final is the year of death or censoring,
and since censoring ha,
the last time we updated the data was in
2001, we have a huge bar at 2001,
just, that's just the last date of
censoring from, for most people.
How many people died or
were alive, this is died or alive, so this
is the alive bar.
And this is the died bar, died here is the
outcome of interest.
And what's nice is that it's pretty well
balanced with survival analysis you
want to make sure you have enough events
and enough censored so
you now, one category sin too small and we
have a reasonable balance here.
This variable films, this was the number
of films that an actor or
actress has made in their career at least
up until 2001.
And you'll notice that that's a highly
right skewed variable.
This is the number of four star films.
And also highly right skewed, which makes
total sense because some people make
only a few films and there might be people
who make upwards of you know 290 films.
Just keep in mind it's a right skewed
variable.
The variable weins which the author has
had originally coded gave you
the number of times people had won, well.
You know, there are some people who have
won two or
three Academy Awards, but that wasn't,
that's very small person.
That wasn't really important for the
analysis that we were doing.
So, I just collapsed it, you either won or
you didn't won.
I already showed you how I made that new
variable.
Same with nominations then.
Nominations is pretty interesting that
some people have won, you know, 11 or
12 nominations.
But again for the purposes of this
analysis I just col,
collapsed into, you were nominated, or
your weren't nominated.
For first film year, this is the year that
somebody fist made a film,
it ranged from 1908 to 1998.
1998.
First win year was from 1928 to 2000.
First nomination year was from 1929 to
2001,
just good to keep in mind those dates.
Time here is, also, I could call age.
So, just make sure that the ages are
reasonable.
They range from about 13 to 104, and looks
fairly reasonable.
So, that just gives you a sense of all of
the different variables in your data set.
You would next want to deal with missing
data.
We don't have any missing data here.
So, you get out of that step for the
purposes of the mentor.
Your next one going to want to understand
you've looked now at the univariate
distribution, one variable at a time.
But you're next going to want to
understand,
how different variables related to one
another in your data set.
So, you want to explore simple
relationships.
And you might want to explore the basic
assumptions, kind of building towards
the fact that we're going to be doing Cox
regression here, for example.
So we can test some of the basic
assumptions of Cox regression.
So in this step, I'm going to look at just
what variables are related to each other.
You need to kind of understand which
variables are highly correlated.
Which variables go together.
I would do, just doing some basic
bivariate analyses.
And I'm also going to test here in just
one, kind of, one variable at a time.
Do we need proportional hazards and
linearity assumptions?
To explore what variables are related to
one another, a very simple, quick, and
dirty thing you can do is just to run a
correlation matrix on all of
the variables.
And to contain that a little bit what I
did in CAS was to say, to give me for
each variable in my data set the top three
variables that
are most correlated with that variable.
So, I asked for example, for gender.
What variables are most highly correlated
with gender?
And what my computer spit out was, the
number of four star films you have made,
the number of films you had made, and your
birth year.
Well I could get this for all of the
variables in the dataset.
Asking for just the top correlations keeps
the matrix a little bit more readable.
And we can study this, and get a sense of.
What potential confounders, what things go
with what,
what things are highly overlapping.
So for
example it's interesting to note that the
men in this status that made more films.
That's probably because there were more
men in film early on.
They are getting more jobs than the women.
And remember, this data set traces back
you know, quite far.
And, other things that in-, int-,
interesting is that the men tend to have
earlier birth years, again that probably
has to do with the fact that early on,
there were probably were only mostly men
in film, so
their birth years tend to be earlier than
for the women.
So, just keep that in the back of your
mind.
Birth year, is very highly correlated with
your year, the year of first film,
and the year of first nomination and the
year of first win.
Well that makes total sense.
Right?
If you were born in 1858, your first film
year is going to be much earlier,
than if you were born in 1980, because of
course you are hitting 20 or
30 years of age if you were born in 1858,
you're hitting, 20 or 30 years of
age in the, you know, the late 1800s and
even before there were films available.
But these are highly, highly correlated.
So you notice that first film year and
birth year have a correlation of 0.93.
Essentially.
Those variables are the s, are measuring
the same thing.
What that's going to tell me, is that I am
not going to bother putting first film
year, first nomination year, or first win
year as predictors in my model.
Because they're just, there so correlated
with birth year.
And birth year obviously is going to be a
good predictor of mortality and so
I'm just going to stick with birth year.
I'm pretty much going to ignore there,
these other variables for the rest of the
analysis.
We keep, the setting the more films you
make the more four
star films you're likely to make.
That makes sense.
The more films you make the, the earlier
you start in making films.
The correlation there is negative, that
makes sense.
The films you make the older you are
because the older you
are the longer time you've had to make
films.
A lot of these makes sense, but you can
look through these carefully and kind of
come up with things, you might not have
expected or might not have thought of.
I won't go through all of them.
I then went and did simple Kaplan Meyer
statistics on all of my predictors,
to see what variables are related to
death.
So starting with birth year, I'm expecting
birth year to be related to death and
indeed it looks pretty related to death.
So I broke birth year up into the lowest
26th percentile, the midi,
the middle 50th percent, and the highest
75th percentile.
Just to have something to plot on the
Kaplan-Meier curve.
However you break it up, it's going to
look pretty predictive.
The p-value from the log-rank test is
highly significant, and you
can see that indeed, if you were born in
later that's the gre, later years that's
the green line, versus if you were born in
the earliest years, that's the red line.
You definitely had worse you had better
survival if you were born later and
you have much more survival, if you're
born in the late 1800s.
That makes terrible sense, medicine has
changed of course.
Longevity has change.
also, gender is another one we would
expect to be a good predictor.
And men obviously, generally live less.
They have a less shorter expected lifespan
than women.
So in, I mean, that bears out in that
dataset.
If for some reason you did this analysis
and
that didn't bear out, that should be a
clue to you, that's somethings gone wrong.
Because women, we know, do live longer
than men.
And, indeed that bears out here.
That p value is highly significant.
So I know that probably, any final models
I build are going to include these two
predictors, because they're just at face
value, obviously related to mortality.
[INAUDIBLE] explain some of the other
variables.
So if you were born in the USA versus born
somewhere else.
That also, if you're born in the US,
you do have a little bit of a survival
advantage.
It didn't quite reach statistical
significance in the log-rank test but
it does look like there's some difference
there.
Especially in the early years.
White race have,
there was only a very small few number of
people who were not white.
So you can see that the red line here, is
very, represents very few people.
But you can see there is some [INAUDIBLE]
survival advantages you might expect for,
for white, versus non white.
Again, the log-rank test doesn't quite
reach statistical significance,
because of the small sample size here.
They have this variable whether or not you
were in drama, the genre of drama or not.
Do you're actor in drama films?
It did, you know, almost reach statistical
significance, but
you can see that the curves, the people
in,
in drama did slightly better in survival
than the people in other films.
There's a slight difference between those
two curves.
The drama being here.
Non-drama.
The difference between those curses are
pretty small though so
at most it will only have a small effect
on mortality.
Now very interestingly if you dump the
number of films and
the number of four star films, which of
course are related,
into [INAUDIBLE] statistics, you see a
huge effect.
So I again, I just divided things for the
purposes of [UNKNOWN] into the lowest
26th percentile, the middle 50 percent,
and the highest 75th percent.
It doesn't really matter how you chop
those up,
as long as you have big enough categories.
So here are the people who made lots of
films.
The top 75th percentile.
These are the less films, the lowest 25th
percentile.
Well wow, you have a huge survival
advantage if you made a lot of films,
especially early on!
You were much more likely to live longer
right, so
those curves are really separated.
But what's going on there?
You have to think carefully about this
one.
So is it the fact that, if you make a lot
of films that somehow,
increases your longevity in that the films
cause you to live longer?
Of course, that's not the case, if you
think about this one carefully.
Right?
So what's happening here, is that in order
to be able to make 290 films or make
a lot of films over a career, you have to
live long enough to make that many films.
So we have an instance here of reverse
causality.
The longer you live, the more films you
can make.
So it's not that the films make you live
longer, it's the other way around.
Same with the four star films.
Both of those came out to be significant
in the log-rank test.
So we have to keep that in mind that, this
is,
most likely this artifact of reverse
causality.
I am not going to use these variables as a
result of,
as predictors in my model of mortality.
They're too confounded by this reverse
causality.
So I didn't do anything further with these
variables because of that.
And when I did the log-log plots, what you
see is kind of interesting patterns, and
a pattern that can tell you something.
So I did the log-log plots, for
this is the number of films, and this is
the number of four-star films.
And you get this kind of tell-tale
pattern.
So what you see is that the curves.
Start, at the beginning are far apart and
then they come closer and closer together
until they merge at the end of the plot.
The the end of the time.
Now remember, time here is age.
So, we're talking about ages on the x
axis.
So, what's happening here is.
This is a pattern that reflects reverse
causality.
What's happening here is that the people
who went on to make the most films they
have, they have a huge survival advantage
early on because it's like somehow ahead
of time, you know that they're going to go
on and make all of these films.
They have to survive long enough to do so.
So their not going to die.
Somebody who made 120 films probably
couldn't die when they
were 30 because they wouldn't have had
enough time.
So early on it look like they have a huge
survival advantage but later on,
they have very little survival advantage.
Because you now, once, even if you made 10
films but you made it to 70.
There's, you know, you've gotten rid of
that reverse causality at the later ages.
Everybody's made it that far, everybody's
lived that long.
So you see this kind of narrowing and
funneling, the plots all come together.
That's sort of a tell-tale sign that might
indicate reverse causality.
I then looked among the other variables
for violations of proportional hazards.
Now all of the variables so far that I've
been talking about,
are the ones that we're going to be
considering as potential con-founders.
But if there's any con-founders that
really do,
highly violate proportional hazard we're
going to want to consider that.
So, I look for violations of proportional
hazard, so this is the birth year, and
I do see some violation of proportional
hazards with the birth year.
So this is Schonfeld residual plot.
You can see that there does seem to be-.
It kind of starts up here and then it
comes down.
And it does seem to have some kind of
pattern over time.
The log log plots also sort of cross over
time.
There is, they don't look nice and
parallel and
birth year is a good predictor here.
So there does seem to be a violation of
proportional hazards with birth year.
That might make sense, because the
increase in your risk of your mortality,
going from, say, 1950 to 1951, in birth
year.
Might be very different than going from
1980 to 1981.
It's kind of, it would be kind of
surprising if that survival advantage.
For increasing your birth year was kind of
totally proportional and
totally constant over time.
Also for for born in the USA, the country
of birth, variable.
When I tested this one I saw evidence of
violation of proportional hazards.
So here's the Schoenfeld residual plot.
There's just a huge violation of
proportional hazards here.
It's clearly going down over time.
The log log plot is narrowing over time so
the two curves are coming together.
So there's pretty good indication of a
violation of
proportional hazards with this one.
This might have something to do with the
fact that if you were
born in a different country.
You know your, that,
that might have the most effect on your
survival early in your life.
And then eventually, if you're living in
the US, making films in the US for
a long time any differences due to your
birth country might wash out over time.
So, there's less of a difference as you
get older in, in your mortality risk.
But those are, I, I tested proportional
hazards for
all of the other variables and except the
main variables of interest.
And none of the other ones seem to have a
major violation of proportional hazards.
But birth year and born in the USA are
important enough,
that we're going to want to kind of
consider that violation later on.
There was only one continuous predictor
that I'm going to be really looking at,
at my data set, which is birth year.
That's the only one that I decided was I
need to move forward.
To further analysis.
So since I'm going to be doing Cox
proportional hazards regression,
I need to check whether or
not we are linear in the law of hazard
with this variable birth year.
So I did a Martingale plot on the left
here and
it looks like the line is nice and
straight.
Now, what's interesting is you'll notice
the scatter of dots down here,
you might wonder what that has to do with.
So this dot here represents for
example somebody who was born in 1899, and
they are still alive in 2001.
So there are 102 and still kicking and
they got huge
Martingale residual because you'd expect
them to be dead by now given their age.
All of these other people also represent
people who were born,
this is their birth here on the x-axis, so
these are the people.
Here who were born in very early years in
this study,
you know, close to the 1900s and have
managed to live a long life.
They're, they've, given their law, their
high age, they're expected to have.
And their early birth years, they're
expected to have died by now but they're,
unexpectedly, they've had an unexpectedly
long life.
You get this pattern here because you had
to have been born,
this dataset ends in 2001, so you couldn't
have lived a whole century unless you
were born in say 1901 or earlier.
And so there aren't, there, some people
born in later years.
Haven't had the opportunity to live that,
so you get this kind of funny pattern.
But the, the general line fit to these
data points looks nice and
flat I also did a dummy plot where I
divided into this is
birth year again, I divided into decades
of birth.
Ad I fit a cor a Cox regression model.
With mortality as my outcome, and
I took the betas from the dummy-coded
decade, birth decades.
And then it looks like indeed it's a
reasonably straight line over time.
It's not perfectly straight, but it's
pretty good as real data go.
As you go up in birth years your mortality
goes down and down.
If, you get better longevity obviously if
you were born later.
Looks nice and linear.
So I'm not going to worry about,
I can model this birth year as linear.
I then got to looking at some basic
descriptive statistics about the main
variables we care about here which is the
winners, nominees and
controls, comparing those groups.
This analysis in no way accounts.
For the fact that people are changing
groups.
So, this is very close to the original
analysis that the authors who published on
this paper in 2001, presented in their
original paper.
And, so what you'll notice is that indeed,
these are the people who won.
These are the winners.
These are the nominated-only group.
And it does indeed, look like there's a
survival advantage.
The p-value is statistically significant.
This is exactly what the authors published
in that original 2001 paper.
You have to think carefully, though, as
we've.
Talked about the,
if you live longer that gives you more
opportunity to win an academy award.
If you die when you're 30,
you're probably not going to have a chance
to win an academy award.
So we have another instance of reversed
causality and
you see that reflected in the log, log
plot.
So here's the log, log plot on the
right-hand side.
You can see that the curves look very
different early on and
then they kind of merge together by the
end.
Somehow we know where basically we're
grouping people by whether or
not they win from the day they are born,
and so we're, we essentially know that
they're going to survive longer because
they had to survive long enough to win.
And that's reflected in the log log quad,
this tells us we need to
model this as a time changing predictor as
I've talked about in other modules.
Oh, we get the same basic pattern when we
look at winners versus controls,
people who are never even nominated,
highly significant, same problem, same
issue.
interestingly, the nominees, those who
were only ever nominated.
Versus controls, we don't see much
difference.
So you don't, maybe there's not as much
reverse class because you can be
nominated as much kind of earlier in your
life.
A little bit of that same pattern in the
log log plot but
not a statistically significant difference
between those groups.
All right, so now I kind of understand
some basic relationships.
Basic assumptions that I'm going to need
to worry about when building my
final model.
Basic things that might be confounders and
that need to be included in that model.
Before I start building a final model and
testing the main hypotheses of my study.
I'm going to make a descriptive table.
You're always going to need a table one in
your medical papers.
So you might as well make that descriptive
table put it in
nice professional looking form with your
basic simple descriptive statistics.
That can also help you to inform your
final model building.
So here's the final descriptive table that
I came up with.
The one that you got for your midterm
might look slightly different.
But basically we're comparing.
We want to compare winners, nominees, and
controls.
For the purpose of this descriptive table
we're going to have to compare groups,
the static groups.
There's not going to be anyway to account
for people changing groups.
We're going to get our basic n's.
Make sure to always include your n's in
your descriptive table.
And then I decided to present the data as
medians and
interquartile ranges rather than means and
standard deviations.
Primarily because I had a lot of right
skewed variables.
And it seemed to me to just be more
informative.
To use the median in their quartile range
here.
For categorical variables, I obviously
used ns and
percents, as we would usually do.
so, you know?
There's some interesting things.
So male gender, for example.
Winners and nominees is pretty close to
50/50.
That's because there's a category where
actresses get to win and
there's a category for men so it is
reasonably even there.
However for controls there are a few bit
more men there, 56% men vs 44% women so
that's a little bit of a difference
between those two groups to keep in mind.
Interestingly the controls were more
likely to be born in the US.
A few more foreign actors and actresses
were in the winners and nominees.
Perhaps, that is because there is a
category for Foreign Films.
Most of everybody is white, as we already
noticed.
People, actors and actresses that were in
dramas were actually more likely to
both be nominated.
And more likely to win.
So dramas, I guess, are.
Dram, will get you a, a best actor or
actress nomination.
And win better than, you know, comedies,
and other types of films.
The birth years.
The percentages still living.
Well, more of the nominees and winners are
still living.
Potentially that reverse causality again.
Nominees and winners made more films than
controls.
The more films you make, the higher chance
you have of winning and getting nominated.
Winners made more four
star films as well.
For the year of first film, the year of
first nomination and
the year of first win for the purposes of
the descriptive table I thought it
would be easier to understand if I put
those in people's ages at first win,
age at first nomination and age at first
film.
As opposed to the years there, I thought
that was more informative so
I changed those to years.
So the winners had an average.
Age of first film of 25, same with
nominees.
It was a little bit later for the
controls.
They got into the game a little bit later,
and
only the winners got an age at first win.
So you see, you, you, you weren't winning
until you're about 40, in your 40s.
Where as you were nominated earlier in
life so
there's that difference and that you have
to
live longer in order to get to win an
academy award.
Notice though, I didn't bother to put p
values in my descriptive value,
one could argue that you could put the p
values in there,
I thought you could interpret this data
table without needing the p values,
if you put them in, it's fine, I just
decided I didn't need them there.
The next thing we are going to do is we're
going to test the main hypotheses.
Do the winners.
Live longer than the nominees, do the
winners live longer than the controls,
do the controls do the nominees only live
longer than the controls?
We're going to use simple models and
graphics to start with, and
just decide on how to model those main
predictors.
I'm not even going to worry about building
a final model yet,
just kind of start with the very simple
comparing those groups.
Now I already showed you that we clearly
violate proportional hazards with
these variables, therein.
We can, if we just think about the
problem,
there's gotta be reverse causality going
on here.
So it's not correct to just model those as
static groups.
Somebody is not a winner from birth,
they're a winner from the time at which
they win that award.
So we know already that we're going to
need time changing.
Variables here, so
I'm going to need to model the winners and
the nominees as time changing variables.
You're in the control group until you're
nominated,
then you're in the nominee group until
you're a winner.
So for the first comparison that I wanted
to do just comparing winners versus
nominees, and not the controls.
What we're going to do is we're actually
exclude anybody who's in control.
So, we're going to exclude individuals
until their age of first nomination.
We only want to compare nominees to
winners.
So, if you haven't yet been nominated,
you're out of this analysis.
So, you're not included in the likelihood.
So, I'm going to exclude people until
their age of first nomination.
And then, I'm going to treat people as
nominees until they win.
So, some people will be nominated and
never go on to win.
Some people will be nominated and go on to
win.
You're a nominee until you win,
if you never win you just stay a nominee
the whole time.
If you then win, you're treated as a
winner.
So, we're getting, we're going to put this
time changing predictors in.
I've shown you the code here in sass.
So basically I'm saying if.
I made a new variable on your age at first
nomination.
Your age at first win.
So age FN is your age at first nomination.
Age at first win is your age as age FW.
So if the.
My, I call the time variable.
That's your age here that, I called it
time.
So if the time is before you're first
nominated, then for
the, this new, this variable I'm naming is
winner, you get a dot.
That means missing data.
You're not included, cause you're in the
control group, and
we only want to compare winners and
nominees, so we're excluded up until then.
Otherwise, if time is greater than or
equal to the age of first nomination,
you've now been nominated, but you don't
have an age at first win.
That means you were never won.
Then of course, you, your, iswinner is 0.
So if you were only ever nominated, you
never won.
You wouldn't have an age of first win.
Then you are not a winner.
otherwise, if your age at.
If your, the current event time is after
you were nominated, but before you won.
Before your age of win.
Then you're still not in the winning
group.
However, if you have been nominated and
you also have won the time the current
event time is past your age of first win,
now, now you're in the winners crap,
group.
And I also added in here, I'm only looking
at people who were ever nominated.
So I excluded anybody who was only ever in
the control group.
Obviously if you were only ever in the
control group.
You never were nominated.
You never won.
So I just said where you were a nominee.
This is only includes people who were ever
nominated.
When I ran this out my hazard ratio that I
get is 0.803.
It doesn't quite make statistical
significance,
although there is a little protective
factor here.
Where winners seem to do a little bit
better.
I use then the same logic to compare
winners versus controls.
The difference here is that nominees are
treated as
controls until they are nominated, then
they are excluded.
So I, I, I will actually want to exclude
the nominated group only.
So you're, a control, up until the time
you're nominated.
If you're nominated but haven't yet won,
you're excluded from the analysis.
However, if you then go on to be a winner,
then you're brought back into the
analysis.
Winners also are treated as controls until
they are nominated, they're.
Excluded until they win and then they are
treated as winners after they win.
So I'm totally moving out the nomination
only category.
And that code is accomplished with the
same kind of logic here.
So now I am comparing winners only, only
winners to controls.
I get a hazard ratio of 0.84, p-value is
about 0.12.
Notice, I haven't adjusted for anything.
These are just my basic models.
Then I compare the nominees to the
control.
So this is, excluding anybody who is a
winner.
So nominees are treated as controls until
they're nominated,
then they switch groups and they're
treated as a nominees.
The winners can be in the control group up
until the time they're nominated,
then they're treated as nominees, but the
moment they win they're excluded,
because I want to take the winners out of
this analysis.
So, this could, accomplishes that.
For this one, interestingly.
The nominees versus the controls did a
little bit
worse in mortality just slightly above
one.
Alright, so now I kind of have established
the basic
relationships, this is an explanatory
analysis so
everything is around my mean hypothesis
that I'm trying to test.
I now need to build a final model
considering potential confounders.
So I want to identify confounders,
possibly interacting variables.
And some of the variables even if their
not clearly confounders, I'm still going
to include them in the final model just
for face validity like birth year and
gender probably no matter what those are
going in final model.
I'm going to put these together in a final
model,
I'm going to compare different models and.
See what effect that has on the point
estimate, the hazard ratio for
winning verses nominees.
So I will just kind of walk you through
what I did for winners verses nominees.
I the process was the same for the other
two comparisons.
But, basically we started when there were
no covariates in the model, but
I modeled winners versus nominees as this
time-changing variable.
I got a hazard ratio of 0.80.
When I then added gender and
birth year to the model, because those are
such strong predictors.
I know that those are going to be in the
model.
They're also potentially confounders as
well.
When I, added them to the model it didn't
really budge my hazard ratio much.
It went up, it attenuated the effect just
a little bit.
So, now we're at a hazard ratio of 0.82.
Not a huge effect, I'm still going to keep
those in the model just for face validity.
And they do change the point estimate
slightly.
now, I then considered all of the other
predictors.
Again, I'm not going to put the number of
films in or the number of four star films.
Because those are confounded by reverse
causality, I didn't bother with those.
I didn't put the year of first film,
because that's so closely tied to birth
year.
I tried all the other variables and so, so
things like whether or
not you were born in the U.S.A., whether
or not you're of white race.
White race didn't seem to be predictive,
it didn't budge the hazard ratio at all.
So I didn't end up in, including that in
the end.
I remember the fact that birth year and
born in the USA both showed violations of
proportional hazards in my earlier
analysis.
So I tried a couple of things to see
whether or
not accounting for that violation of
proportional hazards would have much of
an effect on the hazard ratio for winners
versus nominees.
So for example, I included born in the USA
birth year times time.
The interaction of birth year with time
and
the interaction of born in the USA times
time.
Those would account for the violation of
proportional hazard.
However, putting that in the model didn't
do a heck of a lot.
Now my hazard ratio is up to 0.83.
But it's still around the same.
Another way to account for the violation
of proportional hazards,
rather than putting a time by covariate
interaction in the model.
Would be to stratify on those variables.
Born in the USA is a pretty small
variable, so
I did try stratifying on that, it didn't
change the, anything too much.
When I stratified on birth decade I did
decades of birth,
you don't want to stratify necessarily on
each year.
Because there won't be too many people on
So I stratified on birth decade.
Rather than putting it in the model.
And then I included your gender, whether
or not you were born in the USA.
And this born in the USA times time, I did
a couple of different versions of this.
And it really didn't matter whether I
stratified that born in the USA.
Whether I stratified on birth.
Whether I included them in the model.
Whether, whether I put the time
interaction.
Really none of this changed the point
estimate much.
Stratifying on birth decade, I got a
hazard ratio of 0.81.
So basically we're bouncing around
basically the same point estimate.
That's nice because it really doesn't
matter too much what you include in
that final model.
the, the hazard ratio really doesn't
budge.
So then I ended up putting this together
in a final table where I
show this process a little bit.
I show an unadjusted, a minimally adjusted
and a fully adjusted hazard ratio.
And I did this for the other two
comparisons, as well.
So here's what I came up with for my final
table of hazard ratios.
In the unadjusted model for winners versus
nominees, it was 0.8.
For winners versus controls, it was 0.84.
For nominees versus controls, it was 1.07,
as we already saw.
When I adjusted just for gender and birth
year I get 0.82, 0.87 and 1.09.
Again, not changing much.
None of these are statistically
significant.
When I did a fully adjusted model where I
counted, I counted for
these violations of proportional hazards
for birth year.
And included born in the USA and
the violation of proportional hazards
there it attenuated things.
Well they're pretty similar they're,
they're about the same, just a little bit
different.
So all of this is saying that basically
there does seem to be a slight
advantage for winners versus nominee being
those who are only nominated.
But it's not statistically significant and
if it's there it's very small.
For winners versus controls it was even a
smaller advantage.
And interestingly for
nominees versus controls, it looked like
there was no advantage.
And again, none of these are statistically
significant.
So that was my sort of final model that I
presented as I mentioned there,
you probably will want, would want to for.
Most analysis do some sensitivity
analysis,
we might want to do some checks on this
model.
We can't check proportional hazards,
once we have a time changing variable in
the model.
So we've kind of already done that
proportion hazards checks ahead of time.
the, there's no graphics that we can come
up with that really model this well.
Because of the changing in groups of the
KaplanMeier curves don't really reflect
the changing groups.
So I didn't ask you to come up with any
final graphics, so
I, I, I had you kind of stop the midterm
at the final table.
And for the final example we'll, add some
of those steps such as
creating graphics that, that'll be part of
the final exam.
But that's a basic data analysis, sort of,
you can see a lot of
time gets spent on just basic data
cleaning and understanding the data.