[BLANK_AUDIO]
So up until now,
we've been dealing with data sets that
have had independent observations.
Basically different, unrelated people.
But what about the situation when you have
some kind of correlations in your data?
So maybe you've measured two eyes on every
person in your data set, or
you have sibling pairs.
Or maybe you've done a cluster randomized
trial, and
you've randomized different schools, to
different interventions, then the children
within each of those schools will have
some correlations with one another.
How do you handle those correlations in
the Cox regression model?
That's what we're going to talk about in
this module.
So again, up until now, we've been dealing
with tests that have assumed that we
had completely independent observations.
How do we deal with a situation where we
might have some kind of correlations in
our data?
So in this module, I'm going to tell you
about a very simple fix for
dealing with correlations in the data when
you want to do Cox regression, and
that is to ask for the variances for your
betas to
be estimated in a slightly different way
called the robust standard errors.
If you ask for
those robust standard errors, those
account for the correlations in your data.
And it's fairly simple to get those in all
modern statistical packages.
So, the fix is pretty easy to implement
here.
I'll just point out that there are some
more complicated models for
dealing with correlation.
We are not going to go into those in this
class, but
there's something called a frailty model,
for example, so
there are some more complicated models out
there.
But for a lot of simple cases, this simple
fix will do and so
that's what we're going to deal with in
this module, robust standard errors.
So, the robust standard errors if you took
HRP261 or
something that you saw before when we were
talking about dealing with
correlated data in the context of logistic
regression.
It's the same idea here.
We are going to ask for
our variances of our betas to be estimated
in a slightly different way.
And it's sometimes these robust standard
errors are also sometimes called
the sandwich estimator of the variance,
because if you look at the matrix algebra,
it looks like a sandwich.
And now and I just want to say that I am
trying to avoid going into any
matrix algebra or linear algebra.
I don't expect you to understand the
expressions that are up here unless you
had linear algebra in the past, but I just
want to show you what it looks like to
show you where this name sandwich
estimator comes from.
So basically in the matrix algebra
expressions,
you have kind of the same things on both
sides.
That's what we would kind of referred to
as the bread here.
And then what's important is the meat that
goes inside the sandwich.
And so what we put in for these robust
standard errors,
what goes in this formula here, is the
residuals from your model.
And the residuals from your model will
reflect if you have correlations in
your data, those will be reflected in the
residuals.
So there's a, a math expression that deals
with the residuals that
goes inside this sandwich here, and
that's the way in which we are counting,
accounting for correlations in our data.
If you simplify this formula by assuming
that you have independent observations,
you can then simplify this formula.
Then you'll get simplier estimate for
variates, but that estimate for
variates will be wrong when you have
correlations in the data.
And I don't want to spend too much time on
the math here but,
just to go a little bit further into the
formula.
For those, I'm assuming that everybody has
had Ordinary Least Squares regression,
just regular old linear regression before.
And somewhere in there you may not
remember, but somewhere in there you
probably encountered the formula that you
see on this slide.
So, if the case of ordinary linear
regression.
Just simple linear regression.
Got a line.
One data, we're just talking about one
line here,
with one predictor in the model.
Remember that the line is going to be,
become the best fit line.
But there's still going to be some
variation around the line.
So everybody will have an observed point
and then if you draw down to the point
that they're expected to have on the line,
that's called their predicted value.
The difference between the observed and
the predicted, the value on the line, is
called the residual.
And one of the assumptions of ordinary
linear regression you know, you probably
remember plotting the residuals and
looking for any patterns within the data.
If there's some kind of correlation in the
observations,
you might end up with a non-random pattern
of residuals when you plot them.
But the formula for the variance of data,
incorporates the residuals, but
it incorporates sort of an average measure
of the residuals.
We're assuming that this red of
variability around the line is
the same everywhere along the different
values of x.
So we estimate one variance of y around
the line,
and we assume that there's a single one.
That would not be a good assumption if we
had data where the observations weren't
independent, but this gives us a nice
simple formula for
getting the variance for beta, which you
see pictured here.
In fact, that simpler formula we can back
up a step and
there's actually a more general variance
formula where that comes from.
We can show that the more general variance
formula will simplify to
the simpler formula in the case that we
have independent observations.
So again, this is a sandwich estimator.
I'm showing that the bread, again, on both
sides here.
Don't worry about the details of this
formula.
But this is just a way of estimating the
variances for the betas in your model.
And I'm giving you the formula here just
for a single beta so
that we can avoid any matrix algebra.
Basically, again, the residuals are part
of this formula.
If you assume independence, that your
observations are independent,
then you can assume that there's sort of
an average distance from the line,
an average residual.
You can estimate this expression here as a
constant, and
you can pull it out of the summation sign.
When you'll, you do that, you'll notice
that this cancels with this, and
you're back to the simple formula that I
just gave you on the last slide.
So this will simplify down.
However, if we have some kind of
correlations in our data,
then it may not be fair to estimate the
residuals with a single estimate.
We may need to actually keep the formula
in this more general form, where we
multiply every person's individual
residual with their deviation from x.
So in this way, we are allowing the
residuals,
which reflect the pattern of correlation
in our data, to stand rather than
making any assumptions about the fact that
we have independent observations.
That's the general idea with the robust
standard errors.
It's a way to estimate variance that
accounts for correlation in our data.
So let's actually now just apply it.
Again, it's actually fairly easy to
implement.
I've implemented it in SAS here, but
it's easy to implement in all of your
major statistical packages.
To illustrate the effect of asking for
the robust standard errors, I'm going to
present two hypothetical data sets.
If you were in HRP 261, you saw a version
of these data sets already.
They're very similar to the two eye trial
data sets that I presented when we
talked about correlations in the logistic
regression model.
So, hypothetical eye trial one has a
situation where
researchers have assigned 50 patients who
have disease in both of their eyes,
to randomly receive drug in one eye, and
placebo in the other.
So there's a difference within a person in
what,
which treatment they receive in which eye.
Therefore you can do within person
comparisons.
The outcome here is time to improvement,
rather than just improvement yes or
no, I've now got a time to event outcome,
so
the outcome is the time to it, the eye
improving by more than 50%.
Some people will have that improvement,
some people won't.
Hypothetical eye trial two is basically
the same idea except we are randomly
assigning patients to have treatment in
both eyes, or placebo in both eyes.
And the difference here is that you can
only do between person comparisons.
You cannot do within person comparisons.
Hopefully you've you know enough about
correlated data,
have encountered it in the past, to know
that if you fail to account for
correlations, when you're dealing with
within person core comparisons,
like in hypothetical trial one.
Failure to account for
correlations there will mean that you
actually overestimate your p values.
The p values will be too high.
So you inflate your type two error.
For between person comparisons, when you
fail to account for
the correlations, you do the opposite.
Your p values come out to be too small.
And you have underestimated them, and
inflated your type one error.
And that's illustrated here.
These are some made up data sets where
I've got
some correlation between the eyes within a
person.
For eye trial one, where,
when we're comparing person within a
person because you
can compare the eye that's treated to the
eye that's got a placebo within a person,
I first ran a Cox regression model, where
I just ran a regular Cox regression model.
I ignored the correlation.
My predictor here is treatment versus
placebo.
And you'll see that I get hazard ratio of
1.775,
so indeed the treatment increases your
chances of improvement.
And it's statistically significant but the
p value is 0.02.
When I then correctly account for the
correlation by asking for these
robust standard errors, notice in the SAS
output it says Sandwich Variance Estimate,
because again, this is sometimes called
the Sandwich Estimator.
And it's the same thing.
I look and I get the exact same hazard
ratios.
So, this does not affect my point
estimate.
However, my standard error, which was
0.915 for beta, when I didn't account for
correlation, has now become smaller.
It's down to 0.735.
And as a result, my p values are also
smaller.
So the correct p value here is smaller,
than if you did not account for
the correlation.
So we've you know, you, you can increase
your statistical power by
correctly accounting for the correlation
in this situation.
For eye trial two, where we were doing
between person comparisons,
failing to account for the correlations
will make your p values overly optimistic.
So I first ran a clock progression where I
ignored correlation,
treatment versus placebo, the hazard ratio
here comes out to be 2.9.
This is a totally separate hypothetical
data set so
the point estimates are actually
different.
But, the p value here is highly
significant when I don't account for
the correlation, 0.0008.
When I correctly account for
the correlation using the robust standard
errors, you can see it again that it
says Sandwich Variance Estimate SAS, then
my hazard ratio is exactly the same.
This does not affect the point estimate,
but my standard error goes up.
So it went up from 0.31 to 0.36, and my p
value is actually higher.
So I went from 0.0008 to 0.003.
So they're both still statistically
significant but
you can imagine in a situation where you
might go from being significant to
non-significant, when you correctly
account for the correlation.
So, the robust standard error represent a
simple way to, to account for correlation.
It's simple to implement in the computer.
[BLANK_AUDIO]