[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module,
I'm going to give you a brief overview of
the various statistical tests and
strategies that are available for
analyzing repeated measures outcomes.
So there's a number of ways that you can
handle repeated measures outcomes.
The simplest thing you can do, is
essentially to not handle the repeated
outcome by simplifying it, collapsing it,
or ignoring it.
And you'll see that this actually fairly
widely done in the literature.
Probably because these tests have been
around longer, and they're simpler, so
people tend to feel more comfortable with
it.
So, for example, one strategy is you could
collapse that
repeated outcome measurement into a single
value.
So that each subject only has one value,
say by calculating a slope, or
a percent change or an average for every
person.
You can also just focus on one
measurement.
Usually we focus on the final measurement
because, you know,
often we care about what happens at the
end of the day.
So only compare the final measurement
between subjects.
Running say an ANCOVA, adjusting for
baseline differences, that's called an
end-point analysis.
So there's a number of ways you could
simplify the picture.
These methods of course, lose some
information because you
were kind of again simplifying or ignoring
the repeated outcome.
A second strategy which is also been
around for a long time, and
you'll see in the literature, is to use
some kind of repeated measures ANOVA.
And I'll review how to do a repeated
measures ANOVA this week.
Repeated measures ANOVA is somewhat
limited.
It's an ANOVA, so you have to have a
categorical predictor in there.
There's also some fairly restrictive
assumptions.
And you have to fill in missing data, and
things like that, but again,
sometimes a simple method is easy to get
your head around, so, and
you'll see these a lot in the literature,
so I'll show you that, those this week.
The more sophisticated methods, we're
going to go over in the next two weeks,
and those are the generalized estimating
equations in the mixed models.
These are more sophisticated ways of
handling repeated measures outcome.
They're going to have, they're, they're a
lot more powerful.
There's a lot more you can do with them.
They're going to have a lot of advantages
over the other strategies.
The advantages of what I'd call the
old-fashioned method,
sort of the simplifying or, or ignoring
repeated measures or
even, I would lump in there, the repeated
measures ANOVA or
the old methods, their, their advantage
really is that they're simple.
It's easy to kind of see what's happening,
get your head around those.
They're easier to understand and
implement, people tend to be more familiar
with these methods, and
so, again, that's why you might see them
widely in the literature.
Simplicity can be a good thing.
So if you're doing a more fancy model like
a mixed model, and
you're not quite sure that you've modeled
everything correctly,
it's perfectly fine to run a simple model
as well to kind of just serve as a check.
You shouldn't get wildly different answers
in the simple model.
GEE and mixed models, however, have many,
many advantages that we're going to see,
as, as we start talking about them, in the
next two weeks.
So, one of the advantages is that if
you're doing most of
the simple strategies, including repeated
measures in ANOVA,
you need to have complete data on each
subject.
For example in the repeated measures in
ANOVA, if a subject is missing data from
just one time frame, they're going to be
completely omitted from the analysis,
unless, you do something to impute their
missing data.
So you need to fill in the missing data,
or at least grapple with it.
GEE and mixed models have a way of
handling missing data
that doesn't require you to necessarily
impute.
The other thing about GEE and
mixed models, another thing, is that they
treat time as continuous.
So you'll see this week when we talk about
repeated measures ANOVA,
we're essentially treating time as
categorical.
Everybody has to be measured at the same
time points, and we are not allowing for
uneven spacing in when people were
measured.
So that's a limitation of, of the simple
methods.
GEE and its models are great because you
just treat time as a continuous variable.
GEE and mixed models can handle
time-changing predictors,
which none of the simpler methods can.
They also tend to have less restrictive
assumptions,
because they're more sophisticated you can
build in some complexities.
So for example, repeated-measures ANOVA,
as we'll see this week, requires
a particular correlation structure, an
exchangeable correlation structure.
GEE and mixed models don't necessarily
require that.
So, there's, there's huge number of
advantages that you'll see as I
introduce these more sophisticated models
in the next few weeks.