[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module, I'm going to give you
some strategies for
dealing with repeated events.
So up until now we've been dealing with
the situation where we were
just modeling the time until the first
event.
And that makes perfect sense in the
context of survival analysis.
Remember that these methods were developed
around survival.
Since death presumably can only happen
once, the survival analysis methods
really were kind of first modeled around
time to first event.
However, there are lots of binary events
that
could repeat during the time course of a
single study.
So for example, if you're looking at
fractures, women or
men could have multiple fractures during a
study.
Or heart attacks, people could have
multiple heart attacks or
depression episodes or disability
episodes.
Or pregnancies, depending on how long
you're following people,
all of those things could repeat a number
of times across many subjects.
How do we deal with those repeated events?
So there's a bunch of ways people have
come up with for
dealing with repeated events.
I'm going to go over basically three of
the,
the main strategies that are used to
handle them.
So separate models, counting process
models, and conditional models.
I'll go each, over each one of these in
turn.
Just have a little tiny data set to work
with here.
Here is a very small example data set.,
It only has two subjects in it but
it will give you sense of how the data
would be structured.
So, for example, there's subject number
one.
ID number one has three observations in
this data set because that person started
the study and
then, five months into the study, they had
the event, whatever the event is here.
But then we allowed them to continue in
the study.
We didn't stop them,
end them at the time of event, we allow
them to continue in the study.
The next interval of interest goes, starts
at five, and from five on,
they then again have another event at 25
months into the study.
And then we start the clock again at 25
months, and
from 25 months to the end of the study
which occurred at 36 months,
they did not have another event so they
are just censored at the end of the study.
Subject two again has multiple
observations because they had
multiple events.
So they had an event at 19 months into the
study and then again at 25 months, and
then at 29 months, and
they were finally censored at 36 months
when the study actually ended.
These are made up data, but this was what
a real data set might look like.
So the first strategy, in a way,
is just the simplest strategy that you
could think of.
So one strategy would be simply to run a
new
Cox regression model every time you know,
you get to a new set of events.
So you could run a Cox regression model up
until the time
to first event for everybody.
And then you could run a whole separate
model among everybody who
had a first event.
You could then do a new Cox regression
that represents their time to
the second event.
And then if people, enough people had a
second event, you could again run a Cox
regression model that looked at just the
data of everybody who had a second event,
up until the, they time that they had a
third event and so on.
So, you can repeat this as you know, many
times as you need to.
Now of course, the obvious problem with
this strategy is that, well first of
all you're running separate models, so
you're going to get separate datas for
the time to first event, time to second
event, time to third event, etc.
Now that might be legitimate if, in fact,
the risk factors for
having a first event differ from the risk
factors for having a second event.
So you can imagine for something like a
heart attack.
Perhaps, the risk factors for having a
first heart attack could be different for
the risk factors for having a second heart
attack.
So it might make sense if you're dealing
with something where those risk
factors could be very different.
Of course, the problem here is that you're
going to getting increasingly smaller and
smaller sample sizes.
So your risk set, after you run the first
model, your risk set is then
only people who had a first event and that
might be only a small number of people.
Or, if you keep going, eventually at some
event, the fourth, the fifth,
you're going to have too few people to run
another whole another model.
But, let me just show you what this would
look like in terms of,
the likelihood function.
It's going to be very simple because
again, we would just run separate models
so we would sort of have Cox model one,
and we would do a likelihood for that.
So that's going to be up to the time until
the first event,
so we're going to have two events in this
model.
So both subject one and subject two had an
event.
So subject one had an event at five months
into the study.
So at that time, I don't know what the
predictor is here.
Let's just call it x1 for subject one,
whatever their value is for weight or
blood pressure or smoking, whatever x is.
So they're the one who had the event at
five months into the study.
Who was at risk at five months into the
study?
Well, both subject one and subject two
were at risk, so they are,
they each get a term in the model.
At 19 months into the study, subject two
had an event while, because there's
only two people here, there, subject two
was the only person at risk, so they,
that would actually go to one, but the
likelihood would look like that.
Cox model two, the second model, would
take now, and
look at the time from the first event to
the second event.
So for example, Subject one, you would now
start a new model where you'd count their
baseline as the, five months into the
study is their kind of new baseline and
then they would end at 20 months into the
study.
So it you know, you kind of start the
clock over again.
And now they have an, a second event 20
months after they had the first event.
Subject two has their second event six
months after they had their first event.
So Subject two actually has an event
before Subject one in this schematic.
So, the likelihood term would contain a
term for, for
event six months into the study now.
There's six months since the first event.
Person two would be in the numerator here
for
the first term in the likelihood, yeah,
and both of them are at risk at that time,
and then there's only one person at risk
for the second event.
So, that, just looks like that.
So that's the idea, totally separate
models.
Starting the clock for every new event.
That, of course, doesn't in any way use
all the data at once.
So a strategy that would use all the data
at once that would come up with
a single beta rather than multiple betas.
The, sort of the simplest strategy that
uses all of the data at once is to
do what is called a counting process
model.
You allow the subjects to contribute
multiple observations in the data.
So, each person is at risk as long as they
are observed in the study,
even if they've already had an event.
Up until now, the moment somebody had an
event they were sort of out of the risk
set, they were dropped from the risk set.
But now we're allowing people to recur in
the risk set,
to recur in those denominators in a
likelihood function.
They can occur in the partial likelihood
function in the numerator multiple times.
The problem that this brings up is that we
are now counting the same
person multiple times, as if they were
independent people, and so
we've got a problem where we no longer
have independence of observation.
But we can correct for that fairly simply,
we can correct for those correlations
within person using those robust standard
errors that I talked about earlier.
So that's fairly easy to correct for.
So the counting process model, what would
that look like in terms of the likelihood.
So in the counting process model, what
we're doing, here's Subject one,
here's Subject two, here's time.
And here's say, five months into the
study, 19 months into the study.
So, person one is in the study, they have
the events at five months, 25 months.
25 months would be out here so
they have an event here, and they have an
event here.
And then they're censored 36 months into
the study.
Subject two on the other hand, they're
also censored at 36,
but they have an event at 19 months and
then again at 25 months.
And then again at 29 months.
So they have three events in this study.
How would the likelihood term be set up?
Well every time there's an event,
we're going to have a new term in the
likelihood.
So in this case we're going to have one,
two, three, four, five terms in the terms
in the likelihood.
The first term in the likelihood happens
at the first event time which is
five months into the study.
At five months into the study there are
two people at risk, so
Subject one and Subject two.
They're, they're both in the denominator,
and
Subject one is the one who had the event,
so they'd go in the numerator.
At 19 months into the study, the next
event occurs.
That event occurs in Subject two, so we
get something that looks like this.
Notice that again people are repeating, so
we have to account for that correlation.
With those robust standard error
estimates.
And at 25 months into this study, we have
both Subject one and
Subject two are having the event, we have
to put in the likelihood account for ties.
We'd have to do one of those methods for
accounting for ties, but we'd again have
another term in the likelihood which would
allow both of those, both Subject one and
Subject two to have the event and then the
final term in the likelihood.
Again everybody is at risk.
Everybody remains at risk through the
whole study period at least up until,
as long as we're following them.
So that's the idea of the counting process
model.
You come up with a single beta that
represented the effect of
whatever the predictor is here.
Okay, yet another strategy.
So there's one called the conditional
model.
The conditional model is actually very
similar to the counting process model.
So we're going to count people multiple
times.
They're going to be allowed to reappear in
the risk set even after they've
had an event.
However, we're going to do one additional
thing in the conditional model,
which is we're going to stratify on which
event number you're on.
So that we're only comparing people who
are on their first event to
other people who are on their first event.
We're only comparing people who are on
their second event to other people who
are on their second event.
This recognizes the fact that the baseline
hazard for the first event is probably
different or could be different from the
baseline hazard for the second event.
So once you've had a heart attack already,
your risk of having your first heart
attack may be very different than your
risk for having a second heart attack.
Once you've had a first heart attack,
possibly, your baseline hazard for
heart attack goes up.
And so we want to compare only people who
are on the same event number.
So, we're going to stratify.
That's easy to do in the Cox regression
model because we
can do that stratification that I talked
about last week.
We can stratify on which event number
you're on.
And the way, again, since we're having
multiple people recur in
the data set here, we have correlations,
we're going to correct for
those correlations in our data using the
robust standard errors again.
Now there's two variations in the
modelers.
Kind of two different ways of counting
time in this model.
So I'll show you both ways, you can see
both ways in the literature.
You can just count time from baseline,
the way we did it in the counting process
model or, you can
restart the clock every time there's a new
event, and count time since last event.
And I'll show you the difference of those,
it'll be the easiest way again,
to see the difference is to draw the
picture and
see how that's reflected in the likelihood
function.
So if I choose time since baseline, what's
my picture again?
So again, my picture here, here's Subject
one, here's Subject two,
here's 36 months when both are censored,
and we're
counting time since baseline now, so it's
basically the same picture we had before.
Here's an event happening here, another
event and something looks like that.
What's the likelihood function going to
look like here then?
So now we are stratifying on which event
you're on.
So it's kind of probably helpful if we
actually add to our data set
the strata number, the event number that
you're on.
So just to keep track here.
So this is the first event.
This person is on the first event, now
they're on the second event.
Now they would be on the third event.
They were at risk for the third event.
Person two is at risk for the first event,
and then at risk for
the second event, and then the third.
And then they are at risk for
a fourth event because they actually have
three events.
So we can add, we'd have to add a variable
in
the model that reflected which event
you're on, which event number you're on.
What's the likelihood going to look like
though?
So again, we're only going to compare
people who are on event one to
other people who are on event one.
So when the first event happens at five
months into the study,
both Subject one and Subject two are both
at risk for having their first event.
So they are both going to be included in
the denominator here.
The one who has the event is of course
Subject one so they are in the numerator.
Now we go and look at the next event that
occurs.
So the next event that occurs, it occurs
at 19 months.
Subject one is at risk for their second
event at that time.
But subject two is at risk for their first
event.
So, in fact, because this is such a small
data set that
we don't have anybody else in the risk
set.
So the only person at risk is Subject two
for their first event.
And Subject two has an event at 19 months.
So Subject one is not included in the
denominator now,
at nine, this event at 19 months because
this is stratified on event number.
So this for.
This is a first event strata.
All right?
Now we get to the second event.
Now they're both at risk for the second
event.
So the next events that occur are at 25
months into the study and
just to make this simple, let's say we had
measured it a little bit more finely just
to make this easy let's say Subject one
has the amount of 25.01 and
Subject two has the amount of 25.1 months
so we don't have to deal with ties.
So, [SOUND] now we're on a strata for the
second event.
The next event that occurs is at 25 months
into the study.
Subject one has the event.
Both Subject one and Subject two are at
risk of having the event at that time.
So the likelihood term would look like
that.
Now, however, when the next second event
occurs in Subject two because I've
jiggered the time a little bit here and
this, let's say you know for
sure that the second event happened second
in Subject two.
Well at the time they had their second
event, the, Subject one was no longer at
risk of the second event, so the
likelihood term would look like that.
And, so on.
So you get the idea, we're stratifying on
event time.
So, a slightly different way of running
the conditional model is to instead of
counting time from baseline, is to the
count the time since the last event.
And I started to draw it here to show you
the, the slight difference here.
So if we count the time since last event,
we restart the clock every time a person
joins a new event strata.
And again, it's good, probably here to put
the strata for
the event number; which number event
people are on.
That's like a new variable in my data set.
So for event one, person one is at risk
for event one from zero to five months
into the study and person two has their
first event 19 months into the study.
Then we restart the clock.
So now it actually takes 20 months for the
first person, for
subject one to have the event again.
So we start the clock again at zero and
they have their event,
their second event at 20 months.
Subject two here, if we restart the clock
at 19 months,
only took six months to arrive at, to have
their second event.
So that would be slightly different in the
likelihood then,
because if you think about the likelihood
now, the terms for
event one are actually going to look the
same as before.
So, we have a term where Subject one has
the event.
Both subjects are at risk at five months,
we multiply that by only Subject two is at
risk at 19 months.
Then we get terms in likelihood for the
second event time, again,
we're stratified on event time here, but
now, the first person to
have an event is Subject two, because they
have that event only six months later.
And remember, I kind of said, let's
pretend that Subject one had
an event at 25.1 months, and subject two
had the event at 25 months, so
that we could say subject one was second
in having the event.
Well, now, because we restarted the clock,
and
Subject two had a second event faster,
they get the first term in the likelihood,
so their term, now they're going to be in
the numerator of the risk.
You can see how that changes the
likelihood function, so like that, and
then Subject one gets the next term in the
likelihood and
of course, only the simple things are they
are the only ones at risk, and
then we keep going with event three and
event four etc.
So, you can see how that slightly changes
the likelihood to count time
since last event.
And you'll get slightly different answers
depending on how you count time.
Depending on the situation,
you may prefer, is conceptually one over
the other.
So, that's, those are several different
methods for handling repeated events.
So now I'm just going to show you an
example from the literature where they
had a repeated event and they tried
modeling it with several of
these different strategies to compare
them.
So here's what the data looked like.
They drew a nice little graphic of their
data.
The event here was disability.
And obviously, episodes of disability are
something that can repeat.
What you're seeing on the graph here is
that, for example, this first person
didn't have any episodes of disability,
but they died somewhere during the study.
Subject two, right here was, never had any
episodes of disability.
Subject three had a bout of disability
starting at about 69,
looks like about 69 months into the study.
And this whole thing here is considered a,
a one episode of disability,
all these dots, so every, essentially
month they're having disability.
Those kind of run together into one
episode.
Subject four has an episode of disability
that lasts from about 12
to about 13 months, or maybe 11 to 13
months.
They have another repeated episode of
disability later on in the study.
And Subject five has one, two, three, four
bouts of disability.
And this was a much was a much larger data
set.
So this is just just five subjects
pictured out of a much larger data set.
The authors were actually nice to show the
actual structure of the data.
What does it look like in the data set?
That can often be very useful.
And they were trying to illustrate the
principle of how to apply some of
these different strategies.
So they shared their data structure.
So this, this data set here that you see
corresponds to
the picture on the previous slide.
So subjects one, two and three don't
repeat but
subject four has multiple observations in
the data set because they
have multiple bouts of disabilities, same
with subject five.
The start and end time shows you the time
from baseline to for
Subject one they died at 20 months into
the study so they were censored then.
They only ever, the interval represents
which event number are they on.
They only were at risk for event, one
event the first event.
They never, they never had a first event.
This is a total time in this interval, the
number of previous events here was zero,
and the predictor we're going to care
about is gender here,
so zero means that they were a male, one
is female.
So let's go down to one of the more
interesting ones, so
subject four, who repeats, they start the
study, zero is baseline.
Ten months into the study they have an
event, so that's their, that's
interval one, because that's their, when
they were at risk for the first event.
That interval, the time in that interval
they spent in that interval was ten months
and this person is a female.
They've had zero previous events at that
point.
Their next interval they have a bout of
disability that actually last from,
about ten to 14 months.
So they, they, their next at risk for
having disability,
once they get out of that particular
episode of, disability, they were again at
risk of disability from 14 months and then
at 46 months they have an event.
That's the second enroll because that's
the time period at which they were ri,
at risk for a second bout of disability.
That time interval lasted 32 months, from
14 months to 46 months.
Now they've had one previous event and
they're still female and
then their, the last thing that happened
was they became at risk again.
Their, their second bout of disability
stopped at 53 months.
They became at risk again.
And then, 72 months into the study, the
study ended, and they were censored.
So that has a value of censored.
That's their third interval.
That third interval lasted 19 months
before they were censored.
At that point, they were on their third
event.
So they, they were at risk for this, this
thirdof event since they already had
two previous events, and, of course,
they're still female.
That's the data structure, how they set it
up.
And then they ran a bunch of different
models looking at
the outcome of either bathing disability
episodes, bathing disability, or
other disability other than bathing
disability.
When, and they looked at one particular
predictor, which was gender, so
they compare women versus men.
They're going to get hazard ratios for the
risk of disability for women versus men.
They used a whole bunch of different
models to show what happens if
you handle the repeated events in slightly
different ways.
And in fact there were more models than
I'm showing in this table.
I've compacted this table just to focus on
the ones that we've talked about in
this module.
They went into other types of models as
well.
But this is the ones that are relevant to
this module.
They ran a Cox regression model where they
adjusted the time to
the first disability event, and they
compared again women to men.
So, that's this result right here.
So what you'll see is that the hazard
ratio that they came up with if they
compared women versus men for time to
first event is that the,
the women were, had a 30% higher rate of
the time to, to first bathing disability.
However, for other disabilities, it was
fairly null.
There didn't seem to be a gender
difference.
So that's ignoring all of the stuff that
happened after that
first bout of disability, which is a lot
to ignore.
They then ran the Cox regression model
accommodating,
incorporating the repeated events in a
number of different ways.
So they did the counting process model,
which I talked about,
they then did a modified version of the
counting process model.
What they've done here is they've adjusted
for the number of previous events, so
they adjusted for this previous event's
variable.
They just put it in the model as another
co-variant.
Now the one thing that happens when you do
that is you are assuming proportional
hazards here.
But it, in a way is very similar to
stratifying on the event number which is
what the conditional models do.
So they adjusted rather than stratified
for the event number and that's what you
are seeing on the second row here and then
they did the two different conditional
models counting times and space line and
counting time since last event.
And what you can see is that in the first
counting process model where
they didn't adjust for which event you
were on, for event number.
They did get a slightly higher hazard
ratio for men versus women for bathing.
But for other disability, it's,
that was very similar to some of the other
ones you're seeing here.
When they adjust for event number, you get
hazard ratios of 1.37 and 1.39.
And then for
the conditional models, you're getting
hazard ratios in that ballpark.
So for conditional model A, when we
stratify an event number, and
we get a hazard ratio of 1.35, and a
slightly lower for
other disability of 1.25, and when you do
time since last event,
it attenuates just a little bit, 1.27 and
1.18.
But you can see that they're all
relatively within the same ballpark.
The time to first event model actually
gets a pretty similar answer for
bathing disabilities, but it gets a very
different answer for other disabilities.
All of the other ways of handling repeated
events were significant or very close to
significant with men, women having more a
higher rate of disability than men.
That wasn't true when we adjusted time to
first event.
So you kind of missed something if you did
only time to
first event on the other disability
outcome.
So again, those are a couple of different
ways to handle repeated events in
your Cox regression model.
[BLANK_AUDIO]