[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module I'm going to tell you
about the intention-to-treat principle,
which is applied when you have data from a
randomized clinical trial.
And, this is not specific to survival
analysis.
So, you would apply the intention-to-treat
principle whether you had time-to-event
data or whether you had some other type of
outcome data, from your clinical trial.
So, first of all, what's meant by an
intention-to-treat analysis.
The idea is this, you do a randomized
trial.
You randomize people to different groups.
If you're using an intention-to-treat
analysis you're going to
compare outcomes according to the groups
to which subjects were randomized,
regardless of what happened after
randomization.
So, in the real world, in real world
trials, lots of people,
as I'm going to show you in some examples
in this module,
lots of people will end up switching
groups or violating the protocol.
All sorts of things can happen.
For, if you're doing a true
Intention-to-treat analysis you're
going to ignore all that essentially, and
just analyze the outcomes to what you were
originally randomizing.
So a nice way to summarized that is once
randomized, always analyzed.
And that's well-illustrated if you just
look at the flow diagram.
Most randomized trials will present one of
these flow diagram which shows, you know,
who was screened for this study, who was
randomized to what group,
what happened, how many people were
analyzed.
It's very easy to tell, if the authors
have used an intention-to-treat analysis.
Let me zoom in here.
So, this is just a flow diagram from the
dietary intervention component of
the Women's Health Initiative.
But, here's the key to telling if you've
done an intention to treat analysis.
So, notice we had in this trial 48,000
women randomized.
About 29,000 to the usual diet group, and
19,000 to this diet intervention.
And, notice those exact numbers in 19,541
29,294, and
then you can scroll down and see all these
other things happen.
Some people withdrew, some people lost to
follow-up.
Some people died.
But, how many people were analyzed in the
primary analysis at the end of the day?
19,541 in the dietary intervention group.
And 29,294 in the control group.
Notice these are identical to the numbers
who were randomized.
This would indicated that they've done a
true intention-to-treat analysis.
So, intention-to-treat says, that
participants are going to be
counted in the intervention group to which
they were originally assigned,
even if they refuse the intervention
immediately after randomization.
If they dis, discontinued it sometime
during the study,
even if they followed the intervention
incorrectly,
even if they violated study protocol, they
missed follow-up measurements.
Even if it was found after randomization
and
that they should've been excluded from the
trial in the first place.
All these things we're going to ignore and
once randomized, always analyzed.
That's the pure form of
intention-to-treat.
And you can see that in real-world trials,
lots of things like this do happen.
'Kay so here is a nice figure that was
presented from the Women's Health
Initiative.
This was from the main trial.
The Women's Health Initiative was a large,
randomized trial, that was designed to
compare postmenopausal hormones to a
placebo pill in postmenopausal women.
And see whether or not hormones, which at
the time were thought to be very good for
postmenopausal women, whether they, in
fact, had benefits.
And, what you're seeing here is, the
circles are women who
were originally randomized to the estrogen
and progestin group.
That's the hormone group.
The, the triangles are women who were
originally randomized to
the placebo group.
But, what this graph is showing you is,
what are called the drop-ins and dropouts.
It shows you how much crossover there was
during this trial among
the different groups.
So, this filled in circles are women who
dropped out of the active treatment group.
So, they stopped taking their hormones.
They were randomized to hormones, and they
stopped taking them for whatever reason.
You can see by the end of the trial, we're
talking 35% and or
more of women in that treatment have
actually dropped out of
the treatment group, they're no longer
taking their hormones.
Why might this be, well people get sick of
taking pills.
Also they may have perceived there were
side effects from those pills.
What's really interesting is that the
placebo group also had a very high dropout
rate, and it's almost as high but just a
little bit less than the hormone group.
So, that's this filled-in triangle line
below.
That's the dropout rate over time, for
those who are taking placebo pills.
Remember, the women were blinded they
didn't know whether or
not they were on hormones or placebos, so
some of the women either perceived that
they were having side effects on the
placebo pill.
Or they just, you know, got sick of taking
a pill or forgot or whatever.
And the rate of dropouts was almost as
high in the placebo group,
which I find interesting.
And then besides dropouts we also have,
had,
people dropping into the treatment group.
So women on the placebo pill,
this is the triangles here on the bottom,
dropped into the treatment.
So at the time the paradigm was that
hormones are good for
you, plus menopausal hormones are good,
and so the women weren't sure.
The women in the placebo group weren't
sure they were on the hormones, and
maybe suspected they weren't.
And so they actually went to their or
their doctor recommended to them, if they
get a prescription for hormones.
So they dropped into the hormone group,
they stopped taking their placebo pills,
and
actually dropped into the hormone group,
thinking that they should be on them.
And then finally, there were women who
were actually on hormones,
this is the last graph here, who decided
to stop taking their study drug.
Maybe they weren't sure if they had been
assigned to the hormone group.
And decided to go and get a prescription
for the, those hormones.
So, women in the estrogen and
progestin group actually dropped into
active treatment.
So, they stopped taking their study drugs
and went out and got a prescription for
the same thing essentially.
Because, again, women are blinded, and
they might have wanted to be on hormones.
So you can see that there's a whole bunch
of noise in the study.
Women don't stay in the groove to which
they were assigned in this study.
And yet the intention to treat principle
is going to say all the ones who
are circles are going to be analyzed as
treatment group, active treatment.
And all the ones who are triangles are
going to be analyzed as placebo,
at the end of the day.
Now you might be wondering why we would
use intention to treat.
What's the rationale here?
now, it might not your instinct to say
okay,
we're just going to keep everybody in the
original groups.
You might think, well,
we should account for the fact there's all
this switching around.
So what's the rationale for intention to
treat?
There's sort of two basic reasons.
So first of all, if you're using intention
to treat analysis,
you're preserving the benefits of
randomization.
So the whole point of randomization was to
balance potential confounding factors in
the study arms.
Make sure those arms are balanced.
In things that can be confounders.
If you then go and look and
say well okay I'm not going to analyze
according to the randomization, but
I'm going to go analyze according to who
took hormones and who didn't.
Then you bring a whole set of confounders
and biases back in to this study, right.
The balance will no longer be preserved,
if you're analyzing women according to
what they actually did.
And again, these can be large numbers of
women, or people, in randomized trials,
switching around groups.
So, you lose all those benefits of
randomization by doing intentioned,
if you don't do intention to treat, by
doing intention to treat,
you can preserve the benefits of
randomization.
So that's one rationale.
The second rationale is that it more
closely simulates real life.
So it's the intention-to-treat as opposed
to the actual treatment, and
that's more similar to what happens when
you go to a doctor's office.
The doctor prescribes you a drug, that
doesn't necessarily mean that
every patient is going to go home and take
that drug perfectly.
So patients often don't adhere perfectly
to treatment regimens.
They might discontinue treatment
altogether.
So it's evaluating not how good the drug
is under perfect,
ideal conditions, but how good the drug is
under real word conditions.
If you prescribe it, how likely is it to
have a benefit.
So it's getting more at effectiveness.
Rather than efficacy, which is probably
what we care most about, in most cases,
we want to look at real life opposed to
perfect use.
So those sort of the main two rationales
for using intention to treat analysis.
Now, what effect does intention to treat
have on a statistical analysis?
So basically, we are preserving the
benefits of randomization, so
we're not going to introduce any bias
here.
We're going to avoid that you know,
confounding.
However, we there's going to be all of
this noise that's introduced by
the fact that people didn't actually do
what we think they did, or
what they should have done.
And so that noise is going to have the
effect of diluting our effect sizes.
So it's going to reduce our statistical
power.
If you use an intention-to-treat analysis,
you tend to underestimate treatment
effects.
So you don't get a bias in there, but you
tend to, bring things closer to the null.
We had this additional variability which
sort of waters down the results,
reduces your statistical power.
And it's really easy to illustrate that
with a simple mathematical example.
So, let me just do a simple hypothetical,
mathematical example here to illustrate
how it's going to water down our affect
sizes, make them closer to the null.
So, take the following hypothetical
randomized control trial.
Imagine that you have a drug that actually
is effective, and it's really,
really good actually.
So if you take the drug perfectly,
you have a 25% chance of dying during two
years.
Versus, if you don't take the drug,
a placebo subject would have a 50% chance
of dying.
If that's really the truth out there, then
that's a really good drug.
'because it's cutting the risk of death in
half.
The true relative risk here.
Would be 0.5, 50% less chance of dying in
the treated group.
So now, sort of, if everybody took the
drug perfectly.
But imagine you go out and do a 2-year
randomized trial.
You have a hundred treated subjects and a
hundred placebo subjects.
If everybody took the drug perfectly.
Nobody switched groups.
You would expect to see about 25 deaths in
the treated group, because there's a 25%
chance of dying in the treated group, and
about 50 deaths in the placebo group.
And, of course, you know, give or take a
few due to random choice.
We're not going to get exactly 25, we may
get 26, or 24, something around that.
And so the observed relative risk that
you're going to see it's going to be
somewhere around 0.5, maybe not exactly
0.5 but somewhere around 0.5.
Now imagine that things happen in the
trial, as in most trials.
Start people do in fact switch groups.
So if, fairly early in the study about 25
treated subjects switch to
the placebo stop taking their treatment
group, their treatment drug, and
25 placebo subjects stop taking the
placebo and actually go out and
get the treatment, which actually did
happen.
In the women's health initiative, for
example.
Then, what effect is that going to have on
our relative risk at the end of the day?
Well, now because some of the placebo
participants are actually taking the drug
and getting the benefit of it, we're
actually going to see fewer deaths
in the placebo group, maybe 43 or 44
rather than about 50.
And since some of the people in
the treated group are no longer getting
the benefits of the drug,
we're going to expect to see a few higher
deaths than the treated group.
So maybe something around 31, if you want
the math.
So the observed relative risk is going to
be something closer to one.
So if you kind of estimate it out,
you'd expect to see something around 0.7
even though the true value is 0.5.
You're getting closer to the null, it's a
diluted effect, and that's the general
effect that doing an intention-to-treat
analysis is going to have on your results.
So, that often, for many randomized, for
most randomized trials,
they do some kind of intention-to-treat
analysis as their primary analysis.
Let me just review what the alternatives
to intention-to-treat analysis would be.
So you see in the literature a lot of
times what people actually do is
not a pure, pure intention-to-treat
analysis but
is actually what's called a modified
intention-to-treat analysis.
This is actually probably more common in
the literature.
A pure intention-to-treat would say, once
randomized always analysed, and,
end of story.
But sometimes people will allow some
limited exclusions and
still call it an intention-to-treat.
That's technically then, a modified
intention-to-treat.
So for example, if you were doing a
vaccine trial for
an HIV vaccine, and after you randomized
people,
you discovered that there were a few
people in each of your groups.
Who were HIV-positive before the study
actually started,
because it takes time to do the testing
and everything.
You might find out after the fact, after
they were already enrolled and
randomized, that they, in fact, are
already HIV-positive.
And therefore really shouldn't have been
eligible for he trial.
Do you then go back and exclude them?
Because clearly the vaccine can't protect
them.
Or do you keep them in the analysis?
Well a modified intention-to-treat, for
example, might allow you to exclude them.
You want to be a little bit careful though
when you see studies that
have a modified intention-to-treat.
And the reason is, that there may be good
rationale for
excluding a couple of participants.
But modified intention-to-treat really is
not applied
consistently in the literature.
There's really a lack of standards here.
And it opens up the door that authors
could then either consciously or
unconsciously, you know, say after the
fact, oh well,
maybe I should've excluded this type of
participant.
And if I exclude these types of
participants,
let me see how that affects my p value.
People aren't always, you know, trying to
do this purposely, but
you can see how it would open the door to
creeping in a little bit of bias.
because it then gives you the opportunity
to exclude certain participants.
Perhaps, you know, the ones who didn't
have the outcome you were hoping for.
So you want to be really careful when you
see things where there are exclusions
after the fact.
And preferably those exclusions would have
been defined in the protocol,
before anybody saw the data.
If you're making those modifications after
you see the data,
there is an opportunity to introduce bias,
so be just a little wary of those.
More dramatic alternatives to
intention-to-treat,
where you're truly not doing
intention-to-treat in any way anymore,
would include the as-treated analysis and
the per-protocol analysis.
So an as-treated analysis, would analyze
participants according to
what actually happened, what treatments
they actually took.
So if you think of the women's health
initiative, study for example.
In Cox regression you can have time
changing predictors, so that's great
because you can see over time women
started, started drugs or stopped drugs.
You could change their status.
You could change which group they were in
over time.
And that would be an as-treated analysis.
It would actually incorporate the fact
that they dropped in or
off, or out, you know.
Onto or off of drugs.
That would be an as treated analysis.
A per-protocol analysis is even stricter
than that.
And it's going to drop, exclude everybody
from the analysis, who,
essentially wasn't a perfect participant.
Who violated the study protocol in any
way, so they, they switched groups, or
they didn't come in for all of their
followup measurements or, you know,
they, they shouldn't have been in the
study in the first place.
Whatever reasons, that's going to be an
even more exclusive analysis.
And you can imagine that the problem with
these non-intention-to-treat analyses,
the as treated in the per-protocol,
is that you're losing the benefits of
randomization.
So now all of a sudden you're analyzing
people according to what they
actually did.
And of course, the reasons that they did,
they went in one group or
another, that they took the drug or
didn't, that they came in for their study
measurements or didn't.
All of those things could be related to
the outcomes.
So you're essentially getting back to an
observational study.
It's no longer a, you no longer have all
the benefits of a randomized trial.