[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module I'm going to talk
about the issue of missing data.
So, if you have missing data, if you
didn't get
that repeated outcome measured at every
time point, what's going to happen?
So if you're working on analyses that use
the broad form of the data.
So literally when you put them into your
computer package, it's running, and
it only runs in the broad form of the
data, then any subjects we're missing,
even data on just one time point out of
all the time points.
They're going to be completely omitted
from that analysis unless you
impute those missing data points.
And so this would be things like the
simple meas-, the simple strategies for
analyzing repeated measures, data that I
have talked about.
ANCOVA, also repeated measures ANOVA, as
we'll see.
Those are going to throw somebody out
unless they have all of
the time points measured, or you do
imputation.
So that's a little bit of a limitation of
those methods.
You're going to have to do some
imputation.
However, if you're working on analyses
that used a long form of the data,
it turns out that that, those analyses are
only going to
omit specific time points when a person
wasn't measured.
So if a person was measured at time point
one, two, and
four, but not time point three, they won't
contribute to time point three.
But they will contribute to time points
one, two, and four.
And so the more sophisticated analysis
like GEE and
mixed models will handle missing data in
that way.
And also that slope analysis I told you
about earlier,
actually that handles missing data as
well.
So just to illustrate why this is, take
here,
here's the broad form of the data, and
here's the long form of the data.
This is just some data we had on spine
bone density.
And take for example subject number 25.
In the broad form of the data, she has
spine one and
spine two, but not spine three.
If I go to run a repeated measures ANOVA
on these data, because she's missing,
this row of data is missing one time
point,
it will not be included in the repeated
measures ANOVA.
She will just be completely kicked out of
that analysis.
However, if you turn to, and look at the
long form of data,
the same id number, 25, she now has three
rows in the long form of the data.
She has a spine value for on-, for her
first time period and
her second time period, again missing that
third time period.
But, analyses that run on the long form of
the data will be able to
include this row in the analysis, and this
row.
And the only row that will get kicked out
is this row.
So, she will only be left out when it
comes to the third time point.
The one she actually missed, as opposed to
all time points.
So that's the advantage of the analysis
like GE in mixed models that run on
the long form in the data.
Now let's say that you want to work on the
broad form of the data and
you need to fill in that missing data.
What's a way that you can impute the
missing data?
So for repeated measures data, a very
simple way to
impute missing data is to use what's
called Last Observation Carried Forward.
And that's a very nice name because it's
exactly what it sounds like.
So here's a little bit of an example data
set.
There's just four subjects here, they all
have depression scores and
at time points one, two, three, and four.
And you can see that subject one was
missing the final two time points.
Last observation forward, carry forward,
we'll just carry the last observation
forward.
So she's missing time point three,
we're going to carry forward there the 13
from time point two.
And then she's missing the time point
four, so
we'll carry forward that 13 again.
In this way, we have now filled in all of
her values, so
she will not be kicked out of the
analysis.
And it seems pretty reasonable, since the
last time we saw her she was at 13,
to fill in the rest of the time points
with 13.
That's a much better thing than dumping
her out of the analysis completely.
Down here at subject four we just carry
the 30 forward.
She missed only the second time point.
Since we need to fill in something for
the time point, we'll, second time point,
we'll carry forward that value of 30.
So Last Observation Carried Forward is
easy to implement,
it's easy to understand, and it does a
pretty good job.
Again, it's much better to fill in just
something on those missing data
points than to have the person kicked out
altogether.
[BLANK_AUDIO]