[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module,
I'm going to tell you about multivariate
repeated-measures ANOVA.
So up until now we've been talking about
univariate repeated-measures ANOVA.
Now I want to tell you multivariate
repeated measures ANOVA,
which approaches these types of data in a
different way.
So the key to multivariate repeated
measures ANOVA is,
that there's actually more than one
dependent variable.
Rather than having a single dependent
variable,
we actually have a vector of outcome
variables.
And in fact because of that, it's not just
used for repeated measures ANOVA, it would
be appropriate for other situations when
you have multiple dependent variables.
I'm only going to talk about the case of
applying it to repeated measure and data.
And the best way to understand
multivariate repeated measures ANOVA,
is actually just to think back to when we
did paired T tests.
It's essentially analogous to a paired T
test.
So remember, we used a paired t-test
actually before for
repeated measures, when we only had two
time points.
And the way a paired t-test works is that
you
subtract the values between the two time
points, and you get a difference value.
How much did a person change from time
point one, to time point two?
We're going to calculate the difference
value for everybody, and
then we're going to calculate the average
difference for this sample.
And the null hypothesis for
a paired t test is that the difference is
equal to zero.
So on average people didn't go, didn't go
up or down, they didn't change.
Then there is no effect.
So we would take the average difference
and
divide that by the standard error for the
average differences.
We divided by a standard error.
That's kind of a t distribution.
And so essentially our outcome here is
just difference values.
A single different value for each person.
The only difference with the multivariate
repeated measures ANOVA,
is that we are now going to look at a
vector of differences rather than
a single difference for every person.
So in the example data set I've been
using,
there were five time points, so each
person actually has three differences.
They have the difference between time one
and
two, between time two and three and
between time three and four.
And that, those three values could be
thought of as a vector of differences.
So MANOVA is essentially just a paired t
test where the outcome variable is
a vector of difference values rather than
a single difference.
It's sort of an extension of the pair t
test.
So we can have multiple time points, more
than two.
And we can calculate a statistic based on
the,
comparing the average of the vector of
differences to its standard error.
And the null hypothesis here, is that the
difference one between the first
two time points and zero and difference
two between the next two time points and
zero and difference three between the next
two time points and zero and so on.
That all the difference values on average
are zero.
That would say that there's no changes
happening over time.
And one of the statistics, I'm not going
go into the details of this statistic,
it involves vectors and
things, but you can make a statistic, one
of them is called Hotel Lengths Trace.
So take that little example data set that
I've been using with just these
six subjects.
I had four time points.
So I'm going to get three difference
values.
So now, the values for subject one are no
longer the absolute values.
I don't know what their absolute value of
depression score is, but
I know that they went down two units
between time point one and two.
And then down 14 more units between two,
time points two and three.
And then up 11 units between time points
three and four.
I've now got a vector of differences on
each of these subjects.
Couple of caveats to think about here.
We're rating all of these differences
equally, so
it's hard to interpret them if the time
intervals are unevenly spaced.
So imagine that time point one was zero
months into the study, and
then you measure people again at one
month, and
then you didn't measure people again until
a year.
Well the first difference would represent
the one month change,
the second difference would represent an
11 month change, and obviously those
might be different just because the
different spacing of the time intervals.
So this is assuming we have evenly or
reasonably evenly spaced time intervals.
Where the other assumption is that we have
a normally distributed outcome.
This would following a multivariate normal
distribution, but same idea.
And that we have a homogeneity of
variances at each of
the time points again.
The null hypothesis is that all of the
average different scores are zero.
You can see that the difference between
time rates two and three, it looks like
kind of, there was, we, we already saw in
the picture that it was going down.
There's a lot of negatives there.
And in time points three and four, there
seems to be more positives.
But is that enough to be significantly
different from zero.
I'm just starting this by ignoring groups
and
asking the simple question, are there
significant changes over time?
Are any of the changes, differences
between time points significant?
And when I run these statistics,
I ran the multivariate repeated measures
in ANOVA in SASS.
The p value that I get is 0.1876.
So my null hypothesis is all the
differences are zero and
I can't reject that.
So I don't have evidence that there is
really a significant difference over
time even though there looks to be some
difference in time point three.
Notice you get four slightly different
statistics here.
There are different statisticians who have
come up with certainly,
certain different ways of calculating
this.
In this case,
because the data aren't complicated, all
the p values come out to be the same.
And just compare this to when we did the
repeated measures univariate aNOVA.
This is the time effect that we got when
we just had time in the model and
nothing else, when we were ignoring group.
We got a p value of 0.13 that was adjusted
for the violation of compound symmetry.
So we got a lit, p value that's a little
bit less, than what we got for
the, from the multivariate ANOVA.
But they're both saying that we
don't have enough evidence to reject the
null hypothesis.
We do not have a significant time effect.
Statisticians would recommend that if
there's differences between these p
values that you would choose the Wilks'
Lambda in general.
But if you had a small sample, and some of
the assumptions of the model,
the normality and homogeneity of variances
was violated to use Pillai's Trace,
which was the second one, here.
So that's when I've just put time in the
model,
of course we would also like to
additionally consider group.
Now, it's important to keep in mind,
that when you're doing multivariate
repeated measures ANOVA.
We're looking at difference values.
We never consider the absolute values.
Whether or not you have a depression score
of 30 or 100.
We only compare, consider how much it went
up or down.
So that means that for repeated measures
multivariate, ANOVA,
there are actually going to be no between
subjects effects, okay?
Because I can't tell you whether or not
subject one is higher than subject two.
And I can't tell you whether or
not group A has a higher depression score
than Group B.
I'm only looking at within subjects
effects,
because I'm only looking at the changes
over time.
Now, this was the picture when we brought
group in.
B looks a little higher overall than A.
We will not be getting that group
difference here.
But the pattern over time kind of looks
pretty similar between the two groups.
We already saw that.
So now I'm going to run my repeated
measures multivariate ANOVA with,
group in the model.
And, by the way, in SASS at least, you
just ask for repeated-measures ANOVA and
it gives you both the univariate results
and
the multivariate results in the output, so
you get both.
I'm going to get from the multivariate
repeated measures ANOVA.
I'm going to get here a time effect and a
group by time interaction, and that's it.
So the time effect comes out to be 0.32.
This would say that there's no overall
differences between time.
So overall ignoring group, there doesn't
seem to be any significant time effect.
And again, we saw that in the picture.
If you look at everybody, it kind of goes
like this, and a little bit of a dip in
time point three, but it wasn't enough to
trigger statistical significance.
So there's no significant time effect.
We saw that in the repeated measures ANOVA
univariate version, the p value was 0.17.
So basically giving us the same answer,
not significant.
And then the time by group interaction,
that one clearly the two groups seem to
have the same pattern over time.
So that one's clearly not significant.
So the changes, the differences between
the time points don't seem to
differ between the two groups.
And for comparison the univariate result
for
the time by group interaction was also
highly nonsignificant 0.69.
So we can from the multivariate repeated
measures ANOVA we get basically the same
results as we did from the univariate.
And so if we ask the question, are there
any significant changes over time,
differences between time points?
That's a time main effect.
We did not see a main effect for time.
Now we cannot actually ask the question
about whether the two groups differ at
any time points.
We don't, we are unable to get a group
effect,
the overall effect of differences between
groups.
Again, we don't have any absolute values
in the analysis, so
I can't tell you if group A is higher than
group B overall.
So we're not going to get that from the
multivariate version.
We will get a p value for the group by
time effect.
And therefore we can ask the question
about whether the two groups differ in
their responses over time.
And that was clearly non-significant here,
as we saw.
Now just for fun, I thought it would be
nice to also throw in to the multivariate
repeated-measures ANOVA these data on bone
density that we've been looking at.
So here's the picture again for that.
That we saw for the univariant, repeated
measures ANOVA results,
we had a significant time effect and a
borderline significant time by
group effect, and we get, pretty much same
results here.
So the time effect is significant, 0.002.
It was 0.0006, a little bit smaller when
we did the univariate.
But you can see that on average, it does
look like the bone density's going up.
The group by time effect is borderline
significant.
It was 0.06 when we did the univariate
version.
It's 0.07 when we did the multivariate
version, so about the same.
This doesn't quite make statistical
significance that those groups differ in
their profiles over time, almost.
So we're getting basically the same
answer.
You'll notice that the p values from the
multivariate tend to be just a little bit
higher, than the ones from the univariate.
And that's because if the compound
symmetry assumption is met,
the univariate approach actually has more
power, more statistical power.
Now if the compound symmetry is not met
however,
we are increasing our type one error by
using the univariate approach.
So we're more likely to get a false
positive so
the p values tend to be smaller for the
univariate.
They're appropriately smaller if we meet
this compound symmetry assumption, but
not if we don't.
So there's slight differences between the
two in that way.
They usually give reasonably similar
answers, however.
And so just to summarize repeated-measures
ANOVA.
Both of the univariant and
the multivariate versions, you have to
impute missing data.
If a person is missing just one time
point, they are completely thrown out of
the analysis, so you have to fill in
something, for that missing data.
Repeated measures, univeriant ANOVA
requires compound symmetry.
So that's a restrictive assumption.
Now there are p value corrections for this
as we saw.
We are treating time essentially as
categorical in these analysis.
So we're requiring that subjects who,
they have to be measured at the same time
points, because if everybody's measured at
different time points it really doesn't
make sense to group them into categorical
time points.
And as we saw with the multivariate
repeated measures ANOVA.
Since we're looking at difference values,
we are making the assumption that the time
intervals are reasonably even.
The advantages of the, the map is,
however, they're pretty easy to implement
and interpret.
They're pretty straightforward, once you
get the hang of them, to interpret them.
They're not too complex.
So as we turn to talking about generalized
estimating equations and mixed models,
you're going to see that a lot of these
disadvantages are not a problem,
for those more sophisticated models.
But the models get a little bit more
complicated to interpret.
Just for fun, I thought it would be fun
even though we haven't gotten to GEE and
mixed models yet, I thought it would be
fun just to throw that bone density data,
into a GE model and a mixed model.
And compare with what we got from the
repeated measures ANOVA analysis.
So I went ahead and did that.
You can see it's a little more
complicated.
But I ran a GEE model.
And you don't have to understand all of
this yet,
I'll just sort of walk you through what's
relevant here.
But I ran a GEE model for the same spine
bone density data, so
my outcome here is fine bone density.
And I have three groups, again, black, I'm
calling them black, red, and
blue for simplicity.
The main effects that I'm getting for
black, red, and blue correspond to
the main effect for group, that I was
getting from the univariate,
repeated measures of ANOVA, and those are
not significant, as we saw before.
I am getting a time effect, which is
saying,
does the bone density differ significantly
over time?
But, in these regression models the time
effect is not an average over all of
the groups, it is the time effect for the
reference group only.
So, this time effect corresponds us to the
changes over time for
the blue group, and that's clearly not
significant,
because the blue group isn't changing much
over time.
The, then we have a time by group
interaction.
And we break it down by the black group
and the red group, and
the blue group, of course, is the
reference group.
What do we get?
We get an estimate here that's 0.01, and
0.014.
And what that's saying is that we're going
up by
about one gram per centimeter square,
which is roughly a percent,
in bone density more, per year, in the
black group versus the blue group.
And that does make statistical
significance.
And for the red group, were going up even
a little bit more than that,
about 0.0140 grams per centimeter square.
Per year more, about 1.4% more in the red
group versus the blue group per year, and
that is highly significant.
And you'll notice that we achieve
statistical significance on
the time by group effect in the GEE model
where we didn't in
the less powerful repeated measures ANOVA
models.
And we get very similar results when we do
mixed models.
I won't go through the whole results here
again because you'll
notice the parameter estimates look very
similar, the p values look very similar.
So we're getting a similar result with a
mixed model.
[BLANK_AUDIO]