[BLANK_AUDIO]
So last week,
I told you how to graph continuous
outcomes when you have repeated-measures.
This week we're going to start our
discussion of statistical tests,
that are actually used to generate effect
sizes, and
p-values to go along with those graphics.
So this week I'm going to give you an
overview of
the statistical tests that are available
for analyzing.
Repeated-measures data, with a focus on
continuous outcomes.
I'm also going to tell you about some
tests that actually don't really
handle the repeated-measures very well,
that essentially simplify or
ignore the repeated-measures.
These are sort of old fashioned test.
There's nothing necessarily wrong with
these tests, and
you may have a simple situation, when a
simple test will do.
It's also handy just to have these in your
toolbox, because sometimes you
do a more fancier, complicated model and
you're not quite sure that you're
getting the right answer, you can check,
with one of these simple tests and
make sure that you're getting, kind of a
similar answer no matter how you.
Analyze the data, so we'll go over some,
some options there.
I'm also going to show you how to do
repeated-measures ANOVA this week.
So, again I showed you last week, how to
graph repeated-measures outcome data.
We had an example of spine bone density
changing over the time.
I'm showing you these graphics again here.
I was comparing just three small groups of
women, and
you can see that sort of two of the groups
were increasing.
And the, the group in blue here was pretty
much staying flat on bone density.
The graph has a huge amount of
information,
you can pick up a lot just by looking at
the graphic.
However, we usually want to.
Attach something to the graphic like an
effect size in the p-value.
So, this week, we're going to start
talking about statistical tests,
that can be used for analyzing
repeated-measures data.
[BLANK_AUDIO]