[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about several different methods for
testing the proportional hazards
assumption.
So, remember that now that we're dealing
with things over time,
the hazard rate can actually change over
time.
So, we have to test whether or not the
relative difference between the hazard
rates of different groups, whether or not
that's reasonably constant over time.
So, you can imagine here's two hazard
functions over time.
For two groups.
When we calculate a single hazard ratio,
representing the relative difference
between these two groups,
we're assuming that it's reasonably
constant over time, that is, that sort of
the distance between these two lines
doesn't change too much over time.
That's the assumption.
You can imagine a situation where, because
again,
the hazard rates are allowed to kind of do
anything over time.
Maybe the hazard rate for one group looks
like this.
And the hazard rate over time for another
group looks like this.
Now clearly the hazard ratio very early in
the study is very close together,
very small.
Whereas it's huge later on in time.
And so, clearly it would be kind of unfair
to just report a single hazard ratio here,
because there's something interesting
actually happening to
the hazard ratio over time.
So, it's going to to be important to
evaluate the proportional hazards
assumption.
It's difficult to directly graph.
There are ways to try to directly graph
the hazard functions over time for
differing groups.
They're not perfect, though, and they
involve some assumption so we generally
try to get at the proportional hazard
assumption with some indirect methods.
I'm going to give you four different ways
to
evaluate the proportional hazards
assumption.
There's actually even more than this.
Some of these we've already talked about,
so
I already told you about the log, log
plots.
So, remember this is, you're going to take
the Kaplan-Meier survival estimates, and
you're going to take log, negative log of
those estimates and then just.
Plot those over time, for different
groups.
If the log negative plots, log negative
log plots are parallel,
that implies that the hazard functions are
also parallel.
And I like graphical methods for looking
at the proportional hazards function.
Sometimes it's a little fuzzy.
I mean, clearly if you have something that
looks like this, that's pretty good.
They're nice and parallel.
Clearly if you have something that looks
likes this, they're not parallel.
Sometimes there's a little bit of
interpretation involved because it's not
entirely clear you know is that parallel
enough.
But you have to make some kind of
judgement, but in general again I tend to
like graphical methods cause you can
really see the picture of what's going on.
One of the drawbacks of the log-log plots
is that sometimes you do get these
ones that are kind of ambiguous.
Another drawback is that if you've gotta
continuous predictor,
you have to divide it up into categories
in order to be able to make log-log plots.
So, a couple of drawbacks to that method.
I'll go over some examples of each of
these in turn.
I'm just going to kind of introduce them
quickly to you.
Second method that you can use is, you can
actually include
an interaction between your co-variant and
time in the model.
Because, that's what we mean by a
violation of proportional hazards.
We mean that it's, the hazard ratio is
actually.
Actually changing over time which is the
same as saying that the data is
changing over time.
So if you put in an interaction between
your co-variant in time, and that
turns out to be statistically significant
that would tell you that the data, and
therefore the hazard ratio is changing
over time.
So, that's another way to test and I'll go
over each one of these in detail in just.
Giving a brief introduction here.
I already showed you that you can plot the
Schoenfeld residuals against time to
check for proportional hazards.
That's again another plotting method.
And sometimes, people feel a little
uncomfortable with plotting methods.
Again, I like them, but, you know,
sometimes, you get something.
And, it looks like well, maybe there's a
small pattern over time.
It's a little bit unclear, so sometimes if
you would like a p value method,
that interaction with time is going to be
a p value method.
You can also get kind of a p value out the
Schoenfeld residuals.
You can take the Schoenfeld residuals and
just run a linear regression,
where the Schoenfeld residuals are your
outcome and time is your predictor.
And if that turns out to statistically
significant,
that would indicate that, in fact that the
slope here wasn't zero.
That the slope was something other than
zero, so again,
if you want to p-value test, you can do
that.
Let me go over each one of these now in
turn.
Just to have some data here to work with,
recall that we had an example early in the
AIDS epidemic.
100 people who were infected with HIV.
Some are IV drug users and some and we had
different ages and both IV drug use and
age were very highly related to the rate
of death here.
The hazard ratio for IV drug use was 2.5.
For every one year increase in age, it was
1.096.
By fitting that Cox regression model, we
estimated a single hazard ration.
So, we are saying that there is one hazard
ratio, and
that it's relatively constant over time.
If we now wanted to check the proportional
hazards assumption for
both of those variables, I could do some
log-lot plots.
So, I next did some log-lot plots.
So over on the left hand side here is the
log-lot plot for age.
Now because age is a continuous variable,
if I want to do a log-lot plot.
Plot I"m actually going to have to chop
age up into categories.
So, I divided this into less than 30, 30
to 40 and greater than or equal to 40.
You can see, that these lines are nice and
parallel.
Again, if I chopped up age slightly
differently,
I might get slightly different results.
It's probably a good idea to try different
groupings, but in terms of a log-lot plot,
this is about as parallel as, as real data
gets so that looks.
Nice and reasonable.
That proportional hazards assumption
appears to be met there.
For IV drug use, this is the drug users,
and then this one is the non drug users.
What you'll notice here is that the drug
users' line of
their plot ends really quickly into the
study.
That's because all of them died all very
quickly when, when they were HIV positive.
And we're also an IV drug user, they tend
to die very quickly so
that line doesn't extend anymore.
But if you look at the two lines,
they look reasonable parallel it's perhaps
they are separating a little bit over
time they're getting a little bit farther
apart so they're not perfectly parallel.
But again as real data go,
that probably is very reasonable in terms
of the proportional hazards assumption.
So both of those, I would say, meet the
proportional hazards assumption.
Now, just to give you one that actually
doesn't meet
the proportional hazards assumption, to
show you what it would look like,
I'm going to introduce now another example
from Hosmer and Lemeshow.
These were some data that were collected
from a randomized trial, and
these were drug addicted people,
who were randomized to two different
courses of treatment: a long.
A treatment plan and a short treatment
plan, and there was, 628 was the n here.
The outcome here is time-to-relapse, so
they're getting tre, treated for
their drug addiction.
As soon as they relapse and start using
again, that's the, time-to-relapse here.
There were different predictors that they
had, the one we're going to focus on, for
the purposes of this module, is just which
treatment group they were randomized to?
There were other predictors as well.
Here's the Kaplan-Meier curve for the two
randomization groups.
So, this top line here is the.
Those that were randomized to the longer
course of treatment.
The bottom line here,
are those that were randomized to the
shorter course of treatment.
And the log ring test here is significant.
It looks like there was an advantage here
to be, to being randomized to
the long course because they're not
relapsing quite as quickly.
I mean, it does look like a lot of people
did relapse.
But the longer course seem to take a
little bit longer at least to relapse.
It's hard to just look at the Kaplan–Meier
plots and
make any inferences, about the
proportional hazards assumption though.
You need to actually translate this into
the log-log plot.
So, then [INAUDIBLE] data and tell, and
plotted the log-lot plots for
the two groups.
So here's the log-lot plot for the two
groups here.
And what you'll notice is that there does
indeed a, a.
Seem to be some violation of proportional
hazards, though,
the plot clearly crosses here, and then
has some separation later on,
with the control group here being higher
than the treatment group.
So, this plot, again if the lines crossed
that's
usually an indication of a violation of
proportional hazards, this one in
fact does violate proportional hazards
using many methods to look at these data.
I just do, do want to point out that every
now and then you'll see.
A log-lot plot that looks something like
this,
where they kind of like seem to be
crossing all over the place.
But be a little bit careful,
that doesn't necessarily mean you have a
violation of the proportional hazards.
If they're just kind of crossing like
this,
what that might mean is that there's
actually no difference between the groups.
That capillary minor curves should also be
really close.
And then of course, when there's no
difference between the groups, the,
the plots might go back and forth a little
bit.
But this really indicates no difference
between the groups,
rather than a violation of proportional
hazard.
So, just be aware that you might see
plots, log-log plots that look like that.
So, the second way to test a proportional
hazards assumption is actually just to
enter in to your Cox Regression model an
interaction.
Between time and that the co-variate that
you're trying to test this assumption for.
So, it's going to look something like
this.
So, you're going to take your covariate of
interest, I've labelled it x here,
whether this be age or treatment group or
IV drug use.
You interact that co-variant with time,
and
then you're going to have a beta in the
model that represents the interaction.
If that interaction beta is statistically
significant,
that would indicate that indeed the beta.
For your predictor is changing over time,
and
therefore that you have violated
proportional hazards, and
you can see that here, I can just factor
out the x from both of these.
So, what this is saying is that that this
is significantly different from zero,
this interaction beta, then the beta for
x, whatever x is here, is not static over
time.
It's increasing or decreasing with time.
This is again the time interaction
coefficient.
And again, you're looking for statistical
significance here.
Keep in mind that as with any p-value
tests, a really huge sample is going to be
likely to make everything is going to come
out significant, or
a really small sample might miss
statistical significance.
So, keep in mind that with any p value
test,
you always have to think about how to
sample size factor into this.
That's why I often prefer these graphical
methods.
Now notice that if the interaction term,
if that comes out to be negative,
that indicates that beta is decreasing
linearly with time.
Whereas if this term turns out to be
positive, that would indicate that your
beta for the co-variate interest is
increasing linearly with time.
By just putting this time.
By variable co-variant interaction term in
the model.
It not only evaluates proportional
hazards, but
it could be one way to deal with
proportional hazard violations.
So, it it turns out that you're violating
the proportional hazard assumption,
you could leave.
That interaction term in the model.
It is assuming a particular form, for the
change in the hazard ratio over time.
It's assuming that your beta is always
going up or always going down by the same
amount over time, so that may be true for
some cases where there's a violation of
proportional hazards, and it may not be
true for others.
But, it is something to think about that
it could be one way to correct, for
violations of proportional hazards.
As well as to test for it.
So, let me just give some examples of what
I mean here.
So, I ran two models.
The first model is from the HIV data, and
I put age in the model, which we already
saw with the log-log plot,
looked like it, you know, didn't violate
proportional hazards at all.
And then I put in interaction between age
and time.
The p-value for this interaction term is
clearly non-significant, so
it doesn't look like there's any violation
of proportional hazards here.
The second model here, I fit on the drug
treatment,
that randomized trial data set was 628
people.
I put into the model the.
Treatment randomization,
whether you were assigned to the long
course of treatment or the short course.
And then an interaction between your
treatment group and time.
And you'll notice that the interaction
between treatment, and
time was clearly statistically
significant.
So, that's indicating that in fact we do
violate proportional hazards here.
So, we already had evidence from the
log-log plot of evaluation of
proportional hazards.
This is contributing to us believing that
indeed we are this variable,
the treatment variable, does violate
proportional hazards.
I've already mentioned that the Schoenfeld
residuals, if proportional hazards is met,
will have no pattern over time when you
plot them over time.
So, if you see a distinct pattern when you
plot the Schoenfeld residuals against
time for a particular co-variant,
that would indicate a violation of
proportional hazards.
And I'll just give a couple examples,
I've actually shown this a little bit
already but here's an example,
I plotted for the HIV data the Schoenfeld
residuals for age against time.
And remember.
That we only get a Schoenfeld residual for
every person who had an event.
So, there's a hundred people in this data
set, but
we actually have less than a hundred data
points on the graph.
We plot those against time.
It looks you know, right around, it looks
like you know,
when I fit a line to these data, it's nice
the slope is very close to zero.
So that would indicate that there's no
pattern with time,
no violation of proportional hazards here.
In contrast, let me take the data from
that randomized trial of
drug addiction treatment.
I am plotting the Schoenfeld residuals
here, for treatment group against time.
It's a little hard to see because this is
a binary variable, and
therefore we kind of get just two stripes
of residuals, but when I fit a nice
smooth line to these plots, into these
dots, what you see is that I do, indeed.
Have some pattern over time where the
Schoenfeld residuals appear to be
increasing with time.
So that, again, would suggest that we have
a violation of proportional hazards for
this variable.
Now, very related to the Schoenfeld
residual plots is we
can regress the Schoenfeld residuals
against time in a linear regression.
And again, I, I like the plotting methods,
but if you're kind of.
If you get a plot and you're kind of
unsure from the plot.
You can additionally run a linear
regression, to see whether or
not, at least in a linear regression.
The slope of this line, is significantly
different than zero.
So, here is the one for age, from the HIV
data, against time.
I mean it's clear from the graphic here
that there's no pattern across time.
So, we probably don't need to additionally
run the regression here.
But you can do it.
The outcome will be the show and tell of
residuals.
And my predictor will be time.
And this will be a regular older liner
regression.
So I ran my linear regression.
I look at the data for time.
And clearly, the p value for time is
totally non significant.
This looks like a really, really flat
life.
So, no violation of proportional hazards
apparent here.
In contrast, I can take the Shoenfeld
residuals for
that treatment group in the drug addiction
treatments.
Study, and I can regress that against
time, so
I'd have my residuals again, and time as
the predictor in a linear regression,
and if I go and look at the beta and the
p-value here for this regression,
the p-value for time is clearly
statistically significant.
So, that would again point to the fact
that proportional hazards, is violated for
this treatment variable.
So, again there's many different ways to
test for proportional hazards,
sometimes it's just really clear from the
log log plot and you can stop there.
Sometimes you look at the log-log plot and
you're not sure.
So you might want to try some of these
other methods.
But just to summarize we could examine the
law log-log plots.
Parallel lines mean we have proportional
hazards.
Crossing lines, or
nearly crossing lines, tell us that we
violate proportional hazards.
The drawback here, is was that we could
only use categorical predictors or
we'd have to chop our continuous
predictors into some sort of
category just to be able to do those
plots.
We can also include an interaction with
time in the model,
if that interaction time is non
significant, then there's no apparent
violation of proportional hazards, if we
get a significant interaction coefficient
that would indicate a violation of
proportional hazards.
And in fact, there may be, it may turn out
that that's a way to correct for
the violation of proportional hazard,
is just to leave that interaction term in
the model.
That's going to work for
some situations but not for all, because
that then is assuming that
there's a particular way in which the
hazard ratio is changing over time.
We can plot the Schoenfeld residuals
against time and look for
non-random patterns, non-random.
Patterns would indicate violations of
proportional hazards,
and then finally we could actually take
those Shoenfeld residuals and
regress them against time in a linear
regression.
If our time variable turns out to be
statistically significant that would
indicate a violation of proportional
hazards whereas non-significance would
indicate no evidence of a, a violation of
that assumption.