I'm now going to have you practice
actually writing out
the likelihood when you have a time
changing predictor variable.
And I've made up a little mock dataset
that's small enough that you
can write out the entire likelihood.
So this dataset contains time-to-event,
the event here is death.
So, this is time to death.
Whether or not they die, died is one and
zero is censored.
And then it has a time changing predictor
of weight.
So, weight was measured here at baseline,
three months, six months, and nine months.
And what I want you to do is to write out
the likelihood equation if you
are modeling a Cox regression where you
included weight as
a time changing predictor.
And so what that means is, for
example, the first term in the likelihood
happens when the first event happens.
So the first event occurs at two months
into the study.
So at two months into the study when you
write that term and
a likelihood, you're going to incorporate
the weights that were last measured.
Well, at two months into this study the,
the last measured weight is the baseline
weight because we didn't update the
weights again until three months.
So, for that term in the likelihood you'll
be including the weight at baseline.
At eight months, when there's another
event at eight months, for
that event you're going to include into
the likelihood the last measured weight.
So, the last measured weight at
eight months was the measurement done at
six months.
So you'll be including the weights from
six months into that term of
the likelihood and so on.
There are three events here so there
should be three terms in the likelihood.
So now, I want you to pause the video and
actually try writing out that whole
likelihood on your own.
And then, when you're done, restart the
video and I'll walk you through it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
All right, so hopefully you were able to
write that out without too much trouble.
It is a little cumbersome to write out the
whole thing.
Again, we are doing a Cox Regression Model
here where our only predictor in
the model is weight.
But weight here is a time changing
predictor.
Notice we're going to get one data for
weight, but it's going to be based on the
changing weight.
So, it's going to be interpreted as the
effect for your current or
your most recently measured weight.
How would you actually write the
likelihood out here?
While there are three events occurring at
two months, eight months and
ten months into the study, so our
likelihood will have three terms in it.
What I did to make the problem a little
easier was,
I reordered my observations here from the
lowest time to the highest time.
It just makes it simpler to find
everything when you're writing out
the likelihood.
So, the first term of the likelihood
occurs at two months.
Before two months we have somebody
censored, so they're no longer at risk.
So, the first term in the likelihood will
have in the denominator eight people,
the eight who are still at risk.
Because we're only two months into this
study,
the last measured weight is the baseline
weight so
we'll be using the baseline weight in this
term in the likelihood.
So the person who had the event weighed
240 pounds so
their risk, their hazard is e rate to beta
times 240.
Everybody else who's at risk gets a term
in the denominator here.
So, the person who had the event, of
course, was at risk.
And then everybody else.
So, we had somebody who weighed 110.
We had another person at 130, and 200 I'm
going to just run over the line here.
180, 140, and it's a little tedious to
write out,
but you can write it out without too much
trouble.
So hopefully you've got something like
that for your first term.
For the second term in the likelihood,
it's going to be a little easier because a
lot of things are going away.
We had some people being censored, so now
at eight months into the study,
when the next event occurs, we only have
five people at risk.
That'll make the term a little less
cumbersome.
The weight that we're going to use now
that
we're going to enter into the likelihood
is the weight from six months,
because that was the last weight measured
before eight months.
So, at six months into this study, the
person who had the event was 250 pounds,
and those at risk were 250, 240, 155.
145 and again, I'm going to run out of
room here, I'll just scroll over, and 180.
And then finally, we lose this subject
because they died.
Finally the, the last event time occurred
at ten months into this study, and
there were four people left at risk.
Now there's actually two ways you could
have set this up,
because I had two people at ten.
I had one who is censored at ten and one
who had the event at ten.
And I have got their time as exactly the
same because I rounded the months here.
If you were to put that into SAS, SAS will
count the one who is censored,
the censoring as having at, happened after
the event.
So that censored person would be at risk
at ten months.
So we're going to say that they're at risk
If you did it the other way and, and
dropped them, that's fine too.
You kind of have to know how the algorithm
in the computer is handling it.
But we're going to include the,
we're going to say they were at risk and
then they were censored at ten months.
So, they were at risk at ten months.
So, we're going to have in the numerator
here, now we're using the weights from
nine months into the study, because that
was the last measured weight.
The person who had the event was 280
pounds.
And those at risk.
There were four at risk with the following
weights.
[SOUND].
So that's what the complete likelihood
function would look like here.
We would then maximize this likelihood
function to get the beta that made
our data the most likely.
And just for fun, I actually went ahead
and
plugged these data into the computer and
actually solved for beta.
Now this is a really small dataset and so,
in fact, the estimates that I'm getting
here are really unstable.
But we can actually get a hazard ratio to
pop out out of the computer with some
warnings about convergence.
And just for fun, again, these are made up
data.
When I made these data up, I made it so
that I, you know,
as a person was dying that their last
measured weight was a little bit higher.
I tried to make the higher weights link to
time, somewhere near the time of death.
So, obviously we're expecting to get
something where
there's an association here.
So when I actually ran these in,
in the computer when I used weight as a
time-changing
variable corresponding to the likelihood
that we just wrote out there.
I got a hazard ratio of 8.8, and again
with all the caveats and
this being a very unstable, and very small
sample of made up data.
But you know, because I made up the data
for there to be a link there,
I got a very high hazard ratio.
Now, I then ran a model where I included
a,
vary a predictor, a weight predictor that
did not change over time.
So you could use, like, the baseline
weight here, or you could use, like,
their average weight over the entire time
we saw them.
When I used the baseline rate, I only got
a hazard ratio of 2.7 and
when I used the average weight I got a
hazard ratio of 1.2.
And these is, this is just to show you
that it can make a really big difference,
even with real data, if you actually allow
the predictor to change over time,
it can show when things are correlated in
time.
So, when your current weight, your most
recent weight is the thing that
matters in terms of mortality, that's
reflected better in the hazard rate
when time weight was modeled as a
time-changing predictor.