So, I told you that Cox Regression only
estimates hazard ratios.
It doesn't estimate the underlying
survival curve.
However, I do want to let you know that it
is possible to
pair up the results from a Cox regression.
With a non-parametric estimate of the
survival curve so
that you can essentially get the best of
both worlds.
So Cox regression estimates the effects of
each predictor, the hazard ratios.
Without estimating that underlying hazard
or survival function.
But you can take the results from the Cox
regression.
Which tells you which tell you how much
each predictor contributes to
the mortality rate or the rate of event.
And you can pair it up with the results
from a non-parametric estimate of
the survival group such as a Kaplan Meyer.
And I'm just going to illustrate this with
an example.
So this example,
a data set comes from Applied Survival
Analysis by Hosmer and Lemeshow.
And it, they had some data from early in
the AIDS epidemic on a sample size of 100.
Now this was early in the AIDS epidemic.
So as you'll see that that death rates
were pretty high.
The outcome here is time to death.
And, we're just going to look at two
predictors.
A person's age, and whether or not they
were an IV drug user.
IV drug users were hit very hard early in
the AIDS epidemic, of course.
So just to show you the effect of these
two predictors using Kaplan-Meier curves.
What you're seeing over here on the right
is the IV drug use.
So the bottom curve represents the IV drug
users.
And the top curve is the non-drug users.
And you can see that survival overall was
pretty poor for both groups.
But the IV drug users did much worse.
Their much higher risk group probably had
a higher co-morbidities.
Age of course is a continuous predictor.
So it's hard to do in a Kaplan-Meier.
But you had, you can categorize age to
make a Kaplan-Meier plot.
So that's what I've done on the left here.
So this is the greater than, or,
sorry, this, the, the ones who did the
best is the young group.
So the less than 30 group had the, the
best survival.
The worst survival was in the age group
greater than or equal to 40.
So you can see that clearly,
age in IV drug users strongly related to
survival here.
We can then run a Cox Regression model,
which models the effects of age and drug
use.
And so I've done that now with this data
set.
Notice there's no intercepts in the
output.
Because, again, in a Cox regression we
don't get any intercepts.
So you can see that both IV drug use and
age were highly significantly related to
to death here.
We get hazard ratios.
So the hazard ratio for IV drug use is
2.5.
So IV drug users were 2.5 fold,
had a mortality rate that was 2.5 fold
higher than non-drug users.
The hazard ratio for age is 1.096.
Which looks small, but remember this is
for every one year increase in age.
So just going up one year in age increased
your mortality rate by almost 10%.
So that's actually a pretty big effect.
So those are the results from the Cox
regression.
But what we can do is we can pair up the
Cox regression model
with the Kaplan-Meier estimates of the
survival curve.
And that's what I'll show you now.
So I actually want to show you what's
right here first.
This is the Kaplan-Meier curve, survival
curve for
the entire cohort, not stratified on
anything.
So we, not taking into account age or
anything, just the whole cohort.
The whole 100 people, that's the survival
curve.
We compare that curve up again with the
Cox Regression.
And that's what I'm showing you on the
left here.
This is kind of results from the Cox
regression model.
So, we take the estimates of Kaplan–Meier.
And then we factor in, how does age and
drug use, how do those affect the survival
curve?
This curve I'm showing you on the left
takes just the mean value of age and
the mean value of drug use.
Which will be a percentage.
And plugs those in and then draws a
survival curve.
Since I'm taking the mean age and mean
drug use value at the sample.
I'm going to get a curve that looks
basically just like the Kaplan-Meier curve
for the overall cohort.
That's what I'm showing you here.
So that doesn't look particularly useful.
Because it looks, it's like, why not just
use the Kaplan-Meier curve?
What's useful though is then, you can go
in and rather than use the mean age.
You can plug in different values for age
and drug use.
To get curves for different groups of
people.
And that's what I've done next.
So here I'm showing you two different
types of people.
I'm drawing the survival curve on the
left.
Stay inside here, for somebody who is 55
years old.
This is their predicted survival curve.
They're 55 years old, and they are an IV
drug user.
Those are two hits against them.
They're very, very high risk.
And you can see that their surv, their
predicted survival is that, for
that group, the predicted survival curve
is very, very low.
That is, it's it drops extremely steeply.
In the middle line here, the solid line,
is the predicted survival curve.
And the dotted lines represent the 95%
confidence intervals around that.
You can also put those on.
So you can see that, you know, somebody,
obviously because age and drug use were so
related to survival, that that person is
predicted to die, to die very quickly.
For somebody who's younger and
is not an IV drug user, their survival
probabilities look much better.
So, this is the predicted curve for
somebody age 22 who is not an IV drug
user.
And again, these outer bounds, these
dotted lines,
just represent the 95% confidence
interval.
So, this is very nice.
Because now you have a way to actually get
absolute predicted values for
survival probabilities for certain people.
And to draw nice graphics, which you can't
get if you just use Cox regression alone.