[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module,
I'm going to show you how to code time
changing predictors in SAS.
And we'll also do something similar in the
lab, but this'll serve as an introduction.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So going back to made up data set that I
made you write the likelihood for, so
this was a data set which was looking at
time to death, and
weight was measured at baseline, 3 months,
6 months and 9 months into the study.
And I, the code, the way these variables
are coded, is w0, w3, w6 and w9.
I've named those variables that.
I told you that I actually, this is a mock
data set and
these estimates are kind of unstable, but
I still went ahead and
put this data into SAS and [INAUDIBLE] Cox
regressions with different predictors,
different forms of a predictor in the
model.
So, when I chose baseline weight, so
that as I just put w0 in as my predictor
in the model.
I got a hazard ratio of 2.7.
When I use the average weight, which
doesn't exist in this data set, but
I made a new variable average weight and
I just averaged whatever weights they had
available.
So, add up these four and divide by four
for an example, when I, with that,
that in as a static predictor in my model,
I get a hazard ratio of 1.2.
And as I told you before, when I then
model the weight as a time-changing
variable, allowing it to change over time,
I got a hazard ratio of 8.8.
But how did I actually, do this,
how did I actually get a time-changing
predictor to run in SAS?
I'm going to show you the code now.
So first of all, if you wanted to use a
time static, a, a non
time-changing predictor, like baseline
weight like, w0, that's very easy to code.
You just put the variable in as a
predictor on the model line.
If I wanted to put an average weight,
again, average weight doesn't change, so
I would just use the variable average
weight.
That's easy.
But for a time dependent predictor, it's
slightly more complicated.
So here's what the code looks like that I
used to calculate that
hazard ratio of 8.8.
So, I'm putting in, one of the things that
you're allowed to
do in proc phreg in SAS is that you are
allowed to create variables on the fly.
This is really the only way that you could
code time changing predictors.
You're allowed to name a variable that
doesn't exist in the data set.
There's no variable in the data set called
weight.
I'm allowed to just name it on the model
line,
as one of the predictors on the model
line, and then define it below.
So I'm allowed to just make up variables
on the fly and
define them of, below, and that's what I
have to do for time changing predictors.
So I made up a variable weight, and then I
defined weight.
And basically I said, this time,
whenever I say time in this code, below
the model line, that means the event time.
So whatever event time we're on, whatever
event time we are on in drawing out
the likelihood, we're going to be
comparing that time to, we're going to be
using if then statements to figure out
which weight we should be using.
So, if the event time is less than three,
then the weight that we want to use the
value we want to use for weight, for
this predictor variable weight, for that
event time, is w0, the base line weight.
because that was the most recent weight,
if we're below 3 months in the study.
If the event time is between 3 and 6
months,
then we can use w3, the weight that was
measured at 3 months.
So now my value for those variable weight
changes, when I'm plugging into
the likelihood function changes, to the
weight measured at 3 months.
And then I do a series of if then
statements,
so if the event happens between 6 and 9,
I'll use the weight from the 6 months,
if the event time is after then or equal
to 9, I use the weight from 9 months.
That's the general set up of a code.
Again, you are going to be, when you put
down time here, you mean the event time.
So let me go into this in just a tiny bit
more detail.
What is SAS actually doing behind the
scenes here?
So what SAS is doing is, whenever you name
a time-dependent variable, what it has to
do is it has to create for that variable,
a variable for each event time.
So you can imagine it's basically creating
a temporary data set.
In this case, we had three events, so
the variable weight actually has three
columns, three variables, in the data set.
So weight, there is going to be a weight
at the first event time, 2 months into
the study, a weight at the second event
time which was 8 months into the study and
weight at the third event time which was
10 months into the study.
If we had 10 event times,
there would be 10 columns in this
temporary data set that SAS is creating.
So weight is a multi-column variable.
How does SAS figure out what to put in
each of these columns?
That's where my if and statements come in.
So weight for the first event time.
Remember the first event time here
happened at 2 months into the study.
So when time was 2, what were all the
weights for people?
So SAS goes to the if and statements to
figure that out.
So it says, okay, if the event time was
less than 3, oh, yes.
Check.
The event time was less than 3, so
2 is less than three.
Then I need to use for the val, variable
weight the w0, the baseline weight.
So that's what I filled in here.
All of the baseline weights for all of my
subjects.
SAS then goes to the next event time.
So the next event time occurred at 8
months into the study.
And it goes in through these if then
statements.
Is time less than 3?
No.
Is time between 3 and 6?
Is time between 6 and 9?
Yes.
8 is between 6 and
9, so we're now on this row here.
So if ti, the event time is between 6 and
9, then use the value for w6.
So we're going to use the weight that was
measured 6 months into the study, so
that's what I plug into this column.
Some of the people were no longer
available 6 months into the study so
they just have a missing value.
Then the final event happened at 10 months
into the study.
So SAS creates another column here, and
goes to the code.
If time is less than 3, no.
If time is between 3 and 6, no.
If time is between 6 and 9, no.
If time is greater than or equal to 9,
yes.
10 is greater than 9.
So then we use the weight w9.
We, so I filled in, in this column, the
values for the 9 month weight for
those subjects who, who had a 9 month
weight.
So SAS creates this temporary data set, so
that it can use in the likelihood for the
first event time this column, for
the second event time this column, and for
the third event time this column.
That's what SAS is doing behind the scenes
and
that, you're going to kind of need to know
that in order to be able to
think out exactly how to code your time
changing predictors.
You really do have to think it out
carefully.
Just to give you one more example, so I
showed you this example when we
were talking again in the module about
time-dependent predictors,
what those look like in the likelihood
function.
So we have seven subjects numbered 1
through 7,
and the outcome here was time to fracture
the stress fracture.
We have their various times in this study.
Some of the women took oral
contraceptives.
So we have a date which they started a
time in the study which they started oral
contraceptives and which they stopped.
So subject six never started them and
therefore never stopped them.
Subject 2 started oral contraceptives 10
months into the study but
stopped them at 11 months into the study,
and so on.
And I already show you,
showed you what the likelihood would look
like for these data.
But how would I actually enter these data
into SAS, and
code tells SAS to model this as a time
changing predictor.
What would the code look like?
So I went ahead for this little, little
data set and wrote out some code.
So our model here is time and our element
here is fracture, so
this zero is the censored value, and I've
created another variable on the fly, so
I'm just noticing in my data set there's
no variable called called onoc.
But I'm making up a new variable which I'm
calling onoc, or on oral contraceptives.
And then I have to define it below.
Again, whenever I say time, I mean the
current event time.
So, if they never started oc, so
if startoc is equal to 0, then they can
never be on oc.
So if they never started oral
contraceptives, I know for
sure that they can't be on them.
So I've decided to just put a code right
out there that says if they never starts
oc's, if that's a missing value, then they
can't be on oc's.
So onoc's equals 0.
They're not on oc's.
Else if, if that's not the case, if they
did start them,
then the time at which they started oc's
is less than the event time.
So, meaning that they've already started
them.
And, there, the time that they ended oc's
is greater than the current event time,
then they would be onoc.
So let me give you an example.
If we looked at the woman who fractured at
6 months into the study.
So our time co-event being here at 6
months.
So we're in, thinking about the, sort of
this is the onoc value for
time 6, the event time 6.
If you go through the data set, well this
person has never started oc's, so
she gets a value of, of zero for onoc's.
The second person subject 2, is not on
oc's at that time, because their
startOC is 10, their stopoc is 11, so if
you look at the code, time now is 6.
You know, their startoc is 10.
Well, 10 is not less than 6, so right away
then, onoc is not going to work at this,
and this condition is not fulfilled.
Then I have if otherwise, if the start is
greater than the 6,
so is startoc greater than 6?
Yes.
If either one of those is true,
then you're not onoc's.
If you haven't started them yet, you can't
be on them.
So if I go through the logic here for this
one, then she's going to get a value of 0.
The next one, she started at 0 and stopped
at 12, so we go back to the logic here.
So she started oc, so we go here, else if
start oc, so now our time is again,
the event time 6 months, she started oc's
at 0 months into the study.
She ended oc's at 12 months into the
study, so
0 is less than 6, yes and 12 is greater
than 0, and 12 is greater than 6, sorry.
12 is greater than 6, yes, so then she
gets a value of onoc's is equal to 1.
So she'd get a value of 1.
And you keep going, so Subject 7, 1 is
clearly less than 6.
And 7 is greater than 6, so she would also
get a value of, of 1 for onoc's.
And this one would get 1, this one would
get 0, and this one would get 1.
So, at event time 6, those would be the
women on oc's.
When we then run this model in SAS, we're
going to get a hazard ratio that
represents when you're actually taking or
have recently taken oral contraceptives,
how much does that protect you against
fracture?
[BLANK_AUDIO]