In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about a neat little trick available in
cart regression called stratification.
So, let's say you test for proportional
hazards for a particular variable,
and you find that that assumption is
violated, then what do you do?
So, the first thing you should do is to
try to understand why?
What's going on underneath the problem,
biologically, what, what have you,
that could explain why we're seeing a
violation of proportional hazards?
So, first really try to grapple with
understanding why?
Then auctions for sort of assumptions.
We talked about adding a time by covariate
interaction in the model.
If you're doing that, if you're adding a
time by covariate interaction,
what you're essentially saying is that
you're modeling an extra beta in there,
that tells you that you're, the beta for
your covariate is increasing or decreasing
linearly.
With time.
That model would be the correct model for
certain situations, and
it might not be correct for, for other
situations.
But if indeed, that's the correct model or
a reasonable approximation,
that would be one way to deal with the
proportional hazards is to,
explicitly model the fact that the hazard
ratio is changing over time.
There are other options if it doesn't
quite fit increasing or
decreasing linearly with time, there are
other options such as
adding a time-dependent version of the
co-variate of interest, and
that's something we're going to get into
next week.
A third option is to stratify on that
variable.
If you stratify on the variable, you don't
have to meet proportional hazards.
You will end up not getting a hazard
ratio.
You won't be estimating a hazard ratio for
that variable, but for
many nuance things that you just need to
adjust for, but you don't really care
about the effect, stratification turns
about to be a very reasonable option.
The other option is there may be some
situations where you violate proportional
hazards, but you don't end up modifying
your model in any way.
You can imagine that there might be a case
where the hazard ratio does seem to
be changing somewhat over time.
But, perhaps the summary hazard ratio,
a single hazard ratio, sort of an average
over time is a reasonable summary.
Captures the take home message reasonably
well, so
you may end up just reporting that, but of
course you'll want to note in your
paper that there was a violation, and what
kinds of effects that could have.
But for this module, I'm going to be
focusing on stratification.
I actually think the easiest way to
understand stratification is to start with
the likelihood function.
If you see what's going on in the
likelihood function, I think.
Stratification makes perfect sense.
So, this is a little complicated but I
already took this simple data set and
I, I drew out part of the likelihood
function just so
I wouldn't have to sit here and, and write
everything out which takes time.
But here is the idea with stratification.
This is a data set which.
We've got, time to event, whether or not
the person died,
age, we're going to have a model here, Cox
Regression
model, with one predictor in the model,
which is age.
So the beta I'm writing down here is the
beta for age.
Age, and we're going to stratify on
gender.
How does that actually get incorporated
into the likelihood function?
That's what this slide is showing.
So here is gender, one is male, zero is
female.
So, we're going to start the likelihood
function,
remember the likelihood function, put the
term in the model for every event time.
So, first event happens at times equals
one.
That event occurred in a male, the male
was 60 years old.
So, when we add a term to the likelihood
function, we are only going to
put men into that strata, into that term
in the likelihood function.
In other words, we are only going to be
care, comparing men to men.
So, what you'll notice is that when I
wrote out this first term in
the likelihood function, for time 1, I
only have men in the numerator and the.
In the risk set in the denominator.
So I've got the person who died, was a 60
year old male.
So they get their hazard their chance of
dying at one month is
e raised to the baseline hazard function
and
I'm explicitly putting it in here just to
show you.
How it kind of factors in and then we have
a beta for age in the model.
So, times e raised to beta times the
person's age.
This person was 60.
So, the person who died goes in the
numerator there were four men at
risk at time 1.
The 60 year old the 55 year old man, the
60 year old and the 50 year old.
So, I put a term in the denominator for
each one of them, representing their
probability of dying at time 1.
So, here's the person who actually died.
Here's the 55 year old, the 60 year old,
and the 50 year old.
Notice that they all have the same,
we're assuming that they all have the same
hazard at one month into the study.
And some hazard rate that we can cancel.
But we're only canceling the hazard rate.
For men to men.
So, everybody in this term is a male,
we're cancelling out those hazard rates
for men.
We have, don't have any women, we have
kept, we're keeping the men and
the women separate in the likelihood here.
Now let's go to time 0.3.
At time 0.3 there's another event.
This event happens to be a woman who dies.
She's 65 years old.
What goes in the likelihood?
So, we're going to have a term.
The woman who died, she gets a term in the
likelihood that's e raised to
the baseline hazard at 3 times the effect
of age, essentially.
I've indicated here again that there's
the, the hazard rate for
females at [INAUDIBLE].
Three is female specific.
It might be different than the hazard rate
would be for men.
But we're only care, comparing women to
women so
there's three women in the denominator,
the 65 year old, the 45 year old, and
the 40 year old, who were all the ones.
Who were at risk at time 3.
So again, only comparing women to women,
so,
means we're canceling out the baseline
hazards for women at this time point.
We're assuming it's all the same.
But we've made no assumptions whatsoever
about the relationship between
the hazard function for men, the baseline
hazard function for
men, and the baseline hazard function for
women.
In other words, if we plotted over time,
the baseline hazard function for
men might look like this, and the baseline
hazard function for
women might look like this, and that's
perfectly fine.
Because we are only canceling men with men
and
only women with women, so we're making no
assumptions that those baseline hazard
functions have any particular relationship
to one another.
Just to keep going on the likelihood I
think you're getting the idea now,
by time point 4 was a man so
I've determined that goes in the
likelihood we will only have men.
There were 3 men at risk, the 55-year-old,
the 60-year-old, and
the 50-year-old, and again we can cancel
out the baseline hazards, but
make no assumption about the relationship
between the baseline hazards for men and
the baseline hazards for women.
Now notice, when we set up the likelihood
in this way,
there's a couple of important things.
So first of all, I only have a beta for
age that I'm estimating.
I am not estimating any beta for gender,
because I am never comparing men and
women, so I can't say what the effect of
gender is here.
However, that's fine if I don't care about
the effect of gender, but
I want to adjust for it, and
make no assumption about proportional
hazards, this is the way to do it.
Something else to note, the other
assumption that I'm making here is,
I'm essentially, what I'm doing is,
there's a single beta.
I am using the same beta in the terms for
men as I am using in the terms for women.
So what I'm essentially doing is
calculating a weighted average of
the betas, weighted, you know, there's a
beta for men and a beta for women.
I'm assuming those betas are the same, and
I'm sort of calculating an average beta
across men and women.
The only potential issue there is that I'm
assuming that there is
no interaction between age and gender
here, so
that's something that I'd want to test
before I stratified on gender.
Because obviously I'm, making that
assumption.
I'm just averaging over men and women
here.
So that's the general idea of
stratification again.
It's great for nuisance variables, like if
you've done a multi-site study, and you
need to adjust for the fact that different
sites might be slightly different.
But you don't really care about the effect
of sight, it would be perfectly
reasonable to stratify on site, rather
than putting it in the model.
And just a few notes on stratification.
Again, different strata are allowed to
have different baseline hazard functions,
and there's no assumption.
That those hazard functions are parallel
between different strata.
So that's the, the neat trick here.
Essentially we're, what we get out at the
end of the day is a weighted hazard ratio.
It's been weighted over the different
strata, weighted over men and women.
So again, we're assuming there's no
interaction between,
the stratification variable and the
covariants we.
That we care about.
Again, it's very useful for
nuisance confounders where you don't want
to estimate the effect because your,
you lose the ability to estimate the
effect if you stratify on it.
And again it assumes no interaction
between the stratification variable and
the main predictors.
So, you'd want to make sure that you
tested that from the outset.