So before I show you how to analyze time
changing predictors with
generalized estimating equations, I'm
first going to show you how to graph them.
So I made up a little data set just for us
to have some data to work with.
For time changing predictors.
So in this data set I've got just six
patients and they're all depressed and
they're all given the same drug.
Our time changing predictor here is levels
of some kind of happy chemical in
the brain and our outcome here is scores
on a depression questionnaire.
So for example, subject number one they
had a score of 20 at their,
on depression score at base line that went
down to 18 and
then down to 15 and then popped back up to
20.
Meanwhile their ca, their levels of happy
chemical in their brain starting at
a thousand and increased throughout the
study.
And everybody was given a drug that's
supposed to increase that,
their happy chemical levels in the brain.
So that's the data in the broad form and
of course we'll also be putting the data
into the long form and you can see that
here.
In fact the time periods were not even.
So subjects were measured at base line and
then two months into the study.
And then at three months.
And then at six months.
So time is actually not one, two, three,
four, here it's zero two three six.
So how are we actually going to graph
these data.
So if you've got a continuous time change
predictor and a continuous time changing
outcome, you can actually put both of
those on the same graphic, by having one
on you know, one Y axis and one on a
second Y axis, as I'm showing you here.
So, the, I'm going to graph, both of these
against time, and
I want to say does the change in
depression scores,
does that relate to the change in chemical
levels over time.
And I graphed this, I only have 6
subjects, so I just graphed this to start
with, separately by subject, so here is
the first subject.
So, I already showed you that that
subject's depression scores started at 20.
They went down, and they went back up to
20.
Meanwhile, their chemical levels kind of
had a steady increase over time.
The chemical levels here are in red.
I made up these data, so I tried to make
up these data in a way that,
in general, as the chemical levels go up
the depression score tends to go down.
I then graphed subjects two and three.
You can see same idea.
So for example subject number two, the
chemical level's kind of flat and
then it goes down.
While the chemical level's going down the
depression score is going up.
The chemical level goes up in subject
number three at the same time
the depression scores goes down.
So these are inversely.
They're kind of going together inversely
in each of these individual subjects.
That's subject four and subject five.
Subject four you can see this nice
progression where as chemical level goes
up, the depression goes down.
As the chemical level goes down, the
depression goes up, and so on.
I mean I've made up these data, so
I sort of built in that there's an
association here.
And finally subject number six.
Clearer association as the chemical level
goes up, the, in the brain,
the happy chemical goes up in the brain,
the depression score goes down.
And then we can plot these all together in
a single mean plot, and
you can see that yeah, in general, over
time, as the,
the chemical level seems to drift upwards
over time.
It's not totally perfect, but it's seeming
to go upwards over time.
Meanwhile, the depression score is seeming
to go downwards over time.
So they seem to be doing something
together inversely.
Anyway, this is just to make the point
that you can,
if you have a time changing predictor, put
it on the same graphic as
the time changing outcome as long as those
are both continuous variables.
[BLANK_AUDIO]