[BLANK_AUDIO].
Welcome to unit six.
This week we're going to switch modes.
We're now done with our discussion of
survival analysis.
And the second half of the course is
going to focus on repeated measures data.
This is the situation where you've
measured an outcome variable on
the same people.
At multiple time points.
So, most of the outcomes that we're
going to look at in the second half of
this course are actually going to be
continuous outcomes.
Things like blood pressure, weight, and
bone density.
Because of that, we're mostly going to be
dealing with linear models.
The statistical models that I'm going to
give you are going to be
extensions of our basic ANOVA and linear
regression models.
So what I thought I'd do for the.
Beginning of this week is actually to
review basic ANOVA and linear regression.
Before we complicate them and add the
complexity of repeated measures,
let's make sure we're all on the same page
about just the basics of ANOVA and
linear regression.
This week I'll also just give you an
introduction.
To what does repeated measures data look
like.
So, I'll show you some examples from the
literature.
I'll talk about the different data
structures for repeated measures.
There's actually kind of two ways to
structure the data and
depending on what you're trying to do in
the computer you nee,
you may need it in one or the other form.
And I'll also give you some examples of
how to plot your repeated-measures data.
Plotting is going to be very important
here for
you get to get a real understanding of
what's going on in the data.
Just to ground us on where are we on our
statistical chart of tasks, so
again I will talk a little bit about some
binary repeated measures.
Outcome data in the second half of this
course, but
I'm mostly going to fit, focus on
continuous outcomes.
So, if we have continuous outcomes, these
are things like again, blood pressure,
weight, pain scale, cognitive function on
some kind of continuous scale.
If we have independent groups, or
independent observations,
we're going to be doing something like a
basic ANOVA or a basic linear regression.
I'm going to review those this week.
If we add correlations into the picture.
We have some source of correlation.
Such as that we've measured the same
people over time,
then we're going to need slightly more
complicated statistical tests.
So in the next three weeks I'm going to
review repeated measures in ANOVA,
mixed models and GEE models.
These will handle the correlation due to
having the same people over time.
They would also handle other sources of
correlation such as
clustering although I'm mostly going to
focus on the problem of repeated measures.
This week again though I'm not going to go
over any specific statistical tests for
the repeated measures, I'm just going to
talk about the basic data structure.
So what does the data look like that we're
going to be dealing with in
the second half of this.
course.
Here is just an example of some data that
I analyzed a number of years ago.
This was a data set which was a
longitudinal data set.
So women were measured over time.
These were women runners, and we measured
their bone density at base line.
And about a year later, and then about two
years later.
What you're seeing here is the changes in
bone density over time for
three different groups of women.
And the way that I've presented the data
here is to show you that I started.
I'm presenting it as the mean change from
base line.
So everybody starts at zero.
That's the base line value.
And then I'm giving, every woman gets her
percent change from her base line value.
This is one way to.
Present repeated-measures outcome data.
And you can see that what happens is that
the group in blue here,
they have a slight decrease in the first
year, and
then they kind of go back up to what they
started at.
But they basically have no change overall.
In their bone density.
in contrast, the groups that are in red
and
black here have some increase in their
bone density over time.
About a two or 3% increase for those
groups.
So these are the types of data that we're
going to be looking at for
the rest of this course.