[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module,
I'm going to show you how to analyze
time-independent predictors, that is,
predictors that don't change over time,
using generalized estimating equations.
So first of all, what do I mean by a
time-independent predictor?
So you can probably guess what that is,
but the easiest way to see it.
To see what a time interdependent
predictor is,
is to just look at the long form of the
data.
As I've got in this box over here.
If your predictor of interest has the same
value for every time point.
Within an individual then that is a time
independent predictor.
It is not changing over time.
So for example, I've been using the spine
bone density example.
Here's a person, ID number one.
Her bone density, her outcome is changing
over time.
Her time value is changing over time.
But her group, which group she's in,
whether black, blue or red, is the same at
every time point.
So you can see it in the data set.
If her group were to change then that
would be a time changing predictor.
Of course the case of time independent
predictors is easier so
we're going to start there.
So, in this data set, I had actually
grouped women into whether or
not they got their periods back or didn't
and these are static groups.
I didn't allow the groups to change over
time.
I've shown you these pictures before the
red group and
the black group improve more that the blue
group over time.
You've already seen that.
I now want to fit a GEE model to these
data.
So what's the model that we're going to
fit?
So my outcome here is bone density.
I'm going to have an intercept in this
model.
I'm essentially fitting a linear model.
My model is going to have very similar to
what we had in
the repeated measures ANOVA, it's going to
have time in it.
That represents a time effect.
It's going to have a variable for the main
effect for which group you're in.
And essentially like the group effect in
repeated measures ANOVA.
And then you have to interact any
variables,
any time independent variables that you're
interested in seeing.
What their effect is on the change in bone
density over time,
you have to put an interaction with those
variables, with time into the model.
And you have to remember to put that in.
So for, when we're talking about
time-independent predictors,
you must include an interaction term with
time if you want to
get it within subjects effect.
That is if you want to see what's the
effect of group on the changes over time.
And usually that's what we care about so
that's the model that I fit to these data.
And let me just show you the results.
I chose an exchangeable correlation matrix
to start with because I've
already looked at the correlation matrix
for these data.
And either exchangeable or autoregressive,
when we just had time in the model,
both of those seemed to do, pretty close
to one another.
So we just started with the simpler one,
the exchangeable correlation matrix.
So it's the same data set,
that I showed you in the last module,
where I was showing you that we have,
indeed, significant changes in bone
density over time.
Now we want to see whether that differs by
which of these groups you're in.
So I'm going to just walk you though, how
to interpret all of these coefficients.
All of these parameters from the model.
So starting with the intercept, what does
the intercept represent here?
So the reference group, I've chosen the
reference group to be the blue group.
They are the ones that had the lowest bone
density and the lowest bone
density changes over time, so it just made
sense to make them the reference group.
The intercept of course represents when
everything else in the model is
set to zero.
So, because we have time in the model that
mean that
the intercept represents a base line value
when time is equal to zero.
The intercept also represents the
reference group for
all the group variables so it's
representing the blue group.
So the intercept represents the value for
the spine bone density for the blue group
at baseline.
So if you remember from last week, the
blue group actually started with
a little bit lower bone density than the
other two groups.
It was right around 0.93.
So that's the baseline average spine bone
density in the blue group.
And that's highly significant.
All that means that it's highly
significant is that they didn't have
a bone density of zero which clearly we
wouldn't expect that.
Obviously they're going to have a bone
density something other than zero.
Alright, then we get to the time
coefficient, the parameter for time here.
The time effect from the GE model has a
slightly different interpretation than
the time effect that we saw with the
repeated measures ANOVA.
What the time effect represents here, is
the time effect for the blue group.
This is the change over time,
the rate of change in bone density over
time, for only the blue group.
If you'll remember from the ANOVA.
The time effect in the repeated measures
ANOVA was sort of an average of the change
in time for all the groups.
So, that's not the case with the
regression.
With the regression this is just the time
effect for the blue group, this is
representing the rate in change in spine
bone density over time for the blue group.
Now we know if you saw the picture, go
back to the picture,
they basically were pretty static over
time, they basically kind of stayed flat,
they went down a little and went back up a
little back.
We're assuming a line, we're fitting
lines, so
if we fit a line to those data that I just
showed you.
We're going to get something around a rate
of change of zero which is exactly
what we get here.
The rate of change is essentially zero.
It the p value is totally non-significant.
That tells you that the rate of change for
the blue group in spine bone density does
not differ from zero.
Well, clearly we can see that from the
picture they stayed right about the same.
Alright, so that's the time effect from a
GEE model.
Then we get to the group effect.
And there's two groups here: the black
group and the red group.
And again, this is being compared to the
reference group of, of blue.
So what does the main effect for the black
group and
the main effect for the red group?
This is akin to the group effect from
repeated measures ANOVA.
But they mean, again, something slightly
different than what
the group effect meant in repeated
measures ANOVA.
So if you remember from repeated measure
ANOVA,
the group effect was sort of an average
across all time periods.
Across all time periods is the black group
greater than the blue group for example.
In generalized estimating equations in the
regression model,
the groups effects only, are only
pertinent to base line.
So when time is equal to zero.
When everything else set in the model is,
is set to zero.
You're going to bring in the interaction
effects once your time is
something other than zero.
So, the main effect for group in the GEE
model is
the difference at baseline between the
black group and the reference group, and
the red group and the reference group.
So remember, if you remember from last
week, that the black group and
the red group both were a little bit
higher in bone density at
baseline than the blue group.
And there were both around 0.03, 0.04 more
than the blue group.
So, if we add together the intercept and
the main effect for the black group,
that would give you the average bone
density for the black group at base line.
Notice that the P values are totally non
significant, saying that there is,
that at baseline, there was some slight
differences between the groups in
bone density, but it was not a significant
difference.
The blue group again is the reference
group, so that's just set, fixed at zero.
Then we get the time by group interaction.
And what the time by group interaction
represents is the rate of change,
the difference in the rate of change in
bone density over time for
the black group versus the blue group.
And the time by red group interaction
would represent the difference in the rate
of change over time in spine bone density
for the red group versus the blue group.
So the rate of change for the blue group
was right around zero.
For the black group it's going to be this
0.0108 plus the negative 0.0007.
So you would add the time effect plus the
time by
black effect to get the rate of change for
the black group.
Because this coefficient represents the
difference in rate of
changes between the black and the, the
reference group.
So.
You know, the black group was going up
about one
percent more over time per year than the
blue group.
The time, we set the time to be years so
that this is a rate of change per year.
The red group was also very similar,
was going up just slightly more than the
black group.
0.014.
And notice that both of these are
statistically significant.
That's telling you that the rate of change
in bone density is higher in
those two groups compared with the
reference group.
All of that is very similar to what we saw
in the picture.
But now we have P values and effect sizes
to go with them.
We are assuming here, so go back to the
picture here,
we are assuming what we have done
essentially here is to fit straight lines.
We have assumed that there is a linear
rate of change over time for
all of these three groups, so we fit
straight lines to them.
So just keep in mind that if the changes
over time were not linear.
If they were quadratic or something, we
would have to take that into account.
But linear seems like a good choice here,
they, they look pretty close to lines.
So that was with if I used the
exchangeable correlation matrix.
I'm just going to show you
what the exchangeable correlation ends up
being here.
It estimates the same correlation of about
0.976 5 at all the time periods.
The QIC for this model comes out to be
133.4.
I then just for fun also used
an auto-regressive correlation matrix just
to see if it made any difference.
So here's the results from the
auto-regressive correlation matrix.
You can see we get the basically the same
results.
The changes over time in the blue, black
group and
the red group are significantly different
from the blue group.
Pretty much all of the same answers,
slightly, slightly different estimate.
But basically the same answer.
and, if you go and look at the working
correlation matrix, so
what you'll see is you get two correlation
coefficients.
This one and then you square 0.9999 you
get 0.9998 so
we only, cost us only one degree of
freedom.
The QIC is just slightly smaller than what
we saw with the exchangeable, but
I would say either one of those would be a
good fit.
And going to give very comparable answers.
I also just wanted to show you so
I've now shown you a time independent
predictor that's a categorical predictor.
I wanted to also show you a continuous
time independent predictor so
you have that example as well.
So, I used an example here that comes from
another, version of my runners data set,
but this is from a larger sample from that
runners data set.
A sample of a 125 women.
And I want to look whether or not a
woman's base line calcium intake
was related to her subsequent changes in
spine bone density over time.
And, so notice that calcium is something
that could be a time changing predictor.
I could have measured it and in fact did
measure it at multiple time points.
But for the purposes of this model, I'm
only using the baseline calcium intake,
sort of their first measure of how much
calcium they eat.
And so this is actually I'm making this
into a time independent predictor.
You'll see why there's maybe some
advantages to that when we get to
a later module.
I used here, not the absolute calcium
intake but I use the calcium residuals.
So I did a regression where calcium was
the outcome,
calories was the predictor, and so I get
the residuals from that regression.
Those residuals represent whether or not a
women has a high or
low calcium diet for her caloric intake.
And I put those in standard deviation
units.
So everything here is in standard
deviation units.
So the model that I fit, the outcome is
bone density again.
I have an intercept in the model, I have a
beta for time.
And then I have a beta for your baseline
calcium, that's the main effect for
the time independent predictor of calcium.
And then I've got that interaction with
timing again.
You have to put that interaction with time
in to see what,
what is the effect of calcium on the
changes over time.
So I've got a baseline calcium value
interacting with time.
I went ahead and fit that to these 125
women, fit that model.
And here's the results.
So let me just walk you through what all
these results mean.
So, first of all the intercept, what does
the intercept actually represent here?
So again the intercept is the value when
everything else in
the model is set to zero.
So this would be so time would be set to
zero.
So this would represent baseline.
And remember that calcium is in standard
deviation units.
So a value of zero here represents that
you have the average calcium intake for
the sample.
So a woman with the average calcium
intake.
For this sample at baseline had a spine
bone density on average of about 0.9888.
The value for
time, which is again is in years here,
that does come out to be significant.
it comes out to be about 0.0035.
This would represent the rate of change in
spine bone density.
For a woman whose calcium intake is
average,
who has a standard deviation of calcium
intake of zero.
So if you're kind of average calcium
intake,
you're going up about 0.0035 units of
spine bone density per year,
and that is highly significant, so that is
a significant increase over time.
If you're at the average calcium intake
for the sample.
The main effect for calcium.
You can see is very close to zero, is not
statistically significant.
What that is telling you is that if you
had a higher calcium intake and
base line that was uncorrelated to your
baseline bone density.
However, if you had a high calcium intake
at baseline that predicted that
your changes in spine bone density over
time in the rest of
the study would be significantly positive.
So if you were one standard deviation
above average in
calcium intake that predicts that your
rate of change in spine bone density would
be about 0.0018 higher than somebody who
had just the average rate of change.
So someone with the average calcium
intake,
their rate of change is going to be 0.0035
per year.
Somebody who has, is one standard
deviation above average in
Calcium intake at baseline, meaning that
they kind of have a high calcium diet,
their rate of change is predicted to be
0.0035 plus 0.0018.
So, that comes out to be about .0053 per
year.
And the difference between the average
intake and
one standard deviation above is indeed
statistically significant.
So your having a high calcium intake
predicts a higher change in
bone density over time.