In this next module, I'm going to show you
how to fit a mixed model
with a time independent predictor, and
this is very similar to what we did with
generalized estimating equations, the
interpretation of the beta coefficients is
pretty similar so hopefully if you
understood the material last week,
this module will be pretty easy.
I'm going to use this same data set, on
bone density in women runners,
these 41 women runners, divided into the
three groups.
You've seen these pictures before, so I
won't explain them again.
I'm going to take that same data,.
And fit first in a random intercepts only
model.
So in this model, I just allow the
intercepts to be random.
And I did not put in a random time slope.
And, so what you'll see here is this is
very similar to the results.
That we got out of the generalized
estimating equation for these same data.
The effect for time.
The main effect for time is interpreted as
the rate of change in time for the blue
group, and that's very close to 0 because
the blue group is mostly flat here.
The intercept represents the baseline
spinebone density
a- average score in the reference group,
in the blue group, as before, as with
generalized estimating equations.
The main effect for the black group and
the red group represent the difference at
baseline in the spine bone density in the
black group versus the blue group and
in the red group versus the blue group.
So for example,.
The black group was about 0.03698 higher
in bone density on average than
the blue group at baseline.
Those differences were not statistically
significant,
just saying that at baseline the black and
red groups were higher, but
they weren't statistically, that wasn't a
statistically significant difference.
The blue group is the reference group.
And then we get what we care most about,
which is the interactions between the
group variable and time.
And you can see that we get for
the black vi time interaction .01079 that
would be interpreted at a .01079 increase.
In spine bone density which is measured in
grams per centimeter squared.
However, the average spine bone density
you know you can see
that it's very close to 1.0.
It's a little bit, just a hair under 1.0
in this population.
And so that is very close to a better 1%
increase in bone density, per year,
over time.
And the increase in the red group is just
slightly higher at 0.
0.14 advance per centimeter squared per
year.
And both of those are statistically
significant.
And these are very, very similar
estimates.
To what we've got for a, from the
generalized estimate equations.
If you look at the P values and the data
coefficients, you have to go,
like, to the third decimal place to see
any difference.
I want to just point out the AIC, fit
statistics here.
So, I wanted to point out, that, for
whatever reason we ended up with
negative values for the the AIC, and that
can happen sometime in [UNKNOWN].
Models.
When you have negative values for the AIC,
even though their outputs are.
Smaller is better.
Closer to 0 is better.
So you want to be smaller in the absolute
value.
So the value, we want to pay attention to.
Ignore the sign and just pay attention to
the 410.6 here.
I just want to show you this [INAUDIBLE]
code so
you know exactly what I'm doing here.
I have.
Fit a model with a random statement, but
only a random intercept so far.
So I then went ahead and fed a model with
both a random intercept and
a random slope just to see the comparison.
What you'll notice is that if you just
kind of scan across the point
estimates for the beta coefficients and
the P values,
nothing is material, materially different,
they're all pretty similar.
We're still getting significant effects.
For the group by time effects the beta
coefficients are very close to what we
got before.
So it didn't make a huge difference here.
But I want to point out that the AIC was
about 410 before, it's now at 419.5.
And so we want to be smaller in the
absolute value, so
actually, the random intercept only model
is a much better fit.
Than the model with also a random slope.
The random intercept model only model was
sufficient to capture the between
subject variability and account for the
correlation within subject.
There wasn't a lot of variation in the
slope over time here.
And again just to show you the code, I
have put a random statement in.
Random effect for the intercept and for
time and
I also had to specify the covariance
matrix for
this g matrix of the random effects.
And then finally, I had also wanted to
show you similar to what I showed last
week for generalized estimating equations
that you can put
a continuous time-independent predictor in
as well.
So, I took the baseline calcium in the
diet for these women.
That was in Z scores, I had, taken the
residual calcium to correct for
calories, and I put into, standardized
units, so Z scores.
And we get very similar output again to
what you saw in
the generalized estimating equations last
week.
I ran this model with a random intercept
only,
because that turned out to have the best
model fit again.
This is from a larger data set, this data
set has 125 women.
So more of that same,
more than the 41 women that were included
in the other analysis.
But the random intercept model still
turned out to be superior here.
Let me just walk you through how do I
interpret all of this.
So the intercept is .9888.
So that would say that at base line, when
time equals 0,
and at a calcium standardized residual
square of 0, which would represent,
a Z square of 0 would represent the
average calcium intake here.
So if you were at, have the average
calcium intake at base line then at.
Based on your, spine bone density.
Was, on average, about .9888.
And of course that's significantly
different than 0.
Because we don't have, you know?
You can't have a skeleton that has no,
grams of calcium in it.
The time effect here is also statistically
significant, it's .0035.
And this time effect would correspond to
somebody with,
again, a calcium score, z score of 0.
So the average calcium intake.
They were going up about .0035 in grams
per centimeter squared in
[UNKNOWN] over density over time.
It's a small effect but it is a real
increase over time per year.
If the main effect for calcium here
represents that
every one standard deviation unit higher
than you were in calcium and.
Baseline corresponse is you would have a
slightly lower spine bone
density although it's very, this data
coefficient's very, very close to 0 and
it's not statistically significant.
In other words, your baseline calcium was
not strongly related to
your baseline bone strength.
However, if you're eating a lot of calcium
at a baseline.
If we interact with time, you'll see that
there was a near-significant,
increase in spine bone density over time,
if you had a high calcium diet.
So somebody who had a Z score of one, at
baseline had a high calcium diet,
they were predicted to have a higher rate
of change in bone density, over time.
So if you had the average in calcium, you
were 0.003506.
Somebody who was at one standard deviation
higher than average in calcium
would be predicted to have 0.001807 higher
rate of change so yu can add those up and
they, they're rate of change would be
about 0.005 rather than 0.0035, so
again, it's a small difference,.
But it is statistically significant so
eating more calcium does seem to
positively affect your bone strength over
time.