[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about the different residuals that
are available for Cox regression.
So remember, residuals are useful for
testing assumptions about the model,
we use them a lot, in linear regression,
for example, to say whether or
not we had any violations of the
assumptions of linear regression.
A residual is just some kind of observed
minus predicted for each individual.
So you have a predicted value from the
model.
You've got an observed value from each
person.
You subtract those in some fashion that
gives you a residual.
Now for Cox regression,
it's a little tricky because the outcome
variable is a two part variable, right?
We have time and we have whether or not
they had the event.
So what's the predicted value of Cox
regression going to be?
It's not quite straightforward.
So there's a couple of different types of
residuals that people have come up with.
So first of all, there's something called
a Martingale residual, and
the basic idea with the Martingale
residual is,
we're going to look at whether or not you
had the event.
We're going to compare that to your
probability of having the event
at a given time.
So every person either has the event, or
they're censored at their event time, Ti.
And what we can do is we can say, okay,
you got a one or a zero depending on
whether you've had the event, or you're
censored, and then based on the model,
we can come out with a cumulative or
predictive cumulative hazard.
That's the predicted probability that you
would have had the event by time t.
And t is how long a person was in the
study until they were censored or
had the event.
Let me just give an example.
So, for a subject that was censored at two
months, and
whose predicted cumulative hazard, based
on the model there,
predicted probability of having the event
by two months, based on the model was 20%.
When their Martingale residual was
going to be zero because they're censored,
they did not have the event,
minus 0.2, minus their 20% probability of
having it by then.
So we get a Martingale residual of -0.20.
So people who are censored are going to
have negative values for
the Martingale residual.
Now for a subject to say have a event at
13 months, they have some predicted
probability of having the event by 13
months based on their risk factors and
based on the model.
And let's say that comes out to be 50%,
their
Martingale residual is going to be one
minus 50% because they did have the event.
So they're going to have a positive
Martingale residual.
Essentially, the Martingale residuals will
give you the excess failures.
Plotting these can be useful especially
for evaluating whether or
not a continuous predictor actually has
a linear relationship with the outcome
variable here, the log hazard.
And we're going to get into details on
that in a future module.
But I'll just show you an example of a
Martingale residual plot,
plotting the predictor depression score
against the Martingale residuals here.
So we're going to do some of those plots
in a future module.
Another type of residual that's directly
related to the Martingale residual is
called the deviance residual.
It's basically just take the Martingale
residuals and turn it, normalize it,
make it into a normally distributed
variable.
Makes it easier to interpret.
These residuals are going to be
symmetrically distributed about zero.
They're going to have z scores.
So you know that if somebody has a z score
of positive four or
negative four that that person doesn't
really fit the model very well.
Observations with large deviance residuals
again are poorly predicted by the model.
So, these behave more like the residuals
from ordinary regressions which we're
kind of more use to.
We're expecting them to be symmetrically
distributed around zero and
have a standard deviation of one.
Negative observations, it's going to be
negative.
These deviance residuals will be below
zero for
people who have longer than expected
observed survival times.
And you can plot the deviance residuals
against the covariates to look for
any unusual patterns, the same way we do
for a linear regression or to look for
people who don't seem to fit the model
well.
So again, I'm plotting the deviance
residuals against depression score,
from a data set.
It's pretty well, nicely, you know,
kind of randomly distributed around zero,
as you would expect.
There's a few people who have z scores
that are a little out of bounds, but
it's a pretty big data set, so having one
or
two people around a z score of three
actually would be expected, so
I don't see anybody here who looks like a
huge outlier.
So those are the deviance residuals.
The Schoenfeld residuals turn out, in a
way, to be the most interesting.
We're going to use the Schoenfeld
residuals for
evaluating the proportional hazards
assumption.
Schoenfeld residuals were proposed in
1982, and there's the reference.
The key to understanding the Schoenfeld
residuals is that we're no longer going to
have a single residual for
each individual, which is what you're used
to from other regression models.
What we're going to have instead is a
separate residual for
each person for each covariate.
So if I have age and weight in the model.
Then I'm going to have residuals for age
and
I'm going to have residuals for weight.
But I'm only going to have residuals for
people who have the event.
I will not have any residuals for people
who did not have the event.
So let me explain now how they work.
So the Schoenfeld residual is going to be
the covariant value for
the individual that had the event, that
failed at a given time.
So let's say a time is equal to two months
into the study.
Subject 7 died.
If the outcome here is death.
And let's say that Subject 7 is 65 years
old.
So for that, and let's say age is in our
model, okay.
So we have a co-variant age in our model.
Subject 7, the observed value is 65 at the
time they died,
and we can come up with an expected value.
What did we expect the age to be for
the person who died two months into this
study?
And we're going to subtract those and come
up with a residual specifically for age or
for a particular covariate.
So how do we come up with that expected
value for the covariate at time t?
So again, this is at two months, what do
we expect in terms of,
what do we, how old do we expect the
person who died at two months to be?
We can calculate that as an expected value
is a weighted average of the covariant,
weighted by the likelihood of failure for
each individual who is
actually still at risk at two months, at
time t in the study.
So the residual is the covariant value for
the person who had the event and the
expected value for that covariant for
say age, among everybody who's still at
risk at that time.
And that's equal to everybody's values.
So everybody who's at risk, their age,
weighted by a probability.
And the probability is the probability
that they would have the event that they
would have failed by time t.
So for example, if a person was 56 years
old when they died,
we can calculate the expected value for
age and everybody, P is probability and
everybody who's at risk,
we're going to multiply their age times
the probability that they would have died.
They would've had the event.
So, kind of conceptually, what we're
saying that the person who died was 56.
And based on the fitted model, how likely
is
it that the person who died would've been
56, rather than, say, older or younger?
Were we expecting the person who dies now
to be 56, or something older or younger?
That's the general idea.
And this is probably best illustrated by
just giving some hypothetical example but
with real numbers.
So, let's say we had five people left in
our risk set,
at event time, seven months into the
study.
We had a 55 year old female smoker, a 45
year old male nonsmoker, a female 67
year old smoker, a male 58 year old
smoker, a male 70 year old smoker.
And what we have in our Cox regression
model, the predictors are gender, age and
smoking status, non-smoker or smoker.
But let's say that at seven months, it's
the 55 year old smoker,
the female 55 year old smoker, who is the
one who actually had the event.
So we're going to calculate the,
Schoenfeld residuals for her for,
we can calculate them for age, for smoking
status, and for gender.
So let's say based on our model, based on
everybody's age, smoking status, and
gender, we can calculate The predicted
probability that they would have died,
their cumulative hazard of dying by time
7, we can calculate that for
each person, call it p-hat.
So let's say we do that, based on the
model,
the female 55 year old smoker had a 10%
chance of dying by time 7.
The second person, it was 5%, and so on,
so
just based on the fitted model, this is
what comes out.
You can see that people who were smokers
and
older have higher probabilities of having
died by seven months into the study.
So what is the expected value for age,
then, for
the person who failed at seven months?
We just do an expected value in the normal
way, we take the age for
everybody, weighted by their predicted
probability of dying.
And coming out with, if we calculate it
out,
that they predicted, the expected value
for age here is 60.
So we were expecting somebody, who the
person to, who failed at 7 months,
actually to be a little bit older.
She was a little bit younger than
expected.
So we do, 55, her, her age, the one who
died, her age, minus the expected value.
So she was a little bit younger than I
expected.
Her Schoenfeld residual is negative five.
We can also do the same thing for gender.
Gender's a binary variable, so, male is 0
here, female is 1.
So, everybody who had,
was a female gets a 0 value weighted by
their predicted probability of failure.
Males get 1 weighted by their predicted
probabilities.
When we add these all up we have a value
of 0.55.
That means that we were slightly more
expecting,
expecting a male a little bit more than we
were expecting a female to die here.
So men, males have a slightly higher risk
of dying was the point of this study.
So, she's a female, so her value for the
co-variate gender is zero.
We subtract the expected value of .55, so
she's, gets a value for
this Schoenfeld residual of negative .55.
And so on.
So we can calculate for
every person who had an event, for every
covariant, Schoenfeld residual.
So what's neat about he Schoenfeld
residuals is because they're calculated at
every event time, we can actually plot the
Schoenfeld residuals against time.
And that will tell us something about the
proportional hazards assumption.
So in principle, the Schoenfeld residuals
should be independent of time.
If you plot them and you see a pattern, a
nonrandom pattern, that's evidence of
a violation, not the proportional hazards
assumption for that co-variate.
So for example, going back, imagine we're
talking about age again.
So here is the Schoenfeld residuals for
age.
If I plot those against time, well, if the
hazard ratio for age is changing over
time, it's getting bigger or smaller over
time, then what you might see is that
when you plot this Schoenfeld residuals,
there's some distinct pattern across time.
The Schoenfeld residuals are say, getting
bigger with time.
[SOUND] More away from, you know, having
getting further away from 0 here,
so if you plot it, it might look like, the
Schoenfeld residuals,
if you plot a curve here are getting
higher with time or something like that.
So, we can just plot the Schoenfeld
residuals for
a particular covariate against time.
We're going to talk more about this in a
upcoming module.
But just to give you an example, here's an
example of Schoenfeld residuals for
age from a particular data set plotted
over time.
Looks like there's no real pattern with
time.
So that would indicate that, that
proportional hazard assumption for
age was met.
But here is a plot this was a binary
predictor.
You were either randomized to treatment or
to control.
A plot of those Schoenfeld individuals for
that treatment variable across time and
you can see a distinct pattern.
It's a little hard to see with binary
variables but
we get a smooth curve here, clearly this
the residuals are increasing with time.
This one actually violates proportional
hazards.
So, just common uses of the different
residuals that we get out.
So the Martingale residuals, the most
common use of the Martingale residuals is
you can plot the Martingale residuals
against your continuous predictors to
check whether or not they're actually
linear in the log hazard and
we do have an assumption of linearity
here.
The deviance residuals are often used
because they're nice z scores.
They can be used to check for outliers for
people who have very high or
very low Z scores and the Shoenfeld
residuals as I've already alluded to
you plot those against time to check the
proportional hazards assumption.