[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module, I'm going to show you
how to handle time changing predictors in
a generalized estimating equation.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
So I'm just going to use this same example
data set that I showed you how to
graph in the last module.
So, this was a data set with just six
people.
And, they're all given a drug that's
supposed to
make their happy chemical levels, in their
brain, go up.
And, indeed, you can see, that on average,
this red line is going up a little bit, so
their, chemical levels in the brain are
going up and
their depression scores seem to be going
down concurrently.
Just want to show you again the broad form
of the data because I want to point out
one thing.
So notice at base line their first
chemical level in the brain measurement.
I actually made them all have exactly the
same level, to start with.
And there's a reason that I did that.
That ensures that at baseline, see that
everybody has a quite different depression
scores at baseline, but yet they have the
exact same level of this happy chemical.
This ensures that at baseline, the
chemical level and
the depression score are not correlated.
So there are no between subjects effects
at baseline.
That's going to be important as you'll see
in a few minutes.
If I were to just hand you these data,
I've got my chemical levels in the brain,
I've got my depression scores as my
outcome, and
I've got time, you might just think of
analysing then if you didn't know
about generalized estimating equations
with some kind of linear regression.
So, I am just going to now throw them into
a linear regression to
show you what happens.
It's essentially what we're doing, but
again with this extra correction for
correlation within subject.
So I'm going to look for linear
correlation between the chemical levels
and the depression scores, ignoring the
correlation for
now and the near correlation between the
depression scores and time as well.
Just for now ignoring the correlation.
So I'm just showing you those linear
regressions graphically here.
So I graphed the depression score against
time, and
you can see that it does trend downwards
over time.
The beta coefficient for time is negative.
And I also graphed the depression score
against the chemical levels, and there
seems to be a strong inverse relationship
with a higher level of chemical,
the lower the depression score, the beta
coefficient for chemical is negative.
Of course I've treated this, I've graphed
this and
modeled this as if I have 24 independent
observations.
Clearly I don't.
I have to account for that within subject
correlation.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
But I can also run these two together in a
single linear regression model, so I could
have chemical and time both as predictors
in the model of depression score.
I went ahead and ran that as well.
Again this is just a regular linear
regression.
What you'll notice is that time is pretty
close to zero.
Doesn't seem to be much of a causing
chemical.
Doesn't seem to be much going on across
time.
however, the chemical level does have a
strong inverse relationship with
the depression score, and
that does achieve statistical significance
even in this model.
Pay attention to the standard errors,
though.
It turns out that these standard errors
are too high, and
one we run the correct GEE model, those
standard errors will go down.
You can interpret that beta coefficient
for chemical a 100 unit increase
in the chemical would be associated with a
1.7 decrease in the depression score.
Now let me show you the GEE model that
we're going to be running for
for time changing predictors.
Here's what it looks like.
Essentially we're going to have a vector
of outcome variables, that's our
depression scores, and we have a vector of
chemical levels, and we are correlating.
We're getting the linear correlation
between those two vectors across those
four time periods.
There will be just one data coefficient in
the model for
chemical, but it will represent the
correlation between depression score, and
chemical across those four time periods.
And I just want to point out that remember
that when
we ran the time-independent predictors,
we had to put an interaction between the
predictor and time into the model.
When you have time-dependent predictors,
time-changing predictors,
because what you're essentially doing is
modelling this vector of chemical levels,
or predictor levels, over time, do not put
an interaction with time into the model.
Time is already incorporated within that
vector of values.
If you did put a time by chemical
interaction here,
it would mean something like there was an
acceleration or
deceleration of the effective chemical and
depression score over time.
That's sort of a higher order effect, and
we wouldn't expect that.
So, I'm just going to put in chemical
level I of one data for that.
Now, the tricky part with time changing
predictors is
how to interpret this beta coefficient
when it comes out at the end of the day.
This beta coefficient is going to
incorporate,
encompass two types of effects.
It's going to encompass between subjects
effects and
within subjects effects, that is, your
score and
your chemical across the different time
periods could be related.
Because they were our between-subjects
effects,
they could also be related if they're are
within-subjects effects.
And when you get the beta coefficient out,
you actually can't differentiate between
those.
And what do I mean by a between-subjects
effect, versus a within-subjects effect?
A between-subjects effect would mean that
you've got two different people.
And, one of them has a higher happy
chemical level in
their brain than the other.
That you would expect the one who has the
higher chemical level,
to on average, have a lower depression
score.
That would be in-between subjects effect.
Within subjects effect, would say that if
you've got one person.
If their chemical level changes over time,
you would expect their depression levels
to also change over time.
If their chemical level goes up, you'd
expect their depression level to go down.
So, when you get that beta out, it could
be be, between subjects effects,
it could be within subjects effects, it
could be both of those and
you can't really differentiate.
So I went ahead and ran this model on
these data just to show you what I'd get.
So first of all it looks a lot like the
linear regression model.
Especially in terms of the betas look very
similar to what we got before.
However the standard errors are much much
smaller.
If you remember the standard error for
time was 0.65.
And it's now more than halved down to
0.28.
The standard error for chemical was
before, 0.055.
Also cut by more than half.
That means our P value for a chemical is
even more significant than before.
So, that's the effective accounting for
the correlation.
But what does this beta coefficient of
negative 0.0129 mean?
How do we interpret it?
Well, it could mean that if I've got a
person A who has a chemical level of
1,000 in their brain and I've got a person
B who has a chemical level of 900, it.
Could mean that we would expect, that A
would be about 1.3 units
lower in depression score than B, because
they are 100 points higher on chemical.
I'll multiplying the beta coefficient by
100 here.
So it could be that.
It could mean that somebody who is 100
points higher would be expected to
have about 1.3 lower in depression score.
Or it could mean that if Subject A started
at depres chemical level of 900 and then
they went up to a chemical level of 1,000,
that we would expect person A to go down.
A change of negative 1.3 in their
depression score.
So that anybody who goes up 100 points
would be expected to go down 1.3 in their
depression score.
It could mean both of those, it could mean
some combination of those,
it could mean only one or the other.
So, interpreting coefficients from
time-dependent predictors is tricky.
And again, I've written out kind of
verbally what I mean by
the between-subjects and within-subjects
if you want to see it written out there.
How do you differentiate?
Well you can't differentiate just by
looking at the beta or
the P value from the model.
You have to look, dig deeper into the
data.
In the next module I'm going to give you
some clues about how to do that.
But I just want to point out here that
since I made up these data,
I sort of built in that there would be
more within-subjects effects here than
between-subjects effects.
I set everybody at the exact same chemical
level at baseline.
That means that at baseline, there was no
between subjects effects,
your chemical level was unrelated to your
depression level between subjects.
So, I started with no between subjects
effects and then I, I made up the data,
so as I made people go up in their
chemical level,
I made their depression score go down as I
showed you graphically in the last module.
So probably there's a lot more
within-person effects than between-person
effects in this data set, and that the
beta would be interpreted more as a change
in your chemical level would correspond
with a change in your depression score.
Just to be complete, I want to talk about
the choice of correlation structure here.
We still have to worry about that.
So, I went ahead, and asked for the
empirical correlation matrix here.
And you can see that these are made up
data so
they don't follow any really predictable
pattern.
One time going across went from 0.92, or
0.55, or 0.37.
Whereas if you were two time part, points
different, it was at about 0.69, and 0.77.
So there's no real clear pattern here.
What we would choose.
Well, it's clearly not independent.
We might want to go for
exchangeable because, again, since there's
no discernible pattern,
maybe if we just took the average of all
of those we'd do pretty well.
Autoregressive doesn't seem like a good
choice here because the closest time
points don't have larger correlations than
the further time points.
At least not all of them.
Again, for the same reason probably we
don't want to choose independent.
Maybe an unstructured would do well here,
because there is no clear structure here.
So I tried both the exchangeable and
unstructured thinking,
that those would be the most likely to be
a good fit for my model.
Actually I went ahead and
ran Exchangeable, Autoregressive,
3-dependent, and Unstructured.
I ran all of these just to compare.
And if you look at the QICs, the
Exchangeable and
the Unstructured as expected did the best.
In fact, the Unstructured did just a hair
better than the Exchangeable.
And to just show you that it doesn't make
a huge difference,
I ran both the Exchangeable and the
Unstructured.
I'm showing those models here.
I'm showing the robust entered errors.
You can see that the beta coefficients
from both models are pretty similar.
The model I showed you before was with an
exchangeable correlation matrix.
The standard error's just slightly lower
when I chose the unstructured
correlation matrix.
The p values look the same, although if
you look at the disease score,
it's a little bit more statistically
significant from the unstructured.
But basically you're getting very, very
similar results.
Regardless of your choice of correlation
structure, here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]