Now, let me tell you about an example
trial called the SPORT trial.
This trial actually, generated a lot of
controversy and
a lot of discussion about
intention-to-treat analysis.
So this was a randomized trial, and
they were looking at patients with disc
herniation, with low back pain.
And it's unclear whether or not these
patients benefit from surgery.
We'd like to do a randomized trial to
answer that question.
So, this was a two year randomized trial
of 501 patients with disk herniation.
245 of them were assigned to receive
surgery, lumbar discectomy.
And, 256 were assigned to receive standard
non-operative care to not get surgery.
It turns out to be pretty hard to recruit
for this kind of randomized trial,
because people don't want to leave up to
fate whether or not they get surgery.
They kind of want to make that decision on
their own,
even if it's unclear that surgery has any
benefits.
And, you can see that they also did a
parallel observational cohort study.
So, there were 743 patients who refused
randomization,
didn't want to be in the randomized trial,
but
agreed to be enrolled in a parallel
observational cohort study.
They got to select whether they got
surgery For nonoperative care but
they agreed to be followed and their data
collected.
And you can see that a great majority of
patients actually self-selected to
receive surgery.
They were pretty sure that they wanted to
do something proactive even though we
don't know if surgery is effective.
The outcomes here were three months, one
year and two year changes.
On some subjective scales of pain,
physical function and disability.
Now what was interesting is that there was
a lot of nonadherence.
Again, this is really typical of
randomized trials.
So by the end of two years, only 60% of
those who were randomized to
the surgery group had actually received
surgery.
So just because you're randomized to the
surgery group doesn't mean you're
going to go through with it, only 60% went
through with it.
And also, interestingly, almost half, 45%
of those who
were randomized to the control group, the
nonoperative care group,
eventually went on to receive surgery
within those two years.
So, you know, people are still having
pain,
they want to do something proactive, so
they decide to go and
get the surgery anyway, so a lot of
switching groups in this trail.
Now, let me show you the results.
So there's Three ways that the data were
presented.
So first of all,
the primary analysis for the randomized
trial was an intention-to-treat analysis.
Generally, most people with randomized
trial data will choose
an intention-to-treat analysis as primary
for the reasons we've talked about.
They also then as a secondary analysis
broke intention-to-treat and
said well let's look at who actually got
surgery versus who didn't.
And then finally they have the results of
the observational cohort study where
people self-selected.
So any intention to treat analysis, they
literally said okay, if you
were randomized to surgery, we're going to
take your change in bodily pain, physical
function and disability, your change
scores over the time period of the study.
And we're going to average together
everybody who was randomized to
surgery, and then we're going to average
together everybody who was randomized to
the non-operative group.
And when they do that, they see that there
is a slight, slight benefit for surgery.
So for bodily pain and physical function,
you want this to be positive, that way a
positive indicates an improvement, for
disability you want it to go down, so
negative indicates an improvement.
So the surgery group did slightly better
on all three measures, but
you can see it's clearly not statistically
significant and a very small effect.
However, what was interesting is that in
the as treated analysis, when they looked
at patients who actually got surgery
versus those who did not get surgery.
Then, there is a benefit for surgery, so
the surgery group, the actual
surgery group did quite a bit of better on
bodily pain, physical function and
capability and these were statistically
significant differences between the group.
For the observational cohort study was
very similar to
the Non-Intension-to-Treat Analysis from
the randomized trial at their benefit for
those who are self-selected to surgery.
This generated a lot of controversy and
a lot of discussion because what do you
make up these results.
One could argue that the intention to
treat analysis,
we know when there's a lot of noise and
a lot of switching around of groups that
that's going to dilute effects, so
maybe we diluted our effects so much that
we're not seeing much of a benefit.
On the other hand, one could argue that
the non intention to treat analysis.
And then, of course, the observational
cohort study, are subject to confounding.
And therefore, that the benefits that
we're seeing are due to confounding,
rather than to a true benefit for surgery.
Or, in this case, you, there also might be
a placebo effect.
Because clearly, somebody you know back
pain is fairly subjective.
So somebody who gets the surgery might
just think that they feel
better because of a placebo effect.
It's, it's hard to know, you know ,what
the explanation is here.
And interestingly this study has now been
falled out with these patients,
these patients have been falled to the
eight years.
The intention to treat results still are
very similar when you follow it out to
eight years, a couple of these secondary
outcomes, have a small benefit for
surgery similar to here.
But by eight years achieves statistical
significance, so
maybe a slight benefit to surgery.
But still, the effects are very, very
small.
So it may be that surgery is helpful, or
it may just be that people who
choose to have surgery do better for other
reasons, and it's hard to differentiate.
Those are some of the frustrations
sometimes with intention to tell a treat
analysis that if it comes out to be null,
it's hard to know what to conclude.
When you're planning for an intention to
treat analysis,
you'll of course want to factor in the
kinds of things we've talked about.
Switching groups into your statistical
power calculations into your
sample size calculations to make you sure
that you have enough people to allow for
this kind of variability and noise.
Finally, the last thing that's important
to talk about with intention to
treat analysis is I've been saying once
randomized, always analyzed.
So that means, anybody who gets
randomized,
that you've got to analyze their data at
the end of the day.
But what happens if people never come back
for any follow up measurements?
So you have maybe baseline data on
somebody, but
you have zero follow up measurements on
them.
Or, they come back for
some of the follow up measurements, but
not all of the follow up measurements.
That of course, can happen in a randomized
trial.
How do you analyze them if you don't have
all their data?
So that's one of the major issues with
actually applying the intention-to-treat.
principle.
Now, the best way to deal with missing
data is actually to avoid it altogether.
So, really, a high quality study is the
way to deal with missing data.
Because you follow up withy everybody very
carefully, you try.
As much as possible to avoid having
missing data.
That's the best case scenario is that you
get the data on everybody.
That gets to doing a well-designed,
high-quality study.
So that's, that's the idea.
We would want to start there.
Of course, it's probably you know,
with most real trials, some missing data
is unavoidable.
So what do you do with missing data?
So, first of all,
there are statistical tests that handle
incomplete follow up data.
So we've seen that Cox regression for
example.
If a person is followed you know, for some
amount of time in the study but
then it's a lot to follow up.
We can at least count them for the time
that they were visible in
the sense that were, that we had follow
data on them.
Similarly we're going to talk in the next
few weeks about things call mixed
model and generalizing estimating
equation.
Yes, there are missing value for some of
the follow up measurement but
not all of them, those models can handle
that really well as well.
We can also do imputation.
So we can make some guesses about what
those measurements would of
been had those person come back for their
follow-up.
One very simple one we'll talk about in
the next few weeks is
something called last observation carried
forward.
So, you could you just take, you know,
if you're looking at a continuous outcome
you can take the outcome like the scale,
the bodily pain scale, whatever was the
last observation you saw, and
then you could carry it forward to all
their missed observations.
That's a simple imputation method.
There are, of course many ways to impute
missing data.
We can also do what's called an extreme
case analysis.
So you can sort of take the worse case and
best case scenario and just see how would
that affect your results.
So if you imagine that everybody, you try
an analysis where
you say that everybody who was missing
follow up data had a bad outcome.
See what the results look like, what your
relative risks look like in that scenario.
And then, you try and
say, well what if everybody who has no
follow update had a good outcome.
How, how extreme, how could that affect my
relative risk or
my effect size at the end of the day?
So, you, kind of, look at the extremes and
see...
That will give you some boundaries on
how much that missing data might affect
your results.
You can do something that, sort of, is
similar to that, but covers a wide range,
a wider range of scenarios, which is to do
a sensitivity analysis and
try a bunch of different things possible
things that could have happened,
possible outcomes for that missing data,
so maybe, for
example, instead of Saying that everybody
who didn't come back had a good outcome.
What if 10% of people who have missing
data had a good outcome.
Or 20%, or 30%.
You can try sort of a broader range of
scenarios, again to get a sense of
how big of an effect that missing data
might have had on your results.