[BLANK_AUDIO]
Welcome to week three of the course.
This week we're going to start our two
week discussion of Cox regression.
Cox regression is widely used in the
medical literature because
unlike parametric regression, we're not
going to make any
assumptions about the underlying form of
the baseline hazard function.
And that's going to turn out to be really
convenient.
We're just going to avoid estimating that
altogether.
So this week I'm just going to introduce
you to Cox regression.
We're going to talk about the basic model,
the likelihood function,
how to evaluate some basic assumptions,
looking at residuals.
And I'll tell you about stratification.
We'll also talk a lot about some examples.
Just as a preview, one of the examples
that we're going to talk about this week
was an interesting study that came out in
the Annals of Internal Medicine in 2001.
And you can see that it was about Academy
Award Winners,
always an interesting topic.
The researchers were interested in the
question of whether you know
how people get nominated for the academy
awards, and they say, oh,
it was just an honor to be nominated as if
you know winning doesn't matter.
So they wanted to kind of get at that
question of,
specifically how does winning an academy
award versus just being nominated,
how does that effect your longevity, if at
all?
This gets to things like your social
status affecting longevity and, and so on.
So, what they did was they compared people
who actors and
actresses, who had actually won Academy
Awards with controls -
actors and actresses who had never even
been nominated as well as with nominees.
Those are people who had been nominated
but never won.
So what you are seeing on the left hand
side here is the Kaplan–Meier curve,
comparing the nominees only to the
winners, and
in this initial analysis, it looked like
there was a clear survival advantage for
the winners versus the nominees.
Now this particular paper generated a lot
of debate and
interest because it's not clear exactly
the correct way.
Statistically to look at these data and
this particular analysis stuff for
the one that was first published,
has a bias in it that we will talk about
in an upcoming module.
But in the initial analysis it looked like
there was a pretty clear survival
advantage for the winners, which of course
is, is interesting.
They then used Cox regression to analyze
these data, so Cox regression allows
them to quantify the effect as well to
adjust for potential confounders.
So, you're seeing in the table on the
right hand side over here is the result,
results of Cox regression.
It's also sometimes called Proportional
Hazards Model.
So, this is the results of a Cox
regression model.
I'll just look at the winners compared
with the nominees.
That's a really interesting one.
So in the basic analysis, what, they're
showing here in the table are actually
hazard ratios but they've presented them a
little bit differently.
So this 25 represents the relative
reduction in mortality rate.
In other words, this corresponds to a
hazard ratio of 0.75.
They thought it would be easier to
interpret if they actually did
the percent reduction till a hazard ratio
of 0.75 translates to
a 25% reduction in the mortality rate for
winners versus nominees.
That was in the basic model they tried
adjusting for various things.
It did attenuate a little bit, but
even in the final model, there still seems
to be some survival advantage.
Again these are the types of data that we
can analyze with Cox regression.
There are some fun details of this
particular analysis that we'll get into in
a future module.