In this next module, I'm going to review
the basics of ANOVA and linear regression.
If you're totally comfortable with these
tasks,
if you have a lot of experience with them.
Feel free to skip this module.
Otherwise it's probably worth watching
just to set you up for
the upcoming weeks in the course.
So when you have continuous outcomes and
you have independent observations and
you want to just do some basic statistics
on the means.
Of the outcomes.
You're going to be doing something like an
ANOVA.
An ANOVA will allow you to compare
different groups with respect to
the mean of the outcome.
Or if you want to do something a little
bit more complicated where you've
got multiple predictors maybe continuous
predictors then you're going to
need regression.
And the regression technique for
continuous outcomes, of course, is linear
regression.
For this module I'm just going to review
the situation where we have
independent observations.
So linear models have some assumptions
that it's worth just reviewing here.
When I say linear models, I mean linear
regression and
then all the things that are related to
linear regression so.
Linear correlation, like the Pierson's
correlation coefficient.
And also ANOVA and ttest.
In fact the ANOVA test and the ttest are
just special cases of linear regression,
so these are all fall, these all fall
under a linear model.
So they all have the same assumptions.
So one of the assumptions is that our
outcome variable is normally distributed.
It turns out that this assumption is the
most important for small samples.
If you have large samples, the Central
Limit Theorem kicks in, and
if you violate normality the, these tests
are fairly robust against this assumption.
But especially if you have small samples,
you're going to want to test to
make sure that your outcome variable is
normally distributed.
We also have an assumption of homogeneity
of variances.
Basically, that says that the variances of
that
outcome variable are equal at all levels
of the predictor.
And again, the models are fairly robust
against this assumption,
especially if you have large samples.
But, it's still something that we will
evaluate.
The third assumption is that we have
independent observations.
That's something that we're about to
violate in the,
the rest of this course, because we're
going to have situations where we have.
Repeated measures and we do not have
independent observations.
But the, the basic models assume that we
have this independence.
And then finally, we're dealing here with
linear models, so it's important to
keep in mind that if you're talking about
a continuous predictor.
Such as in a linear regression or in a
correlation coefficient.
You are assuming that that continuous
predictor actually has
a linear relationship with the outcome
variable.
And we've tested for linearity, if you
were in HRP261, we did this testing for
linearity in the low jet.
Or earlier in this course, we tested for a
linearity in the log hazard.
So we've done these tests for linearity
before.
For linear models, it's the simplest.
Because we're just testing whether or
not that predictor has a linear
relationship with the outcome.
And we don't have to do any
transformations of the outcome.
So that's a really easy assumption to
test.
But don't forget that it's there.
That we are making the assumption of
linearity.
When our predictor variable becomes time,
as it will for repeated measures examples.
We are assuming therefore for a lot of the
models we're going to use.
That the changes over time are relatively
constant.
So, just keep that in the back of your
mind.
That's something that you're going to need
to test.
Alright, so just starting with one-way
ANOVA, basic ANOVA.
When do we use this test?
So, we use one-way ANOVA when we want to
test, we want to compare, some outcomes,
some continuous outcomes, and we're
comparing the means of that outcome.
Between more than two groups or greater
than or equal to two groups.
If you have just two groups, this
essentially becomes a ttest.
Of course you can run an ANOVA with only
two groups then, it,
it's equivalent though to the ttest.
You can also have more than two groups
within the ANOVA.
The null hypothesis for an ANOVA is that
the means in all the groups that you're
looking at, however many there are, let's
say we have four here, that the means for
your outcome variable are equal.
This is a global test because notice that
if we reject this null hypothesis,
all we can say is that at least one of
those means is not equal to the others.
It doesn't tell us specifically where
those differences lie.
So after you do an ANOVA, if you have a
significant finding.
Then you may want to go in and find
exactly,
to specify exactly where those differences
lie.
But that's going to require some kind of
correction for multiple comparisons if you
want to look at pairwise comparisons
between diff, specific different groups.
What are we basically doing when we do an
ANOVA?
We're going to be doing some kind of F
test, and remember the idea.
The F test, is that we're going to be
comparing the variance between groups,
to the variance within groups.
And again, I'm assuming that you've had a
course that's covered ANOVA before, so
that's why I'm going over this quickly,
this is just to serve as a review.
So, the between group variance, remember,
is,
to say that's essentially comparing the
means, of the different groups.
So if there's big differences between the
means in the different groups.
The between group variance will be high.
Within group variance which goes in the
denominator is just
the background variability.
So how much variation is there in the
outcome, within a specific group,
that gives you just kind of the background
variability in that
particular outcome measurement?
If the between group variance is very
close to the within group variance.
That would say that the needs between the
groups are just and
the differences are just part of that
background variability.
However if the between group variance is a
lot deeper than the within group variance,
that would tell you the differences in
means between the differences exceeds that
sort of background noise.
And so what we are looking for.
Is, under the null hypothesis, the F test,
the F statistic will equal 1.
If we get a big F value,
the F distribution looks something like
that under the null hypothesis.
Depends on, the exact shape depends on the
degrees of freedom for the numerator and
the denominator.
But basically, under the null, the
expected value here is 1.
And then if we're out in the tails, the
between for
variants is much bigger than the
within-group variance.
So that's going to trigger some kind of.
Statistical significance.
I'm actually going to walk you through the
math in a hypothetical example.
It's worth me walking through the math
because when we turn to repeated measures
ANOVA next week, I will walk you through
the math in that.
I think in order to really understand how
that works,
you need to have walked through the math
once.
I won't be making you do any of these by
hand.
But it's worth having probed the math, so
that you have a good understanding of
what's actually happening in the computer.
So, I just made up some hypothetical data
here.
You know, just completely made up.
But we've got a data set with four groups
and
we've got our outcome variable is a score
on some kind of test.
And, so, let's say we have four different
educational interventions these
are kids who are getting different
educational training.
And they're all taking a test at the end
of the study to
say how much they learned and there's six
per group for
a total of 24 kids here so that's what the
made up data looked like.
So first thing I did with this data,
you're always going to want to plot your
data.
So, before we do any fancy.
Testing.
We want to plot the data and get a sense
of what's going on.
Obviously you can figure out a lot from
this plot.
These are very simple data, we're not
adjusting for anything.
So I just plotted the box and
whisker plots for those scores on this
test for the four groups, 1, 2, 3, and 4.
And you can see quite quickly that it
looks like Groups 1 and
2 seem to have a higher mean score than
Groups 3 and 4.
So you can get a lot out of the plot.
In fact that, this plot automatically gave
me an ANOVA p-value.
So what you're seeing up here is an F from
a one-way ANOVA, and
a p-value which is 0.0003.
So these, this is a highly statistically
significant difference.
Somewhere in there, there lies a
difference.
Again, we can't say, specifically, which
groups differ.
But those groups are definitely not all
equal.
We also want to just plot the outcome
variable of the scores here in
a histogram, to look at whether or not
these are normally distributed.
This is a small sample.
So we would want to make sure that we met
the normality assumption here.
So I plotted these scores in a histogram.
The average scores around high 20s and
low 30s and you can see that it's
reasonably normally distributed.
That's good enough for
us to be able to run linear models, ANOVA
linear regression on these data.
Alright.
So now, I am actually going to walk.
Through the mechanics of calculating that
one-way ANOVA.
And what I've done here is just rearranged
the data a little bit to make this easier.
So here's my four groups, here are the six
kids in each group.
Here are their scores, their, their scores
on that post test.
And I've already calculated for each
group.
The mean score on that test for each
And we saw on the plot, on the box plot
that groups 1 and
2 had higher mean scores than groups 3 and
4.
Group 3 actually had the lowest mean score
of any of the groups.
So I've already calculated those means.
We're going to need those means for
each group, in order to calculate that
between group variance.
The between group variance just says,
how much difference is there, on average,
in the means between the groups?
So, the between group variance.
How do we calculate that?
So, the between group variance just says,
of the overall mean of all 24 kids.
On this test was 27.46.
To calculate the between group variance,
we're going to be taking the mean from
each group.
Subtracting from the overall mean.
And squaring it, and adding those up.
So we're actually going to start by
calculating something called a sum of
squares rather than a variant.
The sum of square is just the numerator of
variance, so if you take a sum of
squares and you divide by the degrees of
freedom, you will get a variant.
But with a nodal we always start with the
sum of squares because it turns out that
the sum of squares have nice mathematical
properties they add up and such.
So we'll just start there.
So the sum of squares, the numerator of
variance for
the between groups, is you take each
groups mean.
So like, group one had a mean of 34.33.
Subtract from the overall mean of 27.46,
square it, these are,
we always square for variances, so we're
going to square those differences.
We do that for each of the four groups.
So you can see that I've already done that
out.
Here, there's only four of them.
We then for ANOVA have to multiply that
total sum by 6, and
the reason is that we want to get 24 sums
squares here, so
that we match the sum of squares within,
we'll also have 24 squared things.
So, we have 4 squared things we're going
to multiply by 6 here, so
we end up with 24.
Square things, so the math will work out.
When I add all of that up, I get a value
of 630.46.
If I were to divide by the degrees of
freedom I would get the between group
variance, but I'm going to just, but for
now stick with the numerator of that
variance, the sum of squares.
That reflects conceptually just how much
difference,
how big is the difference in the means of
the different groups.
Of course there's always going to be
variability.
So what's the background variability here?
That's what's reflected.
WIthin the groups, the within group
variants.
So, what I am going to next do is
calculate the within group sum of
squares and all that is, is I am going to
look at each person and
compare them to their group name.
So, for example, in group one, the overall
mean is 34.33.
There is some variability however, within
that group,
so one person got a score of 35, they were
a little above the mean.
Another person got a 3rd score of 34.
They were a little bit below the mean.
So just how much variability is there, in
scores within a group?
I'm going to calculate that for each group
separately.
I'm going to add up, so, for
example, I'm going to calculate each
person minus their group mean.
Square that.
We're going to be squaring these
differences.
Then, I'm going to do that for the.
Six people in group 1, and then for the
six in group 2.
Then for the six in group 3, etcetera.
And that's what I've done here.
There's going to be again, 24 squared
things I'm adding up.
So I, I haven't.
I'm not going to do them all out right
now.
I've just kind of written, written out
part of these for you.
So, for example, the first person here in
group 1 had a score of 35.
They were about 2 3rds of a point above
the mean.
We're going to square their difference.
The next person, was 34, they're about a
third of a point below the mean,
we're going to square that, we're going to
keep going.
When we get to group 2, we're going to do
32 minus 29.83 squared.
28 minus 29,83 squared, et cetera, and
then finally the last two will be 22 minus
25, and 26 minus 25.
We're going to add up those squared
differences,
that gives us the sum of squares within.
If I were to divide by the degrees of
freedom,
I would get the with in group variance.
And that's analogous to the pool variance
from a ttest.
So we've now calculated the sum of squares
between the groups,
the sum of squares within the groups.
If I were to add those two up, what I'm
going to get is the total sum of squares.
The total sum of squares could also be
calculated manually.
By taking each individual and subtracting
from the over all mean.
So this is the numerator of the variance
for score overall.
So if I just said what's the variance of
score in this data set,
I took those 24 values and calculated
their variance, which you
do by taking each individual person and
subtracting for the overall mean.
The numerator of that would be the total
sum of squares.
So when I add up 630 plus 423 its about
1,053.
The total sum of squares is going to be
equal to 1053.
If I were to divide by the degrees of
freedom, which here would be 23,
I would get the variance for score, just
the overall variance for score.
So those things add up.
The way that ANOVA is usually presented is
in an ANOVA table.
So let me walk you through how to fill in
all the.
Pieces of this ANOVA table.
So, first of all, we have the source of,
and this could be, this is,
they will sometimes say model, I could
also say group.
This is, what's the difference, the
variability that's due to the group or
the predictors in your model if you're
doing a linear regression.
So what's the variability due to groups?
This corresponds to the between group
variance.
The degrees of freedom here are going to
be 3, because we have four groups.
So we were comparing four group means, but
we had to estimate the overall mean as
well.
Here and so we've lost one degree of
freedom, so we have 4 minus 1 is 3,
the total number groups minus 1.
That's the degrees of freedom, the sum of
squares we've calculated on the last slide
to be 630.46, if I divide the sum of
squares by its degrees of freedom, I
get the variance, some times that variance
is also called the mean squares so
just know that those are equivalent.
So, 630 divided by 0.46 will give me a
variance of about 210.15.
If I were squared, to square root that, of
course, I'd get a standard deviation.
For the degrees of freedom for the error.
The error is the within group variance.
This is the background noise, the
background variability.
The degrees of freedom here are going to
be 20,
because I have 24 individuals and I lost.
Four degrees of freedom, because I had.
In order to calculate the within group
variance,
I had to first calculate four group means.
So I had 24 degrees of freedom, but
I lost four for those four group means
that I had to calculate first.
So I end up with 20 degrees of freedom.
Notice if I sum those up, that gives me
the total degrees of freedom.
That corresponds to the degrees of freedom
for the overall variance.
Because, of course, you know that.
The degrees of freedom for
the overall variance is always n minus 1
so 24 minus 1.
We already calculated on previous slide
the sum of squares error,
the sum of squares within, that was 423.5.
If I divide that by its degrees of freedom
I'm
going to get the variants within the
group, that turns out to be 21.18.
Now remember.
That if there's no differences between the
groups, we're expecting the between group
variances, 210, to be about the same as
the within group variance.
You can see that's clearly not the case.
The variance between the groups here, is,
it's about, almost 10 times as big as the
variance within the groups.
So if I divide the 210 by the 21, I
actually end up with an f value of 9.92.
You can see that this ANOVA chart, you
kind of fill in one piece after the other
and you fill it in across, everything is
sequential.
And, the p value that corresponds to an f
value of 9.92
with 3 numerator degrees of freedom and 20
denominator degrees of freedom is 0.0003.
So that's how you would fill out an ANOVA
table.
Again, you're not going to have to do this
by hand.
But when this computer spits this out to
you,
you should know what each of these pieces
means.
We can also calculate what's called an R
squared.
So again, if you total up the sum of
squares, if you add this up,
you get that the total sum of squares is
1053.95, about.
If I were to divide that by 23, I would
get the variance for
score in this data set.
We don't usually put that in the ANOVA
chart.
But if I take the between, the group sum
of squares, and
divide it by the total sum of squares, I
get what's called the R squared value.
I'm rounding here.
This comes out in this case to be about
60%.
So, what that would tell me is that about
60% of the overall variability in the test
scores is due to which group you're in, as
opposed to just unexplained variability.
The error is the rest of it.
So, you can also look at the R squared.
And probably all, you should all have
heard of R squared 3 4ths but
I won't belabor that point.
So that's your basic ANOVA you'll also get
that out of the computer.
Again, but
that's where that output is coming from
that you would get out of the computer.
I just want to point out and remind you
that ANOVA is nothing special.
It's really just a.
Special case of linear regression.
In fact, it doesn't really need its own
name.
We could survive in statistics if nobody
had ever called it ANOVA and
we just always thought of it as a special
case of linear regression.
because that's really what it is.
It's just a linear regression where our
outcome variable, in this case,
is score and what we're doing is we have a
categorical predictor, so,
of course, we're going to have to dummy
code it.
That's equivalent to the ANOVA.
Even though it looks different, it really
is going to give you the same answer.
So, our outcome variable here are these.
Score for dealing with a linear regression
we're going to have an intercept and
then we're going to have, in this case we
have four groups.
So, if we dummy code we're going to end up
with three betas.
And I chose as the reference for
group 3 when I set up this linear
regression model.
Because I know that group 3 has the lowest
average test score.
So it was just easier to relate everything
to the group with the lowest scores.
So now I have a beta for being in group 1.
And x1 will be 1 if you're in group 1 and
0 if you're not.
I'm going to have a beta for being in
group 2.
X2 will be a 1 if you're in group 2, and a
0 if you're not, and I'm going to have
a beta for group 4, which will have a 1 if
you're in group 4 and a 0 if you're not.
When you're dummy coding, you end up with
three variables in the model,
three parameters in the model representing
the four groups.
If you have a zero on all of those if you
have a zero for x1, a zero for
x2 and a zero for x4, then that means by
default you're in group 3 and
your value is captured in the intercept.
So we can run this linear regression;
we're
going to get the same general results.
As from the ANOVA.
Except now we're getting,
there's more information in the table
that's output, because we
actually can see what is the difference in
the means between the groups.
The ANOVA doesn't specifically spit out
those average differences, but
we can get that right out of the linear
regression.
So if we don't adjust for anything in this
model, the Intercept is 20.666,
represents the mean score in Group 3.
And you'll remember that if you back to
that box plot I showed you that it,
well also in the previous slide here.
That indeed, the mean for that group is
20.67.
So that's the mean for group 3, the
reference group.
Everything else then, if you're in group
1, you,
the difference between group one and group
3 is a value of 13.6.
So the difference in the means between
group 3 and group 1 is 13.666.
If I add 20.66, the, the intercept value
to.
Add 13.666 to that, I will get the mean
for
group 1, which was about 34 point
something.
And then for group 2 the difference and
notice that one is statistically
significant, telling you that group 1 and
3 are significantly different.
Then for group 2, the main difference
between group 2 and group 3 is 9.2.
So we saw from that picture, that group 2
had a much higher mean than group 3.
Group 4 and group 3 were actually similar.
Group 4 is a little bit higher than group
3.
It does not a significant difference
between those two groups.
So we could.
Plug in the, the actual fitted model here
would be 20.66 plus 13.66
times X1 plus 9.166 times X2 plus 4.33
times X4.
That would be the fitted model.
But all this represent as those data are
just the difference in means between
the groups and the reference group.
So we can think of ANOVA as a special case
of linear regression, and
set it up that way.
I'll also point out just since we're
reviewing things here,
that since we're in a linear regression,
we could then actually add continuous
predictors into this model.
We could adjust for things.
And that could be useful.
And again gets its spec its, gets a
special name even though it's just a,
again, just a linear regression.
But there's something called analysis of
covariance.
All that means is that you're setting up a
linear regression where you've
got a categoric predictor like the groups
here.
and then you throw in some continuous
things that you want to adjust for.
Like say I'm in these made up data, I then
added a variable age.
And I just made up that.
Let's pretend that the ages were actually
somewhat different between
the different groups.
Maybe this is an observational study and
not randomized, so
different age groups were getting
different interventions, and then
age is related to the test score, cause if
you're older you do better on this test.
So, I made up this new variable age.
And then I adjusted for it.
And again, this is just a linear
regression.
But now we've added to the model that we
had before.
So we had the score is equal to alpha plus
beta 1 plus beta 2 plus beta 4.
Plus now we've having a beta for age.
So now we're adjusting for
age just by putting it into that linear
regression model.
What that gains us if we do it this way,
why this gets its own special name again,
called analysis of covariance.
Is that now if you look at the betas for
the different groups, group 3 is still my
reference here.
What it's giving you is the adjusted mean
difference.
Adjusted for age.
So once I account for age, the difference
between group 1 and
group 3 is now only 6.7 points on average.
Rather than before, it was about 13.6.
So that's telling you that group 1
probably was a much
older group than group 3.
And so they were doing better partly, just
because of the fact that they were older.
Once we account for age by adjusting for
it in the model.
We can get these adjusted mean values,
which can be useful.
Because now you could present a plot, for
example, that showed the adjusted.
Mean differences between the groups, so
that's called analysis of covariance but
again if you never called it ANOVA or
ANCOVA and
you just want to think of all of this as
linear regression, this really just is,
special pieces of linear regression.