[BLANK_AUDIO].
Welcome to unit eight.
This week we're going to start our
discussion of regression methods that
handle repeated measures outcomes.
So this week we're going to be talking
about generalized estimating equations
which is one of the regression methods
that handles repeated measure data.
And there are many benefits of using a
regression method for
handling repeated measures data.
We saw last week that if we wanted to use
repeated measures ANOVA or
repeated measures MANOVA, that there were
a number of limitations to those methods.
So, for one thing they assume that time is
categorical.
Everybody has to be measured at the same
time point.
And for MANOVA, those time points had to
be sort of equally spaced time intervals.
With regression, with generalized
estimating equations and
next week, we'll see, with mixed models.
You can treat time as continuous.
Everybody can have different time points
that they're measured at.
Also, the ANOVA method don't handle
time-dependent covariates and
as you all learned on the mid-terms that
time changing predictors are very,
very important.
And other regression methods will
incorporate in handling it.
For ANOVA you have to impute missing data
or
anybody who is missing even one time point
will be thrown out of the analysis
with the regression methods, you don't
have to
necessarily impute the missing data
because people will only be thrown out.
The time points that they missed.
The ANOVA methods had some more
restrictive assumptions.
Particularly univariate repeated measures
and
ANOVA had a restrictive assumption about
the correlation structure,
the regression methods, don't necessarily
require such restrictive assumptions.
And if you notice when we do the ANOVA,
you didn't get any parameter estimates.
We didn't get any measures of effect size,
for example.
We just got p values.
We'd also like to be able to get some beta
coefficients,
some estimates of effect size, and
regression will buy us that as well.
[BLANK_AUDIO]