In this next module,
we're going to continue our discussion of
repeated-measures ANOVA.
However, we're going to complicate the
picture just slightly by now adding
a comparison of groups.
So, we're going to use the same, simple,
example data set as in the last module.
But now we're going to distinguish between
whether subjects are in group A or
whether they are in group B.
Again, these are depression scores
measured at four time points.
So, we can add that distinction to the
graphics.
So, here I've graphed people according to
whether or
not they're in group B or in group A.
It's a little bit messy to see patterns
here.
So, I'll then graph the mean plots.
So here is the mean for group B and the
mean for group A.
And you notice that group B in general
seems to be
a little bit higher than group A.
But they both follow the same general
pattern over time.
The both start a little higher, kind of
drop a little bit in time point three,
and then go back up in time point four.
And there's a number of questions that we
can ask in terms of
statistical significance.
There's more than one question we can ask.
We can ask about what's called the time
effect.
Is there anything significant changes, or
differences over time?
So, for example,
is time point three significantly
different than the other time points?
We can ask whether there's any change over
time, overall kind of ignoring group.
That's called the time effect.
We can ask whether the groups differ at
all, kind of ignoring time points.
So just overall, sort of
cross-sectionally, is B higher than A?
Is that a significant difference?
That would be called the group effect.
And then, finally, the effect that we're
going to comp, care most about is
actually the interaction between those
two, the time by group effect.
And what that is telling us is whether or
not there any, are any
significant differences in the changes
over time between group B and group A.
So it's the pattern over time different in
group B than in group A?
And that's what we really care about.
From this graphic,
just looking at this graphic, it does not
look like the time by group effect would
be significant here because they seem to
have basically the same pattern over time.
One thing that you need to kind of get
clear in your mind before we
jump into the ANOVA here is the difference
between a between-subjects effect and
a within-subjects effect.
So let me just clarify that a little bit.
So when I talk about a between-subjects
effect,
this is anything where you're literally
just comparing between subjects.
So when we calculated in the previous
module, the sum of squares between,
that was comparing, say, subject one
versus subject two.
That's between-subjects because it's
comparing different subjects.
When we're going to be talking about
groups, comparing group A, for
example, versus group B.
What I'm going to call the group effect.
When we compare the groups, that's
going to be a between-subjects effect.
Because, there are three people in group A
and three different people in group B.
So, any differences between the groups
would be a between-subject effect.
Something where somebody in group A is
different than somebody in group B.
When we talk about within-subjects
effects, so
this is just sort of like the individual
effect.
[SOUND] If we talk about within-subjects
effects, well,
we're talking about things that are
happening over time.
Because, what does it mean to be within a
subject?
That means we've got the same subject at
different time points and
we're comparing the same subject at
different time points.
So, if I compare subject one at time point
one
to subject one at time point two that
would be a within-subject comparison.
And this is going to correspond roughly to
what I'm going to call the time effect.
Over time our individual subject's
changing.
So that's the time effect.
So we want to know whether or not the
within-subjects changes in group A,
for example, are different than the
within-subject changes over time
changes in group B.
And this would correspond to what I'm
calling the time by group effect.
because it's actually asking to look at an
individual subject over time and
say whether or not they're changing.
And is that change different in one group
versus the other.
So in our output from repeated-measures
ANOVA,
we're going to get things that correspond
to between-subject effects,
that is just individual variability, as
well as what group you're in.
And we're going to get things that
correspond to within-subjects effects.
This is the time effect, and the time by
group effect.
You'll get two pieces in your output.
I'm going to start just by analyzing the
data with a regular two-way ANOVA here,
ignoring the fact that we have
repeated-measures just to illustrate.
All of the variability, the sums of
squares, add up in ANOVA.
So we're just going to break down all of
the variability but we're going to
ignore for the moment the, the fact that
we have the same subjects over time.
So I'm going to run an ANOVA, a two-way
ANOVA,
on the long form of the data ignoring the
correlations within subjects.
I have used the long form of the data here
because I'm sort of pretending that I
just have 24 independent people, that's
not the same people over time.
And my predictors are, what time period
you're on, that's like one factor.
What group you're in, that's a second
factor.
And then the interaction,
two-way ANOVAs usually have the
interaction between those two.
So I, this is going to be the incorrect
two-way ANOVA.
But let me just show you how it's
calculated, because there's only going to
be one additional thing we have to do to
do this correctly.
So now we've got the distinction of group
and time.
So I can calculate the, mean for
each group at each time point, and I can
calculate the mean for each group overall.
So now I'm going to calculate several
things.
First of all, I can calculate a sum of
squares between time.
We actually already did that.
So the overall mean for time one was 27.
We subtract the overall, the mean overall
for all 24 measurements, that was also 27.
If you recall the mean for time two, time
point two for
all six subjects was 28 minus the overall
mean, and so on and so forth.
We already calculated this, so that stays
the same.
The sum of squares between time is still
224.79.
Now, we're going to add a sum of squares
between groups, and
how do we calculate that?
Well, we look at the mean for each group
overall, and
the mean for group A and the mean for
group B.
So, ignoring time point, the mean for
group A is 24.75.
We're going to compare that to the overall
mean, ignoring time point, the,
the mean for group B is 29.3.
We're going to compare that to the overall
mean.
So, 29.3 minus 27 squared, plus 24.75
minus 27 squared.
We have to multiply by 12 because we need
24 terms in the sum of squares,
24 sum of squares things, that comes out
to be 126.
So that's the sum of squares between
group.
Now when we calculate the sum of squares
error the unexplained variability,
we're going to be taking the, each person.
And subtracting now from their group and
time mean.
So, so person, subject one, at time point
one, had a depression score of 31.
We're going to compare that to the mean
for group A at time point one.
So we'll do a 31 minus 23,
and then we're going to do a 24 minus 23
squared, 14 minus 23 squared.
So each subject is going to comp, be
compared only to the current time point,
and to their, to their, their group's mean
at that time point.
So we do that for all 24 subjects.
We get 24 sum squares.
That comes out to be 100, 523.
And then there's one additional thing we
need to worry about.
So we've got now, two factors, time and
group.
And we're going to need to calculate the
sum of squares for their interaction.
And the easiest way to do that is just to
remember that sum of
squares always sum up.
So we're going to take the sum of squares
total, which we found,
we calculated before, was 900.96.
We're going to sat, subtract away the sum
of squares for time, the sum of
squares for group, and the sum of squares
error, the ones we've already calculated.
That will give us this, the, sum of
squares for the group by time interaction.
That comes out to be 26.79.
So, not very big here.
That gives us, with our breakdown now.
We know, of course, we've ignored subject,
at this point,
but this breaks down everything else.
We can then ask the computer, or put this
together in a, in ANOVA table.
Again, so we then ended up with our
explained variability.
That's due to which group you're in or
which time period you're at, or
the interaction of those two.
Those summed up to 377.
So if you add up the 224, 126 and 26.79,
that gives you a total of 377.
The unexplained variability is 523, the
total is 900.
We can calculate our F statistic and our
p-value.
It turns out to be not statistically
significant.
And then, we can break it down to the
source of the variability.
So, we have a time effect, a group effect,
and a time by group effect.
We already calculated those, 224, 126 and
26.
We can calculate corresponding F-values,
and
then we get p-values that go with those.
So the p-value for time is 0.11, the
p-value here for
group is 0.06, and the p-value for time by
group is 0.84.
So now, of course, we have to correctly
account for
the between-subjects variability, that's
what's missing in this picture.
So let's do that now.
So to do this the correct way, remember
the unexplained variability is 523.
Once I account for
which subject I'm talking about, I'm going
to reduce some of the variability.
Because subject one, of course, you know,
might be higher than subject two.
They're always going to be higher.
That explains some of the variability.
Same as before, so
I'm going to run a repeated-measures
ANOVA, the correct analysis on this data.
And all that I'm going to additionally add
now, we've already calculated the sum of
squares between groups, the sum of squares
time.
We've already calculated the interaction
between group and time,
now we additionally have to calculate the
sum of squares between subjects.
So how do I do that?
So the sum of squares between subjects I
calculate by taking the mean for
each subject, fro, for each subject.
And now I'm going to compare it to the
group mean.
And so, 25.25 minus 24.75, 26 minus 24.75,
23 minus 24.75,
all of these squared of course.
We're going to do this for all of the
subjects, all six subjects and
then multiply by 4 to get a total of 24
squared things.
This gives me a total value of 150.
If you remember, when we calculated the
sum of squares between-subjects
when we didn't have a group factor in,
that came out to be about 276.
When I calculate it now after I have
accounted for
group, it comes out to be 150.
But remember, that the between,
the sum of squares between groups was
actually equal to 126.
So, if you add those two up, the total
variability between subject was 276.
But now some of the variability between
some of the differences between subject
has, subjects has now been explained by
which group you're in, 126 of that.
So 150 represents the remaining
variability that
exists between subjects not explained by
group.
The unexplained variability is therefore
going to be reduced from 523,
we subtract away this 150 and it's reduced
down to 373.
We've lowered our unexplained variability
now.
In our output from repeated-measures
ANOVA,
we're now going to get two elements.
We're going to get what are called
between-subjects effects.
Usually, these are of less interest.
We actually care less about these.
This, these have to do with the
differences between subjects.
And usually, that's not what we care
about.
We don't care that subject one happens to
be,
have higher depression than subject two.
We care about how things are changing over
time, usually.
So so I tend to end up ignoring these, but
you have to understand where they come
from.
So the between-group sum of squares we
already calculated was 126.
The between-subject variability, the
unexplained variability between subjects.
So the differences between subjects that
aren't due to group but
what's left over is this 150.
This you can, you can compare what's
explained and
what's unexplained here in the normal way
we would for ANOVA.
And you can get a p-value, and this is
what I've been calling the group effect.
So this is completely ignoring changes
over time and
just seeing, out of all the differences
between subject, the subject,
subject one versus two, two versus three,
et cetera.
How much of the differences are explained
by whether or
not you're in group A versus B?
And how much, many of the differences
between subjects are left unexplained?
And so, it doesn't quite come out to be
statistically significant here.
And the picture is, what you're really
comparing is, is line, the blue line,
is it significantly higher than the red
line?
That's what the group effect is asking
about.
Now notice that the p-value comes out to
be 0.14.
Here, if we go back to when I did the
wrong analysis, the p-value was smaller,
it was 0.06.
Because remember, when you fail to account
for correlation for between-subjects
comparisons or between-group comparisons,
the p-values will end up too small.
We see that here.
The correct p-value was actually higher
than what we got
with the incorrect analysis.
So that's the group effect.
Again, we don't usually care whether or
not group B happened to be a little
higher, overall, than group A.
We usually care about comparing their chi,
their differences over time.
But that's what the group effect is.
You also get, within-subjects effects, in
a separate section of your output.
This is talking about the time effect and
the time by group effect.
Which are usually the things that we care
about.
The error, the unexplained variability in
terms of
within-subjects effects, is now this 373.
We already calculated the sum of the
squares between time and
the sum of squares for the interaction.
We take all of these.
We can calculate F statistics and
p-values.
Notice that the p-values that come out
here are smaller than the ones that we
got when we failed to account for the
differences between subjects.
However, again, with this data set, we
haven't met compound symmetry.
So, we would probably be more correct to
report the a,
the corrected p-values that have corrected
for that violation of compound symmetry.
And those are 0.17 and 0.69.
These are not significant, and well, that
kind of matches the picture.
The time effect is getting towards
significance.
And that would say that there's some
differences over time.
And, indeed, if you look at time point
three,
time point three looks a little bit
different than the other time points.
That's what the time effect is asking.
Just is there any overall differences over
time.
Something where there wasn't a time
effect, you know,
would sort of look flat over time.
We have a little bit of a blip in time
point three.
That's, you know, getting us towards the
statistical significant.
The time by group effect is ask, asking
whether the pattern of changes over time,
this is essentially whether the slopes of
these two lines are equal.
And clearly, those lines are pretty
parallel with one another.
So it doesn't look like there's much
differences in the the trajectory over
time between the groups.
And that's reflected in this very non
significant p-value for
the time by group effect.
And that's usually what we care most
about.
So from this repeated-measures ANOVA
analysis,
we can sort of answer three questions.
We can ask is there overall significant
differences between time points.
That's the main effect for time.
We did not find a significant effect here.
I'm reporting the adjusted p-value here,
because of that violation of compound
symmetry.
Do the two groups differ at any time
points?
So this is ignoring time,
just as though a blue line higher than the
red line overall.
And that did not come out to
be significant either in the correct
analysis.
And then finally what we care most about,
do the two groups differ in their
responses over time?
That's that time by group interaction and
clearly that's totally not significant.
And again, that matches what we see in the
picture, but
it's just adding some p-values to it.
Another thing that you can get easily,
at least in SASS, is something that you
can use just for exploration.
I wouldn't use this as a formal test.
But, it's very easy in SASS to ask for
what's called a polynomial.
You can test for the shape of the response
profile.
I find this a useful tool,
because when we build to doing regression
models like GE and mixed models.
We are going to be putting in time as a
linear term, usually.
But what if there isn't actually a linear
change over time?
What if there's a quadratic change?
You can kind of probe that with this
little, asking for
this polynomial, which is one little
additional piece of code,
when you're asking for repeated-measures
ANOVA in SASS.
So it's fun just to ask for that.
Remember that the shape here for the two
groups, it looks something like that.
So that's probably best modeled as, as a
cubic, if anything.
And that's what comes out here, in fact,
that, it gives you some output for
linear, quadratic, and cubic.
Since we have four time points, we can go
up as high as cubic.
And, none of these come out significant.
The cubic one, however, is bordering on
significant.
Indicating that this is probably best mea,
estimated as a cubic if, if anything.
Now let me apply repeated-measures ANOVA
back to that same bone density example.
So remember this is the picture for the
bone density example.
I've got these three groups.
We're measuring their bone density over
time.
And it did look like the red group and
the black group seemed to be doing better
overall than the blue group.
So, I've now, I'm showing you the output
just from
the within-subjects output from a
repeated-measures ANOVA.
I'm not even bothering to show you the
between-subjects output,
although I'll get that output.
The between-subject output would say
whether or not,
overall, ignoring time point the groups
differ, and that's not really of interest.
What I want to know is whether or not
their, their changes in
bone density over time are different
between the different groups.
So, I'm going to get two things of
interest here.
I get a time effect and
a time by group effect when I put these
data into repeated-measures ANOVA.
The time effect is highly significant, and
by the way,
the epsilons here are very close to one.
These data actually very well meet
compound symmetry.
So highly significant result for time.
What that's saying is that, ignoring
group,
if you were to just kind of draw a line
which didn't distinguish between blue,
red and black, sort of the overall changes
across all groups.
You can imagine that it's going to be
something like if this is zero,
they're definitely going up on average.
Even if you average in the blue group,
it's going to be something like that.
So that's saying that there really is a
significant change over time,
highly significant.
Their bone density, on average, is going
up, ignoring group.
The time by group effect is going to
answer the question of whether or
not the, there any differences in the
changes over time between the groups.
It's not going to tell you where those
differences lie because it's an ANOVA,
it's a global test.
But we're bordering, we didn't quite make
statistical significance, but it's 0.06.
Saying that somewhere, some group is at
least one group differs from
the other in terms of their changes in
bone density over time.
And you can see that the blue group
doesn't change,
whereas the other two go out.
Didn't quite reach statistical
significance, but it's very close.
So that would be applying
repeated-measures ANOVA to that example.
Just for fun, I also asked for that
polynomial function, to see whether or
not the changes over time are more linear
or more quadratic.
I only have three times points, so the
most I can ask for is quadratic here.
This corresponds to the picture where I
tried to plot things,
in fitting smoothing lines.
And you can see that it looks like there's
a little curvature there,
but, basically those are pretty straight
lines.
Or, that would probably be best modeled as
straight lines.
The blue looks kind of flat, and then the
other two are going up over time.
And, indeed, when I ask for linear versus
quadratic, I get pretty significant for
linear and nothing for quadratic.
So that just gives me a sense of that
matches the picture.
That probably if I'm going to be doing
regression on these data,
it would be fine for me to model time as a
linear component and
assume that the changes over time were
linear.