[MUSIC]
In this next module, I'm going to show you
an evil trick.
If you've got a binary outcome,
you can actually run it in a Poisson
Regression with a little modification and
it's a way to get adjusted risk ratios and
avoid odds ratios.
So we talked about using Poisson
regression for count data, but it turns
out that you can actually apply Poisson
regression to binary outcome data as well.
Now, there's a little bit of a problem
here, and so
let me just explain what the problem is.
So remember that when you were assuming
that you're on a Poisson distribution,
you're assuming that the mean and
the variance are equal, that's true of a
Poisson distribution.
So that is something that's built into the
Poisson regression.
Now think about binomial outcomes, okay?
Binomial variables.
What's the mean for a binomial?
The mean is n times p.
What's the variance for a binomial?
Recall that a var, the variance for a
binomial is n times p times 1 minus p.
So what's always going to be the case,
when you're on a binomial distribution,
is that the mean is going to be greater
than the variance.
The variance is actually going to be
smaller than the mean.
And you can see that because you're always
multiplying the mean times one minus p.
As long as p is not one or zero, then this
is going to be a fraction.
And so the variance is always going to be
smaller.
Therefore, if you apply Poisson regression
to binary outcome data,
you're going to over estimate your
variance and
standard errors.
So that means your confidence intervals
are going to be too wide.
Your standard errors are going to be too
big.
Your p values are going to be too big.
So certainly you don't want to do that
because then you're going to
lose statistical power unnecessarily.
However, there is a simple modification
that researchers have figured out that you
can do to the Poisson regression to get to
the correct standard errors.
And that's something called applying
robust standard errors.
And it's fairly easy to do in most
standard statistical packages.
It's just a simple line of code.
And so this is great because now you can
take any situation where you've
got binary outcome data and rather than
running a logistic regression you could
instead choose to simply run a Poisson
regression with this modification.
What does that buy you?
Well, if you have a common outcome what
that buys you is that you're
going to get risk ratios.
The Poisson gives you these incidence rate
ratios which can be
interpreted as risk ratios.
Risk ratios are not misleading if you have
a common outcome,
odds ratios are misleading.
I'll just refer you to the reference for
this modification it's a 2004 paper.
This author shows, through simulation,
that this is a reasonable thing to do with
binary outcome data.
Now I haven't seen this applied too widely
in the literature, but
one can make an argument that whenever you
have a common outcome, it's probably
preferable to analyze the data this way,
than to do them in logistic regression.
Because of the fact that,
again, those odds ratios that come out of
logistic regression can be so misleading.
You can try to interpret those odds ratios
well for your readers, but
they still can be misleading, even if you
do a good job in the write up, so.
Just to give you an example of how this
works,
I'm going to go back to that data set that
I have on runners.
150 different women distance runners.
The outcome that we were looking at in an
earlier module was menstrual irregularity
and 33% of the runners in my sample had
menstrual irregularity.
Either amenorrhea or oligomenorrhea.
And now I'm going to use that outcome,
that kind of inclusive outcome as the
outcome for
logistic regression because I want to make
it as common as possible.
Just to show you how the odds ratios get
inflated.
The more common the outcome, the more the
odds ratio are inflated.
The predictor of interest that we were
looking at is a score on
an eating disorder questionnaire.
I'm abbreviating that as the EDIA.
So I went ahead and ran a logistic
regression first.
Again, common outcome.
I get out my odds ratios for the EDIA
score.
This is the odds ratio for a one unit
increase in your eating disorder score.
It's highly statistical significant.
The odds ratio comes out to be 1.12.
You would interpret this as a 12% increase
in your
odds of having menstrual irregularity for
every one point increase in your score on
this eating disorder questionnaire.
Remember, this isn't increase in odds
though, because my outcome is common, so
we would not want to misinterpret this as
an increase in your risk, or
the prevalence of menstrual irregularity.
But, I can also run these same data with
this binary outcome of menstrual
irregularity in a Poisson regression with
these robust standard errors.
And that's what I've done here.
And so here's my predictor variable,
EDIA here's my beta coefficient, and
here's my standard error,
this is the robust standard error, so now
these standard errors will be correct.
You can see that I indeed get a highly
statistically significant effect for
eating disorders scored, just as before.
But now I can take this beta coefficient
and I can exponentiate it and what I
get out are these relative risks, these
risk ratios, rather than odds ratios.
And if I had other things in the model, I
would be getting out adjusted risk ratios.
I am going to use the beta coefficient
this computer output also gave me
the 95% confidence interval for this beta
coefficient, if I exponentiate these,
I will get the 95% confidence interval for
the odds ratio.
I mean starting for the risk ratio.
So, let me just do that now, so I'm going
to exponentiate the 0.0653.
When I exponentiate that, I get that the
point estimate for
my odds ratio is one, sorry for my risk
ratio is 1.067.
So this is an incidence rate ratio of
course,
in this case we're talking about cross
sectional data.
So it's really technically called a
prevalence ratio, so you could
interpret this as, for every one unit
increase in the eating disorder score.
You have a 6.7% increase in your
prevalence of or
risk of menstrual irregularity.
We can also do the 95% confidence limits,
so if I exponentiate those confidence
limits from the previous page, I get a
lower bound of about 0.04, 1.04.
And an upper bound of about 1.096.
So that can be interpreted as the adjusted
risk ratio.
You don't need to worry about this
business about odds ratios being
misleading, you can avoid them altogether.
And just to compare, remember when we did
the odds ratio from logistic regression,
what we got there was point estimate of
1.12 and
a 95% confidence interval of 1.06 to 1.1
about 1.19.
So the width of the confidence interval is
similar here but these are all inflated.
And somebody could misinterpret those as
increases in,
in risk rather than increases in odds.
So sometimes it's nice just to be able to
directly report risk ratios and
this is one way to do that.