[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module,
I'm going to give a brief introduction to
an overview of survival analysis.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, by way of introduction,
I'm going to start with a historical
example of survival analysis.
This is when of the,
one of the first survival curves that you
can find in history.
This was drawn in 1669, and what this
mathematician did,
is he said, out of 100 people, how, when
do people die?
How long do, do people survive?
This is a survival curve, and what we're
showing here is the percent surviving
at any given age And these are ages on the
x-axis.
And you can see pretty quickly that
longevity in 1669 was not so good.
So if you started with 100 people who were
born, that's age zero.
By age six, if you scroll up here, about a
third of them had died by age six.
Only about two-thirds, a little less than
two-thirds,
64% are still surviving at around age 6.
If you go up to age 16, it's only 40% of
people surviving.
So, less than half of people made it to
age 16 back in 1669.
It's really a tribute to to modern
medicine.
If you look at age 20, it's only about a
third of people surviving.
At age 26, it's only about a quarter of
people surviving, by age 36,
five-sixths of people had died, and only
about a sixth,
one-sixth of people made it past age 36
back in, past age 36 back in 1669.
So, the survival odds were not great
living back then.
Again, really good tribute here to modern
medicine.
But this is an early example of a survival
curve, and this is
the kind of curve that we're going to be
looking at in survival analysis.
So we can ask all sorts of questions about
this curve.
So, for example, what's the shape of this
survival curve?
It turns out that this survival curve
corresponds to an exponential function.
We'll see that later today.
So we can define an actual mathematical
function that defines the survival curve.
We can also just ask, you know, about
particular survival probabilities.
What's the, what's a person's chance of
surviving past age 20?
Well, there's only, in this case, about a,
a 33% chance.
What was the probability of surviving past
age 36?
There's only about a 16% chance.
When we do Kaplan-Meier statistics,
what we're actually going to be doing is
just defining the curve based on
the probabilities of surviving past
particular time points.
And this is really what survival analysis
is.
We're trying to estimate this curve, but
the outcome for
survival analysis doesn't necessarily have
to be death.
You'll see that, of course, survival
analysis was built, the, the tools were
built, with time to death in mind, so a
lot of the terminology makes it, you know,
always talks about survival and failure
but in fact, the methods will work for
any binary event, it doesn't just have to
be death.
So we'll see some examples in a minute
that are not just death.
Some of what we care about in survival
analysis is drawing this curve or
defining this curve, but a lot of times
what we care more about is not just, you
know, what does this curve look like, but
we might want to compare different curves.
So for example, we could put the curve
for, you know, today's survival rates and
compare it to survival in 1669.
So a lot of times what we're interested
in, more so
than just drawing these curves,
is actually to compare different groups
with respect to their survival experience.
[SOUND].
Just to give you an example, a more modern
example,
this these are data from the Women's
Health Initiative, which came out in 2002.
This was a very important study, because
they randomized post-menopausal women,
to either take hormone-replacement therapy
or, a placebo pill.
And, the results were very, were very
surprising at that time because people had
thought that hormone replacement therapy
protected women
against coronary heart disease, which is
what's shown here.
And in fact, you can see that these graphs
are pretty intuitive to interpret, that,
this is showing you the cumulative risk of
getting coronary heart disease over time,
and the hormone group is, has a higher
risk than the placebo group.
So in fact it turned out, that the hormone
replacement therapy actually increased,
not decreased, the risk of coronary heart
disease in post menopausal women and,
that was surprising and actually resulted
in the, the study being halted early.
You can see that in the last slide I
showed you an example of
a survival curve where we started at sort
of 100% survival and dropped off.
A lot of times you'll see survival curves
starting at 100% and
dropping down from there.
You also may see survival curves like
this, which show you, the starting at
0% and showing you the cumulative total of
people who develop some kind of disease.
It doesn't really matter which direction
you put the curve in but
when you have an outcome that's relatively
rare, you know, coronary heart disease,
you can see 1 or 2, 3%, a relatively rare
outcome it might be better to describe it,
or to draw it as a cumulative hazard
because if you start at 100%,
you're not going to go down very much.
But you'll see the curves drawn in both
ways.
I'll just note here,
that we're going to be talking about
something called the hazard ratio
that's also printed on this little graphic
in this particular study.
The hazard ratio, which is very similar to
a relative risk, for
coronary heart disease if you compared
women on,
in the hormone group to women in the
placebo group, the hazard ratio was 1.29.
The way that you would interpret that is
that there was a 29% higher rate of the,
of coronary heart disease in the hormone
group versus the placebo group.
So what is survival analysis?
It's a set of statistical tools that are
used for analyzing time-to-event data.
And I'll talk about exactly what
time-to-event data is in just a second
here, but because we're waiting for events
to occur, we're measuring things over
time, we're generally going to be dealing
with data that have been collected over
time, that is, either from a randomized
clinical trial or from a cohort study.
You actually need to know the exact timing
of when things occurred,
when events occurred.
So, time-to-event variables are actually a
two-part outcome variable.
There's two pieces to it, and in our data
set we'll actually store this
outcome variable as two separate
variables.
So, there is a time part.
The time part of a time-to-event variable,
records the amount of time that a person
was in the study,
until they either had the event, or, they
were what we call censored.
And by censored we mean, that, we stopped
following them for whatever reason,
but the last time we saw them, they had
not had the event of interest.
So you either, again the time part is
either the time until the event, or
the time until censored.
And then there's a binary variable that
tells us whether or
not that person had the event.
Some people will have the event.
Some people will develop coronary heart
disease during the study.
Some people will not.
So, this binary variable records whether
or
not a person had the event or, whether
they were censored, and
again censored means that the last time we
saw them, they were event free.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we, it's a two-variable outcome,
we actually need two separate variables in
our data set to store this information.
The time variable gives us the time at
which a person had their event, or
the, at the last time where we saw them
and they had not yet had the event.
And we also need a censoring variable,
which is just a binary variable that
tells us, yes they had the event, or no
they did not, they were censored.
So just to illustrate, let me throw it in,
a simple example here.
So here's some data on time to conception,
just to show you that survival analysis
doesn't always have to have a bad outcome.
So this was some data on 38 women who, all
of them had some kind of treatment for
infertility, so this is a single cohort,
one group of women.
They all had the same treatment.
They were followed for up to two years,
and the event of inter-,
interest here was conception.
These were women who wanted to get
pregnant, so again, it's a happy outcome.
So, time to a conception is the outcome
here.
Just to show you what the data looked like
from that study, it's again,
a two-variable outcome variable.
So we have Time and we have Event.
So the Time, again, tells us the amount of
time they were in the study until they
got pregnant, or until they were censored,
we lost them to follow-up.
The event variable tells us whether or not
they got pregnant or,
whether the last time we saw them, they
were not yet pregnant.
So, as an example, this person here was in
the study for
two months before they got pregnant.
She did get pregnant in the second cycle,
the second month.
Contrast that down here to this person.
This person was in the study for four
months but she did not get pregnant,
so after four months we don't know what
happened to her.
She was probably lost to follow-up, we no
longer have any data on her,
she quit the study for whatever reason we,
we don't know what
happened after four months so, she
contributes just four months to the study,
we at least know that for four months she
was, pregnancy free in this case.
All of the examples that we're going to
deal with in this class are going to
have right censoring, which is the most
common type of censoring.
So right censoring means that you censor
somebody because the study ended, and
at the time the study ended, they still
had not had the event.
Or, because something else happened to
them like they died due to something that
wasn't the event of interest.
So they died before they got pregnant, or
before they had coronary heart disease, so
something else that takes them out of the
study, at, but at the last time we
saw them, they had not yet had the event,
or they were lost to follow-up,
because of course with longitudinal
studies, sometimes people move, they just
decide not to participate anymore, you
lose a good amount of people to follow up.
So all of those would be reasons that
people might be censored.
These are all right censoring because,
right censoring means that we know that
the subject survived event free, at least
up til time T.
They may or
may not have gone on to later have the
event, to the right of, of that time.
This is in contrast to left censoring.
In left censoring, the event would've
already happened before people
joined the study, and we don't necessarily
know exactly when it happened, but those
examples are less common and we're not
going to deal with those in this class.
Everything here is going to be right
sensored.
Now if you're just looking at the data
the, for
the first time seeing time-to-event
outcomes, you might just say,
well, okay, why use survival analysis at
all?
I've got a continuous outcome here, time.
So why not just compare the times, the
mean times or
the median times, between the different
groups using, say a T test or
a linear regression which we already know
about.
So of course the problem with that, just
looking at the time,
is you gotta remember that not everybody
is going to have the event in your study.
So you need to account for the censoring.
If you just looked at the mean times and
compared those mean times between groups,
you would ignore the fact that some people
had the event and
some people were censored.
So that's not going to be sufficient.
You might also ask, well, okay, I've got a
binary outcome here, and sure, you know,
some people took longer to get to that
outcome than others, but, why not just
compare the proportion of people who have
events in all the different groups and
use logistic regression like we did
previously?
And, of course, the problem here is, that,
it ignores the time element.
So, yes, some people had events and
some people didn't and we could just look
at those proportions, with risk ratios,
odds ratios, logistic regression, but that
would ignore the time.
And, the time may make a difference,
right?
If somebody dies two days into your study,
and
somebody else dies ten years into your
study, that's a huge difference.
If we only looked at death, yes or no,
we'd be completely ignoring that
time part, and losing a whole bunch of
information.
We'd be reducing our statistical power and
precision.
So this way, with survival analysis, we're
able to incorporate both the time part and
the binary yes or no they had the event,
or they didn't.
The basic test that we're going to be
using for survival analysis, again,
this is when we have time-to-event
outcomes, this very special kind of
outcome, you could use what are called
just basic rate ratios if you
don't want to do any adjustment and, and
there's only two groups.
For something a little more fancy, you can
do Kaplan-Meier statistics, but
those are not going to be adjusted for
anything so that just allows you
to compare groups without adjusting for
any kind of confounding.
If you want to do any kind of regression,
we're going to be doing either, some kind
of parametric survival model, which I'm
going to talk about briefly this week,
or you can do cox regression which we're
going to spend more time on.
Those are the multi variant regression
techniques when
you have time-to-event outcomes.
And just to give you a little overview of
those tests which we're going to go
into in great detail in upcoming modules,
just to kind of frame them all together,
Kaplan-Meier statistics is what we call a
non-parametric method.
So all that means is that we're not
going to make any assumptions about
the survival curve.
We're going to try to draw the survival
curve,
but we're going to just draw what we see
in our data.
We're not going to assume it follows any
particular mathematical function.
We're not going to be estimating any
parameters, so
that means we're not going to be
estimating hazard ratios or
anything like that.
We're just going to get these pictures of
curves and get a p-value.
No, no, nothing else.
So we call that non-parametric.
We're not estimating any parameters.
Parametric survival occurs, as you can,
guess, they're completely parametric.
This would mean that we're estimating all
the possible param-, all,
all the possible parameters.
So that means we're actually going to try
to,
to fit a per-, perfect mathematical
function to the different survival curves.
And, we're going to, not only compare the
curves, that, in different groups,
but we're also going to try to define the
underlying curve.
What's the shape of that curve?
We're going to estimate all possible
parameters essentially.
Now Cox regression is kind of a compromise
between those two.
So in Cox regression,
we're not going to bother to try to
estimate what's the shape of the curve.
So we don't want to make any assumptions.
We don't have to make any assumptions
therefore,
about the underlying survival curve, what
that shape it follows.
But we are going to try to say what is the
difference between two groups in
their curves, without actually drawing or
estimating that underlying curve.
So we're going to be estimating some
parameters, hazard ratios, which compare
different groups without saying anything
about the underlying survival curve.
So that's called semi-parametric because
it's kind of in between the other two.
[BLANK_AUDIO]