[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to walk you
the,
through the specific steps of 10-fold
cross-validation.
So the idea of cross-validation is the
following.
You want to sort of cleverly split your
data into multiple training and test sets.
In a way that the data that are used to
train the model,
are never the same data that are used to
test the model.
And there's a lot of ways to do this.
So one of them is leave-one-out
cross-validation, where you
literally leave one observation out at a
time, you fit the model on everybody else,
and then you test the model on that one
observation that was left out.
So if you're doing logistic regression,
you take that logistic regression that was
fit and you'd apply it to
that one observation that was left out to
calculate their predicted probability.
And then you do that for everybody so
that every observation was left out once,
and then you'd somehow summarize those
predicted probabilities that were
calculated based on
models where those observations were not
included in the fitting.
For K-fold cross-validation,
you're going to hold out a larger chunk of
the data at a time.
So I'm going to show you the steps of
10-fold cross-validation but
if you wanted to do five-fold
cross-validation it would be very similar,
you would just do it five times rather
than than ten.
So the first step is you're going to
randomly divide your data into ten tenths,
ten pieces.
You're going to to take the first tenth of
the data,
that's going to be your test data set.
You're going to fit your model to the
other nine tenths of the data,
which are now the training data.
Now fitting the model means you're
going to do the,
the whole thing again including both the
variable selection and
the pocketing of the beta coefficients.
That's an important point which I'll get
back to in a minute.
Once you fit the model you're then
going to apply that model to
the test data.
So if you've done logistic regression that
means you're going to calculate predictive
probabilities for
everybody in the test set based on the
model which they weren't used to fit.
Then you're going to repeat that procedure
for all 10 tenths of the data.
You're going to come out with su, you're
going to be able to then summarize all of
the mea, measures of accuracy from the
test data.
You're going to summarize that.
Often we'll take like a mean.
For logistic regression, if you calculated
predicted probabilities from all
the test data, you can put those together,
and make an ROC curve and
calculate an area under the ROC curve.
now, there's a common mistake that people
make when doing 10-fold cross-validation.
And it may, this mistake's been made in a
lot of, like, micro-array and
gene studies.
So, it's very important this little point
I make it in, bullet two here, is that
you have to redo your variable selection
every time for each one of these folds.
So for example, maybe you, you're do a
study on gene and
you do your model selection, your model
fitting, your model building and
you come out with a model that says, this
disease is related to these five genes.
Call them gene A, gene F, gene Z, gene G
and gene H.
Let's say, we started with 26 genes to
choose from.
Usually there's more genes than that, but
some, some set of genes.
And this is the ones that came out in the
end of the final day to,
to be retained in our final model.
Maybe we were using some kind of automatic
selection procedure.
Whatev, however we were selecting these
variables.
These are the ones that made it in the
final model.
And of course, we're doing some
regression,
there's going to be some data associated
with each of those genes.
So there's sort of two pieces here.
There's what genes actually make the final
model, and then there's
the exact weight that they're given in the
final model, the beta coefficients.
When you rerun the model, refit the model
on the, for
cross-validation, you have to do both of
those steps.
Both selecting which genes make it into
the final model and
refitting those beta coefficients, those,
those weights.
What a lot of people forget to do is the
first part of that.
They don't redo their variable selection.
So, if you were to do this wrong,
let's say this again gives you the final
model that you came out with.
At the end of the day,
that's the model you want to validate with
10-fold cross-validation.
You go to do your 10-fold cross-validation
and you get to step two here and
you say okay, now I'm going to fit my
model again on my nine tenths of the data.
So rather than re-selecting the genes you
just start with only this set.
So you fit the logistic regression model
or whatever regression you're
doing with gene A, gene F, gene Z, gene G
and gene H, and you fit new beta.
So you get a beta called a beta star
because you're, you know, it's a new beta.
So you get some new betas, and then you
apply that model.
To your test data set.
That's wrong.
Because you had all these other genes that
you, when you fit your original model.
You had to select which genes were
going to get included in the,
in the predictor set for that model.
What you need to do, the correct thing to
do, is to start over again and apply say,
your automatic selection procedure to the
original set of candidate predictors or
candidate genes in this case.
So that means that the model that comes
out for the first tenth of
your data set for this cross validation,
might be slightly different.
So maybe you get, you know, gene A and
you get gene F and you get gene Z and you
get gene G,
but then instead of gene H you get gene N.
You're you can get a slightly different
set.
And so you need to redo that variable
selection step.
And if you don't, then this
cross-validation will not be valid.
You're then going to do this ten times.
That means you could come out with ten
slightly different models, both in terms
of the beta coefficient and the variables
contained in the, in those models.
Now a question that a lot of people will
have at the end of this is they'll say,
well, okay, well I, now I've got ten
different models.
Which model do I report in my paper?
Well, you're still going to report the
original model that you first fit.
So the validation is what it's buying you
is just getting a better estimate of
the actual model accuracy.
So you're going to re, report the, the,
better ROC area under the ROC curve, but
you're going to report the original model.
This is just to give you a sense of how
overfit that original model is.
There may be reason where you try to use
the, you know,
the different models fit from different
bootstrap samples or something.
But usually we're just doing this
cross-validation to
get a better estimate of say that area
under the curve.
So the fact that we have slightly
different models in every fold is
not a problem.
And this is an important enough error that
people have made in enough microarray
papers and such that it you know, it's
been written about in the literature, so
here is a, a paper writing about this
particular error, and
kind of illustrating what can go wrong if
you make this error.
So what this graphic is showing.
This was a, a paper where they did a
number of simulations, and
they simulated kind of gene studies, so
something like micro array or SNP studies,
where there's a buncha candidate genes.
And what they did in this simulation
though was,
they pretended that all of the genes were
noise.
So, actually nothing is related to the
disease that they care about.
And they went through and they selected
models and
they found that a number of those genes
popped up in the selected models.
As you would expect, there is some, some
type of error going on here so
a lot of those noise genes get selected in
the models.
We're going to then do some kind of
cross-validation to
try get at that overfitting.
And what they did is they, ran the model,
and didn't cross-validate.
They just did some kind of,
what a re-substitution here means just
that you're calculating your
ROC curve based on the original data, and
you're not doing any cross-validation.
They then did the cross-validation wrong.
They cross-validated after the selection
of
genes without re-selecting the genes at
each fold as we just talked about.
That's going to be in the graph here, the
diagonal lines and
then they did it correctly and that's the
checkered pattern here.
And what this graph is showing you here
is, remember these are all noise genes.
So you want the cross, cross-validation to
show you those errors,
to show you where things have been wrongly
classified as being important so
that you want many, many
misclassifications.
When you don't cross-validate you get none
of course because you
haven't cross-validated.
When you do a cross-validation wrong you
only identify a couple of the noise genes,
a couple of the errors.
When you do the cross-validation right,
you identify a huge number of more errors.
So, doing the cross-validation wrong will,
you will absolutely not catch how much
you've actually overfit your model.
Let me just show you an example of 10-fold
cross-validation in the literature.
So the point of this study was to estimate
the probability that a patient who
has a solitary pa, pulmonary nodule,
that's just a like a mass in their lung.
Sometimes you'll have masses in the lung
that are benign.
Some will be lung cancer.
And we need to make some decisions to say
who's likely to actually have lung cancer.
It's actually pretty invasive to go in and
biopsy a growth in your lungs, so
we probably don't want to have to do that
invasive surgery for
someone who has a really low chance of
actually having lung cancer.
So they wanted to come up with the
prediction model here.
They used a data set of 375 veterans who
had these nodules and
the actually done the gold standard test,
the biopsy they
knew that 54% actually had lung cancer and
46% actually had benign masses.
Then they used stepwise logistic
regression so,
they're using automatic selection
procedure coupled with they're doing
a logistic regression because the outcome
here is binary.
You either have lung cancer or you don't.
So they came up with a final model.
So here's the model,
when they ran their stepwise progression
here's what they came, came out with.
So if you were a smoker, you have a much,
much higher probability of actually hav,
having lung cancer, not surprisingly.
Being older was also a risk factor for
having lung cancer,
bigger nodules were more likely to be lung
cancer and if you'd quit smoking then you
were a little bit less likely to actually
have a malignant tumor or lung cancer.
So that was the final model that they
reported in their paper.
And let me tell you a little bit more
about this model,
so I've shown you the odds ratios on the
previous slide.
But we can make an actual, we can
calculate a predicted probability for
everybody, based on the model.
So, remember, a predicted probability from
logistic regression looks
something like e raised to something over
1 plus e raised to
something that's our predicted probability
from logistic regression.
The something here is the alpha plus beta
blah blah blah.
So the alpha here was 8.404.
The beta for smoking we, I showed you as
an odds ratio on the previous page,
now I'm just showing you the beta.
That's the beta for smoking, the beta for
age, the beta for how big the, the tum,
the nodule is.
And a beta for years that they've quit,
every 10 years they've quit smoking.
So this is just the logistic regression
model.
It can be used to calculate a predicted
probability for everybody.
That predicted probability then is used to
calculate, to make an ROC curve and
calculate the area under the curve.
Whey they calculated the area under the
curve just for
the original data without doing any
cross-validation.
That model had an area under the curve of
0.79.
So, pretty good predicted accuracy.
Not bad.
They also showed you that the 95%
confidence interval that the predicted
accuracy is somewhere between probably 74%
and 84%.
Perfect.
Always nice to put a confidence interval
on that area under the curve.
As we know, this area under the curve may
be overly optimistic.
So, if we were to apply this logistic
regression model to a new dataset,
the area under the curve is going to be
smaller and
it might be considerable smaller if there
was a lot of over fitting.
We don't have extra data lying around.
So, instead what they did was to do
10-fold cross-validation to
get a better estimate of the area under
the curve.
So here's how the 10-fold cross-validation
works.
They first took the 375 people and they
randomly divided them
into sets of either 37 or 38, it doesn't
come out exactly even here.
They would then fit the logistic
regression model to the 337, or
338 that were held out.
And they're going to again repeat the
whole stepwise selection to generate
a new model, meaning new predictors might
end up in some of those models.
So re-select the variables, get slightly
new betas.
So slightly different models than the,
from the original.
Then they used the resulting model to
calculate the predictive probabilities for
the test data set say for the 38 who were
held out.
Then you save those predictive
probabilities,
store them in a new data set, save them
somewhere on your computer.
Then you're going to repeat steps two and
three for each of the tenths of the data,
until you end up with a,
everybody having a predicted probability,
and those predicted probabilities having
been calculated on models that those
people were not used to fit.
So then you build the ROC curve with those
predicted probabilities and
you can calculate the area under the
curve.
And that's what they did here.
When they did this, they calculated the
area under the curve.
It was 78%.
It was 79% on the original data.
It only went down to 78%.
That indicates that there were actually
was not a lot of
over-fitting going on in this model.
This model was fairly robust.