Welcome to week seven.
This week we're going to talk about how to
build prediction models.
So last week we talked about the
distinction between Explanatory models and
predictive models.
So, explanatory models are trying to
identify [UNKNOWN] relationships whereas
predictive models are trying to predict
something accurately about the future.
Because those goals are very different,
the model building process is also
going to be different.
So, this week we are going to talk about
model selection and
evaluation in the context of predictive
models.
We'll be using some tools, the bootstrap,
cross-validation, and shrinkage.
I just want to quickly point out one thing
to you,
last week when I was talking about
explanatory models,
I talked about the situation where we had
multiple important predictors.
We were trying to identify multiple
important predictors.
Of an outcome.
And I'll just warn you that in some ways
this is going to look, kind of similar to
what we're doing this week when we're
trying to do prediction modeling,
because we will be trying to find a set of
predictors that significantly relate to
the outcome.
You've gotta keep in the back of your mind
though,
that these two problems are very, very
different.
So when we're trying to identify multiple
important predictors, Of an outcome.
In the causal situation, in the
explanatory case,
we really care about confounding, because
we don't want to accidentally say that
a confounder is related to an outcome when
it's not.
And we really care about chance findings,
we don't want to say that something's
related, when it's not.
When we're talking about finding a set of
predictors for
a prediction model, remember our goal is
just to be able to predict accurately.
So, we're not going to worry so
much about confounding because if we put a
confounder in the model, It doesn't
matter, as long as it's just as predictive
as the variable that its related to.
Which it could be.
We may worry less about chance findings as
well because if we end up with a couple of
extra predictors in our prediction model
that are actually just noise.
It will reduce the, the model accuracy a
little bit.
But we're not so worried about getting one
or two wrong.
Because again we're not making any causal
claims about those variables.
So just keep in mind that even know these,
these may seem the same they're,
they're actually quite different.
Now prediction is everywhere.
So if you pay attention to the news You'll
notice prediction in, in tons of
news stories because everybody wants to
forecast something about the future.
So here's a couple of recent headlines I
happen to see, so
Warren Buffet is offering a billion
dollars if you can get the perfect NCAA
(no period) Tournament bracket to the NCAA
basketball tournament that gets
played every year where you start with 64
teams and you get down to one winner and
a lot of people will bet on this, he is
offering a billion dollars if you can get
it exactly right, now in a minute, I'll
show you what the probability of that is.
Is.
But that's a prediction problem.
And then Nate Silver is often in the news
for prediction.
He of course, accurately predicted the
presidential elections in 2008 and 2012.
He's also predicting things like Oscars
and the Super Bowl apparently.
Prediction was in the news recently also
because people are trying
predict risks of earthquakes.
That's of course very important in the Bay
Area.
So there's so many cases where prediction
comes in.
Just for fun here I want to actually
calculate what's the probability of
winning that billion dollar prize from
Warren Buffet,
we can calculate the probability of that.
So how does the basketball tournament
work?
So, we start with 64 basketball teams.
They are going to play two at a time,
so, they'll be 32 games, from which will
emerge 32 winners.
So we'll know at the beginning of the day
the 64 teams that will start, and
we'll know who's playing who.
After that, we'll get, have 32 teams left.
Those teams will each play each other.
So we'll have a winner and a loser from
each of those games.
We'll get down to 16 teams, and then down
to eight.
Then down to four.
Then down to the final game, and then down
to the winner.
Okay.
So, we can, its actually not too hard to
go through and
say, what's the probability of getting
the, the perfect bracket.
So we have to calculate first of all what
are all the possible brackets that we
could possibly choose if we're in our
office pool for example.
So, the first thing that happens is we
have 64 teams.
We know who's playing each other within
that 64.
Out of that 32 winners.
Well, the pr, the number of different ways
we
can get 32 winners out of those 32 games,
is 2 raised to the 32.
That's because in each game, there are two
possible winners, and there are 32 games.
So we do 2 raised to the 32nd.
So, that's the first step.
That's just to get the first through the
first round of elimination.
Then, we get to this second set, so 32
teams are left.
There is going to be 16 games, two at a
time.
And now, again, we are going to have out
of that two raised to
the 16 ways that those games could sort
themselves out, right?
You could have In, with each game there's
two possible winners,
there's 16 different games.
Well now we can keep going, you can
kind of guess the pattern here.
So, the, the next round, there's going to
be eight winners, so there's two
possible winners for every game, there can
only going to be eight winners.
And then the next round is going to be 2
to the 4,
the next round is going to be 2 to the 2
and
the next round there's going to be only 1
winner out of 2 teams left.
So we just can multiply together all these
2's raised to different powers (no period)
And so, if you just add up the 32 plus the
16, plus the 8, 4, 2, and 1.
You can see this is raised to, this is 2
raised to the 63rd.
There are to raised to the 63rd ways that
you could draw [UNKNOWN] bracket.
That many possibilities.
Well, 2 raised to the 63rd.
[INAUDIBLE] base 2 is not so big.
You might not thing this is huge.
But actually, what value is, is this is 9,
quintillion, which means 18 zeros.
So, let's see, one, two, three, four,
five, six.
[SOUND] I just have to draw it out
because,
just to show you how big that number is.
So, that's 9 quintillion, there are 9
quintillion possible records.
Of course, the probability of winning the
billion dollar prize.
Now this is just if you're guessing, is 1
out of 9 quintillion.
Okay.
So, it's not likely,
that anybody is actually going to claim
this price as Warren Buffett said
billion dollar is pretty safe.
Now of course if you had actual knowledge
about basketball,
you could do much better than these odds.
Because you'd have some sense of who's
likely to win each game, but
still, even in that case the probability
is going to be really, really,
really low that you can get it exactly
right.
It's Oscar time until there's been a lot
of Oscar predictions going on
around in the,
in the news, this was some predictions
that were made from the 2013 Oscar's.
Somebody came up with some kind of
modeling And
predicted out of all of the nominees who
was going to win in each category.
There were 24 categories.This person got I
think it was 19 out of
24 correct which isn't bad.
Then you can see some of there results
here so for best director, they
calculated that the highest probability of
winning went to Steven Spielberg.
In fact, Life of Pi Director Ang Lee won.
So he got this one wrong, but then you can
see he got a lot right,
everywhere it's yellow he got it right.
So Argo he gave a 68% chance, indeed Argo
won, Life of Pi for
best cinematography he gave 95% chance and
that won, best actor, best screenplay etc.
So you can see that there's a lot of
things that people want to predict and
it's a lot of fun to do prediction.