In the last couple of modules, I told you
about the logistic regression model and
how do we interpret the alphas and betas
from logistic regression models.
In this module we're going to take one
step back and
ask the question, where did that alpha and
beta come from?
So you put some data into the computer, it
spits out some numbers.
How is the computer actually estimating
alpha and beta?
This is important to understand because
it's important to have some concept of
what is the likelihood function that will
provide you insight into
the logistic regression model as well as
other regression models late,
that we'll see later on, such as clock
regression.
I'll warn you that the module, this module
is not for the faint of heart.
There is going to be a lot of math and
some calculus.
Just bear with me.
I'm just expecting you to be able to
follow my logic,
not necessarily to be able to calculate
maximum likelihood estimation on your own.
I just want to start by reminding you
about the estimation process that was used
to estimate the parameters, the alphas and
the betas, in linear regression.
So just as a quick review here, remember,
linear regression we
might have some continuous predictor and a
continuous outcome.
We can represent them as a scatterplot.
And we're trying to find the line that
best fits the points on the plot.
So, somewhere there is a line that best
fits these points.
So we can define that line, by defining an
intercept and a slope,
an alpha and a beta.
How did we actually estimate alpha and
beta in linear regression?
Again, I didn't make you do it by hand.
But if you, what is the computer actually
doing?
So the technique that was used to estimate
the parameters in
linear regression is something called
least squares estimation.
And just briefly, what that is, is you see
all these points here.
You're trying again to find the line that
kind of goes through, you know,
best goes through those by the best fit
line.
And what do we mean by best fit?
We want to find the line that minimizes
the distance from all
the individual points to the line, has the
least distance.
So for example, each point has some
distance from the line,
they're not exactly on the line.
That would be the best fit line, so
we want to find the alpha and the beta
that accomplishes that.
Now, notice that some of the distances
from the line are negative,
they're the below, and some are positive,
and
so if we try to do this without squaring,
we'd end up kind of canceling things out.
So the reason there's a square here, is
that the square gets rid of the negatives.
But we define something called the sum of
squares error.
We can make this function or this
equation, that just says the following.
We want to actually add up the squared
distances for, from the line.
So, if I were to make an equation that
adds up the square distances from
the line, I would take i equals 1 to n, n
being your total sample size.
I take the actual values for Y, the actual
observed values for Y for
every observation in your data set, and
then I would subtract the value
on the line, so for example, somebody who
has an X value here of ten,
they have an observed value, but they also
have a predicted value from the line.
That would be here.
Now just to keep it general, for
the moment I'm just going to use alpha and
beta.
We don't know what alpha and beta are yet.
That's what we're trying to solve for.
So we're going to try to find the alpha
and
beta that minimizes the square distance.
But what we're getting here is, what is
the predicted value for y?
Well, based on our line here, the
predicted value for
Y for a given person, as you plug in their
X value into the equation.
Again I'm leaving alpha and beta general
because we're going to solve for them, but
it's going to be whatever alpha plus beta
times the X value for that particular
person that would be their predicted value
which we sometimes represent as Yi hat.
So, we're going to add all of those things
up.
In fact we're going to square, those
distances from the line,
for the reasons I mentioned, to avoid
negative.
So that would be, that is the sum of
squares of the error.
So that is the square, the total squared
distance of all the points from the line.
Now, we want to find the alpha and beta
that minimize the distance from the line.
So, this is a minimization problem, which
gets us into a little bit of calculus.
Not going to go through the calculus here
but I'll just set it up for you.
So there's some alpha or some beta.
We're going to, I'll just look at beta.
Now we're trying to find for example the
beta that minimizes this sum squared of
errors term that has, that gives us the
least distance from the line basically.
And there's some function.
We could take this function here and we
could graph it.
And I'm just making a real simple graphic
here, but
imagine it looks something like this.
There is some minimum point, and we want
to solve for
the beta that gives us the least distance
from the line.
The least sum of square zero.
We want to solve for that point.
Well how do you solve, well how do you do
a minimization problem?
What you do of course is that you
recognize that,
the slope with the tangent line, which is
just another way of saying the derivative,
at the lowest point, that will equal to
zero.
The slope here will, of the tangent line
here will equal to zero.
In other words, the derivative of this
function, if I take the derivative of this
function, I take the derivative of that
and I'm not going to write it out here,
but I take the derivative with respective
data of that function and then I set it
equal to zero and then I solve for either
alpha or beta one at a time.
That's how I can get the alpha and the
beta.
So this was a technique called least
squares regression and
that worked for linear regression.
However, it turns out that that method
doesn't work in
the case where our outcome variable is not
normally distributed.
So we need to move to something which
sometimes people call generalized linear
models, which just means that we want to
generalize the ordinary linear
regression equation.
So that we allow outcome variables that
are not normally distributed such as
binary variables.
And one example of a generalized linear
model is the logistic regression model.
And so what does the generalized linear
model look like?
Well, the right hand side of the equation
looks exactly the same as we
saw with linear regression.
Something like that.
We have some alphas and some betas.
Same linear function.
The only thing is that,
in the right hand side of the equation, we
no longer have Yi.
We no have, no longer have something
that's continuous and
normally distributed, so we have to have
some kind of link function.
This is sometimes called the systematic
component that linear function,
then we have a link function,
which in the case of logistic regression,
the link function was the logit.
But that link function allows us to bring
in these other types of outcome variables.
However, we then need some way to estimate
the alphas and the betas and
we can't use least squares regression
anymore.
So we use something instead called maximum
likelihood estimation,
to estimate alpha and beta.
So, it's just a yet, a different
estimation thing.
A different estimation technique, similar
to least squares regression but it's a,
it's different mathematically, called
maximum likelihood estimation.
Just some examples of generalized linear
models.
So logistic regression is a generalized
linear model.
An outcome variable that we have would be
a proportion.
This is when we have a proportion rather
than you know,
something again normally distributed.
The distribution we have here is a
binomial.
The link function, which is what's key
here,
is the logit function, but there's other
types of
generalizing your models that we're not
talking about in this class.
There's something called Poisson
regression.
So this is where you have an outcome
variable that are counts.
That's often like, you know,
the number of cases of disease in a
certain area of the country.
That could be a count variable.
The distribution here is something called
a Poisson distribution.
That's a pro-, that's a discrete
probability distribution.
And the link function that gets used here
is the natural log.
So that's another type of generalized
linear model.
And you can also kind of think of linear
regression in term, in these terms.
The outcome variable is continuous.
The distribution is normal.
For the linear regression, the function,
the link function is just the identity
function.
That just means that we don't transform y
in any way.
It just stays the same.
That's what we do in linear regression.
So as I alluded to, when you have
generalized linear models,
instead of using least squares estimation,
you're going to use something called
maximum likelihood estimation to
estimate the parameters, in other words
the alpha and the betas.
Now I'm going to introduce you to maximum
likelihood estimation with
a simple little problem.
So we're going to start with a really
simple problem so
that you can just get the logic of maximum
likelihood estimation.
So we'll start with a very simple little
coin problem.
Okay, so here's the problem.
You have a coin, and you know for some
reason that it's biased.
You know that, somebody's told you this is
not a fair coin.
But your job is to kind of figure out
what's the probability of
heads in this biased, this non-fair coin.
In a fair coin, the p would be, here would
be 0.5.
But for some reason we know that it's not
equal to 0.5, or
it might not be equal to 0.5, and you want
to guess at what p is, okay?
You want an estimate, there's an unknown
perimeter here.
The unknown perimeter is p, that's the
probability of the coin coming out heads.
You want to estimate that, so this is a
parameter estimation problem.
There is some true parameter p, some true
probability that the coin will
come out heads, you want to estimate that
probability.
So we can use maximum likelihood
estimation here.
So what are we going to do?
If want to solve this problem,
what we're probably going to do is start
flipping the coin, right.
So the best way to kind of guess, at what
a fairness of a coin is,
is to actually start flipping it and
counting up how many heads we get.
I'm going to make this probably really
simple and assume that we're
kind of lazy here where we're just
going to flip the coin ten times.
We flip the coin ten times.
The coin comes up heads seven times.
Okay?
At that point,
given the data that you've collected, what
would you guess that p would be here?
I think most of us could sort of
intuitively in agree that the best guess
here is 0.7.
Why 0.7?
Well, I flipped the coin ten times, seven
times it came out heads.
My best guess is that the coin is biased
towards heads, with a p of about 0.7.
Now, of course, you'd probably want to
flip the coin more times and
collect more data, but I mean, trying to
keep the problem real simple here.
I think we can all agree intuitively that
given the data that you saw,
the best guess for the estimate of p is
0.7.
So that's very intuitive, but
what we're going to do now is we're
going to solve for that parameter.
We're going to estimate that parameter
using maximum likelihood estimation.
And I'll show you that you get the 0.7 out
in the end,
but this will kind of make you believe
that the math is correct.
Alright, so when we're doing maximum
likelihood estimation the first thing
that we have to do is build a likelihood
function.
So we're going to be maximizing a function
and that function that
we're going to be maximizing is called a
likelihood function.
All the likelihood function is, is the
probability of your data.
So, whatever you see in your data, it's
the probability of that.
And, we can do that pretty easily here,
because it's a very simple case.
We flipped the coin ten times.
We saw seven heads.
What's the probability of that as a
function of our unknown parameter p?
So keeping p general here.
What is the probability of seeing seven
heads in ten coin tosses?
And we're going to calculate the exact
probability of that.
We're not going to be calculating
cumulative probabilities here.
We're going to calculate the exact
probability of exactly what our
outcome was.
Exactly 7 heads in 10 coin tosses.
So, hopefully you recognize that if we're
looking at, we're talking about
the number of heads in coin tosses, but
that's a binomial random variable.
In this case, we have, we did ten flips.
So our N is ten.
And as I mentioned, we're going to keep
our p, the chance of a heads.
We're going to keep that as an unknown.
We're going to keep it general as p.
So we are on a binomial distribution, with
an N of ten.
And a p that's just unknown at that point.
This is what we're trying to estimate,
that p.
Well how would I write out the probability
of getting exactly seven heads in
ten coin tosses then?
Well I'm just going to rely on my binomial
formula here.
Here so we know we're in a binomial
distribution.
And the probability of exactly seven heads
in ten coin tosses is going to be 10 to 7.
Whatever p is, whatever that value is
raised to the 7th.
And then one minus p raised to the third.
And you can do out the 10 to 7,
10 factorial, divided by 7 factorial,
divided by three type trails.
So that is my likelihood function.
That's the likelihood function here.
It's the probability of our data as a
function of our unknown parameter.
That's the parameter we're going to try to
estimate.
This is called the likelihood function and
it gives us the probability of our data,
again as a function of our unknown
parameter.
Alright, now we want to find the p, the
value of p,
that maximizes the probability of our
data.
Right?
That maximizes the likelihood function.
Why is that?
Well, we saw our data, right?
That's what we actually saw in our
experiment.
So we want to find the value of p that
makes our data what we actually
saw the most likely.
So we want to maximize this function.
This is a function and we can maximize it
using calculus.
Alright, so how do you maximize a
function?
So this involves a little bit of calculus.
So kind of, we're going to go through kind
of three steps of how to
maximize the function here.
So first of all, I'm going to do one
little transformation at the beginning.
I'm going to start with the likelihood
function and
then I'm going to take a log of the
likelihood function.
I can take natural log or just any log of
the likelihood function.
So here is my likelihood function and I'm
going to take a log of it.
You know, why would I want to take a log
here.
Well, it turns out that the maximum point
on the likelihood function is
always going to be equal to the maximum
point on the natural log of that function.
So that's a nice thing to know, because it
turns out to
be easier just to deal with the natural
log function than the original likelihood.
So why would I want to take a log,
well it turns out that logs have nice
mathematical properties.
So, remember that the log of a product,
say a times b times c, is the sum of logs.
So if I have a likelihood function that's
a product,
which is usually the case, I have things
multiplied together.
It's nice to take a log here, again any
log, a natural log, or log ten.
It's nice to take a log here, because it
makes it into a sum.
And if you remember way back to calculus,
if it was a while ago for
you, that was easier to take derivatives
of things added together,
than it was to take derivatives of things
multiplied together.
Multiplied things, you had to get into
something called the product rule,
which was a little tricky.
So we're first going to take a look just
to make it easier to take the derivitive.
And the log function has the same maximum
point as the original function.
So next thing we're going to do is to,
we're going to take the derivative,
with respect to p, with respect to the
unknown.
So why are we taking the derivative?
Well, the derivative, remember, is
going to help us to maximize the function.
So if we've got, in this case, our
function is a function of p.
Our likelihood function is a function of
p, so we could graph it like this.
We know that somewhere it has some maximum
point.
We want to find that maximum point.
Where does p make our data the most
likely?
Well, if we take the derivative, that
gives us the slope of the tangent line.
The maximum point is going to occur where
the slope of
the tangent line is equal to zero.
So we're going to take the derivative,
with respect to p, and
then we're gonnaset that derivative equal,
we'll call that y prime,
we're going to set that equal to zero, and
we're going to solve for p.
Because the point at which the derivative
is equal to zero will be the maximum point
of that function.
So that's how we're going to find the p
that makes our data the most likely.
And I've just summarized everything I've
just said on a slide written out in
case you need to see those written out.
Alright, so now going back here, here is
our likelihood function.
This is the function that we want to
maximize.
We want to find the value of p that
maximizes this function, so I'm just
going to walk you through the steps,
applied to this particular function now.
So again, first step we're going to do is
we're going to take a log.
You're going to see why in a minute, and
it's going to be a good day to take logs.
So, if we take the log of this function,
what's going to happen?
Well, remember the log of a product is the
sum of logs.
So this is going to end up being the
natural log.
I'm just going to write K here as, this 10
choose 7 is just a number.
I know when I take the derivative that
constants go away, so
I'm going to save myself time by just
writing log of a constant.
So that was multiplied by this is
multiplied by that, so
we can break this up into, then natural
log of p raised to the seventh.
Plus, again, we're breaking things up into
sums, the natural log of 1 minus p cubed.
Now what's nice also about logs, so again,
we're broke it up into a sum because when
you take the logs, the log of a product is
the sum of logs.
So what's also nice about logs is that the
powers come down in front of the logs,
so hopefully you remember how to deal with
logs.
So we can then realize that we end up with
some constant plus 7
times the natural log of p, plus 3 times
the natural log of 1 minus p.
Okay, so if we apply logs,
we end up with a simpler function where
things are not multiplied together.
Okay.
Step two,
we're going to take the derivative of the
log likelihood function.
So how do I do that?
I'm going to take the derivative for
respect to p or unknown, of the log
likelihood function.
That's this function here.
So I'm just taking the derivative of this
function.
Well, what happens when I take the
derivative of constant, so
the align k is a constant.
The derivative of constant, if you
remember, is just zero.
Alright, now the next term.
The 7 natural log of p.
How do I get the derivative of that
function?
Well the 7 natural log of p, you have to
remember a little bit of calculus here,
the derivative of, of the natural log of x
is 1 over x.
So I've got my 7, my coefficient in front
and then the p goes in
the denominator because the derivative of
the natural log is 1 over that value so
we end up with the derivative and the
natural log of p is one over p.
So I get 7 over p there.
Finally.
For the last term, I'm going to get, again
same idea my coefficient is 3.
I'm not going to write the sign yet
because that's going to change but
my coefficient is 3 and I've got something
natural log of something,
that's going to go on the denominator.
That's the one minus p.
Now, what I just put in the denominator
however is itself a function.
It's one minus p.
So we have to do something called the
chain rule.
This is again making you jog your memory a
little on calculus.
We have to take the derivative of what's
inside those parentheses.
So the derivative of one minus p.
Well, what's the derivative of one minus
p.
The derivative of one is zero.
The derivative of negative p, is just
going to be negative 1.
So we end up with just a, that means we
just ending up with a negative here.
So that's the derivative of the log
likelihood function.
Again, I'm not expecting you to take
derivatives in this class, but
just to follow my logic and hopefully
remember a little bit back to calculus,
and believe that what I've done here is
correct.
So now we've got the derivative function.
We're going to set that equal to zero.
So I am going to say that, that
derivative, is equal to zero Because zer-,
when the derivative is equal to zero,
that's going to be the maximum point.
So I'm going to take the 7 over p minus 3
over 1 minus p.
I'm going to set that equal to zero, and
then I'm just going to solve for p.
So how do I solve for p here?
Well, I can add 3 over 1 minus p to both
sides
of the equation to get rid of the negative
there.
Then I can cross multiply, so we end up
with cross multiplying here, so
we're going to end up with 7 times 1 minus
p is equal to 3p.
I can then distribute the 7 out, it's just
a little algebra.
7 minus 7p, therefore is equal to 3p.
Then I'm going to add 7p to both sides of
the equation, so I get 7 is equal to,
3p plus 7p is 10p, so I get that 7 is
equal to 10p, so
then finally I get that p is equal to 7
divided by 10, while hooray,
it came out to be exactly what we
intuitively want it to be.
We already said that our best guess for p
based on our data should be 0.7.
And indeed when we go through this whole
logic,
of doing the likelihood function and
maximizing it, we get out what we should,
that the best guess for p is 7 10ths.
0.7.
So this is just to kind of help you
hopefully to believe, that the maximum
likelihood estimation works, and it gives
you what you would expect, and hopefully
you can understand sort of the basic logic
of getting to that parameter estimate.
again, I've written out a neat slide
[LAUGH] with the equations just in
case you didn't follow my writing on the
other page.
This is just available for
you if you need to pause the video and go
through the slide that,
the derations on your own with a little
bit of deep writing.
Okay, so again, maximum likelihood
estimation here for
the parameter p is 0.7.
We've managed to prove the obvious but
hopefully it makes you believe in maximum
likelihood estimation.
And of course the point is many times it's
not obvious what your best guess for
the parameters.
Usually our data is very complicated, and
the probability,
the likelihood function of our data is
something extremely complicated, and
we need a computer to solve for the
parameters.
We use maximum likelihood estimation in
logistic regression to estimate, alpha and
the betas.
And I just want to point out, one other
thing here is
that the massive likely estimem-, hood
estimation technique is really cool.
Because, the first derivative, helps us to
find the point estimates,
the actual point estimates for alpha and
beta.
Then, however, if you take the second
derivative, that gets you,
is very directly related to the standard
era, er, error of the alphas and
the betas, to get you the variance of the
standard errors of those point estimates.
And, of course, when we do logistic
regression, we don't,
we don't only need the alpha and the beta
value.
We also need a p value and a confidence
interval to go with those.
That comes out of the standard error.
.
Well, the nice thing is that the standard
error falls right out of
the maximum likelihood estimation
techniques.
So, they kind, they all kind of come with
their own standard error.
I will not go through the math of getting
the variance of the standard error.
We will let the computer do it for us.
But just know that it comes right out of
maximum likelihood estimation.
I want to put one more point with this
simple coin example.
What is the actual value of the likelihood
at its maximum.
So if we take the p that we've estimated
it and we plug it back into the likelihood
function, we can actually calculate the
probability of our data.
So in this case, at the maximum value for
p, the 0.7, if I plug that back into
the likelihood function, so I'm just
plugging in 0.7 wherever we saw p before.
It turns out that we get that the r data a
probability of coming out.
Seven out of ten heads.
That probability was 26.7%.
Now, notice, that's not totally a high
probability.
We could have easily gotten six cents.
We could have easily gotten eight.
But at 0.7, whatever we plug in here for
p, 0.7 gives us the highest value of this
probability.
If I was to plug in 0.65, I would get a
lower probability.
If I was to plug in 0.8, I would get a
So 0.7 gives us the highest probability
for our data, and we can plug back into
the likelihood function to figure out
exactly what that probability is.
Well, we're going to be doing that later
on.
This is a simple example where the
probability of our data,
the value of the likelihood is, is a
reasonable probability.
You'll see that when we, do this, for
really complicated examples,
the probability of our data, that is, that
is most,
highest, probability, might be something
like 1 times 10 to the negative 20th.
There might be a really small probability
just because there's so
many possible different outcomes.
That at it's maximum point the probability
might still be very small.
I'll just warn you that you're going to
see that later.
Then the other thing that we're going to
be
calculating is something called the
negative two log likelihood.
So all this is, is you take that
likelihood value that we just calculated.
And then you take negative two log of it.
It has some uses that we're going to see
later, but just note for
now that when I plug in this probability
and take negative two log of that,
I get a kind of a whole number, and so I'm
taking something that might be
a really small decimal place and turning
it into a nice whole number.
It's easier to deal with.
The negative two log likelihood also has
some other useful mathematical properties
that we'll see soon.