What's interesting about this particular
example,
one of the reasons I like to actually use
this example, is that
the authors made a point of illustrating
something called residual confounding.
And it's very important as we start
talking about statistical adjustment for
confounding, it's really important to keep
in the back of
your mind That adjustment for confounding
is not a panacea.
You cannot adjust away all confounding and
that is kind of well illustrated here.
So, this first regression analysis was
actually included in
the paper just as an illustration of
residual confounding.
What they did,
in that very first regression analysis is
they model age crudely.
They put into their regression as a
predictor you're either younger than 35 or
you're 35 and older.
So they model age as a binary predictor.
When they do that, we are indeed
attenuating the odds ratio.
It's going from 0.8 to 0.87, but we are
not completely wiping out the effect
of confounding by maternal age and that's
illustrated as well by the second
regression analysis because this also
includes age as a binary predictor.
But it also adjusts for
all the other things we're eventually
going to adjust for, race and parity.
What this shows you is that just putting
age in
as a binary predictior does not take away
all of the confounding.
When and the last model, the authors
finally put in
the exact year of maternal age, then, all
of the confounding is removed.
But this is illustrating the point that
when you put in predictors that
are imprecisely measured.
Which is, often times we're not measuring
things precisely,
then there were going to be some leftover
confounding.
Finally, at the end here, they were
actually,
I mean age is one of the things you are
able to measure precisely.
You can get birth dates.
So once they finally put in age as a exact
birth date,
the exact age, then finally they were able
to adjust away for all confounding.
But for most predictors, for
most confounders, we don't measure them
precisely.
And we don't measure the predictors
precisely and
the outcomes precisely in a lot of cases.
So the problem here is that, because
there's error in the various measurements,
statistical adjustment is imperfect, and
that's what we call residual confounding.
And it comes up a lot.
You really cannot completely wipe out
confounding, simply by adjusting for
variables in multiple regression.
Unless you had somehow measured the
variables completely with zero error.
We did it probably in the last example.
Down's syndrome is pretty easy to measure,
to get,
I mean that's it's a very easy one to
measure.
We could probably get a good gauge of
that.
Smoking is relatively easy to measure
although, you know,
there might be some confounding, some
leftover confounding with smoking.
Because it's, we're not going to measure
that, totally precisely.
But age is going to be measured precisely.
So we were able to wipe out most of the
confounding in that example but I'll
just tell you that, residual confounding
comes up a lot with observational studies.
You say oh, I've adjusted for smoking.
I've adjusted for age.
Therefore I've taken care of those.
They're all done with.
They can't be any confounding by those.
But in fact, that's not true.
If you measured your confounders at all
imperfectly, or
if you measured your predictors, your
outcome at all imperfectly,
it's impossible to completely adjust away
all the confounding.
In most cases you end up with some
leftover or residual confounding.
And my favorite example to illustrate that
is, an example that
was in the American archive, the Archives
of Internal Medicine a few years back.
Made a lot of headlines in the news media.
I've shown this table before, I just love
this table as an illustration of why
confounding occurs, and why we have to
worry about confounding.
This was a study that was looking at, I'm
just showing you the men here,
was looking at red meat eating and whether
or not it related to mortality.
And they classified men into different
quintiles of red meat eating,
Q5 being the highest red meat eater.
And I've shown this before, but if you
look carefully at this table, all the,
the risk factors for for, you know, all
the bad health behaviors and
risk factors go up as you go up across the
different quintiles.
So, you go up, your BMI increases.
As you eat more red meat, you, you're more
likely to be a current smoker.
You're less likely to exercise, you're
more likely to eat a lot of calories.
So basically, people who eat a lot of,
especially men here, who eat a lot of red
meat, tend to be risky in many ways.
They have, they just have bad health
habits.
Maybe they're more risk-takers in general.
So this paper was attempting to say,
what is the precise effect of actually
eating red meat with mortality.
And so they said we're going to try to
adjust away for all these [UNKNOWN].
We're going to throw BMI in the model.
We're going to throw smoking in the model.
We're going to throw exercise in the
model.
We're going to try to adjust away for all
those things.
So I'm going to show the, the results of
this from this study.
So this is showing you the mortality
risks.
These are relative risks.
Something called hazard ratios.
This actually came out of Cox regression
and not logistic regression but
Residual compounding applies to all types
of regression.
So what you're seeing here is that for,
let's start with overall mortality.
And actually, let me zoom in a little bit
here so
that it's easier on the small screens to
see this.
So we're going to start with all cause
mortality.
The reference group is the lowest red meat
eaters.
The Q5 is the highest red meat eaters.
And they're show you the risks, the
relative risks, this is called a hazard
ratio, but just like a risk ratio, as you
go up across the different quintile.
So the basic model into adjusted for too
many things and
indeed, you're seeing a nice increase in
mortality as you eating more, red meat.
Then they do an adjusted model.
They're trying to adjust for
all these things that are all different
about heavy red meat eaters.
And what you'll notice is that as we
adjust,
with especially in that last Q5 quintile.
That when you adjust, you started at 1.48,
when you adjust for
all these things, indeed, indeed the,
effect gets attenuated.
It gets closer to one.
So it, it's really, after you adjust for
everything, a 31% increase in your
mortality risk or rate.
And then, but what's interesting here is
you might've just stopped there and
said, okay wow, we adjusted for BMI, we
adjusted for exercise.
You know, the, the others did a great job
adjusting for
everything they possibly could.
This was a nicely done study.
And you might just stop there and say,.
I've adjusted for everything, and it's
still, an elevated risk.
It's still statistically signifigant.
Aha.
Red meat eating is bad for you.
And that's, indeed, what the conclusion of
this study was.
It was widely reported in the media.
What's, interesting, though, is if you
delve in to the specific causes of death.
If you look at cancer mortality.
Okay, cancer mortality elevated,
also elevated in that heavy red meat
eating group.
And again adjusting for the confounding
does tend to make that effect somewhat but
it still remains after adjustment.
1.22 for cancer mortality.
1.27 for cardiovascular disease mortality,
but
here is where it really gets interesting.
So they also put in there mortality from
injuries and sudden death.
They also looked at that, that's a
category of,
of things that people might die from.
So this includes things like gunshot
wounds and car accidents.
Those would probably be the most common.
So whats interesting here [LAUGH] is that
if you look at the risk ratio,
the relative risk here between high red
meat eating compared to
the reference group of low red meat eaters
It's also elevated.
It's this, and the magnitude is almost
identical to the increase in risk for
cardiovascular disease and for cancer.
So that's really interesting, because if
you start to make up a causal story here,
how does red meat eating, heavy red meat
eating.
How does that increase your risk of car
accidents and gun shot wounds?
Well, the, the logical answer to that is
it probably doesn't.
So what we're seeing here,
this 1.26 is almost certainly the result
of residual confounding.
Heavy red meat eaters tend to be people
who have a lot of risky behaviors.
They probably take a lot of chances.
They might own guns and, you know, drive
too fast.
Might drink while driving and
the kinds of things that increase your
things of this type of death.
And notice that when we adjust for
confounding here, there's no change.
So you had 1.24 before adjustment for all
the confounders.
And 1.26 after you adjust.
That's telling you that there's just
something inherently risky about red meat
eaters that we are unable to capture with
the confounders that we've measured here.
And that leads me to believe that the the
relationships detected
here between cancer mortality and
cardiovascular mortality which are about
the same magnitude, 1.27 and 1.22.
that that, those also might be due to
residual confounding.
Heavy red meat eaters just do a lot of
things bad and
that increases their risk of mortality,
but it might not be that
it's because red meat eating per se has a
direct effect on mortality.
All other deaths also, which is sort of a
catch-all category, also is elevated in
a way that makes you suspicious that there
might be residual confounding.
Some people actually wrote letters to the
editor on this particular one
worried about the issue of residual
confounding.
And just to help you recognize when there
might be
residual confounding if you're talking
about a binary predictor, like you know,
you're a high red meat eater or you're
not.
Incomplete adjustment for
confounding can generate spurious relative
risks in the range of 0.6 to 1.6.
So notice the, the relative risk we were
talking about with
the red meat eating example was about 1.2,
1.3, in that range.
So these are small effect sizes.
For the down syndrome example.
The, the effect size was 0.8.
So, those were both within the range of
0.6 to 1.6.
So people, statisticians have done
simulations where they actually
show that residual confounding can cause
spurious associations in that
general relative risk range, 0.6 to 1.6.
In other words, if you see an effect size
of two or three in your data set,
that is usually beyond what residual
confounding can cause.
So residual confounding is kind of limited
in its scope, but
if you pick up a lot of observational
studies, and papers, and the literature.
You will see plenty of risk ratios and
odds ratios that are 1.3, 0.8, 1.2, 4.
These are the, the, when the effect sizes
are these,
this small, this is where you start to
worry that there might be residual
confounding that can completely explain
the association that you're seeing.
I've given you examples here where the
residual, failure to,
to completely perfectly adjust for
confounding, creates spirious association.
however, it can also go in the other
direction.
Residual confounding might also obscure
relationships.
It's causing you to miss associations so
you might end up with a risk ratio of one,
when the true risk rate is 0.8 because of
residual confounding.
Those examples are much more harder to,
find.
They're much harder to uncover.
But they can happen So just keep in mind
that it can go either way.