Well of course I don't think in odds so I
want to go one step further and
translate the odds to a probability.
Well here are the odds the odds is just a
probability divided by
1 minus the probability.
So we can actually solve for p here.
So to solve for p, for example for this
first one.
Then I multiply both sides of my equation
by 1 minus p.
Then I'm going to get that p is equal to
8.33 minus 8.33 p.
I can add that negative, that 8.33 p.
I'm going to add 8.33 repeatable sides of
the equation here [SOUND].
Then I'm going to get 9.33 p is equal to
8.33.
Now to isolate p I'm going to divide both
sides of the equation by 9.33.
A general formula here is, you would do, p
is equal to
the odds [SOUND] divided by 1 plus the
odds.
And when you do that, 8.33 divided by
9.33,
notice, that's always going to be a number
between 0 and 1.
So that's going to give you a probability
that comes out to be 89%.
So the predictive probability for somebody
who does zero hours per week of
homework is they have an 89% of being book
smart.
Less homework, more chance of being book
When you do this for 10 hours per week,
you get 85% is the predictive probability
of being book smart.
For somebody who does 50 hours per week,
they're only, you know, 54% chance.
their predicted probability of being book
smart is only 54%.
Again, none of this is statistically
significant, but just in terms of
the effect sizes here, these would be the
predicted probabilities.
The other thing that is often more useful,
or more commonly used from the logistic
regression law is just to say what's the
relationship between the predictor and
the outcome in this case homework and book
smart.
And as I mentioned earlier the, the beta
coefficient from logistic regression,
what happens is, is if you exponentiate
that beta coefficient from
logistic regression When you exponentiate
that, that gives you an odds ratio.
So we can take this beta for homework here
and
we can exponentiate it and so we can raise
that to point, negative .0389.
When you do that you come out with a value
of 0.96.
So that's the odds ratio here.
I'll show you in a minute why you can
interpret the beta like this.
But what this means is, we have quantified
the relationship between homework
time and your odds of being book smart.
And you would read this odds ratio of 0.96
to say that there is
a 4% decrease in your odds of being book
smart for
every one hour more that you spend on
homework per week.
So, if I just exponentiate that beta the
units here
are one hour of homework per week.
Notice now we've got an odds ratio for
a continuous predictor, you can get that
at a logistic regression.
So now we're talking about the increase in
odds for
a 1 unit increase in the continuous
predictor.
Everything up to now,
when we've done odds ratios, we've been
talking about a binary predictor.
You're either in this group, or you're
not.
But now we can get odds ratios for
continuous predictors.
Well, how does that translate?
How does that beta, become an odds ratio?
Exactly how does that work?
So let me show you that now.
How do we get from beta to odds ratios?
Well, what is an odds ratio?
If I want to know the odds ratio for being
book smart, for the exposure here, which
is more homework time compared to less
homework time, what is the odds ratio?
An odds ratio is a ratio of two odds.
So my odds ratio here would be the odds of
being book smart for somebody who
does more homework, compared with the odds
of being book smart Book smart for
somebody who spends less time on homework.
And if we're just going with units that
I've used here, or
the difference between the numerator and
the denominator, I could make it a one
hour difference in homework time.
So what's my odds ratio for
a one hour change, a one hour increase in
homework time?
How does that affect my odds of being book
smart Well, now I can just fill in,
I fit a model that tells me that predicted
odds of being book smart for
a given homework level.
So I can just plug in that model.
So what's the odds of being book smart for
somebody who does, say,
one hour of homework, compared with
somebody who does zero hours of homework?
The odds, which I can put in the
numerator, so, I fit the model that says,
the log odds is alpha plus beta homework
times the amount of homework.
If I exponentiate that number I get the
odds.
So the odds of being book smart for
somebody who does one hour of homework, I
can put that in the numerator.
I can compare that to the odds of being
book smart for
somebody who does no homework.
So now I made a ratio of two odds, the
odds for somebody who does one hour of
homework, divided by the odds of somebody
who does no homework.
And then we can simplify this a little bit
what you'll notice right away is
a you have to know a little bit about how
exponentials work to
know how I lecture them here to here but
if you have e raised to
a alpha plus beta that's the same as e
raised to alpha times e raised to beta.
Well notice there, they both have the same
intercepts, So
those intercepts we're going to cancel.
That's the nice thing here, those cancel
and if we simplify this.
It just turns out, that we're left with if
e Beta times 1 in the numerator, divided
by e raise to 0 in the denominator, that's
just e raised to Beta Homework.
And so that's.
The odds ratio.
You take the beta from homework, you
exponentiate it, you get the odds ratio.
The actual value for the beta here was
negative .039.
Again, if I exponentiate that, I get an
odds ratio of .96.
So the odds ratio of 0.96 means that for
every one hour increase in
homework per week, your odds of believing
yourself" book smart" decreases by 4%.
Of course, it wasn't significant here.
I want to just extend this logic to show
how not only can we get
odds ratios out of logistic regression, We
can get multivariate adjusted odds ratio.
So just as we made the leap from linear
regression, simple linear regression to
multivariate linear regression, we can do
the same thing with logistic regression.
It's very easy to add additional
predictors to the right side of
the equation.
We can have a bunch of predictors just
like this.
That's our multivariate logistic equation.
And here's some examples.
Imagine, that we did a study where we were
looking at lung cancer.
And let's say for the first logistic
regression model we fit, we put in as
predictors a binary predictor for smoking
and a binary predictor for drinking.
So we looked at smoking, yes or no, and
drinking, yes or no.
Those are two binary variables.
So that's one model we can fit and that's
a simpler model so
I'm going to start there.
The beta for smoking would then represent
the effect of smoking adjusted for
drinking, the beta for
drinking represents the effect of drinking
adjusted for smoking.
We can make it slightly more complicated
by also adding an additional variable,
additional predictor in the model, let's
add also age.
We could then get the effective smoking
adjusted for
both drinking and age, the effect of
drinking adjusted for both smoking and
age, and the effect of age adjusted for
both smoking and drinking.
Let me show you now exactly what I mean by
adjusted for.
When I keep using that term, adjusted for,
what does that really mean?
That means that if I fix everything else
in the model,
it's the isolated effect of smoking, or
the isolated effect of drinking.
So let me show you that mathematically
now, I think it's helpful.
I'm going to start with the binary
predictor,
the model with the 2 binary predictors
because it's simpler.
Again what's an odds ratio?
It's the odds of a disease, say lung
cancer for
an exposed group compared with the odds of
disease for an unexposed group.
If I have just a binary predictor, say,
exposed and unexposed drinker and
nondrinker, smoker and nonsmoker, that's
what an odds ratio is.
My logistic regression model models the
odds of disease for given people.
So I can put in the numerator the odds of
disease for, say, a drinker, and
I could put in the denominator the odds of
Disease lung cancer here for a non drinker
and that's what I've done here so my model
my first model had alcohol and smoking two
binary predictors in it, so if I want to
know the odds ratio for drinking.
Adjusted for smoking, I can just say let
me compare, in the numerator the odds for
a drinker, and in the denominator the odds
for a nondrinker.
So there I put in a 1 for drinking, and a
[INAUDIBLE] in the numerator, and a 0 for
drinking in the denominator.
Now I'm comparing the odds of lung cancer
for a drinker, compared with the odds for
lung cancer with a nondrinker.
Now, I've also got smoking in the model,
so I have to put something in for smoking.
But what if I hold it fixed?
So what if I say I'm only comparing a
drinking smoker to a non-drinking smoker,
so I put in a 1 for smoking for both the
numerator and the denominator.
I hold smoking fixed.
It actually wouldn't matter if I chose to
compare a drinking-non smoker to
a drinking non-smoker.
I just have to hold smoking fixed for both
the numerator and the denominator.
I have to make it the same.
If I make it the same what you can show is
again the intercepts cancel and
now as long as I hold smoking fixed the
the smoking betas cancel.
What am I left Well, if I simplify this,
I just have e raised to beta alcohol, e
raised to zero and the denominator is 1,
so I can show that the odds ratio for
drinking, if I hold smoking fixed,
is I just, all I do is take the beta for
alcohol and exponentiate it.
That gives me the odds ratio for lung
cancer for
a drinker compared to a non-drinker.
And again, where I've held smoking
constant.
Notice, that this will be the odds ratio
for
drinking if I compare two smokers, or if I
compare two non-smokers.
Course so I'm assuming that the effect of
drinking is
the same in smokers and nonsmokers.
I can use the same logic to show you that
this works for
a continuous predictor as well.
So here's a continuous predictor.
For a continuous predictor, I'm going to
be comparing again the odds disease for
someone with a higher level of the
continuous predictor compared to
somebody with the lower level.
For example, image that I've got my second
model here that's got alcohol,
smoking, and age in the model.
Age is a continuous predictor.
If I want to compare in the numerator an
older person,
the odds of lung cancer of an older person
compared with the odds of
smoking of a younger person in the
denominator.
This will give me the odds ratio for an
increase in age.
How much does age affect my odds of lung
cancer?
I'm again going to hold all the other
variables in the models, here, alcohol and
smoking, I'm going to hold those fixed.
So say I have two drinking smokers.
And I'm comparing a drinking smoker who's
29 years old to a drinking smoker who's
only 19 years old.
That's a ten unit jump in age.
And you'll see it wouldn't really matter
if I had put in 40 and 30, or 50 and 40.
Any ten unit jump in age is going to give
me the answer here.
You'll notice that lots of things cancel
out.
That's the great thing here.
So we fix all the other variables.
They all cancel out.
So we're left with, at the beta for age,
in this case if we solve it here.
Beta, e raised to beta times 29, minus e
raised to beta 19,
that's the same as e raised to beta age
times 10,
so what this tells us is that if I
multiply the beta for age, times 10,
and then exponentiate, I will get the odds
ratio for a 10 unit jump in age.
So this would give me, for a 10 unit jump
in age, a decade increase in age,
what's the increase in my odds of getting
lung cancer.
If I wanted to do it for a one unit
increase in age,
I would just take the beta for age and
exponentiate it directly,
that would give me the odds ratio for a
one unit Increase in age.
It doesn't really matter what you pick for
the units of age, but
you want to pick something that's sort of
meaningful a one unit or
ten unit increase is probably reasonable.
That gives you the odds ratio for that
unit jump.
You can see that for
a continuous predictor, the magnitude of
the odds ratio will depend on the units.
It's not going to, what units you choose
will not affect the p value but
it will affect how big or small that odds
ratio looks.
Just keep that in mind.
You always have to get the units in your
table so
people know how to interpret that.
This is the odds ratio for H adjusted, for
smoking and alcohol.
Which means that we've held smoking and
alcohol fixed.
So that is if we're looking at two people
who have the same level of smoking and
alcohol and the only difference between
them is a ten unit difference in age,
this would be the effect of that age.
So just to summarize, the practical
interpretation here is if you
take the beta, the slow from a logistic
regression for any of your exposures,
your predictors, and you exponentiate it
you get the odds ratio for the exposure.
You would interpret that as that is the
increase in the odds of your outcome for
every one unit increase in the exposure,
adjusted for, controlling for,
all the other variables all the other
predictors that are in the model.
And we'll practice looking at an example
of how to use this in the next module.
Just to tell you most computer packages
when you run a logistics regression you
don't actually have to even do the
exponentiation.
Most computer packages will automatically
give you the odds ratio.
So again out of a logistic regression we
get these
multivariate adjusted odds ratios.