In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about Poisson regression,
which is used when your outcome variable
is a count variable,
such as the number of cases of disease
occurring in a particular geographic area
during a particular time period.
Before I can delve into Poisson regression
I first have to
tell you a little bit about the poi,
Poisson probability distribution.
So, this is yet another probability
distribution and remember that
all the probability distribution is, is a
function that sums to 1.
So, if we can numerate all the possible
outcomes here,
their probabilities have to sum to 1.
That's true in the Poisson probability.
It is a discreet probability distribution.
So we can actually talk about specific
outcomes like the probability of
having 0 cases of disease or 1 case of
disease or 2, et cetera.
They're counts.
Like any probability distribution there's
a formula I can give you for
those particular discreet outcomes.
So ,this is the Poisson probability
formula down here.
Mu is just the expected number of
outcomes,
the expected count during a given time
period.
So, we could talk about maybe we're
expecting 10 deaths from
H1N1 flu in a given winter in California.
That would be our expected value then.
We could then calculate the probability
that we're going to end up
with 9 deaths in a given winter or 11 or
10 or 8, et cetera.
We would just be plugging into this
formula.
I'm going to Actually plug some numbers in
with a real example of this formula in
a minute, so I won't delve into the
details of this formula quite yet.
I just want to point out that a Poisson
probability distribution like any
other probability distribution, it has a
mean and a variance.
I won't derive where they come from for
you, but I'll just tell you that again
the mean is just the expected count that's
going to come out in a given time period.
For a Poisson distribution what's really
interesting is that the mean and
the variance are equal.
If we're really got a Poisson
distribution,
that will be true that the mean and the
variance will be equal.
That means the standard deviation will be
the square root of the mean.
So, if we are expecting 10 cases of
disease in a given winter in
California then the variance for
that if we are really on a Poisson
distribution would also be 10.
It's easiest to illustrate a Poisson
distribution by just kind of showing you
an example with actually numbers.
So, let's do that now.
So, let's imagine that in a particular
population this might be
like college students.
The number of alcohol binging episodes in
a month
follows a Poisson distribution with a mean
of 4.
So, in this population on average, people
are binging about 4 times a month.
So, what's the probability, that a random
person will have 0 episodes,1 episodes,
2 episodes, 3 episodes, etc?
We can calculate the probability.
So we're somehow, assuming that there's a
constant rate here, and
that everybody in the population on
average is having about 4 per month.
So we can, this is a count, distribution.
And if we're really on a Poisson, then we
can calculate the Poisson probability for
each of these cases.
This.
So
what does the Poisson Probability looks
like?
They're the probability that a, kind of a
random person will have 0 episodes in
a given month is going to be equal to.
And then we just apply the Poisson
probability function.
Which is, you take the mean, you raise it
to the number of events,
the count that you're trying to calculate
the probability for.
Then you take e, neg raise to negative the
mean, which in this case is 4, and
then you do the count factorial in the
denominator.
So in this case, we're trying to calculate
the probability of 0 events.
So 4 raised to 0 here is one.
0 factorial is also 1.
So this is just going to be e raised to
negative 4,
which turns out to be a value of 0.018.
So there's only about a 1 to 2% chance
that a person's going to have no.
Binging episodes in a month.
What's the probability that x is going to
equal 1?
So we again, we're going to apply the
formula so that's going to be 4,
the mean raised to 1 e raised to the
negative 4 divided by 1 factorial.
And, therefore we're going to have,
that comes out to be a value of about 7%
of those 7% chance of having 1 episode in
the month let me just actually plug into
the formula one more tie to show you,
so for probability of having binging
episodes,
its going to be 4 raised to 2, e raised to
negative 4, divided by 2 factorial.
That comes out to be about 14.65% and then
you kind of get the pattern here.
I went through and calculated the rest of
these.
So ,there's about a 95.5% chance of 3
episodes.
19.5% chance of 4 episodes as the most
likely outcome.
15% chance of 5 episodes, 10% chance of 6
episodes, 5.95% chance of 7 episodes and
if you kept going you would see that the
probabilities are going to get smaller and
smaller and smaller as we get away from
the mean.
If I were to add up all of these
probabilities up in to
the point where the probabilities get
ravishingly small They'll be almost what.
Of course theoretically we can go up to a
hundred episodes but by the time it
gets to a hundred, the probability would
be so small that essentially if
we add up all the probabilities it's
going to be almost, almost that one.
So that's just how the probab, the Poisson
probability.
Distribution works.
Just like for the binomial probability
distribution, I can talk about
the probability of a specific outcome, the
specific number of counts.
And, that's what we are going to be
taking.
We are going to take those Poisson
probabilities, we are going to using those
in the likelihood function rather than the
binomial probabilities.