So now I'm going to give you some details
about how we
actually build the propensity score model.
So here's the logistic regression model
that they used in example 1.
So the outcome here was the Ross
procedure.
If you didn't get the Ross procedure you
got the mechanical valve.
They put into the model 23 predictors, 23
things that they thought would
predict whether or not you were going to
get one treatment or the other.
So things like age, valve disease, gender,
coronary artery bypass, et cetera.
Notice that they're sticking an awful lot
of things in the model.
So one of the things that's different
about propensity score modeling
from the other types of model building
we've talked about is that you're going to
actually try to overfit your model, try to
stuff in as many things as you can,
to get the best fit possible to your
sample.
We want to balance the groups with respect
to all of these different covariates.
For example, two of the propensity score
model against the logistic regression
model, they were predicting whether or not
you got rehabilitation.
They put all sorts of things in their
model.
Actually, 112 predictors.
So, again, we're really going to stuff the
model in the case of
propensity score modeling.
So here are the actual steps of building a
propensity score model.
So, first of all, of course, you're going
to identify potential confounders.
Confounders have to be related both to the
treatment and the outcome.
So if there are variables that are clearly
totally unrelated to either
the treatment or the outcome, it may not
be worth using them.
We're going to be liberal about this, or
in other words, we're going to only take
it out of
the set if it's really clearly not a
treatment or, related to the treatment.
If it's even a little related, we're
probably going to include it in our model.
We're going to then need to impute missing
data for reason we've talked about.
We're going to be building a
non-parsimonious model.
So this is very different than other model
building situations where we're
usually trying to be parsimonious.
Here we're going to just stuff in
everything, maybe putting quadratics,
interaction terms, higher order terms.
We're going to try to really stuff the
model, we're,
we really want to fit our model to our
sample as closely as possible.
That's going to get us the best balance of
covariates in the two
different treatment groups.
Then we're going to take the propensity
scores and
we're going to stratify or, match on the
resulting scores.
And we're going to come up with now,
comparing apples and apples.
So we're going to be now comparing only
people who are in quintile one to people
who are in quintile one, for example, or
we're going to have a matched cohort where
every Ross patient has been matched to a
mechanical valve patient.
So our groups are now comparable, and we
want to assess whether or not those
covariates that we put in the regression
model, whether or not those are balanced.
Hopefully they'll be reasonably balanced.
I'll show you an example in a minute.
If the balance isn't great, we're going to
go back and
actually try to refit the model, stuffing
more things in the model,
other additional confounders, higher-order
terms to get a better fit.
To get better balance and
just to say again what I've said already
about missing data.
After an individual is missing one data
point for one variable, they're going to
be omitted from that logistic regression
model, so it's going to be
very important to impute missing data
before doing propensity scores.
So for example, in the rehabilitation
study,
they put 112 predictors in their models.
Now, only seven of those variables were
missing values.
But each one of those was missing values
for
anywhere between 0.5 to 5.5% of the data
set.
Well, if your one variable's missing 5%,
another variable's missing 2%, and
another variable's missing 1%, over seven
variables if different people
are missing values on different variables,
that can really add up.
So a lot of the sample, could be 15% of
the sample,
would get dumped if you didn't fill those
in.
So you just have to fill them in, at least
with something.
All of our normal rules of
model building aren't going to apply to
propensity scores.
We're not going to worry about parsimony,
as I said.
We're not going to worry about
overfitting.
We're going to try all sort of
interactions and quadratic terms.
We're not worried about chance findings,
here, because we don't care.
We're not going to be using the betas from
those logistic regression model
for anything.
We're just purely trying to compress the
data into a probability.
The one thing that people have found
actually can improve your model fit
here can, you can do a little better if
you omit variables that
are actually totally unrelated to the
outcomes.
And I'd recommend saying like, if your p
value between the potential confounder and
the outcome is greater than 0.2, maybe
don't bother putting it in the model.
The reason is that statisticians have
shown in simulation studies that
including these doesn't benefit you at all
in terms of balancing the covariates or
reducing bias, but it does sometimes make
it harder to find matches if you're
trying to do matching of the propensity
score.
So there may be some advantage to not
bothering with those.
So how do we evaluate whether or not we've
done well with the model?
It's a success if it balances the
treatment groups with
respect to covariates, the covariates
we've measured.
If it, the balance, again,
is not achieved, we're going to have to
refit the model.
So here's an example of how to evaluate
the balance.
We're going to actually look at effect
sizes rather than any p-value tests, So
that if you think about the way people
look at balance and randomized trials,
they usually take the baseline variables
and they line them up between the groups.
And they do some kind of p-value tests.
And they say, oh well, as long as the
p-value is,
you know, not significant, then we're
balanced.
We're not going to want to use a p-value
test here for several reasons.
P-values are highly dependent on sample
size, and
just because a p-value is non-significant
doesn't indicate,
doesn't guarantee that the groups are
necessarily balanced.
You could still have a fairly big
difference in terms of the di,
big, affect size but even if the P-value
doesn't come out to be significant.
So we're going to rely on a,
an effect size comparison, rather than a
p-value comparison.
What we're going to do is, we're going to
compare the difference between the two
groups, the mean difference between the
two groups on every variable of interest.
We're going to standardize it so it's in
standard deviation units.
It's a little bit easier to compare across
different variables.
We're looking for standardized differences
that are less than 10%,
so that the groups differ, by less than
10% of a standard deviation.
That would be considered reasonable
balance.
How do we actually calculate the
standardized difference?
All it is is we take the mean in one
group,
subtract it from the mean in the other
group, that's the mean difference.
And then we put it in standard deviation
units by dividing by
the standard deviation for that variable.
Since we have standard deviations for
both groups, we're just going to take an
average of the standard deviations.
So just to give an example, in the Ross
study, the mean age for
the Ross patients was 41.6.
The standard deviation was 11.
The mean age for the mechanical valve
patients was 49.
The standard deviation was 10.
We average the standard deviations from
the two groups to come up with an average
standard deviation of 10.65, so therefore
the standardized difference
would be 49.5 minus 41.6, about eight
years of difference.
The standard deviation for age is about
10.
So you can see that they're not quite a
full standard deviation away from
each other, and then we typically will
actually multiply this by 100, so
that we can get it in a percentage.
It's just easier to deal with whole
numbers.
So this turns out be a value of 75%.
So the standardized difference here is
75%, meaning that there is,
a difference between the groups of 75% or
three-quarters of a standard deviation.
And this particular study actually has a
really nice graphic that
illustrates looking for balance between
the groups.
So what you're seeing here is the absolute
standardized differences,
these percentages, percent of a
standard-deviation difference between
the groups are on the x-axis.
And all these different covariates that we
want to balance are on the y-axis.
The filled-in circles represent before we
did the propensity score matching.
The open circles, or open ovals, represent
after the matching.
So before a propensity score matching,
you can see that a lot of variables had
very big differences between the groups.
We already saw that when we looked at
table one.
What they did then was to calculate the
propensities for
us, and they did one-to-one matching.
So they would, for every Ross patient who
had a propensity score of 0.5,
they would try to go out and
find a mechanical valve patient who had a
propensity score around 0.5.
And they were able to find matches for
some of the patients in the original
cohort, but not all, so
the matched cohort is actually smaller
than the original unmatched cohort.
When they compare all of these different
variables between the two
treatment groups after matching,
you'll notice that all of these
standardized differences were below 10%.
That's what we want.
That's good balance.
Now we can also use the propensity scores
just to
help us get a sense of who can be compared
and
who, some of the patients in our, study
may just not have a good comparator.
So for example on the raw study they
couldn't find matches for everybody.
That means that there were just some
patients who,
every doctor would give a Ross procedure
to, and there were some patients who just,
every doctor would give a mechanical valve
to.
In other words there really wasn't any
uncertainty for
those patients to begin with, so we really
don't need to say anything, though.
Those patients are going to get one
treatment or
the other all the time anyway.
We don't really need to figure out which
treatment to give them.
So this is just illustrated here.
A really good thing to do is actually to
plot the distribution of
the propensity scores in your different
groups.
So imagine, this is just a made up graph,
but
imagine we've got, a group of treated
subjects.
Then we calculate their propensity scores.
These are the ones that we know actually
did get the treatment, so
not surprisingly they have higher
propensity scores.
The propensity scores for the untreated
group are given with the dotted line here.
So you can see that the distributions do
overlap.
There are some people that are comparable,
but some parts of the distributions do not
overlap.
So, there is a point at which none of the
untreated people got propensity
scores higher than a value of around, that
looks like around 0.75 or 0.8.
Above that propensity score, there were
nobody,
there was nobody in the untreated group
who got a propensity score that high.
That means there's a certain group of
patients that are always going to
get treated no matter what.
And, similarly, on the other side here
there was, among the treated group,
there was nobody who had a propensity
score less than, looks like about 0.25.
So there's just a group of patients who
are never going to get this treatment.
We can't compare them.
We have to drop them out of the rest of
the analysis, and
they're just going to be excluded.
after, if you look inside here,
you'll notice that there are equal, there
are comparators.
So, for example, here, there was at least
one person who you can compare that had
got the same propensity score.
So we can do matching or stratification
there, but
some patients have to be excluded.
That happened in the raw study.
There were people who couldn't be
compared, and they were just dropped.
This is kind of showing the same thing
with a different example,
some real data from real paper.
So, there was, they were wanting to
compare diuretics to no diuretics.
They calculated the propensity scores, the
propensity that you,
the likelihood that you would get
diuretics.
The, you can see that those who did get
diuretics, not surprisingly,
had higher propensity scores.
Those who didn't get diuretics had lower
propensity scores.
There's places where there's no overlap,
so nobody who's in
the untreated group got propensity scores
higher than a certain amount.
These we can't find matches for.
They're going to have to be excluded.
And similarly, among the untreated group,
there were some who had
propensity scores that were so low that
there's no overlap with the treated group.
Those people will be excluded as well.
Then, where there's overlap, we can
develop a matched cohort.
So among the matched cohort,
we're going to find for every no-diuretics
patient, we're going to find a patient who
got diuretics who has the same propensity
score, and that's, those will
become a matched pair in our data set and
taken forth for further analysis.
And finally, you may end up with a
situation where there
is really no overlap and that's
informative too.
If you plot the distributions of the
propensity scores in the two groups, so
here, it's showing, males versus females,
you may end up with so
little overlap that it actually tells you
that we just have, there's, men and
women are just too different here.
We cannot make meaningful comparisons, and
the analysis would stop there.
But that's useful.
That's a useful insight to know that women
are always treated in one way and
men are always treated in the other way,
and there's no overlap.
Therefore we can't compare them.