In this next module, I'm going to walk
through a real example,
just to practice how to interpret the
results of logistic regression.
So I'm going to use a real example from
the medical literature.
This was a case control study that was
done physicians,
who graduated from medical school at UCSF.
What they were looking for, the outcome
they were interested in,
was being disciplined by the Medical Board
of California.
So if a physician gets disciplined by the
medical board,
that's a, a pretty bad thing, so those are
the cases.
They identified 60 physicians who had a
disciplinary action.
Between 1990 and 2000.
Who had graduated from USCF.
Those are the cases and our outcome
variable here is that disciplining,
from the medical board of California.
It's a case control study so
the, the researchers found those people
who had been disciplined.
There's, you know, there, it's fairly
rare, so
they zoned in on them by picking those in
particular.
Then they found controls.
The controls were graduates 196 controls,
who were matched by medical school
graduation year, so
they were the, the same graduating class,
and speciality choice.
So each, for each case, the, they went out
and
found a couple of controls who came from
the same graduating class.
And were from the same specialty choice.
The aim of the study, I'm just quoting
from the paper here, was to determine if
medical students who demonstrate
unprofessional behavior in medical school
are more likely to have subsequent state
board disciplinary action.
So they were going back into the records
of these graduates and
trying to determine if there were things
that could predict subsequent disciplinary
action by the medical board in, in
particular.
They wanted to see if there was some
unprofessional behavior in medical school
that could flag those who were at risk of
this outcome.
It's a binary outcome.
You we're either disiplined are you
weren't.
What kind of analysis are we going to
analyze we're going to use to
analyze these data we could look at our
little chart here we've got
a binary outcome you were disciplined by
the medical board of California or not.
It's a case control study so the, the
outcome is case or control.
We want to do some kind of regression
analysis because it's an observational
study we want to be able to control for
confounder.
That might lead you to think, oh,
I should pick logistic regression and in
fact the authors of
this study did indeed use just a plain old
logistic regression analysis.
I want to just point out here though if
you look closely at this study,
the observations are not independent.
They are correlated.
This was a matched case control study.
Each case was matched to a couple of
controls.
So actually we should be using here the
logistic regression for
correlated data, which is something called
conditional logistic regression.
That accounts for the correlation.
So that's actually the proper statistical
technique that should of been used here.
It would still give odds ratios and in
this case I'm not sure it would of
made a huge difference to the results of
this study.
but, it's correlated data so
that would of actually been the
appropriate statistical test to use.
What's the consequence here that the
others used logistic regression instead of
conditional logistic regression,
we have a situation where we are comparing
within groups.
Remember when we talked about correlated
data, I told you that if you ignore
the correlation when you're doing a within
group comparison,
that your peelers are going to be too
high.
That means you might miss an effect by not
analyzing the data correctly.
So here what you should do is compare each
case to their matched controls.
Cases, those, those case control groups
are more similar to
each other than to other people in the
study.
If you account for that correlation, you
actually would have gotten probably here
a little bit better P-values than what the
others got.
So their analysis could be described as a
little conservative.
Anything that came out significant we're
pretty sure that's real.
But it could have been that those P values
could of come out more significant.
And some of the things that didn't come
out significant,
in the correct analysis might have.
So this is a conservative analysis by
ignoring that correlation.
I just want to point that out,
to remind you the importance of thinking
about correlation.
In any case, the authors used a regular
old logistic regression.
And again these results might be a little
conservative,
we might have missed something here, as a
result.
But we can look at the odds ratios that
logistic regression model and
just I want to walk you through how you'd
interpret this table.
So this is table five from the paper.
This is the results of the logistic
regression analysis.
Notice that they're not presenting any
betas they're just simply going right for
the odds ratios.
They're not presenting any intercepts, we
don't need all of that for
this particular example.
We only care about the odds ratios.
So just, they're just presenting directly
the odds ratios,
the confidence intervals for those odds
ratios, and the p values.
I now want to walk you through what each
of these odds ratios means.
How do we interpret it?
So the first predictor you'll notice here
is male gender.
So the odds ratio here is 1.51.
Now, this is a fairly rare outcome.
So we can interpret the odds ratios like
risk ratios and
there's not going to be any, much
distortion of the effect here.
So the odds ratio is 1.51 for males.
It's not statistically significant, so
we're not sure that it's any different
than one.
We would say that there's a 50% increase
in the odds of disciplinary action for
men versus women, but it's not
statistically significant.
So, this model includes all the things
that you see in table, so
once you adjust for all of these other
factors,
the effect of male being male is not
statistically significant.
The next variable is undergraduate GPA.
This is a continuous predictor.
It ranges from zero to 4.0.
So the way that you interpret this odds
ratio.
First of all, we notice that undergraduate
GPA is protective.
So as your GPA goes up a whole unit.
So this is for a one unit increase in GPA.
That's pretty big.
That's like going from three to four, or
two to three.
A one unit jump in your GPA will decrease
your odds of disciplinary action by 43%.
But, it's also not statistically
significant.
So once you've accounted for all the other
things that, all the other variables you
you see in this table, the effect of
undergraduate GPA is not significant.
It doesn't appear to be an independent
predictor,
although it trends in the direction of
being protective here.
Interesting, the MCAT score, so the way
they measured MCAT score here,
it's this is comparing those who are in
the lowest quartile
of MCAT score to those who are in the
higher three quartiles.
So this is a binary variable here.
If you're in the lowest quartile compared
to the others, your odds ratio was 1.01.
So, after accounting for
all these other things in the table,
there's really no effect of MCAT score.
Interestingly enough, MCAT score was not
an independent predictor at all here.
The p value, as you can see, is very, very
high.
If you, another binary variable if you did
not pass
if you failed in other words if you fail
any of your courses in medical school your
odds ratio was 1.30 so a 30% increase in
your odds of disciplinary action, although
again that's clearly not statistically
significant, so that's very close to one.
Not an independent predictor, but in the
direction of increasing your risk.
Finally, if you had displayed
unprofessional behavior in
medical school severe enough to meet this,
their criteria, if they,
if you had displayed this unprofessional
behavior in medical school,
which they think might be a flag for later
disciplinary action.
This was the only significant predictor
after adjusting for
everything else in the model.
So that doubled your odds of getting
disciplinary action.
And in this case, because the outcome is
fairly rare.
If you said it doubled your risk of having
disciplinary action,
that would actually be very close.
So, that was the only independent
predictor, after adjusting for
everything else in the model.