Now let's go through a real example in
more detail with some real data.
So this is an example that involves time
to conception in women who want to
get pregnant.
So just to show you that we don't always
have to have bad outcomes in
survival analysis.
Failure here.
Failing to survive is a good thing.
You, these women want to get pregnant.
So this was some data on 38 women who got,
who all received the same treatment for
infer, infertility.
So there's only one group here.
And the researchers followed them for up
to two years.
To mark the time to conception.
And, again, the event is conception.
I'm going to say that the women survived
pregnancy free until they conceived.
But of course, again, they, they want to
fail here.
They want to su, to, to get pregnant.
This, this data set is nice and easy to
work with.
Because women can only get pregnant once a
month.
So the time here is just in months.
And everybody has one opportunity to get
pregnant one time per month.
So here's actually the raw data.
The reason I chose this example,
is somebody had actually published the raw
data.
They're nice and simple.
We can look at the raw data and see how it
translates to a Kaplan-Meier curve.
Let me just show you the full
corresponding Kaplan-Meier curve for
these data.
So here is the Kaplan-Meier curve for
the data that I just showed you, already
drawn out.
I'm going to walk you through where it
comes from in a minute.
Just note that this is a step wise curve,
that has nine steps to it.
There are nine unique event times.
Nine unique months in which women got
pregnant.
So we're going to drop the curve nine
times, for those nine event times.
If no pregnancies happened in a given
month,
we don't drop the curve in that month.
Alright.
So how do we translate this into
Kaplan-Meier estimates?
So, starting with what happens in month
one.
So, in month one, six women conceived.
There were 38 women at risk of conceiving
in month one, who were in the study.
Six of them conceived.
So 6 out of 38 get pregnant.
Which means that 32 out of 38 survive that
first month pregnancy free.
And we can represent that on the curve
here.
So, sorry, this is just what I just said.
Six women conceived in the first month,
32 out of 38 survived pregnancy free past
the first month.
So we're going to drop the curve down to
32 out of 38,
because this is the survival probability.
32 out of 38 made it past the first month
pregnancy free.
Of course they, they don't want to.
The outcome here is something that they
actually want to happen.
Now we can also say, well, what percent of
women got pregnant in a, a given month?
So in month one, there were 6 out of 38
who got pregnant, so 15.8% got pregnant.
We're going to call that something called
a hazard rate,
which we're going to return to in some
future modules.
So I'll just point out that the hazard
rate for month one here was 15.8%.
The survival probability is about 84%.
Alright, what happened next?
So, the next thing that happened in our
dataset,
is that at, in the second cycle, the
second month, five women conceived.
And nobody is censored yet.
There's one woman in the censoring list
who has a value of 2.
But just understand that the way these
data were set up,
when we say she censored at two months.
What we mean by that,
is that she made it through two cycles,
two months, pregnancy free.
And at the last time we saw her she, she
was not pregnant.
But she's going to contribute two months
to the study.
So the, we know that she didn't get
pregnant in that second month.
That's just the way the data are coded
here.
So that means we won't have, the censoring
won't occur until after the pregnancies.
So now, what happened in the second month?
Five women conceived.
There were 32 women at risk.
Because we lost six in the first month who
got pregnant.
So 27 out of 32 did not get pregnant.
So they survived the second interval, the
second month, pregnancy free.
So the chances of surviving that second
interval pregnancy free,
if you started the interval, were 84.4%.
To get the cumulative probability of
surviving past two months.
We have to multiply, the probability from
the first interval times
the probability from the second interval.
So now the curve is dropped down here to
about 71%.
So 71% are going to be pregnancy free at
the end of two months.
About 30% would, would conceive in the
first two months.
Now the hazard rate for the second month.
If you make it to month two pregnancy
free.
If you don't get pregnant in the first
month,
what's your chance of getting pregnant in
the next month?
Its actually pretty similar to the first
month.
5 out of 32 got pregnant in month two.
And so the hazard rate here, what were
going to call the hazard rate is 15.6%.
I'll just kind of kind of want to point
out the hazard rates,
because were going to return to those up
in a future module.
So, pretty constant rate of getting
pregnant here.
Alright.
What happens next?
So, in the third month, three women get
pregnant.
One woman, this woman, gets censored right
after the second month.
So she's gone out of the risk set.
She's no longer at risk of getting
pregnant, we've lost her.
So the risk set, the the number of women
who could get pregnant in,
in the third cycle at, in month three, is
only 26 women.
Out of those 26 women, three get pregnant.
23 out of 26 don't get pregnant.
These, they're, they survive the third
month pregnancy-free.
To get the cumulative probability of
survive, surviving past three months,
we multiply the first three intervals
together.
So now the curve is down to 62.8%.
So that's saying that your chances of
surviving past
three months pregnancy-free, our estimate
of that is 62.8%.
I'll just point out the hazard rate for
the third month was 3 out of 26.
26 were at risk of getting pregnant, 3
did.
So the hazard rate here is just slightly
smaller than the,
the first two months, it's 11.5%.
And we can keep going.
So now if we go to the fourth month,
there's now two women who have been
censored.
So they're dropped out, and
then of course all these other women have
gotten pregnant.
So we're down to 22 women, 3 women out of
those 22 get pregnant.
So 19 do not get pregnant.
So 19 out of 22 survive the fourth month
pregnancy free.
So we add that to our cumulative
probability here.
That means our curve is going to drop
down.
If you multiply all of these together our
curve drops down here to 54%,
you can see that on the Kaplan-Meier curve
here.
The hazard rate for the fourth month.
For month four, turned out to be 13.6%.
3 out of 22 did get pregnant.
So that's the hazard rate for the fourth
month.
And we can keep going here.
So at six months no, notice that nobody
got pregnant in month five.
On the pregnancy side there's, there's
nobody at month five.
So we're just going to draw the curve past
month five.
We're not going to draw up the curve again
until we get to month six.
At month six, how many woman are still at
risk?
Well, now we've censored three women.
So we're down to 18 women who are at risk
of getting pregnant.
In our study at month six, 2 got pregnant
and 16 did not.
So the chances of surviving that interval,
pregnancy free was 16 out of 18.
So we're going to add that and multiply
that into our cumulative probability here.
Our cumulative probability at four months
was 54.2%.
We can just multiply that to the
probability for month six.
We get that our, now our total probability
of surviving past six months
pregnancy free is about 42%.
So the way you could use these data,
is you could say to a woman who is getting
this procedure.
Well, we expect about 60% of women to get
pregnant in the first six
months after having this procedure, and
about 40% to not get pregnant.
To, to survive six months pregnancy free,
to use,
again, the language of survival analysis.
And we can keep going here.
I, I decided that I didn't need to go
through ev, walk you through every step.
I think you get the idea.
By the way, the little stars here are
indicating where women are censored.
That's what those stars are.
And, I'm just going to drop ahead, skip
ahead a little bit here.
So we were at six months.
I'm going to skip ahead to 13 months.
Which is the second to last event time, in
which pregnancies actually occurred.
By the time we get down to 13 months now,
there's only 22% of women who wouldn't be
pregnant, or pregnant by then.
And, then let me just do the very last
event time.
So, were're at 22% at 13 months.
The very last, after 13 months, there's
one more pregnancy.
There's one woman who gets pregnant in the
16th month of the study.
At 16 months, there's a lot of women
who've been censored.
A lot of women whom are pregnant.
So there's actually only two remaining at
16 months.
On this side, there's three total women
who are at risk of getting pregnant.
At 16 months, one gets pregnant, two
don't.
So that interval,
the probability of surviving that interval
pregnancy free is 2 3rds.
We multiply that to the cumulative
probability from before, 22%.
We drop our curve down to 15%.
And then the last two women are censored.
They never get pregnant during the time
point of the, course of the study.
So we just draw the curve all the way
over.
And that represented here.
So that is our Kaplan-Meier estimate of
the survival curve.
I'll just point out to you, that if you
look at the end of the curve.
Notice that by the end of the curve, we
only have three women at risk.
And when you have three women at risk and
one gets pregnant.
We're now multiplying this curve, this
22%, by 2 3rds.
So the curve drops quite a bit here,
even though this represents only a single
woman getting pregnant.
What you'll notice at the end of
Kaplan-Meier curves is,
you end up, usually, with not too many
women or people left.
And so the estimates can get very wiggly,
right?
There's a lot of potential for variability
when you have only a few people.
So just be cautious about interpreting the
end of Kaplan-Meier curves.
Because often the sample size is pretty
small by then.
And you know, things may jump around that
don't represent anything real.
It just represents noise.
So what you get out of the computer is you
get this picture of this
Kaplan-Meier curve.
You'll get the picture.
You will also get the estimates of the,
the actual specific values of
these survival probabilities at every
event time.
In SAS the output looks something like
this.
So the estimate of probability of
surviving pass month one,
that's equal to 84%.
You can get the, the actual specific value
here.
Sometimes on the graphic it's hard to get
the specific values.
And for two months the survival
probability was 71%.
At three months it was 62% and so on.
It's also giving you the probability, the
failure probability.
Which is just 1 minus the survival
probability.
And survival curves do come with some
standard errors.
So it is possible to put confidence
intervals around them,
although that sometimes makes the graphic
kind of messy.
SAS also tells you the number who have
failed.
And the number remaining at risk, at each
time point.
So you can get all of that output out of
your computer program as well.