[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to review
the concepts of incidence rates and
rate ratios.
So if you have time-to-event outcome data.
The most basic statistic that you can
calculate is the incidence rate,
which just gives you the average rate of
events over the time period of the study.
You can also compare incidence rates
between different groups
with something like a rate ratio.
Just as an example,
here's some data on 38 women who were
having trouble with fertility.
They were all given a treatment, and then
the researchers followed them for
about two years To see which women got
pregnant or did not.
Everybody got the same treatment so
there's really only one group here.
The left column here shows all the women
who got pregnant,
shows which month into the study they get,
got pregnant.
Remember, women can only get pregnant once
a month.
So the unit of time here is months.
On, on the right hand column, these are
the women who are censored that is that
they did not conceive as long as they were
followed in the study.
To calculate the incidence rate here for
pregnancy then.
The denominator for the incidence rate is
the total person-years of follow up.
Or in this case, I'm going to use the
units of women-months of follow up,
because we are talking about every month
there being an opportunity for pregnancy.
So the denominator here is just the
women-months of follow up.
How many months total did women contribute
to the study?
That is, before they got pregnant, or Or
up until the time that they were censored.
To calculate this is very simple,
we're just going to add up all of the
months that you see in this table.
So one plus one plus one plus one plus one
plus one,
because these first six women all got
pregnant in month one, so
they only contributed one month to the
study before getting pregnant.
So we add that up, we get six plus two
plus two, and so on.
We're just going to literally add these
two columns of numbers When I
do that addition,
I come out with that there were 240 women
months of followup in this study.
That's the denominator.
The numerator here is just going to be the
total number of events that occurred.
How many women got pregnant?
Well, we just say how many women are in
this first left hand column here?
There are 25 women who got pregnant out of
38.
So we had 25 pregnancies out of 240 women
months of
followup That turns out to be an average
pregnancy rate of about 10.4%.
So every month there was about a 10.4%
chance of getting pregnant.
That's just summarizing the little table
here.
Again, the denominator is the women.
Month of follow up there were 25
pregnancies I divide those to get that
the rate of pregnancy was about 10.4% per
month.
And we can convert that into a more whole
number it's a little bit easier.
For people to deal with whole numbers, so
oftentimes what we'll do is multiply by
say a hundred and talk about the events
per 100 women months for example.
So that just makes it a little bit easier
to understand, so if we were to
follow a hundred women for, one month, we
would expect about 10.4 pregnancies.
So that's the incidence rate for pregnancy
for that study.
Just another example to bring in an exam,
an example that has two groups so
we can compare groups.
These are data from a randomized trial.
They were 44 patients with chronic active
hepatitis.
They were randomized to receive a certain,
or to be in a control, and
not receive any treatment.
The outcome here was time to death.
The data represented a little bit
differently in this table, the left hand
column represents the treated group, there
were 22 in that group.
Everyone who is starred, that means that
they were censored, so
the last time we saw them they had not yet
died.
So, for example, this 56 represents
somebody who was in the study for
56 months, the units here are months,
56 months They were alive the last time we
saw, saw them.
But, for some reason they were lost to
follow-up.
So the ones that do not have a star
actually are, represent deaths.
We can calculate incidence rates for each
of these groups.
To do so
I'm simply going to add up the total
number of months in each of these columns.
So when I do that for the steroid group,
I get a value of 2410 months.
I then wanted to convert that to years, so
I just converted the months to years,
so that's 200.8 years of follow up,
person-years of follow-up.
In the control group, there were,
if we just add up the numbers in this
column, there were 1424 months.
Quite a bit less because, actually,
the control group, group died a lot more
quickly.
And if we convert that to years, that is
118.7 years of follow-up.
And then you can just count up the number
who died in each group.
Again, those are the ones that are not
starred years, so if you count them up in
the steroid group there were 11 deaths and
in the control group there were 16 deaths.
Just addition here.
We can then divide those to get incidence
rates in each groups, I've, I've
done that put the, all this information in
a chart and done the division here.
So 11 divided by 200.8 person-years of
follow up in the steroid group
gives us a rate of 0.055, this is in years
so
about 5.5 percent, of the people are
expected to die each year.
Again, it's nicer to kind of translate
that to a whole number so
we multipied by 100.
There were 5.5 deaths per 100 person years
in the steroid group.
In the control group, we divided the 16
deaths
by the 118.7 person years of follow up So
the rate was much higher, 13.5%,
of people were dying every year in the
control group.
So 13.5 events per 100 person years, a
much higher rate.
We can then formally compare those
incidence rates and
the simplest thing to do of course, is
just to say well the rates
are 13.5 events per 100 person years in
the control group.
Versus 5.5 in the steroid group.
We can just subtract those.
That's called an absolute rate difference.
And it turns out that we can say that
there are eight excess deaths
in the control group per 100 person-years.
Another way to say that is if we were to
treat 100 people with steroids,
we would prevent eight deaths per year,
per person year.
I should say.
And that's the absolute rate difference.
What's more commonly reported, however, is
people like to Make ratios of things,
as the relative risk, which is the, to
make a ratio of the two rates.
So, we could also divide the rate in the
control group by the rate in
the steroid group.
And then you would say that the rate ratio
is 2.45,
meaning there is about a 2.45 fold
increase in
the mortality rate in the control group
compared with the treated group.
Finally, just one last example.
This is That survival curve from 1669 that
I've already shown you.
Just out of curiosity, I wanted to figure
out,
well what's roughly the rate of death back
in 1669 for these data.
I don't have all of the data points.
I just have the curve.
So I did a rough estimation from the curve
kind of taking the,
the mid point, of the ranges that are
shown here.
I got that there was about maybe a total
of 1781,
Person years represented here you know
everybody died eventually so
there's a 100 events I started with a 100
people.
There's 100 deaths and they were alive in
cumulative total for
about 70 net 181 person years.
So we can calculate that the rate of death
was .05 Six per year so about your chances
of dying in any given year were about 5 to
6% which is really, really high.
The last thing I want to point out is this
module has talked about incidence rates
which I'm assuming that many of you are
already actually familiar with.
Again, the incidence rate just gives the
average rate
of the events over a given time period.
What we're going to be focusing on more
in,
in this class, is something called the
hazard rate.
So I want to just put in your mind right
now what the concept of
the hazard rate is.
It's very close to the incidence rate, But
it's an instantaneous incidence rate.
So the incidence rate is usually
calculated sort of,
sort of as an average over some time
period.
The hazard rate is what is your,
chances of having the event in any
particular time point.
And that acknowledges the fact that for
some types of things you don't
necessarily have the same chance of an
event happening at different time points.
The incidence rate can change over time.
And so we call that instantaneous
incidence rate the hazard rate, and that's
going to be a topic that we're going to
cover in a lot of detail in this course.
[BLANK_AUDIO]