In this next module, I'm going to
introduce you to parametric regression,
specifically exponential and [UNKNOWN]
regression [SOUND].
So where are we now on our statistical
chart, tests for survival data.
So if we have time to event data, last
week we talked about descriptive methods.
Such as the rate ratio [SOUND], incidence
rates and Kaplan-Meier statistic.
In this week, we are moving towards
regression and of course we
want to be able to do regression so that
we can accommodate multiple predictors,
continuous predictors and adjust for
things and so on.
So this week I am going to tell you about
parametric regression.
In parametric regression we're going to be
estimating all the parameters.
So we're actually going to have to assume
that our survival times take on some
known probability distribution,such as the
exponential [SOUND].
Next week I'll tell you about Cox
regression.
In Cox regression we're not going to
assume that our
survival times take on any particular
distribution.
So that's the difference between those two
[SOUND].
So then in parametric regression we have
to make more assumption.
We're going to assume that the survival
times take on some
known mathematical distribution, such as
the Weibull or the exponential.
And I'm specifically going to talk about
the Weibull and
the exponential, but we could assume other
distributions for
the survival time, such as the normal or
logged normal [SOUND].
We're then going to estimate the
parameters of these distributions.
So for example [SOUND], the exponential
distribution was defined by the fact that
the hazard function was constant over time
it does not change over time.
So for the exponential we are going to
have to estimate one parameter for
the baseline hazard function because
there's only one hazard function that
doesn't change over time.
For the Weibull distribution however
there's an additional parameter that we
are going to have to estimate [SOUND].
So remember that the hazard function for
the Weibull distribution.
Regression actually is allowed to change
over time.
We are multiplying a constant times time
raised to a power.
If k here is greater than one, the hazard
will be increasing over time,
if k is less than one, the hazard will be
decreasing over time, and
remember is k is one, we'll just be back
on an [UNKNOWN] Exponential.
So there'll be one additional parameter
that we have to estimate.
This power is often called the shape
parameter [SOUND].
We'll be estimating these parameters using
maximum likelihood estimation.
So now let me just show you what the model
looks like.
I'm going to start with the model for
the exponential regression because that's
the simplest.
So, we're actually going to be modeling
the hazard function as a function of
predictors of your risk factors.
We're not going to be directly modeling
the hazard function [SOUND].
However, we're actually going to be
modeling the log hazard function.
So you'll notice that it's the log hazard
function that's over
here on the left-hand side of the equation
[SOUND].
We've dealt a lot with logs before.
This is the natural log here that I'm
talking about [SOUND].
We've dealt a lot with logs before.
Logs have nice mathematical properties, so
we're going to deal with logs rather than
the hazard directly [SOUND].
So what's in the exponential model?
Well, we going to have an intercept that
looks, the, the right hand side of this
equation looks like every other regression
model that we've dealt with.
So, we're going to have an intercept,
that will represent here the hazard
function for
the reference group when all of the other
predictors in the model are set to zero.
And then we're going to have some linear
combination of betas and
predictors like we've always had, this
could be age, weight, whatever your
risk factors are, treatment group, that
you want to model the effects of.
In this module [SOUND], I'm mostly going
to be focusing on just the intercepts of
this model, and then in the next module
we'll actually add back the predictors.
Let me just show you though essentially
what we are modelling here again we
are modelling the log hazard [SOUND], you
know, the hazard change over time and
indicating it has hazard as a function of
time, but of course for
the exponential it's going to be constant
over time.
Let me just take a simple model.
So, imagine that I wanted to have, model
the effect of age on the log hazard.
So, if we had one parameter in the model
that was age,
we are modeling things again as straight
lines so the betas here represent slopes.
The alpha represents dy intercept.
So, if I had a model that just had age in
it.
So, my model was alpha plus beta [SOUND]
times age, what I'd essentially be
modeling is I would say there is some
hazard function for a zero-year old.
Of course there, you know, probably not
going to be any zero [INAUDIBLE] in
my study but that's the intercept, the
reference group.
That's the hazard, the log hazard for that
group and
then as we go up in age, probably, we are
increasing in the hazard or
potentially and we are assuming that there
is a straight line relationship there.
So we'll talk more about the betas again
in the next module but
it's essentially the same.
Same kind of regression model we've been
dealing with all along except our
outcome here is log hazard [SOUND].
Again, I want to focus just on the
intercept for
the purposes of this module, however.
The intercept for the exponential is easy
because it's just a constant [SOUND].
It gets slightly more complicated with the
Weibull Model however, because there is
an additional parameter that we have to
estimate to characterize the hazard
function and because the hazard function
[SOUND] for Weibull can change over time.
So recall again that the hazard function
for
a Weibull is just some constant times time
raised to a power.
Well, if I want to model the log of the
hazard function,
I can take the log of both sides here.
So the log [SOUND] of the hazard function
then would be the log of
a constant which is just a constant,
that's what it's representing.
Here by alpha plus [SOUND]
the log of this second term, but of course
with logs you can bring the powers down in
front so that's what's happening here.
We're ending up with the log of time with
a power in front.
There's one additional parameter that we
have to estimate which
characterizes is the hazard increases or
decreasing as a function over time.
So now we have a situation.
Where if we put time [SOUND] on the x
axis, there's going to be a,
an intercept for an alpha here represents
the intercept.
So that represents the hazard rate at time
equals zero, at baseline, and
then that hazard rate [SOUND] or log
hazard rate.
Is allowed to change as a function of time
[SOUND].
[SOUND] And again we then can additionally
talk about how do [SOUND]
certain predictors increase or decrease.
Your hazard rate but we are not going to
add that in right now for,
for in this model we're going to be
focussing [SOUND] just on
that baseline hazard function without any
predictors in the model.
It's once we are spending a few minutes
here just to go over what does
the likelihood function look like if for
doing parametric regression.
So I'm going to just kind of.
Conceptually put out right out a, a very
simple example for a likelihood function.
Just to give you a sense of what the
likelihood function looks like here.
The likelihood function for the parametric
models will have one probability,
one term in it for each person and each
observation in the study.
I am assuming all of you have seen maximum
likelihood estimation before so
that you're familiar with the concept of
the likelihood function.
So again, I'm going to use a really really
simple example here.
Imagine that we're trying to fit a model.
The log hazard rate,
this is an exponential model, so the log
hazard is equal to
alpha the reference hazard rate plus a
single binary predictor in the model.
So x is either equal to one or zero we
have one beta in the.
In the model, very simple exponential
model.
So again, the likelihood [SOUND],
remember, is the probability of our data.
We're actually going to write out a
probability function that
gives the probability of our data and in
this case we're going to
have one term in the likelihood for every
person in our study.
[SOUND] And what are those terms actually
going to look like [SOUND]?
So I'll write it out, it won't write out
completely but kind of give you a sense of
it, so there is two types of people in our
data set, for time to event outcomes.
There are people who had the event, I'm
going to write died here, but of course
it, the outcome doesn't have to be death,
it could be some other event [SOUND].
But people who died or had whatever the
event was, and we have people who
are censored, meaning the last time we saw
them, they had not yet had the event.
They had not yet died or whatever the
event might be.
So, depending on which of those two
categories somebody falls in,
they're going to get different Terms in
the likelihood.
So somebody who actually died, who
actually had the event.
The probability that they are going to get
in the likelihood is going to be equal to
the [SOUND], their survival probability up
until time t,
the last time we saw than the time at
which they actually had the event.
It's going to be their survival pro,
the probability times [SOUND] the hazard
function, their hazard [SOUND].
So, because they survi, we know that they
survived up until time ti.
That's the time that they died.
They survive up until that time and then
they died at time ti.
So we're representing their probability,
what actually happened, as thei,
their survival probability, their chances
of surviving up until time TI
times their chances of dying right at TI
given that they've survived up to TI.
Remember that's what the hazard function
represents.
So everyone who died will get.
These two probabilities in the model.
And of course these probabilities are
going to be functions of
the alpha and beta.
And I'll fill those in in a minute.
For somebody who's censored [SOUND],
however all we know is that they survived
[SOUND].
Up until the last time that we saw them,
up until the their ti their time to event.
But they didn't die in the next instant,
we don't know what happened next,
so all we are going to put in the model
for them is their probability of
surviving up until time ti, the last time
that they saw them [SOUND].
So they just get the survival probability.
So let me just actually fill in with some.
Show you where the alpha and betas [SOUND]
appear here.
So again if we're on a, an exponential
distribution, we're
adjusting the log [SOUND] of the hazard
function is equal to alpha plus beta if
you were somebody, who have, let's say
this is a treatment in a control group.
So if you have the treatment You get beta
times one.
If you're somebody who's in the control
group who didn't get the treatment,
you only get alpha, because you'll get
beta times zero,
so that term is going to go away.
So there's only kind of two types of
people here [SOUND].
This is the, of course, where we're
modeled the log hazard, so
the hazard function itself I have to
exponentiate both sides [SOUND].
So if I exponentiate both sides [SOUND],
I'm going to show that the hazard function
for
a person who had the treatment is going to
be equal to e raised to alpha plus beta.
And the hazard function for somebody.
Who have not had the treatment, who's in
the control group [SOUND].
Again I'm just going to exponentiate both
sides when we erase the alpha.
Now there's something that you need to
know if you're working specifically in
SAS, is that SAS actually require to
negate the alphas and
betas that it gives you out.
So in the output, if you want to translate
from the output into the actual
hazard function, you first need to negate
the model to multiply it by a negative.
So we are actually going to take negative
alpha plus beta,
exponentiate that to get the hazard
function, or negative exponentiate that
to get the hazard function, just a little
detail you need to know.
So if I, imagine I'm putting a term in the
model now for somebody who in my data set
who died at twelve months into the study,
so their Time ti is 12 and they died.
They had the event.
So I'm going to fill in their survival
function [SOUND].
So what's the survival function for an
exponential.
Remember, it's going to be e raised to
negative ht.
That's the survival probability for on an
exponential.
That's the survival function.
And then I can just plug in okay [SOUND],
what was t
they died [SOUND] at 12 months so I'm
going to be plugging in 12 months for
t we wanted their, their probability of
the, of surviving up until time 12.
It's, that's how long they survive.
And then in the hazard function,
we have, let's say that they're in the
control group.
If they're somebody that's in the control
group [SOUND],
then their hazard function is going to be
e raised to negative hazard function, and
remember, hazard function here is e raised
to negative alpha, it's just this.
That's for somebody in the control group.
That's there hazard function.
So I am going to plug in their hazard
function.
So now, we are a, tha likelihood is a
function of alpha.
We also have to plugin a hazard.
So remember that the hazard function,
if I am on an exponential, is just a
constant hazard.
It's just age, well age here [SOUND], is
simply e raised to negative alpha.
So that's for somebody who is in the
control group.
And died at 12 months, I'd put that term
in the model for that.
Now imagine I've got somebody who was
censored the last time we saw them,
they were still alive.
And let's say they were censored at 11
months and
let's say they were in the treatment
group.
So their survival function again is going
to be e raised to negative.
Each t, their t is 11 months.
But their each, their hazard function
[SOUND] now includes beta because there is
somebody in the treatment group, so
we would plugin e raise to negative alpha,
minus beta there.
And every person in the data set would get
one of these terms in the model.
That's the basic idea of the likelihood
function here.
We would, of course, then what happens to
this likelihood function.
We take the log of the likelihood
function.
We maximize the likelihood function to
solve for
the alpha and beta to make our data the
most likely.