In this next module, I'm going to talk
about dummy coding.
I'm assuming that most of you have seen
dummy coding before so
this will be largely review.
I'll go through it rather quickly.
But I'm going to tell you how it applies
specifically in
the context of linguistic regression.
So, when you want to do a regression, how
do you model categorical predictors?
How do you put categorical predictors in
the model.
It's obvious how to put numerical ones in
the model, but
what about categorical predictors?
How does that, how does that work?
So, actually it's very simple for binary
predictors.
If you've got a binary predictor, You can
just code it as zero one and
actually treat it as a number.
0 and 1 are numbers, so we can just treat
it as a quantitative variable and
just stick it in a regression as a 0, 1
variable.
So, that's essentially what we do with
binary variables.
For categorical variables, we're going to
have to do dummy coding.
Dummy coding means that we're going to
re-code the categorical predictor as
a series of binary predictors.
Since it's easy to deal with binary
predictors because we
can treat them as zeros and ones, we can
actually just rip,
re-represent categorical predictions as a
series of binary variables.
That's the basic idea.
So let me just give you a few pictures
here to illustrate.
So here is a logit plot, okay.
So this the logit of stress fractures.
Lower rate of stress fractures in my data
set on women runners this is whether or
not you have amenorrhea.
You either have amenorrhea, which is the,
the most severe menstrual irregularity, or
you don't.
It's a binary variable, so here's my lojit
plot.
Woo-hoo!
If I do my lojit plot there's only two
points, right?
So, there's only two lojits, the lojit for
the 0 group, and the lojit for the 1
group.
And so, since there's only two points,
it's always going to be a line.
Well, guess what, you don't have to do
logec plots when it comes to
categorical variables because primary
variables,
binary variables, two points is always
going to equal a line.
So, that's nice.
One less piece of work that you have to
do.
Binary variables you can just stick in the
model without thinking too hard about it.
What about, though, if you have more than
two categories.
So that's where binary variables, if you
have more than two categories you're
going to need to use To use dummy coding,
and
most statistical packages will
automatically dummy code for you.
So it's not like you have to do this on
your own, but you need to understand what
the computer is doing, and what's coming
out in your model.
So I'm just going to to take a simple
example from this data set
on women runners.
So there's sort of three categories of
menstrual function that
are usually recognized clinically.
Amenorrhea is basically the absence of
periods, or very few periods per year.
Oligomenorrhea is sort of, irregular
periods but
not the total absence of periods.
And eumenorrhea is just normal, you know,
having more than nine periods per year.
So that we can look at those three
categories rather than, we, in,
in an earlier sample we looked at the
number of periods per year as
a continuous variable.
But, since there's a nice clinical
characterization here we could also look
at this variable, as, as a categorical
variable in these three categories.
But how are we going to include it into
the regression model?
So the way that we're going to do it is
we're going to dummy code,
and here's how dummy coding works.
A three level categorical variable will
have Will be dummy coded as
two binary variables.
A 4-level categorical variable would be
dummy coded as
three binary variables and so on.
So we have to pick something as the
reference group.
In this example, it makes sense to, to use
Eumenorrheic as the, the normal
functioning women as the reference So this
is going to be my reference group.
I'm going to define a new binary variable
that is,
you're either amenorrheic or you're not.
So women who are amenorrheic will get a
value of 1 for
this variable, and everybody else will get
everybody else will get a value of 0.
So you're either amenorrheic or you're
not.
So the oligomenorrheic and the
eumenorrheic women will get values of 0.
I'm going to define a second binary
variable, oligomenorrheic.
And if you're oligomenorrheic, you're
going to get a value of on 1 and
if you're not you're going to get a value
of 0.
So women who get a value of 0 on the
amenorrheia variable and
get a oligomenorrheia variable by default
are in that reference,
the eumenorrheic category.
We're then going to take these two binary
vairables and
we're going to put them into our model.
So the logit of stress factors then,
we would model this as in a receipt plus a
beta for
that binary variable eumenorrhea, plus a
beta for the variable oligomenorrhea.
We are, does eumenorrhea come into this
picture well that has been it's, the,
it's absorbed essentially in the,
the intercept, it's represented by the
intercept.
Then we have 2 additional parameters, so
I've got a 3 level categorical variable,
I'm going to have to put.
Two parameters in my model, two betas in
my model.
If I had a 5 level categorical variable,
I'd have to put 4 betas into my model.
Now, pictorially, what we're really doing
is we're just essentially breaking this
into a series of binary variables.
So again, you don't have to do the Logia
plots here because if
you look at the Logia plots, I'm going to
be comparing,
what I'm ending up doing is comparing
amenorrheic women to normal women.
So here's my reference group, the normal
women.
I'm going to compare this is actually
umenorrheic and this is amenorrheic.
This is umenorrheic versus
oligomenorrheic,
that's what the values represent here.
So I compare my amenorrheic woman to my
umenorrheic woman.
It's just a two group comparison, so
again, 2 points make a line.
Notice that the logit for the amenorrheic
group is at negative 2.6,
same logit over here, same group, also at
negative 2.6, but now I'm comparing to
my oligomenorrheic group which has a
slightly lower logit than.
So literally I'm putting into my model a
201 comparisons.
Now when I actually run this in my
statistical program,
I can ask my statistical program to do
this dummy coding for me.
It's usually built-in.
It's very easy to do, for example, in SAS.
And then I can get out some betas.
My betas are all going to be compared to
the reference group,
and of course, since we're doing logistic
regression,
it's nice to translate these directly into
odds ratios.
It makes very interpretable odds ratios
because we're now,
we're comparing Amennoreic to the
reference group and
Oligomenorrheic to the reference group.
So notice that the Amennoreic women,
really do
have quite a,a large increase in their
odds of getting a stress fracture here.
6.8 is the odds ratio.
For them oligomenorrheic women have
somewhat of an increased risk but
the alteration is only 2.4 so not quite as
big and
this one did not come out to be
statistically significant.
So that's the basic idea I'm going to come
out with In logistic regression, an odds
ratio, a separate odd ratio for each
category compared to the reference group.
Now which category am I going to choose to
be the reference group?
That's a decision you usually have to
make.
Of course it doesn't effect the math.
The SAS doesn't order your computer,
doesn't really care what you choose as the
reference group.
But usually there's some kind of a group
that makes sense to choose as
the reference group, and you want to make
sure you go in, and, every computer
package will have a way to, will choose a
reference group for you by default.
You want to go in and change that to the
more, the sensible reference group.
So like if you're doing an experimental
trial,
clearly you want the reference group to be
the control group.
If you're still on the experimental trial
and
there's no natural kind of control group,
you might want to pick the highest risk
group.
If you want to show protective effects.
So like if you want to show that
something,
if the message of your paper is that
something is protective,
you would choose the highest, the group
with the highest risk.
So that your odds ratios all come out to
be below 1, it shows a protective effect.
Or if you want to show something's
harmful, you'd pick the lowest risk group
as your reference group, so that your odds
ratios all come out above 1.
And this again is,
just has to do with the message that you
present at the end of the day.
But it's an important choice, so
you want to think about what makes the
best reference group.