In the last module, I told you how to fit
the baseline hazard function, for
Y [INAUDIBLE] and exponential models,
essentially only fitting the intercept.
In this module, we're also going to
incorporate predictors.
So just to remind you that what we're
modeling in these parametric regression
models is the log of the hazard rate for
exponential models fortunately it's
easy because we just have a constant
hazard rate it doesn't change over time.
So we estimate the baseline hazard rate
for
our reference group with an intercept, and
that's it.
We could then incorporate additional risk
factors.
So we can put in, as we normally do with
regression,
a set linear combination of datas and
predictors.
And that would increase or decrease the
hazard rate.
So say you have smokers perhaps the beta
for smoking would be positive, and
your hazard rate would go up because you
were a smoker.
So we can incorporate these additional
risk factors.
Just to remind you, for the Weibull model,
we had to estimate not only.
The hazard function at time equals zero,
which is what the intercept here,
alpha, represents, but also an additional
parameter that tells us how much or how
how much the hazard function is increasing
or decreasing as a function of time.
So, one additional parameter.
And, but again we can add some, some
predictors and
risk factors to that so that hazard rates
for different groups will be different.
So just to give and
example, I have some data on patients with
HIV early in the epidemic.
the're, the're were many potential risk
factors that could explain why people
survived or lived, survived or died
faster, than one another.
But I just fit some data, just to have an
example to fit the model.
I, I fit an exponential model, so we're
modeling, again, the log hazard rate and
I put one predictor in the model, which is
age.
So this is a continuous predictor.
And of course, regression can incorporate
continuous predictors, but
we can compare people at different age
groups.
So here's that the final model came out of
I've already fixed the negative so
the signs are correct.
So we can figure out the hazard rate by
just exponentiating and then we'd,
of course, have to plug in different ages.
So if I wanted to say, well what is the
hazard rate for
somebody who is 30 years old, for example,
I would plug in 30 for age?
I would solve this equation and it would
give me the hazard rate for a 30-year old.
The hazard rate for a 30-year old is
constant, but
it's different from the hazard rate for,
say a 40-year old.
And that's illustrated on this next slide.
I went ahead and plotted hazard rates for
different age groups.
So in red here this was age equals 20.
Blue was age equals 30.
So again, if you plug into that equation
for
the hazard function [INAUDIBLE] raised to
-5.859 plus .0939 times age.
You can see that the hazard functions, the
hazard rates don't go
up linearly with age, because remember,
we're running an exponential.
So as you go up in age, you know, here's
40, here's 50 year olds, and
here's 60 year olds.
You can see that there's a big jump in the
mortality rate as you jump up in age.
But that's all we've modeled, by the
exponential model that tells us as you
go up in age, you're rate of death goes
up.
We can then plot the corresponding
survival curves,
once you know the hazard rate, you know,
and you know you're on the exponential,
then you know the survival curve.
So here's the corresponding survival
curve.
Here's the 20 year olds, they're doing the
best.
[LAUGH] They're not dying as fast and
here is the 60 year olds, they're dying
much more quickly.
Actually it's a very, very steep drop in
survival for them.
So this is just illustrating that survival
depends on age and
now I have a model that predicts that.
The beta for age tells me that the older I
am the worse I am doing for,
at least for this data set.
We can take the betas from either a
Weibull or an exponential model, and
we can exponentiate them to get hazard
ratios, and
a hazard ratio is just a measure of
relative risk.
It's a ratio of two hazard rates.
So we can compare different groups.
Or if we have a continuous predictor, as
we do here.
We can say, what's the hazard ratio for
a 1 unit increase in the continuous
predictor.
And just to show you how that works here.
Again, this, and the numerator, is the
hazard rate for
a person who is one year older than the
person in the denominator.
So I, my model says this is hazard rate
for somebody's who's 51.
And this, and the denominator is the
hazard rate for
somebody's who's 50, for example.
And it doesn't matter, what exact ages I
plug in.
But I'm going to put one unit higher in
the numerator so that I can get
the hazard range, the hazard ratio for a
one unit higher age when an older age.
So, here's the hazard rate for a 51 year
old.
Here's the hazard rate for a 50 year old.
Well, they have the same baseline hazard
rates.
So those are going to cancel.
And they have only a difference of 1 in
age, so everything's going to cancel
except the e raised to [SOUND] one so,
we're going to cancel out this.
And essentially we're down, we end up with
0.0939, the beta for age exponentiated.
When you exponentiate that you get a
hazard ratio of 1.098.
So this would tell you that for every one
year older in age you were,
there was a 10% increase, or almost a 10%
increase in the mortality rate.
That's a big jump because a one year
increase in age is not a lot.
So we can get relative risks out of these
models.
These, particular models the Weibull and
the exponential, when we assume a Weibull
and an exponential distribution, they are
what we call proportional hazards models.
That means they're models from which we
can get hazard ratios.
We're assuming those hazards are might be
proportional and so
that we could calculate hazard ratios.
There are other types of parametric
models,
like if you assumed a log normal
distribution that you can't get
hazard ratios out of, but from these two
you can get hazard ratios.
And I just want to point out, that if
you're working in SAS.
The way that SAS calculates things when it
gives you out the beta for an exponential
model to get a hazard ratio you first have
to negate the data and the exponential it.
I had already fixed that on the my output
when I presented the model for
the age and HIV data.
For the Weibull Model you have to take the
output from SAS.
The beta and gate it and then divide by
the scale parameter,
which we talked about what that scale
parameter is.
So the hazard ratio calculation takes a
few steps, so
just we'll practice doing that.
Now I want to show you an example where
we're just comparing two groups.
So remember that we had this hepatitis
trial last week,
where 22 people with chronic active
hepatitis were treated with a steroid and
22 were just in the control group, not
treated with anything.
And using data from the trial, I fit
exponential and Weibull models.
Just to remember you, remind you what it
looked like, here's the Kaplan Meier
curves from that data, this indeed had a
certain significant log rate to
test because you can see that the treated
group did a lot better than the control.
The control group is here in red, the
treated group is in black.
So you really wanted to be treated in this
study.
We can take the Kaplan-Meier curves.
And, plot the negative log of the
survival.
The cumulative hazard plots.
So, remember, that, if I plot the negative
log on the Kaplan Meiers curves, yes,
I end up with something that is a straight
line.
That would indicate that my hazard
function is constant over time.
I don't have a perfectly straight line
here so here's the control group.
It's not bad as far as real data go but
it's definitely a little bit curvy.
And the steroid group is even a little bit
more curved.
It's a little bit curved upward which
would,
curved upward would indicate somewhat of a
hazard, increasing over time.
So it's not a perfectly straight line.
Of course real data is never going to be
perfectly straight.
So we'll have to kind of choose carefully
between the exponential and
the viable functions here.
So when you get data, before fitting these
parametric regression laws.
You're going to want to plot this
cumulative hazard function again,
most computers will do it for you, very
easily.
Because we want to compare groups, and we
want to calculate hazard rations.
We also need to do one of these log, log
plots.
And again, all this is, is you take your
Kaplan-Meier estimates.
You take negative log of it, which is what
we just did for
the cumulative hazard plot, and then you
take another log.
And you don't have to do this by hand.
SASS will do this for you, or
whatever computer program you're, you're
in will do this for you pretty easily.
But the reason we want to do the log log
plots, is that,
if we're going to be calculating a hazard
ratio, a single hazard ratio.
The assumption behind that is that there
is one single hazard over time.
So we are assuming that whatever the
hazard function looks like over time.
It doesn't even have to be something very
smooth whatever it is, over time,
the distance between the hazard rate
curves between the two groups is
always the same because otherwise there
wouldn't be a single hazard ratio.
Imagine that, if I were to be able to plot
the hazard functions and I got something
that looked like [SOUND] this' here's
group one, and here's group two.
Well, at, you know, the beginning of the
study, the hazard ratio is 1.0,
there is no relative difference between
the two groups The end of the study,
the hazard ratio might be three.
So, there's not a single hazard ratio if
the hazard rates aren't
parallel over time.
The log-log plot evaluates whether or not
the hazard rates are parallel over time.
Again, we can't easily directly draw the
hazard functions, so
we do these log-log plots.
If I'm looking at these log-log plots, I'm
hoping that the lines are parallel.
These are not perfectly parallel lines,
you can see here,.
But, as real data go, they're not
terrible.
I'm probably not going to make too much of
a fuss.
Over this particular log-log plot.
We are going to talk a lot more about
log-log plots when we get to
Caulk's regression, so I will leave it at
that for now.
But for real data these are kind of
reasonably parallel, probably good enough.
So I took the data from those two groups,
and
I then fit in exponential regression
model.
So here is what I got from the results of
the out put from my computer.
So now I have as an exponential so I have
one constant intercept.
So this would represent, this intercept
would represent the hazard rate for
the control group.
We also get a beta for treatment and that
would represent the increase or
decrease in the hazard rate for the
treated group.
And this is a nice binary predictor here,
so it, you either have it or you don't.
Now, as I mentioned before, you have to be
a little careful because if you wanted to
get the hazard rate for the treated group.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If I wanted to calculate that directly the
hazard rate for the treated group here.
I would have to do remember we're
going to,
the model is the log of the hazard rate is
equal to alpha plus beta here.
So we have to exponentiate it but
you not only have to exponentiate you
actually have to change the signs for
alpha and beta so this is going to be
exponentiate 4.4886 minus
.89008 That would give me the hazard rate
for the treated group.
The hazard rate for the control group
would be equal to E raised to
negative 4.4886, there's, and they don't,
they get nothing.
The beta is multiplied by zero there.
Treated as quoted as one in control of
zero here.
They're going to have a higher hazard
rate,
the treated group is going to have a lower
hazard rate.
I can then divide those two hazard rates
to get the hazard ratio or
I could just take the beta for the
treatment, negate it,
as I mentioned before, you have to negate
it, exponentiate it [SOUND] and
when you do that, you will come up with
the hazard rat, ratio.
So if I do that, and I've already done
that out here, if I exponentiate negative
.9008, that's the treatment effect, I get
a hazard issue of .406.
And as we saw in the Kaplan–Meier curves,
being in the treatment group definitely
protected, reduced the mortality rate, and
that's what the hazard ratio is telling
us, there's about a 60% decrease in
the mortality rate in the treatment,
versus the control.
I'll just point again,
since we're doing likelihood estimation We
get a negative 2 log likelihood.
We also get these AIC criteria,
these information criteria, which I
mentioned in the last module.
Basically, smaller is better, and
you can use them to compare different
models in the same data.
We can use all of these to help us decide
whether or
not an exponential or a Weibull model is
better here.
Oh, I should point out that the treatment
effect the beta does turn out to
be statistically significant.
The p value here is very similar to the p
value we got from the log ranked test
thing, that treatment does significantly
increase mortality.
So then a I sent a Weibull model to these
same data.
So here's the Weibull model fit.
So the estimate,
the intercept is very similar the treated
value is pretty similar,
it's just a little bit higher and then we
additionally estimate the scale parameter.
It comes up to be 1.26 here.
And ab,
since it's above one that would indicate
that the hazard is increasing over time.
And, we saw that in the, cumulative hazard
class.
Those curves were a little bit curved
upward.
Indicating a little bit of increase, in
the hazard, over time.
Now, how do we decide whether or
not we want to stick decide to stick with
the, why the model here?
Or with the exponential model.
We have to kind of compare the two models.
So we can look at the negative two log
likelihoods and these AIC statistics.
So the negative two log likelihood, we've
done before.
If we want to compare two nested models,
and
these are, one has one additional
parameter, we could take the negative two
log likelihood from the exponential model
which is 136.069.
That's the smaller model.
We subtract the negative 2 log likelihood
from the bigger model.
That's roughly going to come out to be,
it's a little bit more than 2,
about 136 minus roughly 134, it's going to
be, just a little bit over 2.
This is going to have a chi square of one
degree of freedom because we have
estimated only one additional parameter,
with a Weibull model and we know that
a chi-square of one freedom 2 is not
going to be statistically significant.
We have to closer to 4 to get statistical
significance.
So that's not going to be a statistically
significant difference
that indicates that it's,
that we're probably not gaining too much
by estimating the additional parameter.
It doesn't seem to add significantly to
the model.
We can also get the AIC.
Now the AIC, the, the first one, which
doesn't have the additional penalty is,
and remember the difference between the -2
Log Likelihood and
the AIC is just two times the number of
parameters.
So we're estimated three parameters so
we're just going to add 6 to the -2 Log
likelihood.
So 132.89, becomes 139.898.
There's a penalty incorporated for the
number of parameters in the model.
The Weibull model, the just a plain AIC is
actually slightly smaller in
the Weibull model compared with the
exponential.
So that one I'm
going to actually argue that the Weibull
model is a little bit better.
But I prefer the AICC which has this
additional [UNKNOWN] for some samples.
That one is 140.36 in the exponential and
140.49 in the Weibull and
again, you're looking for smaller being
better so
that one would say that the exponential
was slightly better than the Weibull.
So you could make an argument either way
here, but I, I probably would default to
the simpler model in this case and just go
with the exponential.
Although, there is a little bit of,
the hazard rates seem to be changing a
little bit over time.
We can also then calculate the hazard
ratio.
So how to you calculate the hazard ratio
from a Weibull model?
So getting sash you first have to negate
the beta, and
you have to divide by the scale perimeter.
So I'm going to take the -1.05 divide by
the scale perimeter 1.267 and
then I'm going to exponentiate that.
That gives the me the hazard ratio for
treatment versus control, it comes out to
be .43, very similar to what we've got out
of the exponential model.
So you can see, it didn't make a heck of a
lot of difference,
which baseline underlying model we assumed
here, to how the ratios come out to be
reasonably similar, about a 60% decrease
in mortality, in the mortality rate.
And then I went ahead and plotted, again,
since we've completely estimated the
survival curve as a mathematical function,
we can plot these beautiful smooth curves.
So, I went ahead and plotted, this is the
Weibull model, for the two groups, and
this is the exponential model, for the two
groups.
And, visually, I can't see too, too much
difference between the two [UNKNOWN].
They're definitely a little bit different,
but you can see that it doesn't make,
the Weibull versus the exponential, didn't
make a huge difference here.
The, Kaplan-Meier curve, is at the bottom.
That's just our observed survival curve,
directly from what we see in our data.
And you can see that you know, are smooth,
parametric estimates, this is,
again, the non-parametric, just what we
see in our data.
This is the parametric models, and when we
plot that kind of as a smooth,
pretend we have a perfect mathematical
curve,
it looks like pretty close to what the
Kaplan-Meier curves look like.
You'll see that the only difference is
that the Kaplan-Meier curves do
have this funny thing of trying, sort of
coming together which would be due to
small numbers at the end of the course and
of course, our perfect mathematical curves
are never come together.
They are always going to be separate.
So it looks like an exponential or
viable as a reasonable fit of the, of the
data here.
I want to just show you one more thing
because next week we
are going to be moving to cox regression
and the difference between
the parametric regression models and the
cox regression model,
is that with parametric regression we are
only going to estimate the hazard ratios.
So if you kind of go back to the model, to
the [SOUND] equations here.
Go way, way back.
So here's like the equation for a Weibull
model.
What we're going to do is
we're not going to bother to estimate the
intercepts at all.
We're going to say, we're going to cancel
out the intercept.
And only estimate the betas.
Okay, so there's going to be no intercept
in the model.
We're not going to assume it fits any
particular function.
Any particular mathematical function and
we're just going to get the hazard ratios
out.
Sometimes that's all we care about, is
just comparing different groups.
So, I then took these data just to show
you to prepare you for
next week how, what happens when I run a
cox regression on these data.
I'm just going to get hazard ratio out, so
I went ahead and
fit these data in a cox regression model,
no intercept because we're
not making any assumptions about the
underlying baseline hazard function.
But we do get a beta for the treatment,
and that's the beta.
You can exponentiate this one directly to
get the hazard ratio, and since that knows
that your, or that your computer problem,
probably from is going to know that you
want the hazard ratio with cox regression
it does it automatically.
We do get a, this is a statistically
significant effect.
And a hazard ratio is 0.435.
So very similar to what I got out of the
exponential in the viable models
in the confidence interval of course this
not cross one since the p value
is significant.
So in terms of that hazard ratio, if
that's all I care about,
it didn't really matter too much if I fit
parametric regression or
cox regression but the cox regression will
not give me out a nice smooth mathematical
curve like the parametric regression will.
[BLANK_AUDIO]