[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to talk
about the chi-squared test.
This should be review, for everybody in
this course.
So, I'm going to just go over this
quickly.
And say a little bit about what the
chi-squared distribution actually is.
And then, I'll just do one practice
problem on the chi squared.
So the chi squared test is used when you
have either a two by two table or
something bigger than a 2x2 table, a
bigger contingency table.
And it's used when you have independent
observations.
But what is a chi-squared distribution?
I've mentioned the chi-squared
distribution a couple of times already
this week.
So, let me just say a little bit about
what it actually that distribution
actually is.
So, I mentioned earlier that a chi-square
with one degree of
freedom is simply equal to a standard
normal distribution squared.
Well what exactly do I mean by that?
One is equivilant to the other.
Well here's the idea, take a z
distribution,
that's just a standard normal distribution
that has a mean of zero and
a standard deviation of one and it's on a
bell curve.
Okay so that's a z distribution.
If you take a standard normal distribution
and you square all of the values, so for
example if you're at a value of two.
And, here's a z of two.
That would suddenly become a value of
four.
That would go to four.
And, if you're at a value of negative two,
that would also go to a value of four.
But, you keep the probability.
So the, the probability of getting
negative two or
positive two, is still the same.
But, we're squaring all the values in this
standard.
If you do that, what you end up with, is
you get rid of the negatives.
So a Chi-Squared distribution, it has a
bound at zero,
you can't have any negatives because it's
a squared thing.
But you end up with a bounded zero, and
then you end up with a long tail to
the right, and I'm not drawing this
totally to scale, it's got to be centered.
In this case, the mean is going to be one.
So if, if we just square the standard
normals, you'll end up with a mean of one,
and you're going to have a whole bunch of
things out in the tail,
because the twos become fours, the
negative two becomes four.
You're going to end up with a longer tail
here.
But mathematically, the probability of any
given set of val-,
given values is the same, it's just one is
the square of the other.
Now, that is a chi-squared with one degree
of freedom, so
that has a direct relation to ship to a
standard normal.
And it gets a little more tricky after
that.
But if you take one z squared and
you add it to another z squared you get a
chi-squared with two degrees of freedom.
So that's what a chi-squared with two
degrees of freedom is,
it's a standard normal squared plus a
standard normal squared.
You can see where I'm going with this.
If you then take a z squared plus a z
squared plus another z squared,
That ends up being a chi square with three
degrees of freedom, and so on.
And all of these of course have different
shapes.
And you can see some of the shapes here.
Which shows you with one degree of
freedom, two degrees, three degrees, etc.
in this little picture.
So, the shape of the distribution depends
on the degrees of freedom, but
there is a strict relationship back to the
standard normal.
And at least with a chi-squared of one,
degree of freedom,
that relationship is pretty direct.
This gets a little more tricky as you go
out, but there's this direct relationship.
Now it's useful to know that the expected
value of
a Chi-Square is always equal to its
degrees of freedom.
So the expected value of a Chi-Square of
one degree of freedom is one,
two degrees of freedom is two, etc.
And also the variance of a Chi-Square is
also,
is always equal to two times its degrees
of freedom.
So sometimes if you don't want to bother
to go look up chi-square.
The chi-square, you know the p value in a
chi-squared chart, you can kind of quickly
look at the value of the chi-squared in,
guessed, based on, you know
two times the degrees of freedom, and, you
know how you can probably guess whether or
not that chi-squared likely statistically
significant, you can make an estimate.
So it's useful to just keep that in mind
the expected value and variance grow.
With the numbers of degrees of freedom.
And again I'll just remind you that when
you're calculated degrees of freedom for
a contingency table, is always the number
of
degrees of freedoms is equal to rows minus
one times columns minus one, so
since we're talking about the Chi-Squared
distribution can be applied to
many different things And it's not just
contingency tables.
But the, the co, one of the common uses of
a chi square is for contingencies tables.
In the case of contingency table the
degrees of freedom is always equal to r
minus, the rose minus one times the
columns minus one.
I'm just going to quickly walk through one
chi square test of
independance from my contingency table.
Again I'm assuming that you've all done
this before to the to be
pretty much reviewed.
So here's some data that I got out of
Agresti's discreet data analysis book.
They were looking at political ideology
and happiness.
So they do a big survey of people and
said you know, are you liberal, moderate
or conservative?
And what's your level of happiness?
We have two categorical variables they've
done this as they,
they could have scored this as continues
variables, probably but this
they've done this as categorical variables
but we have three level categories so
we don't, we no longer on a 2 by 2 table,
we're on a 3 by 3 table.
How can I tell, whether or not there are
significant differences
in happiness between the different
political ideology proofs.
I'm going to apply a chi-squared test for
that, so
when I've got a bigger contingency table I
going to apply the Chi-squared test.
So now I'm actually going to apply that
Chi-squared test here.
So here is my Observe table just copied
from the last slide and
now I'm going to calculate the expected
values.
So we already did this for a two by two
table in an earlier module.
It's really the same idea here, but how do
I calculate my expected values?
So for, the quick way to calculate the
expected count for
any cell is to multiply the row total
times to column total for
that cell, and divide that by the total
end.
Again, why is that?
Because you have the no hypothesis is true
if the,
two things, political bent and happiness
are independent, then.
The probability of being in the in
any given cell should be the product of
the marginal probability so for
example the probability of being liberal
and not to happy will be.
Being that in this particular cell,
if those things are independent should be
exactly equal to the probability,
the marginal probability of being liberal,
the overall probability of
being liberal times the overall
probability of being not too happy.
So you would calculate that by doing 57
out of 321,
is your probability of being liberal.
Your marginal probability of being
liberal.
50 out of the 321 is your marginal
probability of being not too happy.
That's going to give you the probability
of being in this cell.
We always want to get counts for pi
squared so
we were then going to have to multiply
that by n.
Notice those 321's cancel, so
you can always get the expected value by
row total times column total divided by n.
So if I do that here, 57.
Times 50 divided by 321.
I get that the expected count here is
8.88.
So we were expecting only eight and
actually we saw a few more not too happy
people in the liberal category.
Alright, so next I'm going to go on and
I'm going to do the expected value for,
liberal and pretty happy.
I could pick any, any cell to do next, but
I'm just kind of go in, in order here.
So, how am I going to get that one?
I'm going to take the row total which is
57 times the column total which is 155 and
I'm going to divide that by the end, which
is 321.
Which gives me a value of 27.5.
Next I'm going to go ahead and
do the expected value in the Moderate and
Not too happy category.
So here I'm going to be using the row
total of 129 times the column total of 50,
divided by 321.
That gives me an expected value of 20.09.
And then I'm going to do this middle cell.
That's going to be 129 times Times 50
divided by 321.
And that gives me 62.29.
Now I could keep on multiplying like this.
But in fact,
there's an easier way from here on out to
solve the rest of the cells.
So what you have to recognize in a Chi
squared is that the marginals are fixed.
So 50, 155, and 116 those marginal totals.
And 57, 129, and 35, those don't change.
Those cannot change.
So by the time I've solved two cells in
the first row and
I know the total then I know what that
third cell in the first row has to be.
So I no longer have to do any
mulitplication.
And same way that you can see that
everyone of
the cells that's locked into this table I
can fill in simply by subtracting.
What this tells you, is that this table
has four degrees of freedom.
By the time I fill in four cells, the rest
of the cells are fixed.
So, it only has four degrees of freedom.
What that means in terms of my workload is
I only have to multiply out this
to get these expected values for four
cells and
then I am essentially done and I can just
subtract.
Another way to know that this has
[INAUDIBLE] is to do three rows and
three columns.
Three minus times three minus one is also
four.
But you can see that where that.
Comes from is that by the time I filled in
four cells, then I got one row left and
one column left, those are going to be
fixed, because the marginals are fixed.
So there's no more wiggle room.
There's no more degrees of freedom.
I'm just going to subtract, you know,
57 minus 27.5 minus 8.88 gives me an
expected value of 20.6 here.
And I'm subtracting to fill in the rest of
these cells.
So again, 50 minus 20.09 minus 8.88 gives
me 21.0.
So I am filling all of my expected values,
once I do that, then I can calculate.
Now here's just a little side that reviews
how to calculate the expected in case you
need a little refresher on that.
I'm going to just skip over that quickly.
You can pause it if you need to look at
that more carefully.
But now, once I've got my observed and
expected tables, I can calculate my
chi-squared statistics.
It's again a Chi score of 40 degrees of
freedom here.
My observe, the statistic is observe minus
expected squared divided by expected.
So I went ahead just to save us time here
and I plug in each of the values.
So the first cell the observed value was
13 the expected was 8.88.
The next cell the observed was 29 the
expected value was 27.5 and so on.
So there were nine cells on the table,
there are nine Terms is calculating this
chi-squared statistic.
Now, I have to admit that I actually
didn't want to sit there and
have to plug all of this into a
calculator, so I went ahead and
dumped all of these data into SAS, and
actually let SAS calculate this for me.
You're not going to have to do too many
chi-squares by hand, maybe one.
In this class, and then it's rather
tedious, you can see,
to calculate it by hand.
The computer can do it for you.
So when I calculate it out I
get a chi-squared value of seven point
zero seven.
This chi-squared has four degrees of
values of freedoms.
Remember the expected value here is four.
The variance is two times four or eight.
So you can see that seven isn't quite
enough bigger than four to
quite make statistical significance.
It's the p value here comes out to zero
point one three,
again you can go to a chart or you can
have sas or
another statistical program calculate that
for you directly which is what I did.
So it didn't quite reach statistical
significance.
We don't have enough evidence to say that,
you know,
liberals are doing worse on happiness
than, than conservatives.
But as your general setup for
the chi-squared test, you won't have to do
too many of these by hand.
You usually can let the computer do it but
it's good to kind of know what goes on
behind the scenes in calculating this.
Now, I'm just going to show you that if
you wanted to calculate that chi-squared
value by hand and then go get the p value
that corresponds out of it, you can go to
a chi-squared chart like that you can find
in back of an old fashioned text book.
Or, you can go to one of these online
calculators,
if you Google, chi-square P value
calculator, you'll get a ton.
Here's one that I used to get my P value.
Again, I also used SAS, but I plugged in
my chi-square seven point zero seven,
I plugged in the degrees of freedom.
It spits out for me, the two-sided P value
is zero point one three.
So fairly easy to do this online without
having to go to a chart.
[BLANK_AUDIO]