Welcome to week 3 of HRP 261.
This week we're going to delve into
Logistic Regression,
which is a topic that we'll be talking
about over multiple weeks.
So let's see where we are on our
statistical chart here.
So we're going to talk today mostly about
logistic regression.
That's used when you have a categorical
outcome, but you want to adjust for
confounders or look at multiple variables
at once.
You want to do regression.
That's the regression technique.
Today we'll talk about unconditional
logistic regression,
which is what you use when you have
independent observations.
At the end of the week, I'll also briefly
mention exact logistic regression,
which is just what it sounds like.
Logistic regression has an assumption of a
reasonable sample size.
If you have sparse data, those assumptions
fall down and
you need, need to use an exact test.
Similar to the difference between the
chi-squared and the Fisher's exact.
Alright, so just briefly, what is logistic
regression?
So recall that we did linear regression in
the fall, if you were in HRP 259.
It looked like you have some continuous
outcome variable, and
then we're modeling that as a linear
function of some predictors.
And it looked, the equation looks
something like that.
Logistic regression looks awfully similar.
Okay, if you look at the right hand side
of the equation, in fact,
it looks exactly the same.
So we're essentially trying to do the same
kind of equation as we did with
linear regression, a linear function on
the right hand side of the equation.
However, because we don't have a
continuous, normally distributed outcome,
we have in the case of logistic regression
a binary or categorical outcome.
The right hand side of the equation's
going to look differently.
So for a binary outcome it's going to look
like this.
This is what we're going to talk about
today,
that's something called the logit
function.
So the outcome looks a little different,
but
notice, the right hand side of the
equation is exactly the same.
So I'm going to walk you through in the
first module this week.
I'm going to walk you through an overview
of this model.
What it means, how to interpret it,
what does the betas mean, what does the
intercept mean.
Then I'm going to walk you through
examples from the literature that
used logistic regression just to talk
about how to interpret those results.
Then at the, towards the end of this week
I'm going to delve into the math behind
logistic regression.
So it is going to get a little bit mathy,
there will be a little bit of calclus
involved.
But I think it's important,
to kind of open up the black box of
logistic regression and
show you what's behind the scenes, what's
actually going on mathematically.
You will not have to do any of that math
by hand,
buy you need to be able to follow my logic
and understand things like,
what is maximum likelihood estimation, and
what's a likelihood function.
I'll walk you through all of that.
Just to introduce this week, the, one of
the examples that I'm going to be
using of a real world example in the
medical literature.
It came from a study that was looking at
doctors who had been disciplined by their
state medical board.
So this is an example where logistic
regression came into play because if
you look at the outcome variable, it's a
1/0 variable, it's a binary.
You're either a doctor who was either
disciplined or they weren't.
So if we want to do regression here, we're
going to do a logistic regression.
Now this study happen to be trying to find
out whether or
not there was something in medical school,
that could predict which students were
mostly to go on to become doctors that
were disciplined.
Like if you have say, a low GPA or your
MCAT scores were poor,
if you demonstrated unprofessional
behavior in medical school.
Do any of those things, are any of those
flags that can predict the doctors that
are going to go on to have disciplinary
problems.
You'll notice that the set of predictors
here, they,
there's, they may be very highly
overlapping.
And obviously GPA and MCAT might, scores
might be correlated.
They, those might be related to
unprofessional behavior, and
some of the other things they were looking
at in this study.
So we have a set of predictors that we
want to look at simultaneously to
see which one actually has independent
effects, if any.
And so we're going to need to do some kind
of regression technique, so
that's why we end up doing logistic
regression here.
Now just for interest, I'm just going to
show you a couple of
tables from a few other studies that are
showing you what this outcome is.
What does it mean to be disciplined by the
state medical board?
So as background, when we get to this
study that I'm going to present later,
just to show you the kinds of things that
doctors are disciplined for,
on the left-hand side, this table here is
showing you,
it's a little bit old, it's from the
1990s, but it's showing you, in the US,
some things, negligence, you know,
improper drug prescribing is a big one.
If the doctor has an alcohol abuse
problem,
fraud, sexual misconduct, you know, crime.
All of these things are pretty bad things
that you don't want you know,
your doctor to be doing.
The right hand side shows a similar table
from, but
it was data compiled recently from Canada
so you can see
a slightly different distribution, but the
same kinds of behavior.
So these are the kinds of things that
doctors are disciplined for.
And later on this week we're going to look
at what might predict the doctors that
are going to go on to get disciplined.
[BLANK_AUDIO]