In this next module,
I'm going to talk about one of the
assumptions of linear regression that
you really should test if you've got
continuous predictors in your model.
I think it's often an ignored assumption,
so when you are reading papers,
you should look to see whether or not it
was tested, and
if you are doing your own data analysis,
it would be important to run this test.
This assumption is something called linear
in the logit, and it's as simple as, just,
when we do a linear regression, remember,
what do you want to do, of course.
When you do a linear regression,
you want to do the plot and you want to
see if it actually looks like a line.
This one looks like a line.
Here's a scatter plot that doesn't look
like a line.
It actually looks like a quadratic.
So for linear regression, it's really
easy,
because we can just plot x against y and
we can see immediately if it looks like
the, the scatter plot roughly fits a line.
For logistic regression, we're still
fitting lines.
But it's harder to draw this graphic,
because the outcome,
remember, is this logit function.
And there's no way to directly see the
logit function.
The best you can do is, I did some logit
plots, and
the first module for this week in how I
did that, in order to be able to do that,
I had to group people according to their
level of the predictor.
So I can group people who did the lowest
number amount of homework and, you know,
like the ten lowest, the ten people with
the lowest homework time, and
then the next then, and then the next ten.
So I have to somehow group people,
in order that I can calculate the
proportion who've had the binary outcome.
From that proportion I can then calculate
the logit.
If you do that, then you can make some
plots.
But of course, the plot's going to depend
slightly on how you bin people,
on how you group people.
So, I'm going to show you in a minute,
some examples of testing this,
a linear and the logit assumption.
And you'll see that I will usually run
several different graphs with several
different bin sizes, so that I can get a
sense of the data without you know,
being too arbitrary.
And we're looking for that what we're
testing is that if
you have a continuous predictor in
logistic regression,
what we're doing is we're fitting a line
that says that continuous predictor,
x, has a linear relationship roughly with
the logit of the outcome.
So you actually want to make that plot as
best you can and
see if the relationship is really linear,
or if, maybe it's not.
If it's something else, if the
relationship looks you know,
quadratic, that means you're going to have
to model a quadratic variable for x,
you're going to put in x squared into the
model.
Or you might have to transform that
continuous variable into
a categorical variable.
It may not be simply fine to just put that
continuous predictor
directly into the model.
Notice if you have a binary or
a categorical predictor you do not have to
worry about this assumption.
Because, if you have a binary variable, a
binary predictor, you're only doing a 0/1.
You've got only two dots, therefore, and
any time you connect two dots it's
automatically a line.
If you have a categorical predictor,
you're going to be dummy coding it.
So you're going to have a series of 0/1s,
those are all going to make lines.
So this is only a worry when you have a
continuous predictor in
logistic regression.
I'm going to show you some real examples
with real data.
Various examples of where I've had to draw
linear in the logit plots.
This example was from a data set where the
outcome is heart disease.
The predictor that we're looking at here
called tobacco,
this is the number of cigarettes smoked
per day.
An I grouped the data set up into four
bins as well as ten bins just to give
us a, a sense of the relationship between,
the number of cigarettes per day and
the logit, of heart disease.
And again, I have to group people.
And what I'm graphing here is the, I'm
give,
graphing their mean cigarettes per day.
The mean cigarettes per day for
the group against the logit for that
group, the observed logit for that group.
What you can see here is that for this
particular variable,
the number of cigarettes per day, it does
not look linear in the logit.
The relationship between cigarettes per
day and our, the logit of
having heart disease appears curvolinear,
there appears to be a curved relationship.
In both of these graphics you can see it,
that there's sort of a curved relationship
here.
Why is that?
Well, think about the variable, cigarettes
per day.
You have a bunch of people who smoke zero
cigarettes per day.
And then you've got people increasing on,
on their cigarettes per day.
What you're seeing in this graphic here is
when you jump from being a non-smoker to
smoking, you know, some little amount per
day, there's a huge jump in your odds and
risk of getting heart disease.
There's a major steep jump, jump.
But then there's sort of diminishing
returns.
Once you're already a smoker, whether you
smoke a couple cigarettes per day, or, or
more, your risk does go up.
But it doesn't go up as steeply.
And then, when you go from kind of being a
moderate smoker to being a heavy smoker,
your risk also goes up, but it goes up
even less steeply.
So the relationship is really curved
rather than linear.
How might you account for this?
Probably the best way is to think about
cigarette smoking as
a categorical variable.
You might want to model this as
non-smokers versus light to moderate
smokers versus heavy smokers, and that
might be the best way to actually model
this, is that this might be a case where
it makes sense to treat tobacco smoking
cigarettes per day as a categorical
variable rather than continuous.
So that's an example that violated the
linear in the logit assumption.
Here is an example where we're actually
meeting the linear in the logit
assumption pretty well.
This was some data I had on women
athletes, and
the outcome variable here is low bone
mineral density.
So low skeletal strength.
It turns out that women athletes sometimes
don't menstruate normally and
if you don't have normal menses that
actually can reduce your,
your skeletal strength, your, your bone
mineral, bone mineral density.
So that, this was a data set looking at
that.
Again, I did two linear in the logit
plots, so
I'm getting a sense depending on how I bin
things, how many people per group,
that I'm getting the right relationship.
So I grouped it to about 12 bins as well
as five bins.
And you can see that there's of course
more local noise when you have 12 bins,
but the pattern looks pretty similar in
both cases.
I would say that this is pretty close to
fitting a line.
It's not a perfect line, but
it looks like it actually is reasonably
linear in the logit.
In both cases, you can imagine kind of
drawing the line again.
With lots of points, there's going to be
some local variability.
But essentially that's well fit by a line.
So in this case, our predictor variable
here is number of menses,
the number of menstrual periods per year.
So, we're, you know, normally sort of
around 12.
A lot of women athletes are having many
less than that.
And it turns out that there's a linear
relationship here as the number of
menstrual periods goes up.
From 0 all the way up to a normal of 12,
the chances the, or
the odds of getting low, having low bone
density go down.
And it, it appears to be well modeled that
it's linear, so
I could put the number of menstrual cycles
per year in as the predictor variable and
get an odds ratio for every one unit
increase in menstrual and menses.
How does that decrease my odds of getting
low bone mineral density.
This one seems reasonably modeled as a
linear variable.