Welcome to week four of HRP 261.
This week we're going to continue our
discussion of Logistic Regression.
So, last week I told you how to interpret
and estimate the alphas and
the betas from a logistic regression
model.
This week we're going to talk more about
the model over all.
What are some of the ways that you check
the model in terms of assumptions and
model fit?
I'm also going to tell you how to test for
confounding and
interaction within the framework of
regression, and those principles will
apply across many types of regression, not
just logistic regression.
So I'll throw in a couple of linear
regression analyses to illustrate that.
Now the teaser for this week.
This is a study we're going to get back to
in the last module for this week.
This was a study that was looking at what
are predictors of which women will get
their annual breast cancer screening as
they're supposed to.
So get the annual mammography.
This is a binary outcome because either
women were doing a good job on their
screening or they weren't.
And the authors thought that perhaps, if
you had a family history of breast cancer,
you might be more likely to go for your
annual screening.
They also thought that how much you
worried about breast
cancer might also impact the chances that
you would go for your annual screening.
But what's interesting here is that the
authors have thrown in a couple of
interaction terms, and we're going to be
talking about interactions this week.
So if you go down to the bottom here,
you'll notice there are two interaction
terms.
There is worry interacting with itself.
Another way to say that is that we have a
worry squared term.
We also have worry interacting with family
history.
In other words, the effect of worry on
your likelihood of getting annual
mammography might depend on whether you
are a high risk or low risk woman.
And we're going to worry less about the
significance here,
we're not going to pay so much attention
to, to statistical significance.
We're going to talk more about the affect
sizes.
When you have interacting terms in your
model, how do you present the odds ratios?
And in fact the way that the authors have
presented the odds ratios here
isn't quite right, because how, what does
it mean that your
worry squared has an odds ratio of 0.97,
or what does it mean that your
worry times family history interacting
term has an odds ratio of 0.98?
Well in fact really, there isn't a single
odds ratio for these terms.
The fact that there's interaction in the
model,
what that means is, is that there are
multiple effect sizes.
In other words, there are multiple odds
ratios.
There's more than one.
So there's more than one odds ratio for
family history.
Your, your odds ratio for family history
changes depending on your level of worry,
and similarly, your odds ratio for worry
changes depending on both your family
history and your level of worry.
So at different levels of worry,
an increase in worry will have a different
effect.
That's what we mean by a squared term.
We'll get back to this example.
And in the last module of this week, we're
going to have some
fun talking about how to calculate odds
ratios in the presence of interaction, and
how to report those correctly.