In this next module I'm going to tell you
about Conditional Logistic Regression,
which can be used when you have correlated
data and
you want to do within cluster comparisons.
So let me go back to an example that I
introduced in Unit Two of the course.
This is a simple example that we talked
about when we were talking about
McNemar's test.
So it was a one to one matched case
control study.
Each heart attack case was matched to a
control based on their age and
gender, and the exposure of interest was
diabetes.
Just to remind you, refresh your memory.
We these are what the,
the data looked like when we applied
McNemar's test to these data.
So what you're seeing here represents that
there were 144 matched case control pairs.
And 9 of those pairs, both the case and
the control had diabetes.
82 of those, of these pairs, neither of
them had diabetes.
It turns out that those cells, those
concordant cells are non
informative because they weren't identical
in terms of their diabetes.
The cells that are of interest are the
discordant pairs, the 37 and the 16.
So it turned out that 37 of the cases had
diabetes, where the control did not.
And in 16 pairs it was the control who had
diabetes, where the case did not.
We applied McNemar's statistics to these
data.
And remember McNemar's is just b minus c
squared, over b plus c.
Well b and c here are just the 37 and the
16.
So 37 minus 16 squared, divided by 37 plus
16, which is 53.
When you actually calculate that out you
get a chi-squared of 8.3.
This is a chi-squared with 1 degree of
freedom, so
this corresponds to a p value of 0.0039.
We can also calculate a McNemar's odds
ratio for
these data, which we get just by dividing
b by c.
So, 37 divided by 16.
That gives us a value of 2.3125.
So indeed, there is a,
an elevation in your risk of heart attack
if you have diabetes.
I also showed you back in Unit Two,
that McNemar's test is equivalent to
taking that same data and
stratifying on the data by pair, actually
making 144 strata.
Each of the strata only contains two
people, the pair.
But you can do that and
then you can apply Mantel-Haenszel
statistics to that stratified data.
And it turns out that
that's mathematically equivalent to the
McNemar's test.
So you can see that here I've actually
applied Mantel-Haenszel to
the to the stratify data.
I get a chi-square of 8.3.
I get the exact same p value of .0039.
I get the exact same odds ratio 2.3125.
That idea of stratifying on
pair is actually the basis of conditional
logistic regression.
So conditional logistic regression,
the basic idea is that we're going to be
stratifying on the cluster.
Which in some cases might be a pair, or it
can be larger than a pair.
But, you're going to be stratifying on a
cluster and comparing people or
observations within a cluster.
That's how we're accounting for the
correlation.
So I actually went ahead and
ran a conditional logistic regression on
this simple data set,
now of course we could just run McNemar's
test here, we don't need to do regression.
But imagine that there were other things
that we wanted to adjust for
with this data set.
We'd then have to run a conditional
logistic regression.
So here is the results.
Couple of things to notice.
So first of all, that the chi-square comes
out to 7.85.
The p value is 0.005.
And the odds ratio is 2.312.
You can see that the p-value and the
chi-square, and
the odds ratio are not identical to what
we got, from the McNemar's test, and
from the Mantel–Haenszel test.
So, what's happening in conditional
logistic regression,
mathematically, is just slightly
different.
Because we're now going back to doing
those likelihood estimation methods.
Since we're doing something different,
mathematically, we're going to get
slightly different answers.
But you'll notice how close those are to
the answer that we got from McNemar's
test, or from the Mantel–Haenszel test
applied to the stratified data.
One other thing to point out about the,
output here.
Notice, what's different about the output
that we've seen before from
logistic regression, is that I get my beta
coefficient.
But, under parameters, I don't get an
intercept.
So that's the other thing that you need to
understand about conditional logistic
regression, is that we are no longer going
to be trying to estimate the intercept.
And I'm going to show you that, what's
happening mathematically in just a,
a second here.
But conceptually what we're saying,
basically, is every pair, or
every cluster, every strata,
might have its own intercept, might have
its own baseline risk.
So in this particular data set, each pair
is defined by different ages and genders.
So it makes sense that if you're looking
at a pair that is 50 to 55 year old women,
that they're going to have a different
baseline risk for
heart attack than, say, if you're looking
at a pair of 75 year old men.
Right, so we're allowing each pair to have
its own, sort of,
baseline risk of heart attack.
We can't estimate it separately for
each pair, we don't have enough degrees of
freedom.
So what we're going to do instead is
create this conditional logistic
regression, which allows us to cancel out
the intercept essentially, and
not even bother to try to estimate it.
Well, that's generally fine, because in a
case-control study the intercept doesn't
mean a heck of a lot anyway, right.
So a lot of times we don't care about the
intercept, we just care about the beta or
the odds ratio.
And that's all we're going to get here.
Alright, so now I'm going to delve into
the mathematical details of
conditional logistic regression.
So this parts going to get a little mathy,
kind of similar to when we talked about
likelihoods before.
Just to remind you, what is a likelihood
function?
A likelihood function is the probably of
your data.
And what that was when we did regular
logistic regression.
It looked something like this.
So our likelihood function was equal to
each person,
each observation in our data set got one
term in the likelihood.
So, if you were a case.
If you were ha, someone who had the
outcome in the likelihood,
you got your probability of having the
outcome.
And it looks something like that.
Because you, in fact, were somebody who
had the outcome.
Everybody who didn't have the outcome
would get in the likelihood as
a function of their covariates.
Would get their probability of not having
the outcome.
because that's, in fact, what happened.
They didn't have the outcome.
And we would get a likelihood again with
one term and a likelihood for
every individual in the data set.
Now what's different about the likelihood
function for conditional logistic
regression is that you're going to get one
term in the likelihood for every cluster,
rather than one term for every individual,
one term for every strata.
And in this particular example where we're
talking about,
it's going to be one term for every pair.
So the idea is this, your likelihood is
going to be something multiplied together.
So again, we're going to have multiple
things multiplied together.
But the total number of things multiplied
together will be the total number of
clusters in your dataset, rather than
that's a little number of individuals.
Well what are these probabilities that go
into the likelihood?
Rather than modelling this straight
probability of somebody having an outcome
or not, we are instead going to model a
conditional probability.
So now go back to these little pictures I
was drawing.
So imagine here is a cluster of people.
They're, they're related somehow, and each
of these clusters, again,
is going to get one term in the
likelihood.
But the term is going to correspond to a
conditional probability.
So imagine that in this cluster, two
people get the outcome.
I'm going to circle them in a color you
can see here.
So imagine that two people get the outcome
and
the other three people don't get the
outcome.
The probability that we're going to put in
the likelihood is going to be
the probability that it's these exact two
people that get the outcome.
Out of the probability that any two out of
the five would have gotten the outcome.
In how many ways can two people out of
five get the outcome.
Well that's 5 choose 2.
There's 5 choose 2 different ways,
that's 2 out of 5 exactly could've come
out with the outcome.
So we're going to be modeling though, the
probability that it's these particular 2.
So maybe it turns out that the 2 people
that have the outcome they're
smokers you know they have poor diets.
And the 3 people who didn't get the
outcome live a healthy lifestyle and
were non-smokers.
If we plug into our model data about
smoking and
lifestyle, that's going to be reflected in
the beta coefficients that come out.
So, the terminal likelihood is going to
have something in the denominator where we
say, here's all the possible ways that two
out five people could've got the outcome.
And if I number these, let's say if I
number these people1, 2,
3, 4, and 5, just to give them like, ID
numbers here.
So, one possible thing that could have
happened, if I'm conditioning on two out
of five having the outcome, here's one
possible thing that could've happened.
So, it could have been that person that id
number 1, 1 get's the outcome,
and it could have been that person 2 gets
the outcome, and
the 3, 4, and 5, do not have the outcome.
So, that's one way that you could get two
out of five exactly having the outcome.
Now, to write out the probability of that,
you're actually going to have to write out
the probability.
The probability that one, that Person 1,
with all their characteristics gets the
outcome, that Person 2 gets the outcomes,
and then if 3 doesn't, and 4 doesn't, and
5 doesn't.
That's one possible outcome.
You're then going to add that to a term
that represents the probability that
you know, maybe 2 and 3 get the outcome,
4, 5, 1 do not.
And then, and so on.
There's going to be, you know, 5 choose 3
possibilities here.
All of those go in the denominator.
You're writing out all possible outcomes
that represent, here again, conditioning
on the fact that we're getting exactly 2
out of 5 to have the outcome.
Now what actually happened in your
dataset?
That's what goes in the numerator.
So what actually happened here is that
person 2 and person 4 got the outcome.
So in the numerator we would be doing the
probability that 2 gets the outcome,
4 gets the outcome, and then 5, 1, and 3
do not.
And again, that's going to be some
probability terms multiplied together, but
that's the general idea.
We're going to condition on all possible
outcomes that involve exactly two out of
five getting, having the outcome.
But what actually happened in my data set,
what goes in the numerator, is just one of
these terms that represents that it's 2
and 4 specifically who had the outcome.
Remember, we'll be filling in these
probabilities with something from
the logistic regression model.
Now, it's rather complicated to write out
that example that I just gave.
So let's now go back to the simpler
example where we're just
dealing with case control pairs, lot,
little bit less going on in that case.
And we can actually write out the
likelihood more easily for
the simpler case.
So back to our little example with case
control pairs.
Now our clusters just have two people in
them, and
one of the people got the outcome, because
it's case control pairs, so
we know one person got the outcome, the
other person didn't.
So now all we have to condition on in the
denominator is
what are all the possible ways that one
person could get the outcome out of two?
That's a little bit simpler, right?
Not too, too bad.
So we would put in the denominator the
probability that the case gets
the outcome, and the control doesn't.
And we would add to that, the other
possible thing though,
it could have been that the control got
the disease, and the case didn't.
That is another possible outcome that
involves one person getting the disease.
Of course, we know that it's the, it's the
case person who got the disease.
But remember that the probabilities that
go into this
are predicted probabilities from logistic
regression.
So, those aren't going to equal just what
actually happened.
So okay, in this case, that's our
denominator,
all the possible ways that one out of two
can get the outcome.
What actually happened in our dataset, of
course, was that it was the case that got
the outcome, and then the control did not.
And then of course, we're
going to be then plugging in all this,
the, the characteristics of the case, and
the controls, in some alphas and betas,
which I'll just do in a second.
But I just want to kind of motivate,
that's the general idea.
We're modeling some conditional
probability.
What's nice here is that because we have
things in the denominator and
the numerator, we're going to be able to
cancel some things out.
We're eventually going to be able to
cancel the intercept.
So that's kind of the general idea, but
now, what are these individual
probabilities.
I'm kind of writing them out very
generally here.
But what are the actual probability terms
that will go in the model?
So let's actually, specifically put those
in now.
So recall for the simple case, where we
just have a binary exposure,
you have diabetes or you don't, and a
binary outcome.
You are a case or you're not, you're a
control.
The probability terms are actually fairly
straightforward, and
we saw these in an earlier unit in the
course.
So case who has diabetes,
they get this probability of having the
disease in the outcome.
This is the probability of having the
disease if you have diabetes.
This is the probability of, of getting the
disease if you don't have diabetes.
So the beta is multiplied by 0 and goes
away.
This is the probability of getting the,
the disease, the outcome here,
if you have diabetes.
So we put a 1 in the numerator.
And this is the probability of not getting
the disease if you do not have diabetes,
so the beta, again, is multiplied by 0.
We get a 1 in the numerator.
You should kind of be familiar with these
different probability terms by now.
Let me now just actually apply this to
that example dataset of
diabetes and case control.
It's easier to apply it to a real example.
So what would the terms and
the likelihood actually look like for each
of these types of pairs?
So remember we had nine pairs where both
the case and the control had diabetes.
Since we're not incorporating any other
information about these people into our
model it's actually they're going to all
have the same term into likelihood.
There are going to be nine identical
terms.
Of course, if we were integrating other
information like age, and
weight, and so on then everyone would have
a different term in the likelihood, but
I'm trying to keep it simple here.
So what would the term in the likelihood
actually look like here.
So, again, it's a conditional probability
there's two possible ways that
one person could get the outcome here and
one person not get the outcome.
So it could be the case that it's the case
who has the outcome.
And remember, the case here has diabetes.
So here's the probability of getting the
outcome if you have diabetes.
And the case, indeed, has diabetes here.
So it's that probability term.
So that's the probability of the case
having the outcome.
We would multiply that by the probability
that the control does not get the outcome.
So the control is, the control in this
case though,
also has diabetes so they get the beta for
having diabetes, but
they get the probability of not having the
heart attack.
So it could have been that the case had
the heart attack and
the control did not, which was what
actually happened in our data, but
the other possible outcome was that it
could have been that it was
the control who had the heart attack and
the case who did not.
That, that theoretically could have
happened.
[NOISE]
So
this represents that case has the heart
attack, control does not.
And this one represents the case does not,
and
the control has the MI, the heart attack.
Now, notice though, because there's this
very simple example, the case and
the control both have diabetes, so
in fact, the terms, these two terms, are
identical.
Right?
You can see that they're, they're,
they're just the same.
We put in the numerator, the what actually
happened which is what the,
the, the case that the MI.
And that control did not.
But if you start to look carefully here,
what you'll notice, which is kind of nice,
is that all of these terms are exactly
identical.
Because, again this is a simple situation.
So, this is going to cancel, this is
going to cancel, this is going to cancel.
This whole likelihood term goes to 1.
So we're going to get 9, 1s in the
likelihood.
Those aren't going to count at all.
So we turned up that this is also true,
you could work this out for
the situation where the pairs, where the
pair, they both did not have diabetes.
We will also get identical terms, in the
likelihood that we'll also reduce to one.
So, just as with McNemar's test,
the concordant pairs contribute nothing to
the likelihood.
So that's kind of not surprising.
And it's good.
It's kind of a nice check that that works
out as we would hope it would.
So now, let me turn to the discordant
pairs, which are,
of course, where the uh,interesting
information lies.
Alright.
So what if we're talking about the 37
discordant
pairs where the case have diabetes but the
control did not?
What would the likelihood term look like
there?
Alright, so what's the prob,
what's the probability that it's the case
who gets the heart attack?
Since the case here has diabetes,
they are going to have an, a beta in their
likelihood terms.
So this is this is the probability that
the case has the outcome, and then
the control does not.
Now the control here does not have
diabetes, so
they gotta term that's just 1 over 1 plus
e raised to alpha.
Then we add that to the other possibility.
It could have been a case that the case
was not the one who got the heart attack.
So they get a 1 in the numerator,
they still have the beta because they have
diabetes, but
it was the control who got the heart
attack.
The they get e alpha over 1 plus e alpha.
That was the other way that one of the two
people could have had the outcome.
What actually happened, of course, is this
one.
The case had the heart attack, and the
control did not.
And what you'll notice here is that a lot
of things are going to cancel, but
not everything will cancel.
So I will go through the cancellations,
the things that do cancel, in just a
minute here.
But not everything cancels, unlike with a
concordant pairs.
Now, what about the case where it's the
control who has diabetes and
the case who does not have diabetes?
What would change if I were to make this
into the likelihood term for
those 16 here?
So the only things that would change is
that the case would not get beta anymore.
So this is the probability now of the case
getting the outcome.
The control of course, would have the
beta.
This is the probability of the control not
getting the outcome and so and so
forth, we'd have to stick in some betas
here.
And then in the numerator this beta would
go away.
And we would put in a beta for the control
subject.
So that's what term would look like for
the 16 pairs where the control had
diabetes, but the case did not.
Now, this, of course, would be multiplied
together 16 times,
because there's 16 pairs that look like
that.
So now we can simplify these further.
But I've added a little subscript I just
want to point out here.
I've added a subscript to all the
intercept terms.
So I have, for every strata, every pair
here, I'm allowing each pair to have its
own intercept, which I'm representing here
as alpha sub one, alpha sub two, etcetera.
And I can do that,
because I know that the intercepts are
eventually going to cancel out.
And therefore, that we're not going to
have to estimate them.
Because, clearly, it would be impossible
for
us to estimate 53 different intercepts.
But we can allow each strata to have its
own baseline risk, its own baseline
odds here, its own intercept, because
we're going to cancel them in a minute.
I, I notice I have a typo on this line, so
this top one represents the 16 discordant
strata where it was the control who had
diabetes.
The bottom one here represents the 37
discordant strata where
the case had diabetes.
The nice thing, these terms look really,
really complicated and awful.
But you're going to see that a lot of
things are going to start to cancel.
So, first of all, if you look at the
numerator and
the denominator here, all of these terms
cancel.
They all in the numerator and
denominator, these fractions have the
exact same denominator.
So, all of these denominators cancel.
So we can simplify this quite quickly to
something much nicer, which is this e
raised to alpha sub j, which is just the
pair-specific intercepts and
then in the denominator, all we're left
with is the following.
So that one's quite easy.
It reduces down quite nicely and
you'll see there's even more we can cancel
in just a second.
For this bottom one, again all of these
cancel and
we're left with only e raised to alpha sub
i plus beta,
e raised to alpha sub i plus beta plus e
raised to alpha sub i.
And again, I mul, the, the sub i's and
sub j's just mean it's like, everyone can
have their own intercept.
Every pair can have their own intercept.
Well, guess what.
Things are going to simplify even further,
because if you're looking at this
carefully,
you can see now we can actually cancel out
the intercepts.
So let me go ahead and cancel out the
intercepts.
So I've just copied over from the previous
slide,
and this, this, and this will all cancel.
We're left with just a one over e plus,
one over e raised to beta here, and
then this, this, and this will cancel.
So we're left with e raised to beta, over,
1 plus e raised to beta here.
This one we're left with just 1 over, e
raised to beta plus 1.
So that's it.
That's all the terms reduced to.
So they end up to being pretty simple in
the end.
Again, this was just a case where we have
a single binary exposure.
Well, we have 16 terms that look like this
in our likelihood,
we have 37 terms that look like this in
our likelihood, likelihood.
So this is our final likelihood.
Our likelihood is a function of beta.
And there's 53 terms in it.
Now, of course, we also have multiplied a
whole bunch of 1s, but
I haven't bothered to put in the 1s for
the concordant pairs.
Well, we could take this likelihood
function, and actually, it's,
because it's a very simple case, we could
do the maximization ourself.
I'll just walk you through it for fun.
Of course, you don't really have to do any
of these by hand.
But that's, if we wanted to now solve for
beta, it's fairly straightforward to solve
for beta here, to maximize this function
as a function of beta.
We're going to first take the log of the
likelihood to make it easier to
take the derivative.
So I've done that here,
take the log of the likelihood and then we
take the derivative.
We did this in an earlier unit.
I'll refer you back to that if you want to
go through all the details of taking the
derivatives.
Take the derivative.
Set it equal to 0, and then we simply
solve for beta.
And all that you kind of walk it through
that your own if you're interested.
Again, I'm not expecting you to actually
be able recreate this for this class.
What you end up with at the end of the
day, though,
is that beta is equal to the natural log
of 37 over 16 or
equivalent, equivalently, e raised to beta
is equal to 37 over 16.
Well guess what?
That's just the odds ratio from McNemar's
test.
So we solved it out and we are,
we get back exactly what we already know
should be the odds ratio.
So that's our little check that, hey,
this whole method actually does give us
the right data back at the end of the day.
Of course, you can't do it by hand if it's
much more complicated than this, but
it's always nice to do a very simple
example by hand and
just convince yourself that in fact, you
get out what you think you should get out.
And indeed, it works out here.
That's the idea of the conditional
likelihood.
And of course, it's, it can get really
complicated to write out pretty fast.
And what the computer is actually doing is
some kind of version of that in the,
in the background some kind of algorithm
that approximates that in the background.
So let me now just jump, that's the math,
and now let me jump to a, actually
applying this to some, some real data that
we've already seen in an earlier module.
So remember that we have this example of a
hypothetical eye trial.
So, this was hypothetical trial 1.
So remember this is a one where different
people had different treatments in
each eye, so we're going to be thinking
about within person comparison.
So 50 patients with bilateral eye-disease
got a drug in one eye and
a placebo in the other eye.
We're keeping the example simple.
So success of positive outcome here is if
you improve by more than 50%.
The negative outcome is you did not.
Now, we can check to say, I didn't show
you this earlier, but
we can actually check and say, are the
eyes correlated?
We, that's, that, that, we like to know
that in terms of their, who improved, and
which eyes improved, and which eyes didn't
improve.
Was there correlation within a person?
We're not guaranteed that there would be.
We would expect there to be, there doesn't
have to be.
So I can actually check that in my data.
So I've done that now.
Are the eyes actually correlated?
Is eye one and eye two in a, within a
given person, correlated?
So we can just run a Pearson's correlation
coefficient to check that.
And I did that for the 50 people.
Each person has two eyes, of course.
And here are the correlation coefficients.
So we get a correlation coefficient of
about 0.36.
It's statistically significant.
We care less about that than the,
just the fact that that's a fair, fairly
high correlation.
You know, not terribly high, but
reasonably, you know,
there is definitely some correlation
between eyes here.
Which means, if we ignore it,
it is really, it's definitely going to
affect the results.
Now, here is the actual outcomes of the
trial.
I, we've previously analyzed these with
the McNemar's test.
The p-value comes out to be 0.029.
I'm now going to use these data in the
regression context.
We actually could just stop at McNemar's
test, but to illustrate for
you conditional logistic regression,
I'm going to plug these data into the
regression context.
Of course you'd probably be adjusting for
other things to make it even worthwhile to
do a regression.
But it's, we're just going to keep it
simple here.
So first of all, though, I'm going to
imagine that I took these data and
I didn't know about conditional logistic
regression.
I forgot to consider the correlation and
I just plugged this into an ordinary
logistic regression.
I could do that.
My outcome is improved or not.
My predictor here is, if you're a treated
eye or
not, and if I just ignore the correlations
between eyes in the same person.
We're at a regular logistic regression.
This is incorrect.
Here's the results that I get.
So you can see that it's a regular
logistic regression because we
have an intercept which of course will not
be estimated in a conditional logistic.
Notice that we get, here's our beta we get
a p-value of about 0.07.
So that's very similar to what we got when
we ran a chi-square, and
incorrect chi-square on these data.
So this is the incorrect analysis our
p-value is too high because we've
ignored the correlation.
And when you ignore correlations from
within cluster comparisons,
your p-value ends up to being too high.
I then took these same data and applied
conditional logistic regression,
which is not hard to do in the computer.
Most statistical packages will do this
very easily for you.
All you have to do is specify that you
want to stratify on pair in this case.
Or in this case, stratify on person,
because they're,
your eyes are correlated within a person.
So you'd stratify on, say, the subject's
ID number.
And when I do that,
I do the correct conditional logistic
regression, here's what I get.
I get, notice, no intercept, because it's
conditional logistic regression.
I get my beta coefficient, and I get my
p-value.
Notice, now that my p-value is
statistically significant,
the p-value from McNemar's was 0.029.
So I don't get exactly the same p-value,
but they're extremely close.
Again, McNemar's is a little bit different
mathematically than doing
a likelihood estimation method.
Applying conditional logistic regression
really is pretty straightforward.
The interpretation is the essentially the
same as before.
We're going to get odds ratios out.
You'd want to do you can't really do a
logit plot within strata, so
sometimes we might just do an you know,
we might do a logit plot where we don't
account for the correlation,
just being able to plot something if
you've got a continuous predictor.
But you actually can't do it anyway a
logit plot within strata that's not
going to be possible but you can do your
regular logit plots.
The thing that's really most affected by
getting this, accounting for
the correlations is not the magnitude of
the association, but the p-values.
So we want to get the correct p-values,
but
that's not going to affect the logit plot
too much.
So everything else is kind of the same as
we've talked about with regular
logistic regression.
But this is the way that you can adjust
for correlation.
Now, just to point out here that
conditional logistic regression,
think about the way the likelihood is
made.
Every term in the likelihood is comparing
only people within a cluster.
So all conditional logistic regression is
doing is comparing within-clusters.
There are no between-cluster comparisons.
Therefore, if everybody in your cluster
has the same value for
the predictor, you can't do this.
So if everybody in the cluster was treated
with the same treatment,
you can't do a conditional logistic
regression.
So that hypothetical eye trial 2 that I
talked about,
where everybody got treatment in, or a
placebo in both eyes there would be no,
you couldn't apply conditional logistic
regression to those data.
And similarly this we generally don't use
conditional logistic regression for
repeated measures data because if it's the
same person over time,
unless all of the predictors you care
about are changing over time you know,
the same person over time is going to have
the same gender,
they're going to have the same general
characteristics over time.
So, so generally we're not using
conditional logistic regression for
repeated measures data.
[BLANK_AUDIO]