So last week, I told you how to plot your
observed survival function from
your data using Kaplan–Meier method
[SOUND].
Well a lot of times, we'd actually like to
be able to plat that
hazard function that we observe in our
data.
But it's difficult to do it's really hard
to directly plot that hazard function.
So what we tend to do is we use some
alternative plots that give it
the hazard function indirectly and that's
the cumulative hazard function.
And the log-log plot.
I'm going to tell you, mathematically, now
where those come from and then
we're going to apply those, practically,
to real data in some upcoming modules.
All right, so this slide might scare you
just a little bit,
I do not expect you to remember anything
from this slide.
All I am trying to show you here is that
we have now talked about this density
function, the cumulative density, the
survival function and the hazard function.
There are all these function that are
related to one another and so
if you have one of those functions, you
can get any one of the others.
I kind of made that point in the last
module.
So just for fun, I've put all the formulas
here,
I don't expect it will apply these
formulas,
the point is just that if you have one,
you can get all the others [SOUND].
The only one that is going to [SOUND] be
of particular interest to us because it
relates directly to these parts is this
one, where we can
get the survival function from the hazard
or the hazard function from the survival.
The one below it.
I'm going to do the derivations offer
survival from hazard, so this particular
relationship turned out to be useful
because of the fact that it can't directly
plot the hazard but we can directly plot
the survival function using capin-mayo.
So again I'm going to zero element just as
one formula.
I don't expect you to be able to derive
anything, but
I'm going to show you using this formula
why the negative log of
the Kaplan-Meier function, for example, is
equal to the cumulative hazard.
This is a particular plot we're going to
need.
So I'll just derive that for you, show you
that that's true, you don't,
again, don't have to stress out about this
particular one.
I'll just show you just for fun, though.
We have talked about the exponential
[SOUND],
which is a little bit easier to deal with.
So if, you have the exponential function,
if you have,
you have the hazard function, and you know
the hazard function is constant,
which makes it an exponential, so I could
write it like this,
if you know you're at an exponential and
the hazard function is constant,
notice I've dropped a little u here, I've
dropped the time bit.
Well, if I integrate from zero to t just
each, I'm going to get e
raised to the negative ht which we notice
the survival function for an exponential.
So, that might just make you to feel
comfortable that at least something you
expect to come out does in deed come out
of this formula [SOUND].
It's a little [SOUND] more complicated if
the hazard function is changing over time.
Because that makes the interval here a
little bit more complicated.
But, what I want to show you is that if
you have the [SOUND],
you have your Kaplan–Meier curve, your
estimated survival curve.
You know we've looked at those kaplan,
Kaplan–Meier curves last week.
That's not the best drawn [SOUND] one but
something.
Where you get [SOUND] like that.
If you have that, it turns out you can
take those survival probability estimates
everywhere where you're dropping the curve
here and if you just take the negative log
[SOUND] of those values whatever those
probabilities are and you plot those.
So put negative log of the survival,
[SOUND],
against time, you're going to get the
cumulative hazard function.
You can show that mathematically.
So let me give you some examples.
So again, this plot falls directly out of
this relationship here.
So all I did was I took that formula on
the last page and
I took a log of both side because,
remember this was e,
this was e, e raised to this quantity e
raised to negative of this quantity.
[SOUND] So if I take a log of both size, I
get rid of the exponential [INAUDIBLE] and
put the log over here and then this was
negative.
So I taken negative to get rid of the
So what is this formula right here?
This is the cumulative hazard [SOUND].
So if I take negative log of the survival
function,
I'm going to get the cumulative hazard
[SOUND], so
this will be a cumulative hazard and over
time if I plot that.
If I have a constant hazard, it's going to
just be a straight line, so
this is useful because now, I can take the
negative log survival function.
I can plot that and most standard
statistical packages will plot that for
you at the click of the button, you don't
even really have to do any thinking here,
you just ask for the negative log survival
[SOUND] plot.
If, it turns out that you look at that
plot and it looks to have straight line,
then you knew that your hazard function is
probably something close to constant.
So you going to end up with a straight
line, if your hazard function is constant.
And you can see that here because if I
have a constant hazard function, and
I integrate from 0 to t, again I'm
going to get just c times t.
So I'm going to get, the integral will be
a straight line.
However, if the hazard function is
something that's increasing over time,
like the Y that we've talked about where K
is greater than 1,
then, you're going to get something that's
curve ups, upward.
So when you do that plot, the negative log
revival you going to get something that's
curved upwards and you can just see that
here, so if I integrate for
example CT, that's clearly one that's
increasing over time.
So, if I integrate from zero to t of ct,
I'm going to get ct squared.
So, obviously that's going to be curved
[SOUND] upwards because you're,
it's a quadratic.
It's increasing with time.
Finally, if the hazard function is
decreasing over time,
like a Weibull function where k is less
than one, then it,
we're going to end up with a cumulative
hazard function that's curve downwards.
You can see that for
example that if c divided by t is a, for
hazard function it's decreasing over time.
If I iterate from 0 to t, I get z log t
that's going to be decreasing over time.
So it's going to be, curve downwards.
So you can get these negative log plots
and look at them and have some sense of
what the [UNKNOWN] did, what the hazard
function is doing overtime.
So let me just give you a break example of
that.
So remember we had some data from a
pregnancy study last week.
38 women who had a treatment and were then
trying to get pregnant.
They followed from upto two years and
we saw that roughly the hazard rate seemed
to be pretty constant overtime, roughly.
That implies that an exponential model for
these data should be a good fit.
So, this was the Kaplan-Meier Curve.
So, here are my survival probabilities
[SOUND] as estimated,
as observed in my data.
And we sometimes write it like this with a
little hat.
So, that's what we've actually observed in
our data.
I've got all these little survival
probabilities that we
calculated last week.
Now, what if I want to plot the hazard
function for these data?
It turns out to not be that easy to do.
Now, some people have written macros and
things to try to get this I did apply a
MACRO to try to get it to constant,
that the hazard function here, to kind of
see what it looks like over time.
It was kind of a complicated MACRO but
what I get out actually makes a fair
amount of sense.
It looks fairly constant as we're
expecting and puts it at right about 9%
and remember we calculated the average
incidence rate here with about 10%,
so that, it seems about right a little
higher toward the end.
[SOUND] But again not easy to get that
plot.
But what is easy to get is once you've
made your Kaplan–Meier cur,
mei meier curve, you can just ask for your
negative log of your Kaplan–Meier curve.
Most computer packages do it very easily
and here is what I get for this data.
Notice it has nine points because there
was nine separate estimates on
my Kaplan–Meier curve.
We take negative log of those and then
plot those against time.
And you 'll see that it indeed looks like
a nice straight line so
that would indicate that this probably
does have a constant hazard.
And again, that comes from this
relationship here.
This straight line indicates a constant
hazard function [SOUND].
Another thing that's going to turn out to
be useful that we can use
the Kaplan-Meier estimates.
We can start taking logs of our
Kaplan-Meier estimates.
And get some information about the
underlying hazard functions is that when
we get to the situation where we want to
compare two groups, and
to say if the hazard functions of two
groups, what's their relationship?
Are they parallel?
Are they proportional?
We can do something called a log log plot.
I'm going to do the proof for
you on the next slide for those of you who
want to see it.
It is absolutely optional.
But again, it comes out of that same
direct relationship between a hazard and
a survival.
So, we haven't got to the case yet were I
need to show this, but
I'm going to tell you there are,
when we do a lot of these parametric
regression models and also Cox regression.
One of the assumptions is going to be that
we're going to assume that no
matter what the hazard functions are, so
here's the hazard function for
group one, here's the [SOUND] hazard
function for group two.
We're going to assume that those functions
over time.
For those two groups are parallel.
And the reason we're going to want to
assume that is because we want to
calculate a single hazard ratio,
which is the ratio of the hazard rates
[SOUND] for those two groups.
But if the hazards are changing over time
[SOUND], that means that
the hazard ratio itself could change over
time, and that gets too complicated.
We'll deal with that eventually, but
we would like to, we'd prefer that it just
be one hazard ratio that we can report.
So as long as these hazard rates are
reasonably kind of parallel over time,
it's probably reasonal, reasonable to
report a single hazard ratio.
If the hazard rates for whatever reason
turn out to not be parallel over time.
So here's the hazard rate for
group [SOUND] one over time and here's the
hazard rate for group two over time.
You can imagine a situation where two
groups are crossing like this.
Then it wouldn't make sense to report a
single hazard ratio because you
can see that ha, group one has a way
higher hazard at the beginning, but
then has a much smaller hazard at the end.
So there isn't a single hazard ratio
there.
So one of the things that we're going to
need to be able to evaluate, the very
important for a lot of the regression
models we're going to be talking about,
is something called the proportional
hazards assumption.
And is this is just saying that if that
assumption is met that
the hazard functions for the two group are
reasonably parallel.
Since it's hard to directly draw those
hazard functions from out data,
it's hard to evaluate this proportional
hazards assumption directly.
However, it turns out that we already
talked about the negative log in
the survival plot.
That's the cumulative hazard function.
Turns out if you take one more log of that
and you plot the log,
negative log of the Kaplan–Meier estimate
for
one group and another group, here's this
log negative log.
And again, this is a plot you can get in a
click of a button in
most standard statistical packages.
You don't have to think too hard to get
this, but
the computer [SOUND] will give it to you.
It turns out that if the log, negative
log, of the survival functions,
if those are parallel, then it's tr,
the case that the underlying hazard
functions are also parallel.
Since we can't directly plot the hazard
functions,
we instead plot the long negative log of
the survival functions for
the different groups and we look in to see
whether or not those are parallel.
So this is going to be a very important
plot that we're going to use when we're
doing regression and we're going to
particularity talk a lot about it.
When we talk about Caulk's regression,
which is sometimes also called
proportional hazard regression.
So this assumption is obviously very
important for that.
Alright for
those of you who would like me to walk you
through the proof of why the log negative
logs being parallel guarantees you that
the hazard functions are parallel.
I will now show you that if you want to
fast forward over that part of
the [SOUND], of the module that is
actually optional.
Alright, just for fun, if you like to see
proof stand out I am
going to prove to you now that if two
hazard functions are parallel.
Their, their log negative log plots will
also be parallel.
So starting with the second we have two
hazard functions.
I'm going to call one of the hazard
functions for
group' i' each' i' of' t' that's rare
hazard [SOUND] function over time if' j'
of' t' is a second group,' j' group,' j's
hazard function over time.
If group-i's function is always the same
distance from group-j's function we
can just multiply by a constant which I'm
calling HR fit here for hazard ratio but
imagine that's just number [SOUND].
So the proportional hazard's assumption
would say that there is a single hazard
ratio, a single constant that describes
the distance between two hazard curves.
So lets say i, edge i t [SOUND] looks like
that and h j t looks like that.
If they're parallel over time we can
calculate a single hazard ratio that
describes they're always going to be
parallel, so this equation will be true.
Alright, so then if this is true, I can
then refer back to
the relationship between the survival
function and the hazard function.
So the survival for j will just be equal
to e raised to negative of this
integral from zero to t of the hazard
function for j.
I then can do the same thing for the
survival function for
i, except remember the hazard function for
i is a function of the one for j.
So I am now going to plug in for each i of
t for the hazard function of group i,
I am going to plug in the hazard ratio
times the hazard function for j.
So now we only have one unknown.
The hazard function for j that we're
dealing with.
I can go one step further now and
just recognize that I can take a constant
out of an integral.
So it, the hazard ratio is just a
constant.
I'm going to pull that out of the
integral.
Just a little bit of math there.
I can go one step further then, and also
pull the hazard ratio out of the power.
So e raised to hr times something is the
same as e raised to
that something raised to hr.
So, I'm just doing a little bit of
mathematical rearrangement here.
I can show therefore that the survival
function for i is equal to
the survival function for j raised to hr.
And why the survival function for j?
Where did this come from?
Well, this quantity right here.
That's raised to the power hr is this
quantity right here.
So this is equal to the survival function
for j.
So I've just replaced that quantity with
the survival function for j.
And now we've shown that the survival
function for
i Is equal to the survival function for j
raised to the hazard ratio, this constant.
That's true as long as their hazard
functions are parallel.
Alright, but then we can go even a little
bit further.
So now, to get rid of that power, we don't
like power.
So we can take a log of both sides.
That will get rid of that power.
So I take a log of the survival function
for i and then I take the log of
the survival function for j, raise to the
hazard ratio power.
Well that hr can come down in front
because the logs you can get rid of
the powers.
So, the log of the survival function for
i is equal to hr times the log of the
survival function for j [SOUND].
going to go one step further here and then
take the log, negative log of the survival
function for I just bear with me to show
you, I'll show you where this is going.
So we take the log, negative and we can
gate both sides and
then take the log of both sides of this
equation.
So I get the log negative log of the
survival function for i, is equal to
the log of negative HR times the log of
the survival function for j [SOUND].
All right, well, keep going a little bit
further,
the reason we take another log here is
that we can if we take a log of
our product that's equal to the sum of
logs.
So, this one says the same, but then this
becomes the log of
HR which is just a constant plus the log
negative log of the survival curve for
j the survival function for j.
So notice now we have the log negative log
of the survival curve for
group i is equal to a constant because the
log of a constant is still a constant,
plus the log, negative log, of the
survival curve for j.
So that tells you that the log-negative
log plots should now be parallel and
they'll differ by this constant log of HR.
So that is the proof, there if the log
negative log plots are parallel,
then the hazard function, underlying
hazard functions are parallel.
So we are going to apply this to some real
data in some upcoming examples,
with a few more explanations here for
those who need a little more tips on the
math here [SOUND].
We're going to then apply this to a some
upcoming examples, and
I'll just give you an example of a log
negative log plot.
Plot just so you'll [INAUDIBLE] to
recognize these.
So these, these are some data comparing a
treated group
here to a control group here.
And [SOUND] this is showing you the log
negative plots of [INAUDIBLE] log
negative log survival plots of those two
groups.
Again the survival plots were just a
Kaplan-Meier plots.
We look at those log, negative log parts
we are looking to see whether or
not they are parallel.
With real data, of course, it's never
going to be perfectly parallel.
I would say that these data aren't bad.
One of the groups has many events occur
very early on and
there is no, kind of no more data.
But they look pretty parallel while they
certainly cross over and
we are going to talk a lot more about
interpreting these log, log plots
in a future module but I just wanted to
sort of a mathematical background.
So that you know where these log-log plots
come from.
[BLANK_AUDIO]