In this next module,
I'm going to tell you about different
strategies that you can use to
select the variables that are going to go
in your final prediction model.
So, first of all, before we even talk
about variable selection,
the first step of model building, of
course, is to understand your data.
To know what variables you have in there.
To understand their distributions.
To make sure you know how much missing
data that you have.
And that you've done something to deal
with it.
It's going to be very important to impute
missing data,
as you're going to see in a minute.
You need to decide on how you're going to
be modeling your predictors.
Are you going to be modeling them as
categorical, as standardized variables,
as continuous variables, all the things
we've talked about.
You'll probably want to consider some data
reduction.
So maybe your,
some of the variables are going to be too
hard to measure clinically.
And so therefore, they wouldn't be great
for a clinical prediction model.
Or maybe you apply, there might be some
cases where it's even worth apply,
applying some formal data reduction
techniques,
like principal components analysis.
But somehow you're going to get your
variables down to a more manageable set.
And then there's a lot of different ways
we can approach model building, and
everybody has slightly different
preferences.
So, you know, it's really great to read
the literature and
see what different people do, but I'm
going to give you some general strategies
that are typically used just to get you
started.
And so you might choose to do your
prediction modeling with some kind of
manual selection, as opposed to an
automated model building procedure.
So, you know, a typical thing that people
might do is they might do,
start with some kind of univariate screen.
So you might say, well, all the p-values
we saw in the delirium example,
that if the p-values were greater than
0.15, we, in univariate models,
we're just going to eliminate those
variables.
So some way to, again, get that candidate
set of predictors down to a smaller set,
before we do any further modeling.
So that's very typical, you probably
want to also use some clinical
judgment there, about what variables to
move forward.
So then, you're going to enter any
significant or
near significant variables from the
univariate screen,
you're going to put them together into
some kind of multivariate model.
Again, as they did in that delirium
example.
And, you know, especially if we're doing
manual selection,
you're going to use some clinical judgment
about which variables to move forward.
And if there are highly correlated
predictors that are essentially measuring
the same thing, you're probably going to
want to drop one of them and
not enter all, both of those forward.
So there's going to be some judgment that
you make here.
Then you're going to put all of those
variables,
again you're putting all those variables
into a multivariate model,
making some judgments.
And then once you have that, that big
multivariate model, then you're
going to start manually pruning the
nonsignificant variables from the model.
And people will use different criteria.
They might the prune the ones that are
greater than 0.10,
as we saw in the delirium example.
Sometimes people will choose 0.05.
But you're going to get rid of the
variables that aren't significant, or, or
not, at least, near significantly related
to the outcome.
And there might be some iteration between
these different steps,
if you're doing this manually.
At the end of the day, you're going to
come out with some kind of final model.
Of course, you're going to need to
validate that model, and
that's going to be true in all of these,
when we're building prediction models,
we're going to need to validate.
Now I'll just tell you that, in validating
the model,
a lot of the internal validation methods,
which make, reuse the data basically,
will involve you having to repeat your
entire model building strategy again.
You won't really have to repeat the
univariate screen because that will come
out the same every time.
But any kind of multivariate model and
you'll have to repeat, in selection
procedures, you'll have to repeat again.
If you've choose, chosen to do a manual
selection procedure in
your model building, that means you'd have
to go through those steps again.
And so, sometimes if you're doing some
kind of the internal validation techniques
where you have to run through multiple
iterations of this, that can,
can be a little bit more work.
So just realize that one of the reasons
that you'll often see people will
choose automated selection procedures for
their variables is for this very reason.
That the validation step involves you
re-running the whole modeling,
model selection procedure on new sample.
And so that can be quite difficult if
you've done manual selection, but
still, there are arguments for
doing manual selection, because again, it
builds in more clinical judgement.
There's you know, the, there has some
advantages as well.
But you know, commonly you will see that
people will use some kind of
automated selection procedure, especially
if they're going to be
doing internal validation where they have
to reselect the model multiple times.
So how do those work?
So basically you're going to probably be,
you might be running some kind of
univariate screen.
Sometimes people will not run a univariate
screen,
they'll just choose a set of predictors
and move them all forward.
But usually we're going to be pruning out
at least some of the variables based on
clinical judgement and what things are
highly correlated, and
may, maybe measuring the same thing.
We're going to cover the candidate say,
set of predictors.
And then we're going to put them into an
automated selection procedure in
your computer.
And, there's different ones, backward,
forward, stepwise, best subsets.
Most common statistical packages will have
all of those built in.
So, you run your regression using
automated selection.
Your computer basically chooses the best
set of predictors.
However, these automated selection
procedures have a bunch of
drawbacks we're going to talk about.
You're definitely going to need to
validate your model.
And again, that may involve you going back
and
rerunning those automated selection
procedures on multiple samples.
Now for example, on multiple bootstrap
samples from your original sample.
So let me take a minute here and
talk a little bit more about the automated
selection procedures.
They have some important drawbacks that
you should be aware of.
First of all, there're multiple different
types they come out to
be pretty similar as I'll show you in an
example in a few minutes.
But forward just means that you're, the
way that the model is built is that
you start with an empty model and you add
variable once at a time, and
keep them in if they meet some p-value
criteria.
Say, p is less than 0.05 or maybe p is
less than 0.10.
However, you want to set that backward,
starts with all the variables in
the model and then prunes them out if the
p-value is too high.
Stepwise does both of those things, so
it's more iterative, it puts some in,
takes some out, depending on the p-values.
So, all of those are available in most of
your major statistical packages,
and they tend to give fairly similar
results, although not identical.
Now the problem with automated selection
procedures,
they have a number of drawbacks.
And in fact, if you're doing explanatory
modeling,
I'll recommend that you don't use them at
all.
When we're trying to do explanatory
modeling, and
we're really trying to get at causal
relationships.
These just have so many problems that I
think that I'd recommend you
always do some kind of manual model
selection procedure.
Here are some of the problems with the
automated selection procedures.
So, what you're doing is you are weeding
through a large set of potential predictor
variables and a large set of potential
combinations of those variables.
That is going to mean that you will have
chance findings.
Your type 1 error will be high when you're
doing these automated selection
procedures.
I'll show you an example in a minute where
we can guess that the,
the type 1 error rate was about 16% with
automated selection
procedures in a particular simulation,
I'll show you.
So there, the p-values, your p-values are
going to be underestimated, so
your type 1 error is going to be much
higher.
So if you use a p-value cut off of 0.05,
the true type 1 error might be 16%,
the true significance level might be 16%.
So your p-values are going to be much too
small.
You're also going to over estimate your
effect sizes.
So all your betas are going to be biased a
little bit too high.
You're going to be a little bit overly
optimistic.
And also you're going to be overfitting
your model,
which just means that you are fitting to
all the little quirks in your data.
Which means if you calculate something
about how well does your model fit your
data points, it's going to look like it
fits them better than it does.
It's going to look like the model is more
accurate than it actually is.
So you're going to get model overfitting.
The underestimation of p-values and
the overestimation of effect sizes, those
are important.
We most read when we talk about prediction
models, about the overfitting part.
But we're going to try to, in some cases,
to correct also for
the overestimation of the effect sizes.
Because all of these things are going on,
it's absolutely important that we
validate.
If you're going to use automatic selection
procedures,
you absolutely, absolutely must validate,
either an internal validation or
an external validation.
And you should also be aware that there
are some
modern techniques that are being applied
to automatic selection procedures.
That are slight modifications that can
actually improve all of these things.
So, reduce the chances of type 1 errors.
Shrink the effect sizes down to more,
reasonable effect sizes.
And, also correct for over-fitting.
So one of those modifications that you can
use is something called shrinkage.
And so, the basic steps are the same at
the beginning.
You're going to come up with some
candidate set of predictors,
based on either clinical judgment,
univariate screen,
some combination of those.
Then you can apply an automated selection
procedure with shrinkage.
And all shrinkage is, is it's this attempt
to shrink your
beta coefficients to adjust for the fact
that they're too big.
So one very easy way is to apply what's
called a shrinkage factor.
And that would say something like,
we're going to multiply all of our beta
coefficients by 0.8 in order to adjust for
the fact that they're a little bit
overestimated.
So they're going to get a little bit
smaller and a little bit closer to 0.
Estimating that shrinkage factor takes a
little bit of work.
But applying it to all the betas is just a
multiplication thing, so
that's not too hard.
Penalized maximum likelihood is a way of
shrinking the coefficients as you
estimate them.
So, all this means is, remember that the
way we're running say,
logistic regression, is we're fitting some
kind of likelihood.
And what you can do is to the likelihood
or the, the negative 2 log likelihood,
which is actually what we often look at,
we can subtract some kind of penalty, or
add some kind of penalty to that.
And that penalty term will then
automatically shrink the coefficient.
So your beta coefficients will come out
smaller than they would have had you
not applied that penalty.
There's another procedure called the, the
Lasso, or
the least absolute shrinkage and selection
operator,
that also applies a penalty to the maximum
likelihood equation.
But it not only shrinks the beta, betas,
but it also prunes some of
them out of the model, so it sets some of
the betas all the way down to zero and
drops those variables from the model.
So this one's great, because it not only
corrects the fact that your
effect sizes are a little bit too big, but
it also performs model selection and
gets rid of some of variables that, some
variables that shouldn't be in the model.
And of course even when you run these,
you're going to need to validate the model
at the end of the day.
I just want to walk you through an example
where somebody actually applied shrinkage.
This is a nice example.
It's worth looking at if you're interested
to get more details about shrinkage.
Because they were specifically trying to
apply shrinkage to some real data to,
to show clinicians how to use this
technique.
And I think it's a nicely written paper,
so I'll refer you there.
But basically, they are aiming to build a
prediction model for pulmonary embolism.
Sometimes people come in to the emergency
room, and
they have signs where it, it seems like
they might have a pulmonary embolism.
But we want to know who is really likely
to have it and
needs to be sent on for further testing,
and who's unlikely to have it.
Their data set that they used here was 398
people.
43% of them actually had a pulmonary
embolism, actually had the event.
It's a binary, so we're going to be using
logistic regression.
They had 27 candidate predictors that they
wanted to test in their model building.
So what they did was they performed
actually three different model
strategies just to illustrate how to do
these things.
So the first model strategy, which is at
the label here, is no shrinkage.
They just applied an automatic selection
procedure to their 27 candidate variables,
and they came out with about 13 were
retained in the model.
And here are all the ones that were left
in the model, these two actually were
pruned from the model, did not end up in
the model, in the final model.
So here's all the variables that were
left, and
here are the beta coefficients that were
estimated when we just ran a regular old
logistic regression with no corrections.
The area under the curve came out to be
78%.
They then said, okay,
let's apply a shrinking factor to all the
beta coefficients, okay.
So that's what they've done here in step
two.
They calculated that their shrinkage
factor here was 0.71.
And I'll refer you to the paper if you
want more details about how they got that.
But I'll just mention that one of the ways
you can calculate the shrinkage factor is
with bootstrapping.
And so, that's saying that our, we need to
shrink all the beta coefficients by 0.71.
So to do that, all we have to do is
multiply the beta coefficients from
the original model by 0.71.
So 0.19 times0.71 gives us 0.14.
0.17 times 0.71 gives us 0.12, and et
cetera.
And so, it's going to have all the same
variables in the model, but
the beta coefficients are shrunk.
When we do that, the area under the curve
shrinks as well.
And it goes down to 0.72, so it's telling
us that our original model,
the area under the curve was a little bit
overly optimistic, too high, and
now we've got a better estimate of that
after we've done shrunk, shrinkage.
They then did a penalized maximum
likelihood estimation.
So all they did there is, there's, there's
an algorithm in the computer.
Some statistical packages like R have this
built in.
Others don't have this yet.
But there is a, a procedure in there where
you can say,
I want to run this penalized maximum
likelihood, estimate, estimation.
You have to define how big you want that
penalty to be.
But then, in the process of fitting the
beta coefficients,
there's a penalty applied within
estimation.
And so you can see the resulting beta
coefficients here.
Also, you'll notice that, there, there's
nothing, some, a couple of
the variables ended up in this model that
didn't end up in the other models.
The shrinkage here is different depending
on the beta.
So if we just compare the original model,
the 0.19 to the,
what comes out of the penalized maximum
likelihood estimate, 0.17.
This one's shrinkage factor was 0.89, it
only was shrunk by 11%.
However, there was whatever this weta-led
index is.
It had a beta coefficient of 0.17 in the
original model.
It went down to 0.06.
So that was shrunk by 65%.
So that's all that last column needs.
The area under the curve here for this
model is 0.75.
So, here we have two different ways to
apply shrinkage.
There's yet another way of penalizing the
maximum likelihood estimate,
again called the Lasso, where it will
actually prune some of the model,
the variables out of the model at the same
time.
What do we gain by doing this?
Well, this picture is trying to get a
little bit at what you're gaining here.
So here is, we've got 20 observations from
the data set.
We take their values and we calculate
predicted probabilities from them.
So this is, this over here is a on the
y-axis, is predicted probability.
So these are just some predicted
probabilities of individuals from
the original data set.
So you apply the original full unpenalized
model to the,
to a particular person's values.
This person had a really high predicted
probability of having pulmonary embolism.
These are the predictor populations for
20 people for the, from the unpenalized
model.
When you apply the penalized model,
you'll notice what we do is we ended up
shrinking those predictor probabilities.
They're a little bit closer together.
There's a little less variability now.
What's that, what that's going to have a,
an effect on, basically, is when the
predicted probabilities are allowed to be,
we, we don't have as many extreme
predicted probabilities.
When they're allowed to be a little bit
more extreme, that can overfit, right?
Because you can have, you can be fitting
predictive probabilities of 0.99.
For a percent.
And that might just mean that we've over
fit to that person.
So we end up with a little bit less
extreme predictions over here
on the right.
All right, one more approach I just
want to mention here.
So you can again kind of get a set of
candidate predictors and
use automated selection, but add onto that
automated selection some kind of
bootstrapping to do variable selection.
And I've told you at this point enough
about bootstrapping that you
can follow the logic here.
This is a way of selecting the variables
using a combination of
automatic selection with bootstrapping.
And then again, here you're going to
want to validate the model.
So here's how this would work.
I'm just going to illustrate this with an
example.
So some researchers actually wanted to
come up with a prediction model for
30-day mortality using patients with heart
attacks.
So what's your chance of dying in 30 days
after you've had a heart attack.
They had a sample of 4,911 patients.
They had an initial set of 29 candidate
predictors, okay.
So what they did was to do bootstrapping
to draw bootstrap samples
from their original samples.
So their original sample has 4,911
patients in it.
They then drew 1,000 bootstrap samples
from that original sample.
So remember, bootstrap samples means I'm
sampling with replacement.
So some observations will appear multiple
times, and
some observations will not appear at all.
That way I can come up with 1,000
different samples.
Still they each are sample size of 4,911.
So, we still have samples of the same
size, but
the compositions of these samples is
different.
Remember, in any given sample about
two-thirds of the observations will be in
that sample, and about one-thirds of,
one-third of the observations will not be
included in that given sample.
So we have 1,000 now, slightly different
samples.
And then, the point of this study was
actually to illustrate the problems with
backward, forward, and stepwise
regression.
So what they did was they actually ran
backwards, forwards, and
stepwise selection on all 1,000 samples.
All three algorithms on all 1,000 samples.
They used a p-value cut off of 0.05 for
the automatic selection procedures.
It's automatic though, so at least this
can be done on a computer,
it's not like you're having to do this a
thousand times by hand.
All right, so what did they find?
So literally what they're doing, they're
taking these 29 candidate predictors from,
they're taking one of the bootstrap
samples.
They are running backwards, forwards, and
stepwise selection on those
29 predictors for a particular bootstrap
sample, and coming up with three models.
And then they're repeating that for all
1,000 bootstrap samples.
So they're coming out with here, 3,000
different models.
What's really interesting is that the
models that they get from these
slightly different samples, remember
different bootstrap samples you know,
share about two-thirds of the observations
are the same across these.
They're slightly different samples, but
they're coming out with pretty different
models.
So in red here, it's showing the results
from the backward selection, in yellow,
it's showing from the forward selection,
and
in blue, showing from the stepwise
selection.
And you can see that the three selected
procedures give pretty similar results.
This is just a frequency distribution, a
histogram, showing you,
remember, there were a total of 29
candidate predictors.
They were showing you the final models
contain anywhere between 8 and
19 predictors.
How often did those different model sizes
occur?
So, a couple of times, the automatic
selection procedures in the bootstrap
samples about, you know, maybe one, little
less than 1% of the time,
came out with only eight predictors in the
model.
There were a few times, a handful of
times, where they came out with 18 or
19 predictors that were retained in the
final model.
And then we get everything in between.
Most commonly, somewhere between 12 and 13
variables were selected.
But you can see there's a lot of variation
here showing you that if you,
you know, there's a lot of chance, a lot
of noise here.
Because just depending on exactly which
bootstrap sample you've got,
you've got a very different final model.
And then they went a little even, one step
further here.
This is a very useful graphic.
Again showing you backward selection in
blue.
Forward selection in this kind of reddish
color.
And stepwise selection in yellow.
Again, the three selection methods giving
you pretty similar answers when applied to
the same sample.
But here's what they're showing you.
They're showing you, here's the 29
original predictor variables on
the x-axis.
And here's the number of times that the
variables were chosen out of
1,000 different samples.
So, for example, age was chosen for every
single bootstrap sample.
For every selection procedure, forward,
backwards and
stepwise, age was chosen 1,000 out of
1,000 times.
That tells you that this is a really
robust predictor, because no matter what
the quirks of the particular sample were,
age was chosen in all of those models.
shock, blood pressure,
glucose white blood cells were also chosen
almost in all of the models.
Urea was also chosen a pretty high
percentage of the time,
more than 90% of the time.
So, that's telling you that there are some
variables which are clearly related to
the outcome of mortality here.
That even chance differences in what made
it into the sample doesn't make
a huge difference.
However, if you look at the other side of
this distribution curve,
what you see is there's a whole bunch of
variables where they made it into
the model a couple of times, you know, 10%
of the time, 20% of the time, but
they didn't make it into most of the
model.
That said, by chance, they can make it
into a model, here or
there, pretty easily.
But this is probably not robust.
It's probably just that they're making it
in by chance,
because we have a high chance of a type 1
error here.
So this just gives you a sense that these
automatic selection procedures do
have a lot of problems, because you're
getting a lot of different answers.
And depending on exactly the sample you've
got, sometimes the variable's included,
and sometimes it's not included.
So a lot of the variables that end up in
the final model may not be robust.
And, when they counted up how many
different final models they had, so
when just looking at backwards selection
only.
Out of the 1,000 different bootstrap
samples that they applied backwards
selection to, they came up with 940
different final models.
Now this is not talking about differences
in the beta coefficients.
This is just talking about which variables
out of those 29 were selected for
the final model.
So they came out with 940 different
combinations of variables, out of 1,000.
So that tells you that you can get quite
different models, this is telling you
a little bit about the instability of
these automatic selection procedures,
which again was the point of this paper.
They then not only did that, but they
added a random noise variable.
So in, to that candidate set of 29
predictors, they added a couple of
variables which were just noise, that they
knew were not at all related to mortality.
They wanted to know how often would those
make it in, with a p of 0.05,
less than 0.05, would make it in to some
final models?
So it turned out that 16% of the time,
those noise variables appeared in 16% of
the models.
So they didn't have a less than 5% chance
of appearing in those models,
they had a 16% chance of appearing in
those models.
So we had about a 16% chance of false
positives here, not a 5% chance.
So that tells you that our type 1 error
rate is somewhere, you know,
that our significance level is really
around 16%,
even though we used a p-value cutoff of
0.05.
So that's really useful to understand.
If you look back to this graph here, you
can see that, you know,
16% is a 160 out of 1,000.
A lot of variables had appeared in about
16% of the models, and
these are the real variables.
These are actual variables that appeared
in about 16% of the models.
You can be sure that these variables are
probably just noise variables and
actually have no relationship to
mortality.
Now, as I mentioned, six predictors were
selected in more than 90% of the models,
so that suggests that those are really
robust predictors.
So, you could actually use this setup of
combining automatic
selection with bootstrapping.
You probably want to pick only one of
backward, forward, or
stepwise, you don't need to do all three.
But you could do one of those and
you could, you would figure out which were
the really robust variables.
So variables that were included in say,
more than 90% of the models.
Or sometimes people will use cutoffs of
more than 80% or
even more than 60% or 70%.
You could use some cutoff and say,
well, all of those variables are pretty
robust because they were selected a lot.
So they're unlikely to be just chance
findings, so
you then choose those variables and you
put those variables into your final model.
So you could use, also use this
combination of automatic selection and
bootstrapping for variable selection.