Welcome to HRP 261.
This course covers more advanced
statistical tests for
analyzing discrete data.
So the data sets that we're going to deal
with in
this course have outcome variables that
are categorical.
That could be binary, ordinal or nominal
categories.
We're going to cover a number of tests in
this course.
Both those that we use when we have
independent observations as well as
tests that are used when you have
clustering in your data sets,
some kind of correlations among your
observations.
We'll also talk about the situation where
you have sparse data.
The concern when you have sparse data is
that most of our statistical tests work
by, we take a discrete distribution and
we approximate that with a continuous
distribution.
For example, we might take a binomial and
approximate it as a normal.
That is fine if you have large numbers,
but
it can fall down if you have small sample
sizes, especially if you
have certain cells in your data set that
are very, have very few observations.
In that case you want to use exact test.
All those exact tests are, is we just go
back to the discrete distribution, and
we avoid approximating.
So let me just give a quick overview of
the tests when we're going to
cover them in the course.
In fact, this week, the first week of the
course,
we're going to run through a whole bunch
of these statistical tests.
I'm assuming that because you've had a
prior course in statistics you
will have encountered most of these
before.
So we're going to quickly run through all
the tests that are used for
the situation where you are not trying to
adjust for anything.
Where you're just trying to compare two
variables in a,
some kind of contingency table.
So these would be the risk difference or
relative risks, chi-squared test,
McNemar's test or the Fisher's exact test.
Again, I'm assuming most of these will be
familiar to you, so I'm
going to go through this rather quickly,
assuming that it's largely review.
If you were in HRP259 in the fall, you
should have seen all of
these tests already, and this week should
be fairly easy.
It should be mostly review,
maybe a few additional points I, I'm
adding to those tests.
But we'll run through that rather quickly.
Then next week we're going to talk about
the Mantel-Haenszel Chi-Square test.
This is the situation where we want to
stratify our contingency tables.
We're essentially adding a third variable
into the picture.
We'll also talk in detail about
confounding and interaction.
It will be important to understand these
well before we move on to
regression modelling.
The rest of the course, the remaining
eight weeks of the course,
we're going to be talking about
regression.
So we're going to be covering all of the
rest of these tests,
which are all regression methods.
Mostly versions of logistic regression.
We'll talk about ordinal, multinomial,
conditional, and
exact logistic regression.
We'll also talk about GEE modeling.
A lot of what we're going to discuss in
this course has to do with,
how do you build a regression model?
And those principles,
although we're going to be applying them
to logistic regression in this course,
are in fact applicable to other types of
regression such as linear regression.
If you did not take HRP259 in the fall and
you're not coming out of a medical or
epidemiology background, and you don't
really, aren't really familiar with
the various study designs that we use in
epidemiology and medical research, I would
recommend that you take the optional,
watch the optional module on study design.
So with terms like cross-sectional study,
cohort study, randomized trial, case
control study, if those aren't familiar to
you, you need to watch that module.
This is not a course in Study Design, but
the way that we analyze our data is
always going to be influenced by the study
design from which the data came, and so
I will be throwing around those terms and
assuming that you're familiar with all
those study designs.
So please watch that if, if you're not
familiar with those things.
What we're going to cover this week in
Unit One is all of the following tests.
Again, these are just your basic tests for
analyzing data in contingency tables.
So this includes risk ratios, odds ratios,
risk difference, and McNemar's test for
correlated data.
Those apply in the situation where you
have two binary variables and
you just want to see if those binary
variables are associated.
So, a 2 by 2 table.
If we want to do a larger contingency
table,
like a 3 by 3 table, you have to use a
chi-squared or a Fisher's Exact test.
And, of course, the chi-squared and
Fisher's Exact tests can also be applied
to the 2 by 2 table.
So I'm going to run through all of these
tests this week, and
again hopefully this is mostly review for
you.