So I've told you how to test for
interactions in the logistic regression
model and see whether the interacting
terms are statistically significant.
What I haven't told you is how to
calculate effect sizes or
odds ratios in the presence of
interaction.
So that's what we're going to do in this
module.
So this module will get into some math
derivations.
I think they're, really fun.
They're a good challenge.
Hopefully you'll enjoy them too.
But, there is a little bit of math.
And so I am going to be throwing up a lot
of exponentials.
And I just want to quickly remind you that
if you have something like this,
an exponential function raised to a sum.
That is the same as e raised to e, a,
times e raised to b, times e raised to c.
I might jump between the two of these
quite quickly, so
if you haven't thought about the way that
exponentials work in a while you
might just want to quickly review that in
preparations for
the derivations in this module.
So the example I'm going to be referring
to in this module,
which we're going to use for some practice
data, to figure out how to do, calculate
odds ratios when we have interaction
terms, is a rather fun data set.
It's actually quite challenging, much more
challenging than the data set you're
going to have to deal with for your
homework.
So this was a study that was,
it was a population-based study about
seven, 800 women.
The outcome variable was annual
mammography use.
So if you went and got your annual
mammography,
you get a yes on this variable, if you
didn't, if you weren't good about the,
that annual screening, you get a no.
So we have a binary outcome variable.
The authors were interested in sort of two
different predictors.
So one, they thought that women who
worried a lot about breast
cancer might be more likely go get their
mano-, mammographies every year,
because if you're worried about it, you
might want that screening.
Or they also thought it was potentially
uh,the case that if you were
really worried, that you might actually be
less likely to go get your mammographies,
maybe you just don't even want to think
about it or
deal with it because you're just so
worried about it.
So, it could kind of go in either
direction.
So, they looked at worry.
The way they measured worry was as a
continuous variable that
ranged from a value of negative 6 to a
value of positive 6.
It was a nice, normally-distributed
variable.
They also looked at family history.
So, if you're a woman who has had a family
member who's had breast cancer,
you might be more likely to go in for
those, that annual screening.
So they wanted to look at the effects of
family history.
And then they were also interested in
looking at to see if there was
an interaction between family history and
worry, because maybe whether or
not you have a background of having a
family history, maybe that
influences the effect of worry on whether
or not you're likely to get a mammography.
So complicated picture here.
And I'll show you the results that they've
presented in their paper.
So this, these are the results from a
logistic regression model
that included the following things.
It included family history, that's, you
are either a high-risk woman or
a low-risk woman, is the other way they
talked about it in the paper.
Included age, included worry, this
continuous worry variable, huff.
But now it gets interesting.
It also include a worry squared term.
That is essentially worry interacting with
itself.
And it included this interaction between
worry and family history.
And there's actually good reason for
including both of those interacting terms
in the model, yeah, which I'm
going to show you in the minute, the, the
picture that was included with the study.
So there's a good reason to include those
because of the graphical display of
the data that the authors were nice enough
to put in their paper.
Now what's a little confusing here is that
the author has
presented single odds ratios for all these
interac- all these variables that
are involved in an interaction; that's
family history and worry.
They've said, oh, well the odds ratio for
family history is 1.14, the odds ratio for
worry is .96, etc.
In fact, the whole idea of an interaction,
if there are interactions in the model,
that means that there is not a single odds
ratio for either family history or
worry and so it's kind of misleading.
It's not quite right way to present the
data here to present a single odds ratio.
There are actually multiple odds ratio for
family history and
multiple odds ratios for worry.
And that gets really confusing because
they've presented odds ratios for
the interacting term, which really have,
actually, no meaning.
So we probably would've been better off
presenting betas in this case, or
doing the little exercise that we're about
to go through, to, to get a sense of,
to calculate the fact that there are
multiple odds ratios.
For the purposes of this exercise I'll
just note we're not really going to
pay attention to which of these came out
to be significant.
In fact, only age and worry squared turned
out to be statistically significant here.
We want to calculate the, the correct odds
ratios and
the odds ratios in, if, if it even comes
out to be 1.0,
the effect size is important even if it's
null.
So we want to know what the effect size is
regardless of whether or
not it's statistically significant.
So in a minute I'm going to walk you
through the exercise of
actually calculating what are these odds
ratios supposed to
be because there isn't a single odds
ratio.
It's going to involve a little bit of
math.
But I just want to show you that one of
the reasons that I chose to, to use this
paper as an example is because the authors
presented this wonderful graphic, and
I'm a sucker for good graphics.
So what they did to produce this graphic,
I mean, this graphic essentially tells
the whole story in a way, I might even
suggest that we don't
try to give effect sizes in any other way
than potentially to present the betas from
the logistic regression and the graphic
and not even try to go to odds ratios.
You're going to see it gets confusing when
we get to odds ratios.
This graphic is just beautiful.
So this is showing you the worry on the
x-axis.
The rate of mammography use on the y-axis.
And there's two groups.
This is the high-risk group.
This is the women who have a family
history, so
their family history value is equal to
one.
This is the low-risk group, the dotted
line is the low-risk group.
Their family history value is equal to
zero.
Authors call them average risk because
they're just at normal risk for
women in the population.
And what they did to make this graphic is,
remember we have to looked at grouped data
in order to make any kind of graphic here,
because it's every woman either has her
annual mammography or she doesn't, so
it's a one zero variable but what they've
plotted here is the percent of women.
So what they did is that each level worry,
at each one unit different level of
worry they looked at all the women say,
who had a worry of negative five in both
of these groups, and they just said if
there was 100 women in this group and,
you know, 55 of them had their annual
mammography, then they plotted 55%.
So that group had a 55% rate of
mammography use.
This group here was a little bit higher
than that at about 60%.
And they plotted that for each different
level of worry.
So this, these dots represent grouped
data.
A group of women,
what was their uh,mammography rate for a
given level of worry in these two groups.
And the graphic is just beautiful.
Hopefully, I'm going to assume, although
the others don't tell us in the paper,
I'm going to assume that where these
curves came from was that they
actually drew the curve by, based on the
logistic regression model.
That would be the way that you should do
this.
So I'm just going to assume that these
curves represent the curves from
the logistic regression model.
And what you can see here is,
here's the reason they put a worry squared
term in the model, is that graphically,
you can see that there is a quadratic
relationship with worry.
So if you're super un-worried, that's at
the negative end of things,
ou're less likely to get your mammography.
It kind of goes up as you get more
worried, and then as you get more,
even more worried, as you get in the kind
of severe end of worry,
you're less likely to get mammography.
So again, maybe women who are very worried
just don't want to even deal with or
think about it and they don't go in for
those annual mammographies.
The curve, the relationship, the curve
between worry and rate of mammography use,
differ somewhat among those with a high
risk and those with a low risk.
You can see that the two curves are
actually,
the shapes of those curves are actually
somewhat different.
It turns out that the difference between
these two curves is
not statistically significant, as we saw
from the logistic regression model but
they are somewhat different.
This is not a logic plot.
This is just plotting the percentage in
each group.
So, this isn't directly from the logistic
regression model.
But that shows you the general
relationship here, and
that's going to probably translate to
something similar in the logistic model.
In a way, again, if you just look at the
picture you
kind of get exactly what the logistic
regression model is telling us.
But now I actually want to go back and
figure out the odds ratios.
How do you calculate those odds ratios in
the presence of interaction?
And this is going to be a hard problem
because we have three things going on here
that make this problem tougher than the
one that I will give you for
your homework.
We have a continuous variable that's
interacting with things.
It's easier to do this when we have two
binary variables.
But we've got a binary and a continuous;
worry.
We have a, a variable interacting with
itself, so
worry times worry is worry interacting
with itself.
And then we've got the interaction.
So we've got essentially two interactions
and a continuous variable.
This is what will make this problem a lot
of fun.
What I did,
though, is, we cannot calculate the odds
ratios without knowing the betas.
We actually have to take the odds ratios,
which I'm going to assume that the way
that the authors got those odds ratios
that they presented in
their table was that they just took
whatever beta they got, say the beta for
family history, and they exponentiated it,
and they called that the odds ratio.
So, for example, the 1.14 they probably
got just by
exponentiating whatever beta came out for
family history.
What we're going to do to get back to the
betas which is what we really need here in
order to be able to do this correctly, is
we're going to take the natural log.
So, I took the natural log of 1.14.
That's just 0.14.
And so that's what you're seeing in this
table.
I went through and took the natural log to
get all of those betas.
So this gives the, back the original
logistic regression model and
now we can go back and
correctly calculate the odds ratios that
ought to come out of this model.
So I've just rewritten in this slide what
I just gave you in the last slide.
This is the, the logistic regression model
written out.
We did, we don't know what alpha is
because
they didn't give us that information in
the paper.
It actually doesn't matter because,
as you're going to see in a minute, all
the intercepts are going to cancel.
Everybody has the same baseline risk, so
that will cancel out.
So here is the logistic regression model.
We are going to plug into this model to
see what the odds ratios actually are.
And this will take a little bit of math
here.
But here we go.
So we're going to start with calculating
the odds ratio for
family history, the binary predictor.
That one's actually a little easier to
calculate.
So that's why we're going to start there.
So I want get the odds ratio for annual
mammography in women
with a family history compared with women
who don't have a family history.
Binary predictor.
Now, we know that because there's an
interaction term in
the model between family history and worry
that there is not a single odds ratio.
The odds ratio, the relationship between
family history and
mammography depends on the level of worry.
So to make this easy, we're going to start
with this simple case.
We're going to start with a case where
we're at a level of worry equals zero.
Depending on what worry is, the odds ratio
for family history is going to change.
So all we can do, is sort of calculate it
for different levels of worry.
So imagine we're at a level of worry of
zero.
I'm starting with worry of zero because
that makes things cancel out of the model.
Well what is an odds ratio?
An odds ration is a ratio of two odds.
In the numerator we're going to get at the
odds of annual mammography use for
women with a family history.
And we want to compare that to the odds
for women with a family history,
with the, without a family history, family
history is equal to zero.
So that's what we want to put.
Well, where do we get the odds from?
We plug into the logistic regression model
to get the odds for
each of those types of women.
So that's what I'm going to do now.
So what about the odds for a woman with
family history.
So her odds based on the model, I'm just
exponentiating both sides here based on
the model is e raised to alpha, alpha's
going to cancel so it doesn't matter what
it is, plus 0.14 times 1 because she has a
family history, minus 0.03.
I'm going to, this is for, this is age.
But I'm just going to plus in an age of
50.
It actually doesn't matter what I plug in
here,
because we are calculating the adjusted
odds ratio.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to hold age fixed.
Whatever we, whatever the age of the woman
in the numerator,
we're going to give the same age to the
woman in the denominator.
That's what it means to adjust for age.
We're holding it fixed.
We're comparing only 50 year olds to 50
years olds.
I can put any number in for age as long as
I hold it constant.
Then we get negative 0.04 times Worry.
Well, what's Worry here?
It's zero.
Then we get negative .03 times worry
squared while, again,
zero squared is just zero.
And then we get negative .02 times, times,
worr, times the interaction between worry
and family history while worry is zero
that also goes to zero.
So you can see a lot of things are
going to drop out here.
Now I'm just going to re-write something
here.
I am going to just remind you that we can,
this,
it will easier to see that things cancel
if I actually go through and
say, well this is the same as multiplying
by e raised to each of these things.
That'll just be easier for
you to see that when I'm cancelling things
that I'm justified in doing, so.
So, all of this is the same as multiplying
e raised to alpha plus 0.14 is the same as
e raised to alpha times e raised to 0.14.
Now what goes in the denominator?
So, now we want to compare to a woman who
does not have a family history.
So, she gets for the family history term,
a value of zero.
We're going to hold age fixed, so she gets
the same value for age.
We're going to uh,give her a value of zero
for worry,
because we're saying this is at, comparing
two women who have a worry of zero, so
all the values of worry, this is, are all
going to be zero, so
that's going to make this problem a little
easier.
So worry go- is at zero, we're, we're
saying this is the odds ratio at
a worry of zero, so we get- we're noticing
that a lot of things cancel here.
So e raised to alpha, that's going to
cancel for
both women, this differs between the
women, so she gets
e raised to .14 in the numerator, that's e
raised to zero in the denominator.
The term for age is going to cancel, we're
holding age fixed, so
there should be no additional effect for
age.
And then since worry is held at zero, all
these things are just zero,
they're all going to cancel.
That makes our life a little bit easier
here.
So what is this simplified to?
This simplifies just to e raised to 0.14,
e raised to zero in the denominator here,
e raised to zero is just one.
So this turns out to be just e raised to
.14.
So at a worry of zero, all we have to do
is take the beta for family history and
exponentiate it, and that gives us the
odds ratio of 1.14.
Now that's what the authors reported in
their paper, but
that's only the odds ratio when women are
at a worry level of zero.
So we actually need to do a little bit
more work to figure out what
the general formula for
the odds ratio is here, because the odds
ration is actually a function of worry.
So, I'm going to do one more example, and
the we can just, just general it.
So, what if I am instead at a worry level
of say, five.
I could just pic any value here but we're
going to generalize this in a minute.
So if I'm at a worry level of 5, I'm
going to go through the same logic,
except some terms are not going to cancel
out anymore.
So family history, odds ratio for family
history, for mammography use,
let me compare a woman with a family
history, so
she gets the following values, e raised
to, it doesn't matter what age is,
I'm going to cancel that out anyway,
because we're going to hold it fixed.
But now we have to put in something for
worry.
So she gets a value of 5 for worry, a
value of 25 for
worry squared, and for the interaction
term she has a worry value of 5 and
she has a family history, so 5 times 1 is
equal to 5,
so her interaction term, she gets an
interaction term of 5.
What about the woman who does not have a
family history that we're comparing to?
So in the denominator the odds for a woman
who does not have a family history but
is at a level of worry five, she's getting
e raised to alpha.
She's getting e raised to 0.14 times 0,
because she doesn't have a family history.
So her value there is 0.
Again, we're just holding age fixed, so
that's going to be the same for both.
Now, she also has a worry level of 5, and
she also has a worry squared of 25.
However, for the interaction, she has a
value of zero for
family history so her interaction is going
to be 5 times zero, or zero.
So, she's actually going to get a zero
there.
Now let's go and see what things cancel.
So, the alpha is going to cancel.
The age term is going to cancel.
The main effect for worry and the main
effect for worry squared are going to
cancel, because those are the same since
worry is held fixed.
But, we're going to have this additional
term here from the interaction.
E zero raised to zero goes to 1.
So we get, this is what's left, we get
that the odds ratio here
is equal to e raised to .14,
this e raised to 0 goes to 1, minus e,
times e raised to point 1,
oh this is .02 times 5 is .10, or we can
rewrite that as e raised to .14 minus .10.
So I've just simplified this, let me
simplify a little further,
I get that it's e raised to .04, which is
equal to 1.04.
So what happened here is at a higher level
of worry,
family history actually matters less, the
odds ratio for
family is closer to 1 when we get to a
higher level of worry.
And we've gotta go back to the picture
here, we can see,
let me just take you back to the picture,
that at higher level of,
worry, that the difference and, and
different levels of worry,
the effect of family history differs, and
that's what's captured here.
And we can even make this into a general
formula.
So, you'll notice that all I did here,
the, the odds ratio in general is going to
be e raised to 0.14.
So, we're always going to have that e
raised to 0.14,
but then it's going to be minus 0.02 times
whatever the worry level is.
So, I happen to have a worry level of five
here, but if I had a worry,
a different worry level you would see that
captured, you could just plug in that w.
If the worry is zero, you're plugging in
zero, so that's why at zero it
becomes an odds ratio of 1.14, but that is
the general formula, for, and
there's an infinite number of odds ratios
here depending on the level of worry.
What if somebody had a level of worry of
negative 5,
well if you had a level of worry of
negative 5, this would be .14 minus .02
times minus 5 would be plus .10, so that
would come out to be e raised to
.24 Which is going to be an odds ratio of
around, it's a little bit more than 1.25.
So that's going to be a little bit higher.
So if you're at a lower level of worry,
then your family history is is mattering
more.
So that's what the, the model is telling
us.
There is a function, the odds ratio is a
function of worry here.