In this next module I'm going to show you
how to compare Kaplan-Meier curves from
different groups.
So to illustrate the points in this module
I'm going to use some example data,
which is comparing two groups.
Kaplan-Meier statistics can be used to
compare multiple groups three,
four, whatever.
But we'll keep it simple by just focusing
on a two-group example.
So these are some real data that come from
a randomized trial,
researchers randomized 44 patients with
chronic active hepatitis to a kind of
steroid, or to no treatment or control.
And then, were going to compare the
survival curves here.
So let me just show you what the data
actually look like here, So
the data are similar to before,
we have this kind of two part outcome
variable where we have time.
Which is either the time to sensoring or
the time to the event.
And the event here is death, and, then we
have an event variable, that's
the binary variable that tells you one,
they died, or zero, they were censored.
We also have a variable that captures
whether or not they were in
the treatment group, so we have a treated
group and a control group here.
So this is just showing you the data in a
slightly different way.
The two columns represent the two
treatment groups,
and this is a little different than how I
showed you the pregnancy data.
The starred values are people who were
censored, and if you don't have a star,
that means you had the event that you die.
So that's just another way to represent
the data.
Let me show you what these look like when
we put them on a Kaplan-Meier curve.
So now we have two groups.
The red group represents the control
group.
The black line represents the treated
And, as you can see, the open, here, is
death.
So you can see, you clearly want to be in
the treatment group, right.
The control group falls off pretty
quickly.
The treatment group seems to do much
better.
Now, be a little careful, when looking at
these curves, your might,
your eye might kind of go to the, end of
this curves and
you might say, well, it looks like they
kind of come together, eventually.
Time is in months, by the way.
You know, at the end of about 175 months,
it looks like the curves, converge, or
something.
But be very careful.
There's very, very few subjects left here.
And this probably doesn't represent a
whole heck of a lot.
A little bit misleading.
So we want to know whether or not these
two curves are statistically different.
We're going to, I'm going to show you some
tasks to look at that in a minute.
But again I just want to
point out that the end of this curve's a
little misleading to the eye.
So, there's six controls in the control
group who just kind of are censored, or
live until the end of the study.
You can see these little Ls here are
censored people.
There are only six controls left here at
about 70 months into the study.
So, these last six because none of them
died, it drags the curve all the way out.
But that's just due to six people, maybe
there are some people who can live with
chronic hepatitis, but that's why that
curve gets dragged all the way out.
And also there's this large drop in the
treatment curve at about 160 months.
And what's happening here,
is there's actually only three people left
in the treatment group at that time point.
When one person dies out of that three,
the curve drops like two thirds.
That's a big drop in the curve.
So, it also makes the curve look like it's
closer to the control curve.
But again, don't over interpret that.
Small sample sizes at the end of the
curves will often cause them to
move around like that.
So now lets look at, are these two curves
statistically different?
There are p-value tests that we can use to
evaluate the null hypothesis for
these tests would be that the two curves
are the same.
If we get a significant p-value that would
say we would reject a null hypothesis,
and conclude that they are significantly
different.
So that the test that,
main test that we are focusing on in
something called the log rank test.
You can see the results of the log rank
test here.
The p-value indeed comes out to be
statistically significant of pf 0.03.
So that would say that the two curves are
significantly different.
The log rate test is a chi-square
statistic.
It's a chi-square with one degree of
freedom.
And I'll, so
I'll show you in a minute that it's
actually a Mantel-Haenszel chi-square.
But this is one of the tests that you can
use,
the most commonly used to compare survival
curves.
And then again it could be used for more
than two groups.
So what is the Log-rank test actually?
I'm going to kind of walk you through the
math.
It's not something that you'd probably do
by hand, but
it's good to have an understanding of
what's going on behind the scenes.
So the Log-Rank test turns out to just be
a Mantel-Haenszel chi square test of
independence.
And we talked about the Mantel-Haenszel
test earlier when we talked about
stratifying for confounding.
So we used the Mantel-Haenszel chi square
test To stratify on confounders to
see whether or not an exposure and
an outcome were related after adjusting
for confounding.
The idea is similar here, except rather
than stratifying on a confounder we're
going to stratify on event times.
At every time when events cur, occur, when
people died.
We're going to be comparing the treated
and
control group at each one of those event
times.
The event times here are the strata.
So, again, the Log-rank test looks just
like the Mantel-Haenszel test statistic.
In this case the strata are the unique
event times.
And every month where people died in this
study,
that is an event time we're going make a
two by two table.
So there are K Strata K unique event
times,
and each event time in each one of these
strata we're going to look at
how many people were at risk at that event
time.
And we're going to compare the number of
events occurring in one group
versus the other.
Treated versus control in the case of our
example data.
This just makes a simple two by two table
at every event time.
The Mantel-Haenszel statistic, or the
Log-rank statistic here is just,
we're going to take the observed value of
a in every strata, and
we're going to compare it to the expected
value of a in the strata.
Now this is a two by two table that has
only one degree of freedom.
I could have chosen to peg this statistic
on b or c or d.
A is usually the most interesting cell, so
I've just chosen to focus on A.
But because the table only has one degree
of freedom,
I get the same value whether I focus on,
which ever cell I focused.
So, the, this is the observed value, we
take the observed value of cell a.
To calculate the expected value of cell a,
we're going to calculate that in the
normal way would would for
any chi squared statistic So, if group and
events are independent,
the probability of being in cell a would
just be a plus c times a plus b.
In other words, the row total times the
column total to get the expected value,
then we'd divide by n.
So row total times column total divided by
n gives us the expected value for
this cell.
For all of the strata, we are going to
take observed minus expected,
we are going to sum that up over all the
strata, that's the summation there, and
then we are going to square the whole
thing.
In the denominator, we are going to sum up
the variance of a for every strata.
The variance formula is the row, row one
times row two,
times column times column two, divided by
the sample size in that stratum.
And squared times N minus one.
Now this is a little bit of a complicated
formula,
I'm not expecting you to calculate this by
hand.
Just realize that we the reason that's the
variances that were
working on a hyper-geometric distribution,
that's the variance of a hyper-geometric
distribution.
That's what a follows.
But that will be the variance for a give
a, and then we add,
of all the variances, over all the
different strata, that's our denominator.
Again, this is identical to the
Mantle-Haenszel statistic for
stratified unconfounders.
Now, a couple notes about this.
So first of all,
how do you know that this is a chi-square
statistic with one degree of freedom?
How do you know that this complicated
formula follows a chi-square?
Well, we can do a little bit of algebraic
rearrangement and
show that this statistic, what you see
here, is just the same as saying,
I want to add up all the different
observed a's over different,
all the different strata, so it's the sum
of observed a's.
We can rearrange that expected value as
well.
And show you that this is,
we are subtracted the expected value of
the sum of ace.
So that's equivalent.
We'd be then squaring all of that in the
numerator, so
it's something minus it's expected value,
and observed, minus it's expected value,
and then in the denominator, we have the
variants of that same thing again.
We can do a little bit of re-arrangement
that,
that is just equal to the variants of the
sum of a case.
We have got an observed, minus an expected
squared, divided by it's variants,
that's going to follow a chi-square with
one degree of freedom.
Or if you took the square root, you would
see that it's an observed minus
an expected divided by it's standard
deviation that follows a z squared.
Sorry a z sta, statistic if you take away
the square root.
So that, that's why this is a chi-square I
have written that out if
you can't read my handwriting.
I have written that out again there, and
again the variants formula just comes from
the fact that it's a hypergeometric
distribution.
So just a little bit of mathematical
background there.
Let's now actually show how to apply this
for real data.
So, going back to our hepatitis randomized
trial.
I'm displaying now some output from my
computer,
that summarizes all the different events
in the control group.
It also gives me the numbers at risk which
makes it easy because it's been
tabulated for me.
So if we look in the control group, this
is showing me the times, and
it's showing me when events occurred.
So, at the first time point,
with zero time zero, of course nobody has
had the event then.
The first event occurred at month two,
the first time we update the survival
estimate.
In month two there is one person who dies.
There were 22 at risk.
That's in the control group.
Now, in the treated group, there's also a
death at month two.
So at time point two, there's one death in
the treated group,
there were also 22 at risk.
So, the first stratum here is going to be
month two, because that's
the first event time, and we're going to
represent the data in a two by two table.
There were 22 people in the treated group,
and
22 people at the cont, in the control
group at risk at month two, total of 44.
There was one event in the treated group,
and one event in the control group.
We can represent that in a two by two
table.
This is the first stratum, the first event
time.
We then can say, well what's the observed
value of a here?
Here, that's just one.
There's one in cell a.
What's the expected value of a here?
Well, there were a total of 44 people,
there were a total of two events,
22 people in each group.
If the no hypothesis is true, and there's
no relationship between what group you're
in, and whether or not you have the event.
Then we would expect an even distribution
of events over the two groups.
So if there's two events total, we'd
expect about one in each group.
And that's what the expected value tells
us.
So 22 times two divided by 44 gives us an
expected value here of one.
This is the expected value under the null
hypothesis.
The variance is going to be the row one
times row two,
times column one, times column two.
That's the numerator, and in the
denominator the number is still at risk at
that event time, that's 44 squared times n
minus 1 43.
Again don't worry about having to
calculate out the variants.
Just realize that there is a way to get
the variance of a as well, and
that comes out to be 0.244 here.
So that's for the first stratum, the first
event time.
Let's go back to our data and see what
happens next.
So in the control group, the next thing
that happens is that there is a,
one death at month three.
So now we're up to two people failed,
there was 21 people at
risk At month three, one of them died in
the control group.
But let's look at the treated group.
If you look at the treated group, there
are no events at three months.
So there's still 21 at risk, but there are
no events.
So the 2 by 2 table for the second event
time.
The second stratum, that for month three
looks like this,
there was 21 still at risk in the treated
group and 21 in the control group.
Remember we, we lost, one died in month
two in each of the groups, so
we lost them.
Total of 42 are still at risk at event
time two.
The observed value for cell a here is
zero.
There were no deaths in the treated group.
The expected value, however, is a half.
Under the null hypothesis, we'd expect if
there's one total death,
then we'd expect about half in one and
half in another.
Of course, you can't have a half a death,
but that is just an expected value.
So 21 times one divided by 42 gives us an
expected value of 0.5.
The variance, if you plug into the
variance formula,
comes out to be a quarter.
And we can keep going here.
So, the next event time occurs at month
four.
In the control group at month four,
there's one more death.
There was just 20 at risk now in the
control group One of them dies.
In the treated group, there are no deaths
at month four, so we still have 21,
who are left, 21 at risk.
We represent that in our two by two table.
There were 21 treated at risk but only 20
control individuals at risk for now.
For a total of 41, at event time three at
four months.
The observed value for cell a is zero
here.
The expected value is one times 21 divided
by 41 or about 0.5,
and the variance here comes out to be 0.25
again.
So that's the values for the third strata.
And then we can keep going, you could do
this for every event time.
Of course you don't want to do this by
hand, the computer will do this for you.
But then we take all of those observed
expectant and
variances, and put them together in this
test system.
So there's 20, 22 unique event times in
this case.
I'm going to add in all the observes,
minus the expecteds and divide it by the
variances.
So, we had a one observed in the first
strata,
minus one expected in the second strata.
And there were zero observed minus a half
expected, and so on the variances.
For those first three strata, we're .24,
.25 and .25.
And then we would keep going across all
the different strata.
When you add all that up squared in the
numerator, add up the denominator.
It comes out to give you, if you did it
all at, a chi square value of 4.66.
And that's exactly what we saw from the
computer before.
So if we look at the output from the
computer, the Log- rank test,
indeed, had a chi square of 4.66.
That corresponds to a p-value of .03.
Now, as I mentioned,
the log rank test is most commonly used to
compare different groups in Kaplan-Meier.
There are other statistics that you could
use, however.
So I'll just point those out to you now.
So first of all there's something called a
likelihood ratio test.
The negative two Log likelihood ratio.
You should recognize that, that comes from
maximum likelihood estimation.
So this value must come from some kind of
regression.
And in fact, it comes from assuming an
exponential distribution.
So if your data, actually if your survival
curve actually follow a particular
distribution called the exponential, you
could fit a regression here.
That regression will give you a p-value
using negative two likelihood comparison.
Now you'll see that when we do that here,
the p-value comes out to be very similar.
But there is an assumption here So
just keep in mind that there is an
assumption in, in that test.
So unless you've evaluated that
assumption,
you probably want to avoid that one.
Now the Wilcoxon statistic, is also a chi
score with one degree of freedom.
It's really actually just a version of the
Log-rank test.
All it does is it weights the strata by
their size.
So remember, the earliest, event times are
going to have the most people.
So those are going to get the highest
weight.
So it's going to give a little bit more
weight to earlier time points.
It's going to be a little bit more
sensitive to differences at earlier time
points.
There might be a reason why you care about
giving more weight to earlier time points.
If, if there is a reason for that then you
might choose the Wilooxon test.
You can see that we get a slightly p-value
of 0.01 there were
really good differences early on in, in
this data set.
So if there is some reason you,
you want to wait those earlier time points
more heavily the Wilooxon will do
that for you.
But as I mentioned the Log-rank is the
most commonly used,
it actually turns out that they have the
most statistic power to test
differences between groups that fit in
proportional hazards model.
So it works well as a set up for
Cox regression which is also called the
proper proportional hazards regression.
So if you are, you are planning to do Cox
regression usually for the descriptive for
the Kaplan-Meier you end up recording the
log-rank.
Rank test that's most commonly done.