In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about multinomial logistic regression
which is used when you have a categorical
outcome that has more than 2 levels.
So, so far we've been talking about binary
outcome But what
if your outcome variable is a categorical
variable with more than two levels?
What do you do then?
So, one of the things that you'll see that
people sometimes do in the literature is
they'll actually just collapse that
multilevel categorical variable into
only two categories.
Unfortunately, that's not ideal,
because you're losing a lot of information
when you do that.
Now, that would make sense if, say one of
the categories had only very few
people in it and there wasn't a big enough
sample size in one of
the categories you may then have to
collapse it.
But assuming you have a reasonable sample
size in each of the categories it's not
ideal to collect them and to lose that
information.
Another thing that you could do, which is
conceptually pretty
easy is just to think about the outcome
variable and dummy coat it.
So, I told you how to dummy coat.
Predicting the variables,
dummy coating the outcome variable would
work in exactly the same way.
Dummy coat the outcome variable and you
simply run a Series of binary regressions.
Each of those regressions will compare one
of the categories to
the reference category.
And you could do that, conceptually
there's nothing new,
it's very easy to understand.
I'm actually going to walk you through An
example of doing this,
because I think conceptually it will be
very easy to get your head around.
And this is actually not all that
different than doing multinomial with
logistic regression.
Of course the optimal thing to do, is to
do the multinomial logistic regression.
This is the preferred...
Thing to do.
Assuming that your statistical package
will run it for
you is a lot easier to implement than you
running a series of multiple regressions.
So this is the preferred technique but I
just want you to understand that it's
not very different from just fitting a
series of binary regressions.
You're going to get almost the same
answer.
They're going to be slightly different for
reasons I'll talk about.
But conceptually, it's very similar to
just running a series of
binary regressions.
And since you already know everything that
you need to know to run a series of
binary regressions, I'm going to start my
example there because I think it's
easy to follow and to get your head
around.
So, the example data that I'm going to be
using in this module,
is some more data on runners I.
Do a lot of studies on runners.
This is an older data set,
some cross-sectional data, on 150 college
aged distance runners.
And we were looking at the outcome of
menstrual irregularities.
So it turns out that a lot of distance
runners, have irregular periods.
This is not great because it's,
that's tied to having lower bone density
and being at risk for fractures.
But the outcome, menstrual irregularity,
is actually a three level categorical
variable.
So clinically, we say that women are
Eumenorrheic, if they have normal periods.
In this data set 2 3rds of them, 100 out
of 150, Were Eumenorrheic.
Then women may also have irregular
periods.
So we call that Oligomenorrheic, and the
periods are just irregular, but
not completely absent.
And we have 37 women with Oligomenorrhea
in this data set.
And then finally, sort of the most severe
mestrular, menstrual irregularity that
women can have is to have absolutely no
periods, or very, very few.
And that's called Amenorrhea and we had 13
women in that category.
So, that's the outcome variable.
It's three levels.
Now, you could say, okay, well, I have
sort of two bad comes here,
Oligomenorrhea and Amenorrhea and maybe, I
could just collapse them and
look at that group as whole but again, why
use that information?
Because they, Oligomenorrea group and
Amenorrhea group are actually different
and we can analyze them separately.
The predictor that I'm going to use for
this particular example is one of
the things that we know causes menstrual
irregularity is disordered or
restrictive eating, not taking in enough
calories for the amount you're expending.
And so we had a measurement of uh- eating
disorder a score on a,
a particular questionnaire, so the this
variable I'm abbreviating as the EDIA.
It's basically a score that ranges from 0
to 21, 21 would mean that you had lot of
extreme behaviors in terms of eating and
restricting your caloric intake.
So let's say I didn't know anything about
multinomial logistic regression, but
I knew about regular old logistic
regression.
Here's one thing that I could do to handle
these data.
I could say, okay well,
I want to compare the amenorrheic women to
the eumenorrheic women, and
I want to compare the oligomenorrheic
women to the eumenorrheic women.
So, I could literally run two logistic
regression models.
So in my first model, I would have a
sample size for this model of 113.
I would compare the eumenorrheic women,
the normal or
reference group, to the 13 women who were
amenorrheic.
I would exclude the women who are
oligomennorheic.
So, I would exclude that other category
entirely.
My predictor here is this EDIA score and I
would put that into the model.
What I am going to get out from the model,
therefore, is an odds ratio that tells me,
if I increase By one unit in my eating
disorder score,
what is the increase in my odds of getting
amenorrhea?
I could run that.
I'm going to get an alpha and a beta, or
an odds ratio from that model.
And then I could do the same thing but
looking at the outcome of oligomenorrhea
rather than the outcome of amenorrhea, so
I would exclude the amenorrheic women from
the next analysis This model will have 137
women in it.
I will compare just the oligomenorrheaic
women to the reference group,
again with the predictor of eating
disorder score.
And I will get out some kind of odds
ratio.
This odds ratio will tell me what's my
increase in my odds of
getting oligomenorrhea for every one unit
increase in this eating disorder scale.
These logistic regressions will work in
all the same ways that we've
already talked about.
So let me start with this first model
here.
Modelling the odds of amenorrhea.
So, if I'm going to run a regular logistic
regression,
first thing I should do is take my
continuous variable,
my EDI score and plot it against the logit
of the outcome.
And the outcome here is amenorrhea.
So again we are completely Excluding the
oligomenorrheaic women from this analysis.
When I do the logit plot, you can see that
it is pretty linear in the logit and
of course, we want to check that.
It's reasonably fits a straight line here.
So then I'm just going to run my logistic
regression model,
which I went ahead and did.
Here is the results.
So my alpha, my intercept, is negative
3.1, my slope is 0.1609,
that's my beta coefficient for this eating
disorder score.
For.
You can see that the p value for EDIA is
highly significant.
And the beta coefficient is positive so as
you go up in your EDIA score, you indeed,
do have an increase in your odds of being
amenorrhea.
And, notice that the,
the model that we're getting out here,
this is the logit of amenorrhea.
Is equal to negative 3.15 plus 0.1609,
times the EDIA score, that's our model.
If you look back at the Logit plot from
the last slide,
this model directly corresponds to that
Logit plot.
So,the intercept in my model comes out to
be negative 3.15 well, you can see if I
fit a straight line, that's indeed exactly
where I would Hit the Y axis here.
And also you could figure out that the
slope does indeed look like about .16.
And it's highly significant.
We can also talk not just about the beta
coefficients but
we can translate that beta-coefficient
into and odds ratio.
So ,I went ahead and did that as well.
So if I look at the odds ration for
a 1 point change in this eating disorder
scale score.
Which again goes from 0 to 21.
So the 1 point change isn't huge.
A 1 point change.
Corresponds to an odds ratio of 1.175.
So, that would that you, your odds of
being amenorrheic
goes up by about 18% for every 1 point
increase in your eating disorder score.
Now, that's a small unit.
We could also maybe look at this Standard
deviation of EDIA score as your predictor.
So this standard deviation of EDIA score
of this group was about six and so
if we looked at a one standard deviation
increase,
if your EDIA score goes up a whole
standard deviation, then the increase
in your odds of being amenorrheic is 160%,
the odds ratio is 2.6 or 2.7.
So, you can see of course it looks more
impressive if we use a bigger unit for
EDI score.
So, that's the logistic model for
amenorrhea, I will also show you the ROC
curve for amenorrhea.
First of all, the area under the curve
here was about 75%, so
we actually have pretty good predictive
ability with just this one question here.
The, these are pretty tightly linked
dimensional function and
restrictive eating.
I want to point out something that's kind
inside here about the ROC curve that
something we haven't talked about yet in
this class.So,
just wanted to note to you that notice
that this ROC curve kind of has a,
a plateau in it and it, we called it an
infliction point.
Sometimes, when people are building
clinical prediction models.
They don't want to talk about the
continuous variables.
So in this case, our predictor is this EDI
score.
And they don't want to like have to plug
that continuous predictor into
a logistic regression model in order to
get out a predicted probability.
They want something that has a little more
clinical utility that could be, sort of,
applied quickly, you know, in the
emergency room.
So, we're not going to be plugging into a
logistic regression model.
In the emergency room for example.
So, there's like kind of one cutoff.
And how can you, what's a way that you
could choose that cutoff?
So sometimes people will use the ROC curve
to choose, a clinical cutoff.
Now of course, whatever cutoff you choose,
based on one set of data.
That's going to be very fit to that
particular data set, you are.
You course you're going to need to
validate that cut off in other
populations.
But just to show you kind of how you would
decide that, notice that this ROC curve
you could go up, as you go up in
sensitivity steeply,
initially, there is not much corresponding
drop-off in specificity.
So, if you climb up to this point in the
curve,
you get this great increase in sensitivity
pretty quickly without any little with
very little cost to specificity.
However after this point and this point by
the way corresponds to
a predictive probability of I think this,
.14% in that...
Corresponds to an EDI score of 9.
So, that dot right here was, if you made
your cut off for a test positive
an EDI score of 9 or greater, that would
give you this little dot on the graph.
But notice then,
if you were then to make the cutoff
higher, say to choose a score of.
10 or 11 or 12 to kind of be your cut off
you all of a sudden don't gain
much sensitivity at all but you have this
huge drop in specificity.
So, if I was to try to kind of make a
clinical cut off based on this
ROC curve this one kind of has a nature
point that you can see you might want to
put the cut off right there.
So, if I look at this cut-off, of, say if,
if you have a score of greater than or
equal to 9 on this questionnaire where you
are going to be a scream positive for
being likely to have the outcome of
menstrual irregularity here.
That gives a sensitivity of 69% and a
specificity of 85% for
detecting amenorrhea and that's probably
about the best we can do.
If I put the cut-off anywhere else, there
is going to be a such a,
huge drop in specificity.
That is probably not going to be optimal.
So you can use an ROC curve in this way,
this is something we haven't talked about
yet, to try to find a clinical cutoff.
But again, be very careful in doing this,
because of course, we've overfit for sure
to this particular sample,
you know the cutoff of nine is very
specific to this particular sample.
We'd want to validate that that's going to
hold up in other different samples and
bigger populations.
But I just wanted to mention that because
we haven't talked about that use of ROC
curves Curves you.
Okay, now kind of coming back to the
discussion on the multinomial regression.
So we ran the logistic regression with
amenorrhea versus umenorrhea
as the outcome.
I can run a similar logistic regression
but
now focus on the outcome of oligomenorrhea
and exclude the women with amenorrhea.
And that's what I've done here.
I'm showing you the logistic, the logit
plot, so
the logit of oligomenorrhea is the outcome
now, my predictor is still this EDI score.
This graph represents 137 people we've.
Excluded the women with amenorrhea.
This looks again, nice and linear in the
logit.
So we have a nice linear relationship
between the score and
the logit of amenorrhea.
the, you can see that the intercept's
going to come out somewhere around
negative 1.5 or a little bit lower than
that.
In the slope it's going to be positive.
And, indeed, when I run this data in a
logistic regression model,
here is my outcome.
I indeed get a slope, or a little bit less
than negative 1.5.
My beta coefficient this time is 0.10,
so it's smaller than the beta coefficient
was when the outcome was amenorrhoea.
But it is still highly Statistically
significant.
We can also calculate the odds ratios.
So,the odds ratio for a one unit increase
in this score I get about a 10 or
11% increase in my odds of oligomennorhea.
If I look at a standard deviation increase
in this score,
my odds ratio is 1.85 or 1.86.
So, I get about an 86% increase in my odds
of oligomennorhea.
So that you can see that the relationship
between this EDIA score and
oligomenorrhea is not as strong as it was
for the more extreme outcome of
amenorrhea, but I can report these
separate, these odds ratios separately.
Just to show you, show you the ROC curve
With EDI predicting oligomenorrhea,
the area end of the curve is a lot less
steep so
this, this score is not as predictive of
oligomenorrhea as it was for
amenorrehea also it doesn't, the ROC
doesn't have you kind of
a similar nice cut off point as it did for
the amenorrehea outcome.
But that's all that you would do if wanted
to run a series of
binary logistic progression here.
Then, what you would report in your paper
with the odds ratio for amenorrhea, for
every you know,
increase in EDAI score and then you would
report the odds ratio for amenorrhea.
You would get, you would report those odds
ratios separately.
In fact, doing the multinomial regression
is really not very different than that.
So, I, now, I took all these data and
I put them into one Multinomial regression
in my computer and here are the results.
So, what you'll get in your output is
you'll have two intercepts and
you'll have two betas.
You'll have an intercept for the outcome
of amenorrhea and an intercept for
the outcome of oligomenorrhea.
And similarly you're going to have two
betas.
A beta for amenorrhea and a beta for
oligomentherea.
If you go through this output and look at
the beta coefficients and
their standard errors and the p-values
What you're going to notice,
is they're almost identical, to the ones
that I got when I just ran a series,
of separate binary logistic regressions.
So, it's really not very different.
They're going to be slightly different,
for
reasons I'll tell you but they're, almost
identical.
So for example the intercept for
amenorrhea, from the multinomial model,
when you ran everything together.
Is negative 3.19 when we
ran amenorrhea separately that intercept
came out to negative 3.15.
So it was in the second decimal place it
was slightly different.
The beta coefficient here for amenorrhea
is 0.1656.
When we ran it separately for amenorrhea,
the beta coefficient was 0.1609.
So again, a change in this time in the
third decimal place.
So, we're, it's a very small difference.
Similarly the standard errors the standard
error before for the beta coefficient for
amenorrhea was 0.0436.
It's exactly the same here.
That we probably have to go out a few
decimal places to see any difference.
And if you look, if you compare.
With the, the previous models I show you
for oligomenorrhea, you'll see same thing,
the beta coefficients that intercepts the
standard error,
the P values are almost all, almost this
exactly the same often you know,
a little bit different in a few decimal
places.
Similarly, if we translate these data
coefficients into odds ratios,
the odds ratios look similar to what we
saw before as well.
So, the odds ratio for amanorrhea is 1.18.
The odds ratio for oligomenorrhea is
1.106.
So, 18% increase in my odds of amenorrhea
as I go up in my EDI score.
But only a 10% increase or 11% increase in
my odds of oligomenorrhea.
But everything else is kind of looks very
similar.
You would report these separate odds
ratios in your paper.
So that's it really, that's all that
multinomial logistic regression is doing.
You're going to get separate odds ratios
for
the different outcomes compared with the
reference category.