[BLANK_AUDIO]
Welcome to week eight.
In the last couple of weeks we've been
talking about model building.
This week we're going to switch modes and
I'm going to tell you about some
additional models that are available to
you when you have discreet outcomes.
Besides just a binary logistic model that
we've been talking about so far.
So if you look at the medical literature,
when you have discreet outcomes.
By and large, across the medical
literature you'll see that
typically people will choose to use binary
logistic regression to analyze that data.
However, you're not restricted to binary
logistic regression.
There's a whole host of other models that
are available to
you when you have [INAUDIBLE] outcomes.
And for example, if you have ca, a
categorical outcome where there are more
than two levels, you could collapse those
categories into just two but
there's no reason that you have to do
that.
You could instead choose to do something
called multinomial logistic regression or
ordinal logistic regression.
Also, sometimes you'll have count data.
Count data are technically discrete, they
are not continuous, right,
because counts can only take on the value
zero, one, two, three, etc.
Now sometimes when we get count data,
if it turns out to have a large range of
possible counts, when you look at
the distribution of that count data it may
turn out that if the mean is somewhere.
Quite of a lot higher than zero and
there's a large range of possible counts.
If you look at the frequency distribution,
the histogram, it may turn out that
those counts look close enough to a normal
distribution that you may decide that you
just want to analyze that with linear
regression and that's perfectly fine.
However, count data often do not look that
way.
So typically with count data, you'll see
something that seems more like this.
You have a lot people down around zero,
one, two,
three, low numbers of events, and then you
have some kind of right tail.
That certainly is not a normal
distribution.
And if you have data that looks like that,
then it's preferable to analyse that count
data with something called the Poisson
regression, or
negative binomial regression.
So there's a lot of other choices besides
just the binary logistic model that we've
focused on so far.
I'll just mention that I focused on the
binary logistic model for
talking about the general principles of
model building, but
those principles would apply to these
models as well.
They're transferable principles.
Of course each of these models will have
its own little idiosyncrasies in
terms of the assumptions that you have to
check and
exactly what measures you're getting out
of the model.
But by and
large, those principles of model building
will apply to these models as well.
And just a little preview of the types of
data that we're going to be
talking about this week.
So later this week again we're going to be
talking about count data.
And I found some, an example data set that
was looking at the outcome here as counts.
The outcome is the number of world records
in swimming that are broken each year.
And that's a count because obviously you
can't break one and
a half world records, you have to break an
even number.
And those data are shown plotted here from
1969 to 2009
this is the number of world records that
were broken each year.
And there are a lot of different events in
swimming, and there's men's swimming and
women's swimming so there's a lot of
possible.
Records to be broken.
So kind of a large number get, can be
broken in any given year.
But whats interesting if you look at the
pattern here.
there, the number of records being broken
was pretty high in the early 70s and
then it kind of goes down and there's not
as many record being broken in the 1990s.
Maybe we've kind of peaked in terms of
technology and things.
But then all of a sudden there's this
spike back up as you
look in the 2000's and that probably has
to do with new technology, new types of
swim wear that have actually made a lot of
world records in swimming fall.
And therefore we could choose to analyze
these data with something like
a Poisson regression or a negative
binomial regression.
Those models are specifically for count
data.