In this next module I'm just going to give
you some examples of Kaplan-Meier curves
from the literature to get some practice
on reading Kaplan-Meier curves.
So, the first example is just a fun
example that comes out of
the British Medical Journal's Christmas
edition and for
those of you who aren't familiar with it,
this is a satirical addition that they put
out, it's just for fun.
And somebody submitted a paper on the
survival analysis of chocolates.
So again, just a fun example here.
The study design, this was a study they
actually did carry out,
was that they actually placed two types of
chocolate boxes, Quality Street and
Roses chocolates and on different wards in
the same hospital.
They used eight boxes in the study,
containing a total of 258 chocolates.
Now, in fact, the others have in no way
accounted for
the fact that chocolates within the same
box might some how be correlated.
We are going to forgive them that, again,
because this is just a fun little example.
So, each chocolate is an observation and
they're following the chocolates.
There's somebody kind of hiding in the
back watching the chocolates being eaten.
They're following the chocolates.
Each chocolate until it was eaten, each of
these 258 chocolates.
The main outcome measure was the median
survival time of a chocolate.
How, how quickly do chocolates on a
hospital ward get eaten?
And they also looked at things like,
did the nurses versus the doctors eat more
of the chocolates and so on.
Anyway it's just a fun example and
they generated a nice Kaplan-Meier curve
for the data.
Again, we started with 258 chocolates in
eight different boxes.
There were two types of chocolates, the
Quality Street which is from Nestle, and
Roses which is from Cadbury.
You know, it looks like that Cadbury box
is a little prettier.
Perhaps that's why that, the Roses, the
Cadbury chocolates,
got eaten a little bit faster.
And you can see that that type of
chocolate is pictured in blue,
the bottom curve on this Kaplan-Meier
curve.
So, they were eaten more rapidly.
And what's so nice about this Kaplan-Meier
curve is that they nicely placed
the number of chocolates who were still,
that were still at risk of being eaten.
On the bottom here, it's always good to
put your sample sizes on the bottom like
this, so that you know, especially when
you get to the end of a Kaplan-Meier
curve, that there's very few observations,
people, chocolates left at risk,
and to be a little careful at the end of
that Kaplan-Meier curve.
The time here is given in minutes, so
minutes from the box being put on the
ward.
Obviously we started with 100% chocolates
and we drop off from there.
Again, the Cadbury Roses, chocolate seemed
to be the prefer,
preference because they were eaten at a
faster rate.
Couple of other things we can pick up off
of a Kaplan-Meier curve,.
What if we wanted to know, what is the
median survival time for
a chocolate on a hospital ward?
So, what we can do is look for the 50%
line.
This is where we have 50% survival.
We are going to just kind of draw over and
find at
what point was there chocolates survival
probability in each of the two groups.
And in fact, the fifth, the median
survival time is
shorter in the Roses chocolates and we'd
have to keep going over and
the median survival time is longer for the
Quality Street chocolates.
So, you know, you're just guessing here,
but
it looks like somewhere around, close to
100 maybe, were the Roses,
as the median survival time in minutes for
the Roses chocolates versus for
Quality Street, it appears to be somewhere
around 125 minutes.
And this was a statistically significant
difference with a log rate test.
Anyway, that's just a fun example.
Another example that's a little bit more
serious but
another one of my favorite, examples of
Kaplan-Meier curve.
This is also from the British Medical
Journal.
A little bit of an older study, but makes
a really important point.
So, what the researchers here did was they
looked at a bunch of grants that
were funded.
And, so that's what we're starting with at
baseline,
this is the time at which the grants were
funded.
And there's a, little less than 200 grants
here, or
more, but more than 200 grants here that
were funded.
And they follow them until publication.
So, the outcome is something positive,
it's the time-to-publication.
So, you actually want to have a curve
here, unlike in,
when we have survival curves.
For this curve, you want to be on the
curve that's dropping steeply,
because that means you got published
quickly, so
time to first publication from a major
grant.
And what they were interested in is that
they thought that
grants that ended up to going on to have a
study, that had a significant or
positive finding, might be more likely to
be published rapidly than a, a study that,
that came out with a no result, didn't
find what it was hoping to find.
This gets at the concept of publication
bias,
which is a major concern in literature.
And, indeed, that's exactly what they
found.
So, the black line here.
The dark black rine, line represents the
studies in which, sort of, the main thing
that they were looking at for this study,
was found to be significant.
They actually, kind of, found what they
were looking for.
They got a significant result.
You can see that that line drops rather
rapidly.
We can look at the median time to
publication if you
have a significant result.
The median time to publication from
funding, if you had a significant result,
was about five years.
And a lot of these studies are trials and
things, they take time to, to actually
carry out the study.
As expected, null results, that is where
you did not find a significant result.
That's the gray line here.
Had a much longer time until publication.
The median time for that group was closer
to eight years, actually.
So, hugely different.
Again, this is gets a publication bias
because sometimes a null result is
just important, is often just important as
a positive result.
So, the fact that these pub, that these
publications are being held out of
the literature for so long creates a bias.
What was also really interesting, which I
love about this study,
was they looked at another group, which is
actually,
really, kind of ended up being a small
group, but pretty interesting here.
So this top line, what is that?
That represents non-significant trends,
so,
if the main hypothesis of your study, you
end up with,
at the end of the day, what we call sort
of a non-significant trend,
it probably means something like P is less
than 0.1 but greater than 0.05.
Didn't reach conventional statistical
significance, but
there's a hint of something.
Maybe the power was too low.
It turned out that that took the longest
to get published,
which I find really interesting.
So, something a little bit about human
nature, we don't like things that are in
a gray area, so those researchers had the
hardest time getting those published,
which is interesting.
So, that's just another example of a
Kaplan-Meier curve.
Just one more set of examples here,
because I want to make one additional
point.
One place you'll see a lot of Kaplan-Meier
curves these days,
is everybody wants to do gene signatures
and
bio-marker signatures for prognosis for
different diseases.
So, very commonly we see in the
literature,
people trying to come up with gene
signatures that can predict, for example,
what cancer patients are most likely to go
on to, have a good result, and which ones
are most likely to, to go on to have a bad
result, and that can guide treatment.
So you're going to, somebody who looks
pretty low risk for
recurrence, you might treat them less
aggressively.
Whereas, somebody who looks very high risk
for
recurrence, you might choose to teat them,
treat them more aggressively.
Just a little caution on these is that
there's been a lot of
things published on gene signatures for
cancer prognosis in the literature that
really haven't held up.
That haven't been able to be replicated
later on.
And you can imagine that there's probably
good reason for that, which is that when
we do things like gene signatures we're
looking at a huge, huge number of markers.
You might be looking at 5,000, 10,000,
20,000 genes.
There's a huge chance of Type one error
here.
And a huge risk of over fitting.
So, a lot of these genes signatures that
look good for a particular group
then fall down when later we try to
validate them in an independent sample.
Now, I'll just show you some examples of
that now.
Sometimes these curves look so beautiful
that they can be very seductive but
be careful to make sure that things have
been properly validated.
So, just as an example,
this was a study published in the New
England Journal of Medicine in 2007.
They found a five gene signature, so some
particular combination of low and
high expression in five genes that seemed
to predict survival in non- smell,
small cell lung cancer.
And, we don't have to go into all the
details.
I don't really want to go into all details
of this particular study.
You can see that there is a whole bunch of
Kaplan-Meier curves here.
But just the broader point is, if you look
at all these
different Kaplan-Meier curves, it does
look like they have pretty good
separation between low risk cancer
patients, who are more likely to survive,
and high risk patients who are more likely
to die and to die more quickly.
So, if you look across the Kaplan-Meier
Curves,
they are representing somewhat different
things, so
some of them are showing relapse free
survival versus overall survival,
one is the outcome of death, one is the
outcome of recurrence and
they're showing it in some slightly
different groups.
But in all the cases, they seem to have
fairly good separation and even g is
actually looking at an independent cord
and even though the curves are a little
bit closer together, they still seem to
have pretty good separation.
All significant long range tests, the last
one,
the log rank test only came up to be 0,.06
but the rest.
You can see the log-rank tests were all
highly statistically significant.
So, looks like there, you know, maybe have
found a good gene signature.
However, others then tried to replicate to
independently validate this
particular signature in a, an entirely new
cohort of patients, and
they didn't find such good separation.
I'm not exactly sure what's going on here,
because they're, turns out the,
the not very many of the patients are
classifying as low risk, so
the low risk group is very small here.
But in any case,
it doesn't seem to separate well at all,
so it makes some question about how
good of a prognostic marker that five gene
signature really was.
And you see this in a lot of examples, so
just one more example,
this is another three gene signature for a
non smell,
small cell lung cancer that was in the
Journal of Clinical Oncology in 2007.
Again, it looked like had really, pretty
good separation of curves.
A lot of the genes had been identified in
other studies.
So, there was some good repeatability
here.
This is showing you stage.
Everybody is in panel B, it shows
everybody.
And then it's broken down into stage one
and stage two patients for lung cancer.
But in any case, again, we've got these
beautiful Kaplan-Meier curves.
Highly significant P values for
the log rank test, looks to be pretty good
separation.
However, when another, that same group had
then tried to validate this in a totally
new sample of lung cancer patients, the
left panel shows stage one patients and
the right panel shows stage two patients,
there wasn't such good separation and
the log rank test is totally null on the
left panel.
And null on the right panel it,
even though there looks to be a tiny bit
of separation there.
So, the point being that, even though
these Kaplan–Meier curves can often look
beautiful when applied to the data that
was used to fit the model,
many times those data don't hold up in
future samples.
And there's a great study in the
literature that's worth me pointing out.
Where some researchers try to get at this
point,
they actually simulated some data to, to
make this point.
So, what they did is they had a data set
of 129 cancer patients and
they knew their time to death for those
patients.
What they then did was though,
to create some mock gene expression data
for 5000 genes.
So they just kind of generated 5000 random
variables off of a random normal
number generator for the 129 patients,
pretending that these were some genes.
Obviously, these variables are completely
random and
have no relationship whatsoever to
survival.
They're just noise.
What they then did was though, because we
have 5,000 variables.
You can imagine here that the type one
error rate is huge.
They are going to find some things that
appear to significantly predict
survival in this group even when they
don't and that's exactly what they showed.
They fit prognostic models for the real
survival data.
They actually know the time to death for
these people using these totally made up
variables.
They get it properly, so
they randomly divide 129 patients into
training sets and test sets.
They only developed the model on the
training sets and then they
properly tested the model on the test sets
who had not been used to fit the model.
They generated Kaplan-Meier curves on the
training data.
Those are obviously going to be over fit,
they're going to be,
because these are what we call
re-substitution statistic.
So this is, again, measuring performance
on the same data that were used to
fit the model, but they then properly
tested the models also on the tests and
then they repeated the simulation a number
of times just to make a point.
So here is their results.
They're fun to look at.
So what you see on the left-hand column
here is the Kaplan-Meier curves
from the Training sets and the log rank
tests that go with them.
Again, based on these 5,000 mock genes.
You can see great separation.
So, they were able to find a set of genes
out of these 5,000 that really predicted,
for each one of these training set the,
who was going to survive for
a long versus a short amount of time, low
risk versus high risk patients.
Huge separation, beautiful Kaplan-Meier
curves, that looks great, and
you can imagine that being published in
the literature,
an everybody being seduced by that.
however, when they then took that same
gene signature that they got out of
the training set and applied it to the
validation set,
the, the data that were held out and not
used to fit the model.
They got no separation at all, the,
the difference from the curves, as we'd
expect, completely disappears, so
now all the Kaplan-Meier curves are
completely overlapping.
The log rank tests are all non
significant.
This is to illustrate that point where
you're not expecting these gene,
these genes shouldn't predict survival
because they're totally made up data,
they have nothing to do with survival.
And then that's illustrated here.
But again, it's easy to get seduced by
these beautiful Kaplan-Meier curves on
the left hand side.
And again, they did this, the simulation
ten times, so
this is just showing you the results for
all ten simulations.
You see the same thing, great separation
on the training set,
totally overoptimistic performance values
when applied, when you're looking
at the training data that were used to fit
the model, when you apply that model to
the validation set, there's absolutely
nothing there, no predictive power [SOUND]