Now we're going to apply maximum
likelihood estimation to
the specific case of logistic regression.
So again, what's our logistic regression
model look like?
Let's write that out to start.
So we have this logit function is equal to
alpha plus beta and
times x, and there might be more than one
beta in the model.
For simplicity I'm just going to stick to
one beta for the moment, but
just realize that there may be more than
one beta in the model.
What we're going to be trying to do now is
to
write out what is the likelihood function
for a logistic regression.
As a function of the unknowns that we want
to estimate, alpha and beta in this case.
So what is the likelihood function going
to be for logistic regression?
So it may help to put a simple example
here.
So hearkening back to the example I talked
about earlier,
where our outcome was a doctor being
disciplined by their state medical board.
I'm just going to give you two
individuals, the likelihood function by
the way for logistic regression is going
to have a term for
every person in our study, so I'm going to
start with two individuals as examples.
So imagine we've got person one from our
data set.
This person is somebody who indeed was
disciplined.
So the outcome of discipline by the
medical board,
that value is equal to one for this
person.
So they actually have the outcome.
They are a case in this case.
And let's say that our predictor, let's
use a simple predictor here, so
let's say we wanted to know whether or
not GPA as an undergraduate predicts
discipline by the medical board later on.
And so let's say their GPA, that person's
GPA happen to be,
we'll make it really abysmal, 1.0.
Make it really bad.
Here's the second person who's in our data
set.
That person was not disciplined.
So they are control, not a case.
They have a value of 0 for that variable
discipline.
The outcome variable.
And, let's say they had a great GPA, we'll
give them, you know, I don't know if
you can get over 4.0, we'll give them 4.0,
saying that's the highest you can get.
Alright, so those are just two examples
that I can have some numbers to
plug in here.
So now, imagine we fit a logistic
regression model.
So we fit a logistic regression model.
Our outcome is this disciplinary action by
the medical, state medical board.
And we're going to have some alpha that
we're trying to solve for
plus some beta that relates to GPA.
If I want to know, if I was to write a, an
equation for
the likelihood here, just for these two
individuals.
So again, the likelihood is going to be a
function of alpha and
beta, because those are the unknowns we
have to solve for later.
So what's the likelihood function?
If, if for this particular logistical
regression model, for these two people.
So the first person here actually got the
disease, or
had the outcome, they got disciplined.
So, that's what we saw in our data.
This is a person who was disciplined.
Therefore, what they're going to get in
the likelihood model
is the probability that, that particular
person would actually be disciplined.
That they would have a value of 1.
The second person did not get disciplined.
So we're going to plug into the likelyhood
the probability that they
wouldn't have gotten disciplined.
because that's what we saw, they were not
disciplined.
And then we're going to plug in a new term
for every person in our data set.
But I'm just going to focus on two to keep
it simple here.
Now, what is that actual, what is that
probability?
Well that probability, remember what we
get out of a logistic regression model is
we can calculate the predicted probability
for
a person as a function of their predictors
such as GPA in this case.
And we showed earlier that the probability
from a logistic regression model,
the probability of having the outcome, is
equal to e raised to alpha plus beta,
whatever the betas are.
In this case, it's beta GPA.
And you're going to plug in the person's
actual value for GPA and
then 1 plus e alpha plus beta in the
denominator.
I showed you in an earlier module that
that gives you the predicted probability
for person i.
That's the probability of having the
event.
You can also calculate for a person the
probability of not having the event.
We're going to need that for the controls.
That's just going to be 1 minus what you
see here.
Well 1 minus all of that, will just give
me, 1 over 1 plus e
raise to the alpha plus beta times the xi,
for the person who is not disciplined.
So, this is how we calculate the
predictive probability and
1 minus that predictive probability.
Well now we're going to do that just
plugging in the actual data from this
particular dataset.
So the person who, got disciplined, their
probability of being disciplined as
a function of alpha, the unknown alphas
and betas, and
their actual GPA is just going to equal e
raised to alpha plus beta GPA
times in this case they have a GPA of 1.0,
so we're just going to plug that GPA in.
And the denominator is going to be 1 plus
that same term.
So that's the probability for the first
person.
The probability for the second person, the
probability that that, the second
person would not have been disciplined,
it's going to be one minus that, so
it's going to be 1 over 1 plus e raised to
alpha plus the beta GPA.
And that person had a value of GPA of 4.0.
And then you're going to continue on this
likelihood function.
You can see this likelihood function is
going to become rather complex.
You're going to continue that on for all
the other, one term for
every person in the study.
That's the formula of likelihood function
for an unconditional logistic regression.
Alright, so what does this do?
This is going to be a, you can see quite a
complicated likelihood function although
I'm going to use the simple example and
actually maximizes simple example later in
this Module.
But what, what conceptually are we doing?
We are saying, I want to find, I'm
going to then maximize this long, long
function to find the values of alpha and
beta that make my data the most likely.
So what's that going to look like?
Well, let's say that GPA is indeed related
to discipline.
So we get a lot of people who are
disciplined having low GPAs, and
a lot of people who are controls, who
weren't disciplined having high GPAs.
So what that's going to mean is that we're
going to end up finding out
that beta all the cases where the beta
appears in the numerator.
Those are going to be the cases where the
GPAs are low, and where it's only in
the denominator, it's going to be the
cases where the GPA is high.
So mathematically, when we go to maximize
that function,
it's going to turn out that we're going to
see a connection between GPA and
who got disciplined and who didn't.
So we're going to find a beta that
connects those two.
So again, we're going to take this
complicated likelihood function,
we're going to maximize it to solve for
alpha and
beta, and that's going to define the
relationship between GPA and the outcome.
Just written out in a slightly different
way.
We're going to be multiplying for all the
cases everybody who had
the outcome the probability, the predicted
probability that they would have a,
an out the outcome using the logistic
regression model.
And for all the controls,
all the people who didn't have the outcome
we'll be multiplying their probability of
not having the outcome because that's
actually what we saw.
We saw exactly these people have the
outcome and
exactly these other people did not.
Now that's one of many possible outcomes.
Imagine you have 100 people in your data
set.
These particular 50, where the cases in
these particular 50 were the controls.
That's one possible outcome.
That's the outcome we saw.
But imagine all the other possible
outcomes.
The person with the GPA of 1, could have
actually not been disciplined.
And so on.
You can imagine that there's a huge,
huge number of possible outcomes here.
We saw one particular outcome.
The likelihood function defines the
probability of that outcome.
So again, just kind of plugging in here
for
all the cases we have some logistic
regression model, the probability from
the logistic regression model of being the
case is that.
The probability of being a control is that
and we'll try and
solve for these betas and alphas.
And of course we're going to be plugging
in for
every person their individual values of
these x's.
You can see, it would be really tedious to
maximize this function by hand, but
there's ways that the computer has of some
iterative methods that will
actually essentially do this maximum
likelihood problem.
What are we going to do?
Well, it's just like we did with the coin
problem.
We're going to take the log of the
likelihood function so
that the product becomes a sum, because
we've got this huge product,
we need to make it a sum to make it easier
to take derivatives.
We're going to take the derivative of that
log likelihood function,
we're going to set that derivative equal
to zero, and we're going to solve for
the alphas and betas.
So in the exact same way we did with the
coin problem, there is a way to get,
from that likelihood function, to get the
to maximize it to
get the most likely alpha and, alphas and
betas given our data.
Now, what actually goes on behind the
scenes in the computer,
it doesn't actually really take the
derivatives.
It uses an algorithm that kind of
approximates that.
But that turns out to be very good and
it's computationally feasible.
But I'm going to actually walk you through
doing out the,
the calculus for a very simple logistic
regression example.
We're going to take the example where we
have just a 2 by 2 table,
binary outcome, binary predictor, and
that's it.
We're going to translate this into the
logistic regression picture.
So, if we have just a 2 by 2 table, what
goes in cell A?
So, cell A is all the people who did have
the outcome and were exposed.
And we have in my logistic regression
model here,
remember, it's going to be something very
simple.
It's just going to have an alpha and it's
going to have a beta.
And that beta's for a binary variable.
So, X is going to be equal to either one
or X is equal to 0 and that's it.
So, it's a very simple model.
Call this beta 1.
So if you have the exposure, you're
going to be multiplying beta 1 times 1,
and so you're, you will have beta 1 in
your equation.
If you have the disease, you get e over 1
plus e rather than 1 over 1 + e,
so it gives you again,
the probability of having the disease is
equal to this e over 1 plus e.
The probability of not having the disease
is equal to 1 minus that,
which is just turns out to be 1 over 1
plus [INAUDIBLE].
So if you are not exposed and you have the
disease, what happens?
Well your predicted probability of having
the disease based on
the logistic regression model is your,
you, your x value is 0.
You do not have the exposure, so the beta
term goes away, so your probability of
having the disease is just e raised alpha
over 1 plus e raised to alpha.
What about somebody who doesn't get the
disease, but was exposed?
So that person's logistic regression
equation will be alpha plus beta times 1,
so the beta will remain in, because
they're exposed.
However, they did not get the disease.
They're a control, so we calculate for
them the probability of not getting the
disease, because that's what we saw.
So that's this 1 over 1 plus e.
And then for somebody who has neither the
exposure, nor
the disease, the beta drops out, so it's
just e over, it's e, e raised to alpha.
And they didn't get the disease, so it's
just 1 over 1 plus e.
So those are the probabilities for what we
saw in this experiment for
every person who either, have the exposure
or it, or you don't.
You either have the disease or you don't
and that translates to different terms,
these four different terms that will go in
the likelihood function.
And just to show you if I actually
multiply in this case a times d divided by
b times c, when I do that, you notice a
lot of things cancel here.
Cancel.
And we end up with.
This also cancels, we end up with just e
raised to beta.
Well, guess what, the odds ratio is a
times d divided by b times c, and
it's also e raised to beta.
So that assures you that it comes out as
we would expect.
So now, just to plug in some real numbers
so
we can actually do a maximum likelihood
estimation problem here.
So let's, simple example.
You are either older or you are younger.
Are you more likely to have heart disease
or not?
Very simple example.
Some numbers thrown in this example.
There were 21 people who were over 55 who
also had cardiovascular disease.
22 people younger than 55 who did and so
on.
So we're going to take these data and
we're going to put them into the
likelihood function.
So what's the likelihood function going to
look like here?
So this is again the like, the model here,
the logistic regression model is really
simple.
It's just alpha plus beta 1 times x 1.
X 1 is either 1 or 0, it's a binary
predictor.
So you're only going to have beta 1 in the
model if you're older, if you are exposed,
you're not going to have beta in the model
if you're unexposed because it
will just be multiplied by 0.
So going, using those four terms that I
already showed you for the predicted
probabilities for each of the different
types of people in my 2 by 2 table, so
this was the predicted probability for
those who got the disease and
had the exposure this is the probability
of being a control for
those who were controls but had the
exposure and so on.
Well every person, now in that cell a, for
example, is going to get that same
likelihood because this is a very simple
example and everybody shares exposures.
There's only one binary exposure.
There were 21 people who get that term in
the likelihood.
We're going to multiply that 21 times.
There were six people who were exposed but
did not have the disease.
And they are each going to get this term,
we are going to multiple that 6 times.
There were 22 people who get this term and
there were 51 who
have neither the exposure nor the disease
and they're going to get this term.
So even though the likelihood function for
a big study like this is, you know,
there's lots of people that we have to
multiply one term in the likelihood for
each person.
There's a lot of people that look the same
for a simple 2 by 2 example, so
we can simplify it.
This represents a, a very complicated
function,
however, because we have a lot of things
multiplied together.
But in fact, for this very simple case, we
can maximize this function by hand, so
we're going to do that now.
So that's the likelihood function, this is
the probability of our data of seeing
exactly 21 in cell A, and exactly 6 in
cell C etcetera, as a function of
our unknowns alpha and beta, so now we're
going to try to solve for alpha and beta.
So as I mentioned before, you want to
first take a log, because that
will help to linearize the function and
make it easier take, to take derivatives.
So I've gone ahead and taken a log here.
So, just some rules to remind you about
how logs work,
I've put those little rules in yellow up
in on the top in case you've forgotten.
But if I'm going to take the log of the
likelihood function,
I've already done it out here just to save
time just,
I just want you to follow what I've done.
So I'm taking the log of this function.
So remember that with if you take the log,
the powers come down in front, and
things that are multiplied together become
added together.
Things that are in the denominator when
you take a log become subtracted.
So hopefully you can follow the logic
here.
I'm not going to go through,
just to save time here, of how to take the
log of this com, complicated function.
I've done it out here again for this first
one.
You take the log, the 21 comes in front
because that's a power.
You'll be adding the log of e raised to
alpha plus beta,
I guess I'll just do the first one out
here, so, you get the idea.
That was raised to 21, when we take the
log, the 21 comes down in front.
We end up with the natural log of e raised
to alpha plus beta, but
remember that the natural log in e are the
inverses, so
in fact those cancel and we just end up
with 21 times alpha plus beta.
For the denominator we end up with the
negative, the 21 remains in front,
21 and then we just end up with the log of
1 plus e alpha plus beta.
There is no way to simplify that because
the log is applied across the 1, e and
d, and so on and so forth.
So you take the log here.
You did this whole function out and you
take the log.
For fun, if you want to do it on your own
feel free to pause the video and
try to, to do that out on your own.
Make sure you get the same answer as me.
All right, so here's the log likelihood
function.
Next thing we have to do to, to find the
maximum point is to take the derivative.
So again just to kind of save time here
I've gone through and
done out the derivatives already.
For a fun challenge for those of you who
are interested you could
pause the video and try to take the
derivatives on your own.
But I'll just walk you through the general
logic here.
So there's two unknowns so we have to take
the derivative with respect to
alpha separately from the derivative with
respect to beta.
Now where did the various things come from
in the derivative?
So, let me talk about the derivative with
respect to beta first.
So the first term is 21 alpha plus beta.
Well if I multiply that out, I get 21
alpha plus 21 beta.
Alright.
Alpha, when we're taking the derivative
with respect to beta,
the alpha becomes a constant, so the 21
alpha actually will,
when we take the derivative it's just a
constant, will go to 0.
21 beta will become 21, so
hopefully you remember your rules of
derivative, you have 21x,
if you take the derivative of that that's
just going to be 21, you lose the x.
Okay, so that's the first.
Second term here requires you to remember
little bit more calculus but
basically again I got a beta in this term,
so
this is not a constant since my beta is my
unknown.
The negative will be preserved.
The 21 will be preserved.
So we'll still have the negative 21, and
then you have to remember, how do you take
the derivative of a log.
So the derivative of a log is, the
derivative of the log x is 1 over x.
So in this case the derivative of log of
everything that's in that parentheses,
that just goes in the denomenator.
Kay, so that, the derivative of log x is 1
over x.
So we put here everything that's inside
these parentheses, 1 over that.
Then we have to use chain rule.
So what's the chain rule?
So the chain rule says that we then have
to take the derivative of everything
that's inside the parenthesis.
So again the derivative of 1 is 0 because
that's a constant.
But what's the derivative of e raised to
alpha plus beta?
Well it might help you to remember that
the derivative of you know,
e raised to x is just itself e raised to
x.
the, the x, so that is easy,
the derivative of the exponential function
is just the exponential function.
So in fact when we take the derivative of
e raised to alpha plus beta,
it just becomes e raised to alpha plus
beta.
We then have to take the derivative of
beta but that's just 1.
So we don't end up with anything extra
there.
So that defines this term here and we do
the same logic for the next term.
And then we take the derivative with
respect to alpha, so
we get a 22 alpha becomes 22 and so on and
so forth.
So that's how you take the derivative, and
again I don't want to over emphasize the
actual mechanics of doing the derivative.
It's most important that you just believe
me that those are the derivatives and
if you want and you're interested and it's
fun for
you to do calculus, feel free to, to go
through that on your own.
All right, so next we're going to maximize
the function.
So we'll start with the derivative of
alpha function.
We actually need to solve for
alpha first so that we can then plug alpha
into the function for beta.
So, here's what we get out when we set
that function that
I just showed on the previous slide, the
derivative with respect to alpha.
When we set that equal to zero, we get out
this function here and
then it's just algebraic rearrangement.
So, you know, I,
I'm just algebraically arranging here in
order to be able to solve this function.
So I'm going to add up these two because
22 e over alpha plus 51 or
e over alpha this gets me the 73 here, the
denominators are the same
cross multiplying doing you know, some
subtraction the division here.
So I end up with if I solved all the
algebra here.
And again, feel free to kind of pause the
video and walk through that on your own.
Make sure you get the same answer, but I'm
going to go over it quickly to save time.
The we end up that e alpha is equal to 22
over 51.
So e alpha, e raised to alpha is 22 over
51.
Notice what that is.
So think back to our 2 by 2 table, we had
21 in cell A,
we had 6 in cell C, 22 and 51, so what
was, what's the 22 over 51?
Well that was among the unexposed, that is
the odds of disease in the unexposed.
Well that's what alpha represents, alpha
represents the odds of
getting the disease in the unexposed
group, because that's the group you have,
you get alpha if you're, if you are
unexposed and the beta drops out.
And only the intercept applies to you,
so that's the odds of disease in the
unexposed.
Now we can also take the natural log of
this 22 over 51 and
we will get a value of about negative
0.84, so
the, so alpha, e alpha is 22 over 51,
alpha is equal to -0.84.
That represents the log odds of the
disease in the unexposed group.
So that's maximizing alpha.
We can then take that alpha and plug it in
to solve for beta.
So now we're going to maximize the beta
function.
So again, take the equation, the log
likelihood equation that I showed you in
the earlier slides, set that equal to 0.
Do some algebraic rearrangement and
notice that I've I'm going to have to plug
in for alpha.
So later on I'm going to plug in the 22
divided by 51 for alpha.
When I've solved down then I can just plug
that in for e alpha.
So I do some algebraic rearrangement here.
Set the derivatives equal here.
Do that algebraic rearrangement, solve for
e raised to beta.
That becomes 21 over 6 divided by e raised
to alpha, then I plug in we
already solved for alpha, that was 22 over
51, and when I solve this out,
I solved it out in such a way that I can
show you that the e raised to beta just
turns out to be our normal odds ratio, so
21 times 51,
6 times 22, so A times B, divided by B
times, A times D divided by B times C.
That gives us our odds ratio that we're
expecting there so
e raised to beta, we've proven, then just
comes out to be the odds ratio that we
normally see from a two by two table.
We can also solve all the way for beta, so
if I take the log of this value,
21 times 51 divided by 6 times 22.
That's going to give me that beta is equal
to about 2.09,
and of course if you exponentiate that
you'll get the odds ratio.
The odds ratio here comes out to be about
8.
So now we solve for beta using maximum
likelihood estimation.
And I'll just show you that I threw these
data also into a computer, and
I ran them in a logistic regression.
It's a very simple problem, just a two by
two table, but
you can run a logistic regression on it.
The outcome will be you get heart disease
or
not, and older age is the binary
predictor.
And indeed, just to show you where you
find these things in computer output.
We get the estimates that we just
estimated by hand,
from maximum likelihood estimation.
So we get that negative 0.84 for the
intercept, we get the 2.09 for the beta.
Those estimates, you know the computer
does easily for you, so
we don't have to do these by hand, but
it's good just to walk through that whole
logic one time so that you've seen it.
I'll just point out that not only do we
get the alpha and
the beta, we also get the standard error
here.
I'll talk more about that in the next
module.
But as I mentioned before, maximum
likelihood estimation spits you
out the standard error, which is a
function of the second derivative.
Notice that both of these came out to be
significant in these,
in this case, the odds ratio here came out
to be 8.
I get that just by exponentiating the
2.09.
I'm just going to throw in one more
example, just for fun,
if you've had enough, you can, you can
stop here, but just for one more example
to see the likelihood again done out for a
slightly more complicated data set.
This is a two by four data set rather than
a two by two data set, but
imagine again our, our outcome here is
heart disease, you either have it or
you don't, and then there's various races.
There's usually a categorical variable in
this data set.
You see this written down in the
contingency table,
we could apply a chi square here.
We could also run a logistic regression.
And what would the likelihood function be
here?
It's only slightly more complicated, but
just let me remind you what the, this is
going to involve dummy coding.
So what the logistic model will look like,
there will be an alpha.
I'm going to make the white group the
reference group here, and
then we're going to have a beta for the
other races.
So a beta for black, and a beta for
Hispanic, and a beta for other, and these
are dummy code of variables, so you're in
one of those four groups, you get a 1 for
one in those and a 0 for the rest, if you
get a 0 for all three you end up,
you'd just be in the reference group, that
means you're in the white group.
We can code this any way you want.
Any one of those can be the reference
group.
I coded in this way because the reference,
given the, the reference group,
the one that has the lowest risk of heart
disease.
So that's what a logistic model would look
like.
What does the likelihood function look
like?
Again, this is for fun, but
just to show what the likelihood function
would look like, we have group data again.
So there's five people that look the same,
20 people that look the same.
But the terms, so for, if you're white and
you do have heart disease, the predicted
probability from that logistic regression
model would look like this.
There's five of those people.
And everybody's going to get the
intercept, and
if you're in a different racial group,
you'll also get the additional beta for
the race group that you're in, and
I've just raised all of these to the
numbers from that contingency table.
So that's what the likelihood function
would look like here.
Now actually applying calculus, here to
take the derivative and solve for the,
you know, for each one of those betas is
beyond what I would ever want you to do,
but you could do it if you had to, or even
let the computer do it for you.
So I just plug these data into a computer.
The computer maximizes that likelihood
function for me.
Here is the results that we get out at the
end of the day.
Again, I get some estimates.
Those come out of maximum likelihood
estimation.
They come with the standard error.
We also get to see whether or not
individual betas are significant or not.
We also get something out, up here called
the likelihood ratio test,
which I'm going to talk about in the next
module.
Just point it out here.
So you get, it's a chi squared value, in
this case it has, it's a chi square with
three degrees of freedom, and that's
because there's three betas in the model.
We so we get three degrees of freedom.
So that comes out to be significant and
what the interpretation there is that
tells you that race,
that categorical variable, overall, has
some predictive power here.
That's different than looking at the
individual p values for
the individual racial groups.
This gives you a total over the
categorical variable of race,
it's more similar to a chi-square.
Overall, there's some difference in heart
disease, somewhere among those races.
And that's what the likelihood ratio test
tells you.
It looks at all those three betas at once,
rather than giving you individual betas
for, p values for the individual betas.
So I just allude to that, because we're
going to be
talking about the likelihood ratio test in
the next module.