In this next module, we're going to dive
right in to the logistic regression model.
We've talked about, when you have binary
or categorical outcomes that, that is when
you're looking at proportions, we've
talked about some statistical tests,
when you don't want to adjust for anything
that you can use.
So this is like the risk difference,
relative risk, the chi square test,
the McNemar's chi-square test.
So we talked about those, but what about
when you want to
do a regression analysis when you have a
binary or categorical outcome?
In that case, you're going to be using
logistic regression,
which we're going to talk about in this
module.
I want to just give you a little overview
of logistic regression.
So to remind you,
when we did linear regression, the model
looked like the following.
We were predicting the value of some
continuous outcome variable,
call it y, as a function of x.
Here's the simple linear regression model.
We have the intercept alpha, and beta is
our slope.
So that was the simple linear regression
model; in the multivariate regression
model, we can add some additional betas
and exes, additional predictors.
That makes it then a plane or a higher
dimension thing.
But, essentially we're fitting lines,
linear regression.
Logistic regression actually isn't that
different; the right-hand side of
the equation is identical in logistic
regression.
So it's going to look something like this.
There's a linear combination of betas and,
and exes, risk factors; it looks exactly
the same.
And everything's going to be set up
exactly the same in terms of
defining the predictors of the, of the
model.
You can put binary predictors in; you can
put continuation,
you could put categorical, you can do
dummy coding.
All of that is the same as with linear
regression.
What's different in logistic regression is
the left-hand side of the equation.
We are no longer modeling Yi, the outcome
variable, directly,
rather, we're going to be modeling a
transformation of the outcome variable.
In logist-, the case of logistic
regression,
we're going to be modelling the log odds
of the outcome.
And I know that sounds terrible, that's
called a logit function, but
don't worry I'll explain why in a minute.
We're going to be modelling this logit
function, the log odds of the outcome,
that's our outcome variable.
We're going to be modelling that as a line
though,
as an alpha plus a beta x, a intercept and
a slope.
Because we've made this transformation,
the beta is just slightly more
complicated to interpret than the beta
from linear regression.
So for linear regression, the beta was
just the slope.
It's, as x goes up by one unit, how much
does y go up?
So there was a direct interpretation.
It's just slightly more tricky to
interpret the betas from
logistic regression.
But actually, it's not terrible, because
the betas from logistic regression,
if you exponentiate them, what it gives
you out is the odds ratio.
And I referred to, in the second week of
the course,
we talked a lot about odds ratios, and I
told you,
hey, logistic regression spits out odds
ratios, and this is where it comes from.
The betas can be directly interpreted as
odds ratios just by exponentiating,
and the reason there's an exponential
involved is because our outcome variable
involves a natural log.
So this is just the overview of where
we're going this.
Just keep in mind that the right hand side
of
the equation's the same as with linear
regression.
So we're still fitting a line its just
we're fitting the outcome variable,
there's something trickier going on.
Let me start here with a simple example
using that example data set,
data set on my Stanford students.
One of the questions I asked my Stanford
students is whether or
not they considered themselves to be
book-smart or street-smart.
This is a binary variable.
Book smart the, the variable is equal to
one,
that means that they consider themselves
book smart.
If the variable is equal to zero, the way
I've coded it,
that means that they consider themselves
to be street smart.
So we can see that this is the book smart
group over here, and
this is the street smart book group over
here.
And I, just as an aside, I've been asking
this question to lots of
Stanford students just for fun over the
years.
And it generally comes out about 80% of my
Stanford students consider themselves to
be book smart, and about 20% consider
themselves to be street smart.
And that was indeed the case in this
little practice data set,
it's right around 80%.
I wondered if book smart students did
more,
spent more time on homework, were more
studious, than street smart students.
And so I wanted to look at the variable
homework in the number of
hours per week that they spent on
homework.
That's another question that I had asked
these students.
And we can look at that here and
I've done this, I've looked at this
graphically here.
So, I'm graphing my predictor variable is
just the binary a yes, no, book smart or
not and my outcome variable here is
homework and the number of hours per week.
And now surprisingly the number of
students who consider themselves book
smart as you can see from this graphic
here, actually on average, do
slightly less homework than the students
who consider themselves street smart for
whatever reason.
So it went kind of in the opposite
direction from what I might have expected.
This analysis, this graphic that I'm
showing you here actually coincides with
a linear regression.
So the way I've set up the problem now is
I've got a binary predictor variable, and
a continuous outcome variable, homework.
And we could model this with a linear
regression using what we
talked about last week.
When we have a binary predictor, it's a
very simple linear regression.
Right, that line is just, you connect to
the mean for
the street smart group with the mean for
the book smarts group and when,
if you connect two points with a line
that, that defines a line.
And so we end up with a very simple line.
So we could answer this question,
look at this question in this data set
with a linear regression or
even a T-test, which of course is a
special case of a linear regression.
This is cross sectional data, however, so
I've happened to pick, just for
the purposes of illustration in, for this
slide to put book smart as the x variable,
as the predictor and homework as the
outcome variable.
But because this is cross sectional data,
I could ask, I could flip that.
I could ask not whether or not whether you
classify yourself as book smart,
predicts the amount of homework you would
do, but I could, ask it the other way,
does the amount of homework you do, the
amount of time you spend on homework,
predict whether or not you consider
yourself book smart?
So, I'm just going to flip the x and y
variables.
So here's the graphic when I flip the x
and y variables.
So, now my x, my predictor variable is
continuous: the number of
hours spent on homework per week.
And my outcome variable is this binary,
this yes,
no: zero is street smart, one is
booksmart.
We've got a new graphic and we could try
to fit a line to these data.
But look what happens when I try to fit a
line through these data; notice that
all of my my outcomes are either all one
or
all zero, so you just get these two
stripes.
And it doesn't, it doesn't seem optimal to
try to fit a line.
I did fit a line to these data.
You can do it, you, this is a linear
regression line so
I fit the linear, the best fit line to
these data.
But you can see, that if you look at
this picture it doesn't really look like
that line fits the data very well, right?
I mean when we were doing linear
regression last week,
we had these scatter plots and
we were trying to find the line that was
kind of very close to all those dots.
Well, this line does, I mean, you can fit
it,
but it doesn't look very close to all
those dots.
It doesn't look like a very good fit.
So a linear regression model was not
optimal here.
Well, what do we do?
Again, I told you, we're still going to
want to fit lines here, so
how can we still fit a line but do
something other than linear regression?
How could we, what could we do?
So what we could do here is to transform
the outcome variable.
Again, I still want to fit a line
ultimately, but I don't want a zero,
one variable as my outcome, because a
zero,
one variable just doesn't fit well to a
line.
It has only two possible values.
So what could I do?
How could I transform that binary, that
zero,
one variable into something that better
fits a line?
Well here is one thing; this is where just
a starting point because we're
going to go further with this,
but let's just start with with some simple
thing that we can do.
So recognize that instead of modeling it
as a yes, no,
a zero, one, what if we could somehow
model it as a probability?
A probability, as you know, is a value
that ranges from zero to one,
but it can take on any value between zero
and one.
So we would do a little bit better,
we would put in all these values between
Between zero and one back into play.
If somehow we could model this as we could
make the outcome variable
the probability of being booksmart, rather
than yes, no you are booksmart.
Just looking at the data here, you can
see,
well, that's not immediate obvious,
immediately obvious how you would do it.
In fact, we're going to do something
called the logit,
which is the function of the probability
and
in fact, what the computer is going to do
is do a little algorithm involving some
calculus to calculate the probability,
here, the logit.
But we could kind of approximate it just
actually looking at the data, and
I think this is the best way to, to
understand it.
So, if I wanted to get a probability here
rather than a zero,
one variable, imagine I did the following.
What if I just, to get a probability, I'm
going to have to
look at more then one person, I'm going to
have to look at a group of people.
So what if I kind of arbitrarily looked at
you know, a group of people let's
just pick say the, the 10 people with the
lowest amount of homework time per week.
Notice that these little red dots here,
actually some of these dots represent more
than one person, because there were a lot
of people who had tied values.
They selected the same number of homework
and they also called themselves book smart
for example, so that, well, each of these
dots may represent more than one person.
So imagine that this and this what I put
in this box here, represents ten people.
I could look at the, say the ten people
with the lowest amount of homework time,
putting in the lowest amount of homework
time, and
I could count up how many of them called
themselves book smart and
how many of them called themselves street
smart.
And I could calculate a proportion, a
percentage, a probability.
So let's say, I'm just making this up, but
let's say when I calculate that, again
since some of these dots are overlapping,
I can't do it exactly, but from the
graphic, but let's say I count up and
I find that among those doing the least
Amount of homework, let's say that
90% of them, again I'm just making this
up, let's say 90% of that 10,
nine out of 10, consider themselves book
smart rather than street smart.
Now I've got a probability, rather than a
zero, one.
And I could do this for
the next next group of ten, the next
highest in homework.
Maybe in the next group, the probability
is again I'm just making this up,
is 85% and I can't tell, because again
these dots are overlapping.
Maybe that comes out to be 85% but I could
go along and I could group people,
I have to group people in order to be able
to get a percentage, a probability, but
I could come up with some probabilities.
And of course the probabilities I come up
with are going to depend exactly on how I
group them, but just realize that the
grouping is just for
the purposes of illustration.
When you actually do this with calculus,
you don't have to make any arbitrary
groupings.
Of course we won't go through the calculus
here, but the computer does that for you.
So if I could get that probability, now I
can make a graphic which is
my predictor variable is the number of
hours of homework per week,
the continuous variable.
Now my outcome variable is a probability,
a number that ranges between zero and one.
I have fewer dots on this graphic.
I'm going to just for now, talk about the
graphic on the left side, this 10 groups.
Notice I have fewer dots on that graphic,
none of these dots are overlapping
anymore.
So, I actually have a, I had, my previous
graphic represented 48 people,
this graphic only represents 10
observations.
I divided those 48 people up into roughly
even, groups of 10 groups of,
you know, somewhere between about four or
five per group.
And I got those percentages and I plotted
them here.
What you notice is,
this is much more amenable, this, this
scatter plot, to fitting a line.
Right now we've got dots all around the
range, and
you can imagine actually fitting a
meaningful line to those dots.
As I mentioned, this is just for
the purposes of graphing, just to show you
the concept.
And, so it's arbitrary how I group people,
so of course,
the graphic's going to look a little bit
different depending on how I group people.
So just to show you that I also divided it
into five groups, there's 48 people, so
this is roughly groups of, you know,
eight, nine, or 10, and
I calculated the proportion who considered
themselves book smart,
that probability in each of those five
groups and I plotted it here.
By the way when I'm, each of these groups
of course has a range of homework values.
I'm using the mean homework time for each
group,
that's what I'm putting in the plot here.
So for example, the lowest homework group
on this plot here, they have
a mean homework time of just, you know,
and maybe, thirty minutes to an hour, and
there, the proportion that considered
themselves book smart was right about 78%.
So I'm using the mean, just for graphical
purposes.
But the picture looks a little different
depending on how you group it, but
you can get the idea.
Now we've put back all the numbers between
zero and
one into play, it makes much more sense to
fit a line.
But this is still limited, okay, so this
is not, we're going to go further than
that, with this, because a probability is
a number that's bounded between zero and
one, so it's still a bounded quantity.
You can't go lower than zero, you can't go
higher than one.
The problem with that is, imagine when we
fit a line, when you fit a line,
theoretically, that line can go anywhere
from negative in-,
the y-value can go anywhere from negative
infinity to positive infinity.
So, well this, this is still not perfect.
So, what we're going to do is, instead of
directly having the probability
be the outcome variable, we're going to
make a little transformation.
So, probability is bounded from zero to
one.
If I divide the probability however, by 1
minus the probability,
that of course is what we had learned
earlier is the odd.
So divide the probability by the
probability of something not happened, so
the probability divided by 1 minus the
probability.
That's what we learned in Week two of the
course is in odds.
Why would I want to do that?
Well, a probability can't be bigger than
one,
but an odds can go from anywhere, anywhere
from zero to positive infinity.
The odds has no right-hand bound.
So now we've put in all the positive real
numbers back into play.
We're still missing the negatives.
How can we get the negatives back in?
So here's where the natural log comes in.
So if I then take the natural log of the
odds, it turns out that when you take
a natural log, any value that was below
one now becomes a negative number.
So this, the natural log of the odds,
actually ranges from negative,
can theoretically range from negative
infinity to positive infinity.
So now we've put all the numbers back into
play, so now this is the most optimal for
fitting a line.
So the outcome variable for logistic
regression, as I've mentioned earlier,
is actually going to be the natural log of
the odds of the outcome; a little
complicated but it's for mathematical
reasons that we, we choose that.
And just to illustrate, I took those, the
same groupings, ten groups and
five groups, where I had calculated the
percent, the probability of
being book smart in each of those groups
and I transformed that into a log odd.
So that is I took the percentage divided
by 1 minus the percentage and
then took the natural log of that number.
This gives me some numbers like 0.5, 1.0,
1.5, 2.0.
The, the log odds has no inherent meaning
to me, but that's okay 'because when we,
eventually we'll translate it back into
something meaningful.
But now, this outcome variable is a number
that can theoretically go anywhere from
negative infinity to positive infinity,
makes a very fit, nice for fitting a line.
I'm graphing here the logit for each of
these groups against again, the mean
homework time in each of those groups, and
you could fit a line to that.
And that's what we're doing in
logistic regression; that's the line that
we're fitting.
So we're going to estimate an alpha and
beta, an intercept and
a slope for that particular line.
As I mentioned, the groupings here are
completely arbitrary.
When you actually do this in the computer,
there's calculus going on, and so
you're going to get the best alpha and the
best beta.
When I do this graphically, it's a little
bit of an approximation.
You can see that the line is slightly
different when I group it into ten groups,
than when I group it into five groups;
these lines are slightly different.
But, we can actually kind of look at these
graphics and just kind of
visually approximate the equation of that
line, so I'm going to do that now.
This is not as good as doing the calculus
in the computer, but
it is, it'll give us a little bit of an
approximation.
And it'll, I think it's also good for
illustrating what's actually going on
here.
So what is the equation of this line?
There's two lines here and we can kind of
say the,
the real line is going to be somewhere
around the these two.
So first of all what's the intercept
value?
So if I just look at the graphic, my
intercept for this line over on the left
side is oh, I'm going to guess about 1.6,
you know I'm just approximating here.
And the intercept over for
the line on the right hand side of the
page is maybe about 1.8.
So lets just kind of call it that the, the
equation for
this line again if we're kind of saying
there's one line here that we're trying to
approximate, maybe it's around 1.7; I'm
just making,
it's somewhere in that ballpark, maybe
around 1.7 is the intercept.
How would I get the slopes of these lines?
Just visually here, how could I
approximate the slopes of these lines?
So what's a slope?
It's rise over run.
So, I could say well, how much have I gone
up in the y variable and
how much have I gone up in the x variable?
So I can just kind of look at this as a
triangle here and
say, well, what's the, how far did I go
on, on the x-axis?
I went from about zero to 40, so the x
changes about 40 here for this triangle.
On the y end of things, yeah,
if you kind of approximate it's maybe
going from about 0.3 maybe to 1.6.
I'm going to just call it 1.3, so sorry
the,
you the, we go up 1.3 in the log odds.
So the slope here is going to be rise over
run so 1.3 divided by 40 or
approximately 0.03 so the slope here is
about 0.03.
For this line we can use the same kind of
logic.
So, for the x we went over about 35 here,
that's about zero to 35.
On the y end,
we've gone up a little bit bigger, maybe
about 1.8, from one to about 1.8.
The slope then would be 1.8 divided by 35,
which is about 0.05.
So, you know, this somewhere, I'm going to
approximate somewhere between 0.03 and
0.05, let's call it 0.04.
And of course this is negative,
I should emphasize here that this is a
downward slope.
We've gone down, 1.3 or down 1.8 in y.
So both of these slopes are negative so
on average, the slope is going to be
somewhere around negative .04.
This is just my graphical approximation,
but
that's what we're doing on logistic
regression, that's the line we're fitting.
Now I'm actually going to put the data in
the computer and
let the computer use the beautiful
calculus to estimate this perfectly to get
the actual best intercept and best beta
slope that fits these data.
And I'll show you that our approximation
wasn't bad.
Here's what the computer comes out with
when it does what's called maximum
likelihood estimation, this involves
calculus.
And, this is just the way that using some
calculus that we're getting
the best alpha and the best beta here, the
best fit line.
So, when I do this on the computer, the
intercept comes out to be just over two.
So it's just slightly different than what
we did, got in our approximation.
The slope came out to be right around
negative 04, negative .039.
So, and where did I get those in the
output?
Here's the estimate for the intercept,
that's the alpha estimate.
Here's the estimate for the beta, that's
the estimate for the slope.
Along with the alpha and the beta, we also
get a p-value to tell us whether that
alpha or beta is statistically different
than zero.
A beta of zero would mean no association,
same as it did with linear regression.
So the intercept is clearly significantly
different than zero.
again, that's not all that meaningful
here,
because we wouldn't expect the intercept
to be zero.
However the, the p value for homework is
not statistically
significant, so as you might have guessed
just looking at the picture, there
isn't a strong association here, so it's
not statistically different than zero.
Probably meaning it doesn't look like
there's a lot of evidence that
homework and whether or not you consider
yourself book smart are related.
But here's the final model.
The log odds of your, the log odds of
being book smart or
considering yourself book smart is equal
to the intercept 2.12 minus the slope
0.039, and we would of course multiply
that beta times the amount of homework.
So this is a continuous predictor.
So we would be multiplying the amount of
homework for
a particular person, times that slope.
What's this logistic regression equation
useful for?
So, just like when we talked about linear
regression, there's many,
a couple different pote-, potential
functions here.
So one thing is we could use the logistic
regression equation model to try to
do some kind of prediction.
This is very useful in clinical
applications,
because often we want to classify people
as having a condition or
not having a condition, that's a binary
outcome.
So if we're doing that kind of prediction,
we would likely be using logistic
regression.
So we can try to come up with a set of
predictors that predicts who's going to
have a disease or not have a disease.
So that's one of the functions of logistic
regression prediction.
A second function of logistic regression
which is probably used even more often,
is just to try to say, is a particular
predictor like homework,
related to the outcome, in this current
case, book smart or street smart?
Are those variables related, is a
treatment related to an outcome?
And that's very useful in, in and of
itself and
of course we can say is that predictor,
that treatment, related to the outcome
after adjusting for potential confounders?
So that's another very Important use of
the logistic regression model.
I'm going to start by talking just briefly
about the first of these aims,
which is the prediction end of things.
Again, here's the logistic regression
model, we've modeled the outcome
variable that is the log odds of the
outcome, we were modelling that as a line.
Let me take that model that we just fit.
And, how would we actually apply it to
make some predictions?
So, if you're somebody who does no
homework per week, zero hours of homework
per week, you could plug in that value for
homework, of zero into the model.
You get that your predicted logit is 2.12.
As I mentioned most of us don't think in
logits, so in
a minute we're going to do something with
that number to make it more interpretable.
But if you did ten hours per week of
homework,
you could plug in ten, the predicted logit
there is 1.73.
If you did 50 hours per week, the
predicted logit is 0.17.
So the more homework you do, the more the
logit goes down.
Well, I don't want to deal with a logit,
because, a logit, I,
I can't think in logits.
However, we can get this, notice that
there's a probability in there.
What we want to get out is the predicted
probability of the outcome,
the predicted probability of considering
yourself book smart in this case.
I want to isolate this predicted
probability.
Well, it's actually not that hard to do,
right?
We've got one equation, one unknown.
We can isolate that probability.
So how do we do it?
First thing that we're going to want to do
is,
we're going to want to exponentiate both
sides.
So, for example, the zero hours per week,
that person would be predicted to have
a logit of 2.12; I can then exponentiate
both sides of those, of that equation.
So that would tell me that the odds for
somebody who does zero,
homework per week is the exponential
raised to 2.12.
That value is 8.33 if you actually
calculate it out; so
e raised to 2.2 is 8.33.
That's the odds for a person who does, the
odds of
being book smart per person who does zero
hours a per week of homework.
Then we could exponentiate this 1.73, that
will give me the odds for
somebody who does 10 hours per week that's
5.64; we could exponentiate the 0.17, that
gives me the odds for somebody who does 50
hours per week that comes out to be 1.19.
So your odds of being book smart, again,
goes down,
as you do more homework per week, sort of
the opposite of what you might expect.
But of course this is not statistically
significant.