In this next module, we're going to talk
about the concept of interaction.
I mentioned it briefly in an earlier week
in this course.
But now we're going to really delve into
the concept.
And I'm going to show you how to test for
interaction in a regression model.
First of all, what is interaction?
Interaction is when the effect size
differs significantly between
different subgroups.
In other words, the relationship between a
treatment and
an outcome might differ depending on say,
whether you're a man or a woman or some
other subgroup characteristic.
For example, if you've got a blood
pressure treatment that
works significantly better in men than in
women, that's interaction.
That would mean that the effect size for
the blood pressure treatment was
significantly bigger in men than in women.
Another term you'll sometimes heard used
is effect modification.
Effect modification and interaction mean
the same thing.
You could say that the effect of the blood
pressure treatment
was modified by gender or you could say
that the treatment and gender interact.
Either one is fine.
How do we test for interaction in a
regression model?
So to test for interaction in a regression
model,
you can add an interaction term to that
model.
And I'll show you what that is in a
minute.
If that interaction term is statistically
significant,
that indicates, that's proof of
interaction.
Let's use this little blood pressure
example.
If I want to test for interaction between
gender and this blood pressure treatment.
Blood pressure is a continuous outcome
variable.
So I'm going to be running a linear
regression here.
I'm going to include in my model, a beta
for treatment, and a beta for gender.
And I'm also going to include a term for
the interaction between gender and
treatment, and what that is,
is it's literally, I'm going to multiply
the value for gender times the value for
treatment, so let me illustrate that by
writing out a little mock data set.
You've got some variable gender,
in this case I've coded it that one is
male and zero is female.
I've got another variable that's
treatment, one means you're on the drug,
zero means you're on placebo.
Then I've got ID numbers, let's call them
one,two and three, so
let's say the first person here was a male
and they were on the placebo,
they will get the values one for gender,
zero for treatment.
Then we've got a female who was on the
treatment, that would be a zero, one.
And then let's say we have a male who's on
the treatment, that's a one, one.
If you multiply those values together,
that is what an interaction is,
it's gender times treatment,
it's literally we're going to multiply the
values of those two variables together.
So ID number one gets a value of one times
a value of zero.
That's going to give them an interaction
term of zero.
The ID number two, gender is zero,
treatment is one, 0 times 1 is 0.
ID number three, 1 times 1 is 1.
Notice that if you've got two binary
predictors, a zero one variable and
another zero one variable.
The only people who are going to get a one
for
the interaction are the people who have a
one on both of those binary variables.
So in this case,
only people who both are male and got the
drug will get a value of 1.
Everybody else gets a value of 0 for that
interaction.
That's the, the data, the variables that
we're then including in the model.
If the beta for the interaction comes out
to be statistically significant.
This would indicate that there is a
significant interaction And
the way you would interpret the betas from
the model, the beta for
treatment in this case, because women is
the reference group, the beta for
treatment represents the treatment effect
in the women.
The beta, the treatment effect for the
men, you get by adding the treatment
effect, the beta for treatment plus the
beta for interaction.
So men, their treatment effect is beta
treatment plus beta interaction.
In other words, the interaction term
represents the difference in
the treatment effect between the men and
the women.
So if that's significantly different,
that indicates a significant difference in
those effect sizes.
Just in, as a side note here.
There is also a beta gender here.
This term would just indicate whether or
not there was a main effect for gender.
That is whether or
not males have higher blood pressure than
females, unrelated to the treatment.
So that's what a model with an interaction
term looks like.
Now let's visit some real examples of how
to apply this in the medical literature.
In this trial we had women smokers who
were concerned about their weight.
They were afraid to quit because they were
afraid of gaining weight.
These women were randomly assigned to one
of four groups, so
they were randomly assigned to either get
weight-focused counseling or
to get standard counseling and they were
randomly assigned to get a drug,
an anti-smoking drug, bupropion or to get
a placebo.
So that makes up four total groups.
The outcome here was smoking abstinence.
It was biochemically confirmed.
It's a binary outcome.
You either were abstinent or you weren't.
So that means we're going to be using
logistic regression to analyze the data.
Here's the results of that study.
It's a rather busy table, so I'm going to
zoom in on some things now.
First of all, we're looking at actually
three different outcomes here.
They measured the abstinence rates at
three months, six months, and
12 months into the study.
So each of those rows represent a
different time point in the study.
If you just look at the placebo groups
within each of those counseling groups.
You'll see that the rates of abstinence
are pretty similar.
So at three months it was 18%, were at,
were in the placebo group.
In the weight-focused counseling group,
were abstinent versus 19% in the placebo
group in the other counseling group.
Those rates look very similar to what we
would say here is that there
doesn't appear to be a main effect for
counseling.
In the placebo groups,
those quitting rates in the two counseling
groups looked pretty much the same.
What about an effect for a drug?
So if we compare the placebo group to the
drug group within each of
those two counseling types, what do we
see?
It appears that the drug actually does
improve quitting rates in both groups.
So if I look at the weight-focused
counseling group,
if you were in the placebo group,
the quitting rate was 18% at three months,
versus in the drug group, and it was 41%.
At six months, you also see a similar, a
pretty big increase.
In the standard counseling group, the drug
also appears to have an effect.
At, the effect isn't quite as big, but
you do see almost a doubling of the
quitting rates if you add the drug.
So, for example, in the placebo group,
at three months, the quitting rate was
19%, then went to 33% in the drug group.
At six months, it went from 10% to 21%,
so there's a pretty big increase basically
a doubling of
quitting rates in the drug group even
within the standard counseling group.
Now as we talked about in the earlier
module on this example,
the P-value's highly significant for the
weight-focused counseling group,
the P-value comparing placebo and drug
within that group.
It didn't quite make statistical
significance.
It, within the standard counseling group.
But it's very close to that.
What we would conclude is there just
appears to be a main effect for drug.
Overall, drug seems to be doing something.
Even though it didn't quite reach
statistical significance in the standard
counseling group.
We talked about not misinterpreting those
P-values in an earlier module.
If you look at the, what the authors
concluded in the media coverage of
this study, here's the basically
conclusion that was drawn.
Among weight-concerned women smokers, drug
therapy increases cessation rates
when added to a specialized weight
concerns intervention,
the weight counseling, but not when added
to standard counseling.
The implication there is that there is an
interaction.
They're saying that the drug works in one
group but not the other.
They're implying that there is an
interaction between drug and
counseling type.
However, they haven't done any formal
analyses to test for an interaction here.
So there is, they haven't specifically
talked about interaction, but
that's really the implication here.
And they haven't formally tested that.
So I actually took the data in their paper
and ran it in a logistic regression to
test for interaction, to see whether or
not there really is an interaction.
And what would it mean if there was an
interaction?
So just go back to this slide for a
minute.
An interaction would mean that the drug
effect, the difference between, you know,
going from here to here, the difference
between placebo and drug was much bigger
in the weight-focused counseling group
than in the standard counseling group.
It does appear to be somewhat bigger.
That the change from placebo to,
to drug, appears to be somewhat bigger in
the weight-focused counseling group, but
not a lot bigger than in the standard
counseling group.
We can formally test whether or not that
effect size is bigger.
We can run a logistic regression with an
interaction term.
Here's the logistic regression model
[INAUDIBLE].
Outcome is smoking abstinence.
I'm going to put in the model a main
effect for drug, a main effect for
counseling type, and an interaction
between drug and counseling type, and
these are all binary variables.
When I run that model using the data that
was available in the paper,
I find a significant effect for drug.
There's a significant main effect for
drug.
I find nothing for counseling effect.
The counseling, the beta for
counseling does not come out statistically
significant.
And the interaction between drug and
counseling type also does
not come out to be anywhere near
statistically significant.
Indicating that we can't say that there's
a difference in how that
drug works in those two groups.
And here I'm just showing you the P-values
for interaction from those models I ran.
I ran three logistic regression models for
each of the time points.
And in none of the cases Does the P-value
even approach statistical significance, so
we have no evidence that the effect of the
drug differs by counseling type.
Our main conclusion then, our correct
take-home message would be that the drug
improves quitting rates over counseling
alone, period.
There's a main effect for drug.
There's no main effect for counseling
type, and
there's no interaction between drug and
counseling type.
It's not statistically significant at
least, so we don't have evidence
that the drug behaves differently in those
two groups, at least not from this study.
The second example I'm going to show you
is a cross sectional study of
about 1700 men and women.
In this study, they actually did formally
test for
interaction and they actually did find a
significant interaction.
This study was looking at the relationship
between sleep duration and
sleep problems and hypertension.
It's a cross sectional study but
they treated hypertension as the outcome
variable.
Hypertension is binary, yes, no.
So we're going to be using, they did use,
logistic regression.
Let me show you the main results of that
study,
this chart's a little complicated, so I'm
going to kind of walk you through it.
And I want to actually also write out the
logistic regression model that
was used here.
I think it's, it, it's a little
complicated but it's instructive.
So first of all, what are we looking at?
The outcome here is hypertension.
So we're looking at odds ratios for
hypertension based on two predictor
variables.
Sleep difficulty and sleep duration.
If you read the fine print, I just want to
note here,
that there's other things in the model
between, besides those two predictors.
It says all data were adjusted for age,
race, sex, BMI, et cetera, et cetera.
So, there's a whole bunch of other
variables in the model that I'm not even
going to bother to write out in the model
but they're,
those predictors are also included in the
model, just to adjust for confounding.
The predictors that the researchers cared
about here were two predictors,
sleep difficulty, which is a three level
categorical variable.
You were either a normal sleeper, that's
the reference group.
You had poor sleep, kind of not at the
level of insomnia, but some trouble.
And then you could have insomnia, which is
really troubled sleeping.
They also looked at a three category
variable for sleep duration.
So they categorized people as getting more
than six hours per night,
getting five to six hours per night, or
getting less than five hours per night.
The reference group is getting, is the
highest sleeping group,
more than six hours per night.
They ran a logistic regression model with
those two categorical variables as well as
the interactions.
So let me write out that model,
again we're modelling the log odds of
hypertension.
It's going to have an intercept.
And because we've got a multilevel
categorical variable,
we're going to be dummy coding, so this is
good review of dummy coding.
The reference group is normal sleepers.
To dummy code a three level categorical
variable I need two dummy coded variables.
So normal sleepers will will not get its
own beta but I'll have a beta for
poor sleep, and I'll have a beta for
insomnia.
If you have a zero, zero for poor sleep
and
a zero for insomnia you are by default in
the normal sleeping group.
For sleep duration, I'm going to put in,
the reference is greater than six hours,
so I'm going to put in the beta for
five to six hours, and I'm going to put in
the beta for less than five hours.
If you get a zero on both of those binary
dummy coded variables,
that means by default you're in the
greater than six hours duration group.
That's how I dummy code those two
predictors.
But now, the researchers also put it in an
interaction term between those
two predictors.
So let me show you what that looks like in
the model.
If we're interacting two three level
categorical variables,
we're going to end up with four
interaction terms in the model.
First of all, we're going to have an
interaction between poor sleep and
five to six hours duration per night.
We're going to have an interaction between
poor sleep and
less than five hours per night.
We're going to have an interaction term
for insomnia,
times the five to six hour duration, and
we're going to have an interaction for
insomnia and the less than five hour
duration.
Plus remember this model also has all
those other betas for
the confounders that I'm not going to
bother to write out.
So it's a little complicated, but
each of these interaction terms is either
a one if you are in that group.
So for example, the, the poor sleep times
five to six hours per week.
If you're in the poor sleep group and
you sleep five to six hours per night
you're going to get a one for
that interaction term, everybody else is
going to get a zero.
So this breaks down to a bunch of binary
variables.
From all of these betas,
by fitting all these betas you are able to
get an odds ratio for
each of these different categories of both
sleep duration and sleep difficulty.
That's what they generated here.
They generated those odds ratios right
from the logistic regression model.
If you look at the fine print, it says the
interaction between insomnia and
objective sleep duration is statistically
significant.
So two interaction terms came out
statistically significant, those that
interacted insomnia, not poor sleep but
insomnia, with the short sleep duration.
And you can also see the interaction just
by
looking at the odds ratios that were
generated by the model here.
So if you look at the odds ratios again,
the reference group is normal sleepers who
are sleeping more than six hours per
night.
If you compare poor sleepers and
insomniacs who, where,
everybody is sleeping at least six hours
per night, long sleepers,
you'll notice that poor sleep and insomnia
didn't make much difference.
There the odds ratios are 0.79 and 1.31.
So you don't really get much increase in
your chances of
hypertension if you have bad sleep as long
as you're sleeping enough every night.
If you move over, however, to the group
who's sleeping much shorter,
five to six hours per night, then you'll
notice that normal sleepers and
poor sleep there wasn't too much going on.
But, those who have insomnia and
are also sleeping only five to six hours
per night have a 3.5 odds ratio there,
so a drastic increase in the odds of
hypertension.
finally, if you look at the really short
sleepers, the effect of insomnia is even
greater, so as you get up to the insomniac
group, and you're having really poor
sleep, you get a increase, a much bigger
increase in your odds of hypertension.
And notice that this odds ratio comes out
statistically significant.
So does this one.
So again, there, there's a significant
interaction here.
The sleeping difficulty doesn't seem to
matter as long as
you're getting enough sleep, but if you
are not getting enough sleep,
then the sleeping difficulty seems to
really impact your risk of hypertension.
That's what, that's what the interaction,
that's the sort of verbal way to describe
the interaction here.
I want to point out and remind you that we
are dealing with odds ratios here, and
as I told you, talked a lot about in week
two of this course,
odds ratios, you have to be careful about
interpreting them.
This was a cross-sectional study.
The outcome was extremely common.
In the reference group, about a quarter of
people in
the reference group had hypertension, so
the outcome is very common.
So you have to be careful about
interpreting,
these odds ratios look really big, 3.5 and
5.1.
You would not want to say that this was a,
that this 3.5 represented a three-fold
increase in the risk of hypertension in
this group, and you would not want to say
that this five, this odds ratio of
five represented a five-fold increase in
risk of hypertension.
Since the outcome is common these odds
ratios are distorted.
These are not the increases in risk.
They are the increases in odds.
If you use the little formula I gave you
in week one you could actually convert
back and figure out the risk ratios, the
corresponding risk ratios.
It turns out that there's more like a
doubling in the risk of hypertension here,
not a fivefold increase, so I don't want
you to forget.
When we're doing logistic regression and
you're getting odds ratios,
be careful about the interpretation when
you have a common outcome.
This final example actually comes from a
paper that
I wrote in graduate school and so excuse
the,
the poor resolution of the graphic it's a
little bit of an older paper.
But this involved a, an interaction term
that we found in a linear regression.
So just to show you how this works also
for linear regression.
We were looking at three outcomes.
This was looking at bone density so
we looked at the bone density in the spine
and in the hip, and overall in the body.
Those were the outcomes.
Since our outcomes are continuous, bone
density is continuous,
we were actually doing linear regression
here, not logistic regression.
Women athletes, this is a study about
women athletes, women runners.
Women athletes sometimes if they have
disordered eating And
irregularities in their menstrual cycle,
it can cause them to lose bone density.
That's what this paper was about.
So we were looking at kind of two factors
here.
We were looking at an eating disorder
score, called the EDI score.
This tells us about eating, disordered
eating behavior,
so higher scores is, women is more likely
to have some kind of eating disorder.
We also looked at menstrual cycle, and so
we divided women into two groups.
Those with the normal menstrual cycle,
those are the eumenorrheic women,
those are all the bars in the back of
these graphics, and
women with menstrual irregularities, we
call that the oligo and
amenorrheic group and that, those bars in
the front.
So we looked at those two menstrual groups
as well as this disordered eating
score and we looked at the interaction
between those two things and
we did find a statistically significant
interaction here.
And it's kind of nicely pictured in these
graphics.
So what's happening here is that if you
look at
the women who already have menstrual
irregularities.
If you look at the effect of eating
disorder score, that doesn't seem that
their bone density changes much at all
across different eating disorder scores.
Once you already have menstrual
irregularities,
there doesn't seem to be much additional
effect of eating disorder score so
the bone density is pretty flat across
those different eating disorder
score groups.
If you look however at the women with
normal periods, the eumenorrheic group,
the bars in the back.
You can see there's a pretty dramatic
effect for eating disorder scores, so
as your eating disorder score increases,
your bone density goes down quite a bit.
That's in all three sites.
So interestingly, there's an interaction
here because the the effect
of the eating disorder score was different
between these two menstrual groups.
And that had some certain implications
that were of interest.
But we got this significant interaction in
a linear regression by
including the interaction between EDI
score and and menstrual group.