In this next module, I'm going to talk
about the statistical tests that we
use when we have correlated data in a two
by two table.
This is less common, but it does come up
sometimes.
So for those of you who took HRP259 in the
fall,
I told you about McNemar's exact test.
I'm now just going to extend that to tell
you about McNemar's chi-squared test.
So, for correlated data in a two by two
table,
we're going to be using some kind of
McNemar's test.
Now I'm assuming that you've all have had
a previous course in statistics and
that you're familiar with the concept of
correlated observations, so I'm going to
go over this very quickly, assuming that
you already have the background here.
The correlated data arise whenever we have
pairs or clusters of observations that
are essentially more related to each other
than to other observations in the data
set, and this commonly comes up in things
like, when we have repeated measures.
So, you measure the same person before and
after a treatment, well,
that person of course is going to be
correlated to themselves.
Or, perhaps you're doing something like,
measuring twin pairs, and
of course, the people within a twin pair
are going to be more correlated to
each other than other people in the study.
Or you might have a situation where you're
measuring multiple lesions on each person.
Well if the unit of observation that
you're looking at is the lesions,
those lesions within a person are going to
be correlated to one another.
Or if you are in ophthalmology and you're
looking at a person's eyes and
you measure both eyes from the people in
your study, and
you measure at, again, the unit of
observation is the eye,
then eyes within a person are going to be
correlated to one another.
You get the idea.
It's important to understand that when you
go to analyze your data,
if you ignore these kinds of correlations,
one of two things can happen.
So if you're doing some kind of
within-person comparison, so
let's say you're looking at the same
person before and after,
or you're comparing one half of a person's
face to the other half of their face.
Or some kind of within-cluster comparison,
like within, you know, a twin pair.
And you ignore the correlations, you're
actually going to overestimate your
p-values, so you might miss a
statistically significant effect.
You, you're more likely to make a type two
type of error.
However, if you're doing some kind of
comparison where you have correlated data,
but you're looking at comparing between
people or
between clusters, so like I have two eyes
within a person but
I'm comparing both eyes in one person who
is treated with a treatment to
both eyes of somebody else who is treated
with a placebo, and if I ignore those
correlations in that case, I'm actually
going to underestimate the p-values.
I'm going to be over-counting things and
I'm going to be overly optimistic.
I might find something to be statistically
significant that I shouldn't have.
So both of those situations can occur.
Obviously you're going to have problems
with your statistical inference if you
ignore correlations.
One case where correlations come up that's
worth mentioning,
is when we do something called pair
matching.
So, pair matching is in a way in your
study design to control for confounders,
and to actually increase the power of your
statistical test down the line, and so
we often do this with case control
studies.
You take a case, you get somebody with it
a particular disease, and then you go out
and find a control for that person, but
you just don't pick any control.
Maybe you pick somebody who's around the
same age as the case and
also is of the same gender and
perhaps also is a smoker or non-smoker,
maybe match them on smoking.
When you do that, you're controlling for
all these extraneous sources of
variability, you're increasing your
chances of being able to see a signal.
Of course, you have to remember to account
for
this pair matching at the end of the day
when you analyze your data.
So here's something, you know, you might
match one control to
one case based on things like age, gender,
and smoking again.
So let me just give you an example where
pair matching was done.
This was a study from the New England
Journal of Medicine many years ago, and
they wanted to know whether or
not getting a tonsillectomy was related to
the chances of getting Hodgkin's disease.
So what they did was they found 85
Hodgkin's patients, and they looked for
a control out of the siblings of the
Hodgkin's patient.
They looked for a sibling who had not had
Hodgkin's disease but
was of the same gender, and also was in a,
you know,
reasonably similar age bracket, within
five years of the patient's age.
So this was a way for them to try to say,
to then look at,
did the case have a tonsillectomy in the
past, and did the sib control?
We've got pair matching here because
obviously the case and
the control are more related to each other
than to the, everybody else in the sample.
So this was actually presented in the New
England Journal of Medicine incorrectly.
So here is how the authors re-, reported
that data.
They had 85 cases and 85 controls, and you
can see in this two by two table,
they reported each case and control
individually, and
there's no accounting for the fact that
they had matching.
When you calculate just the basic odds
ratio from this two by two table, and
the basic chi square statistic, it's not
significant, and
your odds ratio comes out to be about
1.47.
Well, that's actually not the right way to
analyze these data.
Several letters to the editor pointed out
that the investigators had failed to
account for the pairing.
The correct way to analyze these data is
to put them in a two by two table,
not individuals in those cells, but pairs.
So every number in this cell represents
now, a pair, rather than an individual.
So what the, what the correct way to look
at these data is to say,
okay, within a case-control pair, who had
a tonsillectomy and who didn't?
So, it turns out that there were 26 pairs
where both the case and
the control had had a tonsillectomy in the
past, and
there were 37 pairs where neither of them
had had a tonsillectomy in the past.
Well, it turns out that those cells are
not informative.
They don't tell us anything.
They don't help us to say whether or not
getting a tonsillectomy is related to
getting the disease, because both people
had the same status on tonsillectomy.
The informative, the interesting cells,
turn out to be the discordant pairs.
So this is where a case had had a
tonsillectomy and
a control had not, or vice versa, and
you can see that among the discordant
pairs here, there were more discordant
pairs where it was the case that they had
the tonsillectomy and not the control.
When you analyze the data this way, doing
what's called a McNemar's odds ratio and
a McNemar's chi-square, it turns out that
the odds ratio is much bigger, it's 2.14,
and the chi-squared test is almost
statistically significant.
So as I mentioned, ignoring the
correlations for
within-pair comparisons like this will
make your p-value too big, so
when we correctly analyze the data the
p-value becomes smaller here.
So this is the kind of situation where
we're going to need a McNemar's test.
Let me just introduce yet another example.
Here's a larger study, where they were
looking at myocardial infarction, so
this is having a heart attack.
They looked at people who had had a heart
attack, those are the cases, and
controls who had not, and they matched
them, one to one, on age and
gender, which of course are very
highly-related to having heart attacks.
The question in this study was whether or
not having a history of diabetes would
increase your risk of having a heart
attack.
So here are the data correctly presented.
So, there were 144 pairs in this study.
And what you'll notice is that nine pairs,
both the case and
the control had diabetes.
82 pairs, neither the case nor the control
had diabetes.
Those cells turn out to be
non-informative.
What are the informative cells here?
Again, the informative cells are the
discordant cells,
the ones where the control and the case
don't match, that's the 37 and the 16.
How do we analyze these data?
We can actually calculate an odds ratio
based only on the discordant pairs.
That's called a McNemar's odds ratio and
it's very simple to calculate.
We take the discordant pairs and we say
what is the, among the discordant pairs,
what's the odds that the pair contains a
diabetic case,
rather than a diabetic control?
And we get that odds just by dividing 37
by 16.
So it's the simplest odds ratio you'll
ever calculate.
We're simply going to divide 37 by 16.
We get an odds ratio here of 2.3.
So there's a twofold increase in the odds
of getting
a heart attack if you are diabetic.
That's how you would interpret that.
So that's the McNemar's odds ratio.
Very simple to calculate.
We also want to get a p-value here, so we
can cal-,
we can do what's called a McNemar's
chi-squared test, and
now I'm going to lead you through the
logic of that test.
Again it focuses only on the discordant
pairs.
The null hypothesis here is that being
diabetic is unrelated to
having a heart attack.
Another way to say that is that the
chances among the discordant pairs
that it's the case that's diabetic,
should be equal to the chance that it's
the control that's diabetic.
So when we restrict our analysis down to
the discordant pairs,
what we'd expect to see if there was no
relationship between diabetes and
heart attacks, we'd expect to see kind of
an even number, an even split.
It would be equally likely that it would
be the control that would be diabetic as
it would be that the case would be
diabetic.
Now you can see clearly we don't have an
even split here.
We have 37 pairs, discordant pairs, where
it was the case that
was diabetic versus only 16 where it was
the control that was diabetic.
You can see that that's pretty unbalanced,
and we're going to think that that's
probably going to be something
statistically significant.
But our, under the null, we would expect
to see half here and
half in cell B and half in cell C.
So we start with that null hypothesis, and
what we have to recognize now, is that we
actually have a binomial distribution.
Okay, so
if you think about this carefully, I have
53 discordant pairs here.
Okay?
Under the null hypothesis of no
relationship between diabetes and
case control status, I would actually
expect to see about
half the pairs would be in this cell and
about half would be in this cell.
I see, expect to see an even split.
Of course, we always know in statistics
that nothing ever gets evenly split,
especially since we can't have half a
person, so
we're going to expect to see about 26 or
27 in each cell.
Instead we're seeing here a 37 to 16
split, and we say,
well, is that discrepant enough from 26 to
26?
Is that a big enough discrepancy from the
null hypothesis,
where we're sure that that sort of rises
above just random chance?
How do we evaluate that?
Well we can recognize here that what we
are, we have under the null hypothesis,
we are on a binomial distribution, and
that binomial distribution has an n of
53 because I have 53 pairs, and we're
expecting half of them, so my p is 0.5.
We're expecting half of them to have a
diabetic case rather than
a diabetic control.
So our null hypothesis here is that we're
on a binomial with an n of 53 and
a p of 0.5.
Now, how do we then calculate a p-value
for this null hypothesis?
So what we would have to do,
if we wanted to just stick with the
binomial distribution here, is we would
have to calculate the probability of what
we observed, and everything more extreme.
So this is the p-value that we would have
to calculate here.
We would go, okay the p-value is equal to
what we observed.
Well we observed, that out of 53 pairs,
37 of them ended up having a diabetic
case, and of course, the chance
of having divided by the case under the
null is 0.5, so we raise that to 37.
We raise the 0.5, 1 minus that to 16.
So that's the probability of getting 37
discordant pairs where it's the case that
has diabetes.
That's exactly what we observed.
But then, we have to calculate everything
more extreme than that.
And these, I'm just applying binomial
probabilities here.
So, what's the probability of where I
would've got 38 diabetic cases and
15 diabetic controls?
Well that would be 0.5 raised to 38, times
0.5 raised to 15, and we can keep going.
Well, what's more extreme than that?
Well, I could've got 39 diabetic cases, so
that's 53 choose 39,
0.5 raised to 39, 0.5 raised to 14 and
you can see that we're going to have to
keep going for a long time here.
That's going to take us a while, because
we have to get all the way down to 0,
and then that will give us the one tail,
and
we would have to multiply that by 2 to get
the two tail.
It's rather tedious to calculate out the
exact binomial probability.
Your, of course the computer can do that
for you easily.
But, what we can do instead is that we
know that when we have a large enough n,
when n times p is greater than 5,
we can actually just do a normal
approximation to the binomial.
So, just to remind you how that works.
What we say is, okay, think about what a
binomial looks like.
Our expected value here is 26.5, and
expect to be around here, and
then my binomial is going to look
something like this.
It's very likely that I'm going to get
things in the range of you know, 26, 25,
24, and then it's going to kind of drop
off from there.
So if did out all of the binomial
probabilities,
this would be all the way from zero to 53,
so you know zero here 53,
I could get anywhere from zero to 53 pairs
having diabetic cases.
Of course the probabilities are going to
be very low on those tails.
I'm going to end up with something that
looks very close to a normal distribution,
so I'm going to approximate it as a
normal.
I'm going to say, well, whatever the
expected value and variance for
the binomial is,
I'll just pretend I'm on a normal with
that same expected value and variance.
You have to remember, what is the expected
value for a binomial?
So the expected value of a binomial is n
times p,
which in this case is 53 times 0.5, which,
it just comes out to be that 26.5.
And notice, we didn't even need to know,
we just intuitively knew that that's
going to come out to be 26.5.
What's the variance of a binomial?
You'll have to jog your memory a little
bit here.
So, the variance of a binomial is n times
p times 1 minus p, and
of course the standard deviation would be
the square root of that.
So what's n times p times 1 minus p here?
So, n is 53, p is 0.5, and 1 minus p is
0.5.
So the variance here will come out to be
53 times 0.5 times 0.5,
and the standard deviation would be the
square root of that.
I'm just going to leave that, I,
we don't actually need to even solve that
out quite yet.
I'll just leave it like that.
So now I'm just going to assume that I'm
on a normal with that same mean and
standard deviation.
So if a normal curve with a mean of 26.5
and a standard deviation of the square
root of 53 times 0.5 times 0.5 what did I
actually observe in this case?
Well, I observed that I was at 37.
So 37's going to be somewhere about here,
and I want to know,
what's the area to the right of 37?
And, of course, I'll double that to get
the two-tailed p value.
I observed a value of 33.
My expected value, so, z score, of course,
you calculate by
simply subtracting the observed minus the
mean, divided by the standard deviation.
My expected value here is 53 divided by 2,
and my standard deviation is 53 times 0.5
times 0.5.
When I actually calculate that out, I get
that the difference is 10.5.
I'm 10.5 away from the expected, and my
standard deviation turns out to be 3.64.
My z value comes out to be 2.88.
Now clearly, if you know anything about z
values,
clearly a two point, a z value of 2.88 is
going to be out, way out in the tail.
The p value is going to be quite small, ao
it will be statistically significant.
So that's much easier, doing that
approximation is much easier than
doing out the entire binomial probability.
Now McNemar was clever here, because he
recognized that there's an easy pattern,
that all of these situations where you
have paired data in a two by two table
like this, they all are going to come out
to be exactly the same binomial and
the exactly, and we're going to, we can
generalize it.
So we can actually figure out a general
formula that can be applied every time.
So that is, you don't have to
go through that logic that I just went
through every time.
At the end of all this,
I'm going to give you a simple little
formula that avoids that logic.
So, I'm now going to generalize.
Rather than plugging in the 53 and the 37,
et cetera,
I'm just going to plug in the b and the c.
So if we're in the same situation, we've
got paired data, we've got discordant
pairs b and c, we know that the observed
value is going to be whatever we signed b.
Now I could calculate relative to c but,
doesn't matter.
I'm just going to pick, I'm going to look
at the,
the discordant pairs where it's the case
that has the exposure.
So I'm going to look at b, that's my
observed value.
What's my expected value?
That's going to be b plus c, which is my
total number of discordant pairs.
That's the 53 in the previous slide.
B plus c divided by 2,
because remember the expected value here
is n times p, p is a half.
So it's the total number of discordant
pairs divided by 2.
That's going to be my expected value in
all these cases.
What's my standard deviation going to be
in all these cases?
Well, it's again going to be n, which is
just b plus c times p times 1 minus p.
Well p is always going to be 0.5,
1 minus p is always going to be 0.5 under
the null hypothesis here.
So we can simplify this out algebraically.
I've done all the algebra here,
a little bit of algebra, and we come out
with a general formula.
So z is always going to be equal in these
cases to b minus c divided by
the square root of b plus c, and in fact,
you can apply that here.
We saw 37 was b, 16 was c.
Divided by the square root of 53.
If you calculate that out, indeed you will
get a value of exactly 2.88.
So, that is a simple little formula that
saves you having to do out the logic.
Now, McNemar went a little, one step
further.
He didn't like the fact that there was a
square root in the denominator.
That annoyed him, so
what he did is he said, well, I'm just
going to square this quantity.
So if I take this whole quantity, and I
square it, I can get
rid of the square root in the denominator,
and that's all I've done here.
If I square the whole thing, I end up with
b minus c squared in the numerator, and
b plus c in the denominator.
Again I can apply that here just as 37
minus 16 squared, divided by 53, and that
will come out to be the square of 2.88,
which is about 8.32, in this case.
This no longer has a z distribution.
It no longer has a standard normal
distribution, but if you
square a standard normal, you end up with
a chi-square with one degree of freedom.
So this is has a chi-square with one
degree of freedom distribution.
All that means is I'm going to take that
8.32, and
I'm going to go to a chi-square chart with
one degree of freedom to find the p value.
I will get the exact same p value from
taking the 2.88 to a z chart as I
will from taking the 8.32 to a chi-square
chart.
Those are mathematically equivalent.
So that is the McNemar's chi-squared test.
Very simple to apply if you just use this
little formula, but
important to know where it comes from.
I'll just end here with a quick note about
what we call the McNemar's EXACT test.
So the McNemar's chi-square test, built
into it, you saw that we
have this step where we're making a normal
approximation to the binomial, and
again, I kind of drew it out.
And, you know, if your binomial
distribution, you know,
looks something like this, we don't do too
bad if we just pretend that's the normal.
But imagine you have a case where you have
sparse data.
So you might have very [UNKNOWN] very
small.
You might have a very small sample of some
cells.
It might turn out that these bars are
quite big,
because there's only a few bars.
There's only a few possible outcomes.
Now when you approximate with a normal,
well you have these big gaps and
you're ending up with things that are way
off.
So, if you have very sparse data, the rule
of thumb being that n times p
is less than 5, then you don't want to
rely on the McNemar's chi-squared test,
you want to go back to calculating out the
exact binomials.
And, presumably if the ns are very small,
hopefully there aren't too
many binomial probabilities that you have
to calculate out.
So that's all the McNemar's EXACT test is.
It just kind of goes back one step.
And the example that I like to use for
illurating, illustrating the McNemar's
EXACT test, is the following study.
So here's another example of correlated
data.
This was a sunscreen study, so researchers
wanted to know, if you put SPF 85 or
like a really really high SPF sunscreen on
your face,
is that really any better then putting SPF
50 right?
Like, the sunscreens are coming in a
ridiculously high,
you can see SPF 100's out there.
Is it, does it really help you to put the
higher SPF on?
So to test that, what they did is they
took 56 subjects who were out skiing in
Vail, Colorado on a sunny day in the
winter.
We're going to get a lot of sun exposure,
they were out most of the day.
They assigned them to apply to one side of
their face SPF 85,
and to the other side SPF 50, and it was
blinded and randomized.
So they, the person didn't know which side
of the face they were applying to and
it was random which side the SPF 85 versus
50 went on.
They were outside for about five hours.
This is a split phase trial, because we
want to compare within a person,
within a person, did the SPF 85 side do
better than the SPF 50 side?
And the outcome here was whether or not
the person sunburned.
So this is a binary outcome.
You either got a sunburn on one side of
your face, or you didn't.
Now, when the researchers reported the
data,
they actually didn't report the quite, it
quite right.
So here's how they reported the data in
their paper.
There were 56 people, so there were 56 SPF
85 sides of the face, and
56 SPF 50 sides of the face.
You can see that in their two by two
table,
they're analyzing things at the level of
side of the face, but
of course, those 112 sides of the face are
not independent.
Some of them are related.
If you are a person who burns on one side
of your face,
you are much more likely to burn on the
other side of your face.
So, this is ignoring the correlations that
are built into this data set.
Now the authors did do a good job at
recognizing
that they needed to use an exact test.
We have sparse cells here.
We have a cell with only one person.
So they recognized that they needed to use
an exact test.
They applied a Fisher's exact test and got
a p of 0.03, but in fact they could have
gotten an even slightly better p value had
they analyzed the data correctly, and
that's what I'm going to do now.
The correct way to analyze these data is
to actually look at,
within a person, so only compare a person
to themselves.
You compare one side of a person's face to
the other side of their face.
When you look at the data this way, and
I've put them now into a two by two table,
now, the, notice there were only 56 things
in the table,
because now we're looking at the level of
a person,
comparing one side of a person's face to
the other side of that same person's face.
When they looked at that data, when you
look at the data this way, and, and
the authors nicely, actually said this in
their paper,
they just didn't apply the correct
statistical test.
It turned out that in all the cases where
somebody sunburned there was
one person who's sunburned on both sides
of the face, the, equally sunburned on,
in both sides of their face, no matter
what the SPF was.
There were seven cases where people
sunburned on one side of the face, but
not the other.
So, this is important, and what it turned
out was that in all seven of those cases,
the person sunburned on the SPF 50 side
and not the SPF 85 side.
That is starting to provide some data
that,
that seemed to provide evidence that the
SPF 85 actually does something better.
Now, of course, there were 48 people who
didn't sunburn on either side.
There was one person who sunburned on both
sides.
Those people are not informative, so
what we're going to zoom in on is this
zero and seven, the discordant pairs.
There are seven discordant pairs.
Under the null hypothesis, if the
sunscreen doesn't matter,
it would be equally likely that the burn
in those discordant pairs would have been
on the SPF 85 side.
So in other words, under the null
hypothesis,
we are on a binomial distribution with an
n of 7 and a p of 0.5.
If the null hypothesis is true,
it should have been equally likely to get
a burn on SPF 85 versus SPF 50.
So, what did we actually see?
Well, we observed, not a 50/50 split here.
We observed a 7/0 split.
So what's the probability that we would've
observed that?
And there's the only thing that's more
extreme or
equally extreme here is we could've seen
zero and seven in the other direction.
That is, we could've seen seven burns on
the SPF 85 side and
zero on the SPF 50 side.
So what's the probability if we're on a
binomial distribution with an n of 7 and
a p of 0.5, of getting none, no sunburns
on the SPF 85 side?
So we can just directly calculate out that
binomial probability.
So if we run a binomial with an n of 7 and
a p of 0.5, the probability that we
get 0 sunburns on the SPF 85 side would be
exactly equal to 7 to 0,
0.5 raised to 0, times 0.5 raised to 7,
and that value comes out to be 0.0078.
So there's a very small probability we'd
see seven to
zero split if there really was no
difference in the sunscreens.
Now that's the one sided probability.
Course we have to account,
we have to do a two-sided probability
because we have to account for the fact
that there is a way to have an equally
extreme outcome in the other direction.
We could have ended up with all seven
sunburns on the SPF 85 side and
not the SPF 50 side.
That's an equally likely extreme outcome
and
there's no reason that, you know, there
could be some reason that
SPF 85 actually increases your risk of
sunscreen, so we can't rule that tail out.
We have to calculate the two-sided
probability here.
To calculate the two-sided probability it
is going to be that 0.0078, which we
just calculated, and then the other tale,
the probability of getting all seven
sunburns on the SPF 85 side, would be 7 to
7, 0.5 raised to 7, 0.5 raised to 0.
Notice that that comes out to be exactly
the same, a value of .0078.
The two-sided probability is just double
the one-sided probability.
So this comes out to be a probability of
0.0156, sorry,
there two-sided probability.
So that's the exact probability of the,
what we've observed and
everything more extreme.
We have to use an exact test in this case,
because of the fact that we have sparse
data.
If I had tried to approximate this with a
normal, my inference would have,
my p value would have been off.
Notice that when the authors ignore the
correlations and
they use the Fisher's exact test, they got
a p value of 0.03.
When you correctly analyze the data
accounting for
the correlation, the p value becomes even
stronger.
It becomes 0.0156.
Now in this case it, it didn't make a
difference in terms of whether it
turned out statistically significant, but
you could see that in many cases it could.