In this next module, I'm going to show you
how you can apply principal
components analysis to real data.
So, I'm going to use this example of 91
women runners,
this data set that I've been referring to
this week.
This was a data set I was looking at.
On potential predictors of bone density
and
stress fractures in adolescents women
runners and
this is a group that's at risk of low bone
density and therefore a fracturing.
The researchers measured a number of
variables.
So they looked at variables like body size
and
composition that's strongly related to
bone density.
Running performance because this is a
group of runners.
Menstrual function, which is also linked
to bone density as well as
things about diet and disordered eating.
I am going to focus on the subset of the
variables just to keep this
exercise manageable.
I'll focus on these three categories and
some of the variables that were measured
within those categories.
So I'm going to look at 11 variables.
I'm going to apply a principal components
analysis to 11 variables.
And there, these variables are largely
very correlated to one another.
So the variables that I'm going to look at
Within body size and composition.
They performed a dexa on these women to
measure their bone density and
as a part of dexa measurement, you can get
other things like the android fat ratio,
which is a marker of visceral fat.
Your a precise measurement of fat mass,
you can get lean mass, of course you have
BMI and height.
Of course, we've seen these variables
before For and
they're also not unexpectedly highly
correlated with one an other.
If you have more lean mass you're likely
to have more fat mass etcetera.
There were also several measures of
running performance and
training, general competitiveness, the
best mile time, how many miles per
week the women ran and the pace at which
they ran their intervals.
Again, not surprisingly correlated within
that category.
There were several variables of menstrual
function, I'll just use a few here for
this exercise.
Manarche age, that's the age at which a
woman started menstruating,
the menstrual periods she had in the past
year and
the average number of periods she had
since menarche.
Again, all highly correlated.
Different categories here were also
correlated with each other so for
example if you had a higher fat mass and
you weighed more,
you tended to be not as Competitive and
this could be bidirectional that is,
if you carry more fat, that might slow you
down, but also if
you're more competitive and you're running
more, that might lead you to be leaner.
But the pretty strong correlation between
fat mass and
weight, the body composition measured and
the performance measure.
And then, also fat mass was pretty highly
correlated in weight Was pretty heavily
correlated with menstrual function, so
women ,um, if you carry more fat now, so
you tend to have a more normal menstrual
function ,uh, within this population.
So a lot correlations here, a lot of
things are heavily correlated.
We're going to take these 11 variables and
put them in a Principal Components
Analysis, and try to come up with
a smaller subset of variables that
represents some of these constructs.
So here are the steps of ,uh,
Principal Components Analysis laid out,
I'm going to take you through,
walk you through each one of these in turn
applied to this particular dataset.
So let me do that now.
So the first thing that you need to do Is,
you need to impute any missing values in
your data set.
This becomes very important because you're
often doing a principal
components analysis on a large number of
variables.
In this case 11, but it can be much larger
than that.
If an observation is missing, even one
data point.
From one variable in that set.
That observation will be thrown out of
your analysis.
So you might think that your sample size
is 500,
but when you apply the analysis if you're
not careful, and a woman is missing a,
you know, different women are missing
different values here and
there, you might, might end up with a
Sample size for your analysis of only 200.
You can really weed down your sample size
fast.
So you always need to fill in that missing
data somehow.
Be very cognizant of missing values.
The other thing that you need to do is you
need to standardize your
numeric variables ,so that they all have a
mean of zero and a and
the standard deviation of one, we talked
about that in an earlier module.
I just want to to make a quick note here
that we're mostly dealing in
principle components analysis with numeric
variables.
Principle components analysis is based on,
as we saw in the last module,
the linear relationship, the linear
correlation, between pairs of variables.
And so ,all of the assumptions of linear
regression actually
technically apply here.
That is you're supposed to have,
continuous normally distributed variables.
In practice sometimes we don't worry so
much about those assumptions.
Just because we're,
at the end of the day your goal here may
not be to calculate P values.
You may just want to exploring your data
and
get a sense of which variables to go
together.
For exploratory purposes it really doesn't
matter if you violate those assumptions.
So you might even end up throwing in some,
you know,
binary variables into the analysis.
Uh,but technically, the assumption is that
you're dealing with normal distributed,
continuous variables.
So we're generally going to be dealing
with numeric variables.
Those numeric variable need to be
standardized.
The next thing that we are going to do is
we are actually going to apply
the PCA and you can do this in most
standard statistical packages you just
have to figure out how to click the right
button so I Put my 11 variables into SAS.
I applied my, my principle, principle
components analysis there.
And, I'll show you the result in just a
minute.
But the first kind of decision point that
you have to do in the analysis is that you
have to decide on how many components, how
many variables to retain.
So we, we're starting with 11 variables.
We want to compress that to a smaller
number.
I, at some point I have to decide.
Am I going to extract three variables?
Am I'm going to extract four, or five.
How many components am I actually going to
keep?
And there's a number of different criteria
that are used to make this decision.
There's no hard, and fast rule, and really
a lot of times you
need to take into account your own
particular data set, and the goals of your
analysis that really a lot that should
drive how many components you retain.
But let me go through each of these
different kind of
commonly used criteria in turn So
again I applied that principle [INAUDIBLE]
analysis to my set of 11 variables.
When you apply PCA to 11 variables,
you will come out with 11 components, as
you can see that I did here.
Here's one of the outputs that you get
from your statistical package.
You get the Eigenvalues.
And remember that the Eigenvalues just
represent How much
variance is explained by that particular
component and
they've been ordered here from the highest
to the lowest.
So very simple criteria for
deciding how many components to retain is
to just at the eigenvalue.
Some people will say if the Eigenvalue is
greater than one,
you keep those components.
Any Eigenvalues less than one, you get rid
of those components.
So that, by that criteria, we would split
it at four.
And the idea here is this, every variable
that entered into the model,
has the variance of one.
So every single variable alone,
the original variables, each explain a
variance of one.
If the Eigenvalue for the components is
greater than one,
that means that they explain more of the
variance than any single variable.
So then, it would seem like we're getting
more information than a single variable
could give us, so it's worth keeping them.
But if your, Eigenvalue is less than one,
then you're, that component contains less
information than a single variable and
it's not worth keeping.
So that, is a rule that often people will
use.
It has its advantages and disadvantages.
In the end of the day, in this particular
example,
I did end up For several reasons, deciding
to go with four components,
to retain four components, but that's one
criteria that you can use.
It shouldn't be the only one you look at.
So that's just saying for
each individual component, does it explain
enough variance to be worth keeping it?
You can also look at the cumulative
variance explained by all the components.
So, the first component explains about 32%
of the variance.
The.
If you add in the second component That's
[UNKNOWN] is explaining an additional 20%
of the variance.
So you get up to explaining about 50% of
the variance,
51% of the variance of your original
variables.
Adding a third component gets us to 64%.
Adding a fourth component gets us up to
76%.
So by the time we get to four components,
we've explained 76% of the variance in the
original 11 variables.
So, we've done pretty well.
Now, you could make an argument here that
if you went up to five components,
you'd actually get yourself up to 84%,
that's an 8% jump.
So it might be worth retaining that one
last one, the fifth one.
After that you can see you don't gain that
much.
By any additional components, you know,
really diminishing returns.
You're getting five or three, two percent
more explained.
So probably we're going to want to stop
here in either four or five.
So that, the Eigenvalue ,uh, greater than
one criteria is easy.
You can also look at the percent of
variance,
total variance explained it again I'd say,
you know,
I'd either stop at 76% or 84% is probably
one of those is you know,
you're getting most of the weight of the,
of explaining the total variance.
You're explaining the total variance in
11.
From 11 variables in only five variables
you just spend 84% of it so
that's pretty reasonable ,so you can look
at that.
Another thing people commonly look at is
something called the Scree plot.
All the Scree plot is it takes that data
that I just showed you in table form and
it just plot it.
So here's the Eigenvalues and then on the,
that's on the y axis.
On the x axis is, are the components.
They're just numbered from one to 11 in
this case.
One is whatever one happened to have the
highest Eigenvalue.
They're ordered from highest to lowest,
and then we just connect the dots.
So it's a very simple plot to make.
And what you're looking for in this scree
plot is essentially, a lot of scree plots,
I'll show you a made up one in a minute,
they kind of just, there's a steep
decline.
And then they kind of level off.
And when you have this kind of inflection
point,
we call that the elbow of this free plot.
And the idea would be that you're, you
know,
you're explainig a lot of the variants and
then suddenly you get down here and
there's not much more to explain and you
level off.
And so you're going to retain Either ,ah,
the number component that
marks the elbow or even one less than
that, that's the typical way people do it.
Now ,this particular plot for
this particular data set, unfortunately it
is not great.
It doesn't have a clear elbow.
So I can't say well, you know,
maybe say at component 3, maybe that's the
elbow because it starts to level off.
But then, you know, it kind of goes
steeply down from four to five.
So maybe, it levels off at four, five,
maybe it levels off at six,
it's really hard.
There's no clear elbow here.
But you can see here you know your
displaying less and less of the variance.
And at some point, definitely by, by six
it's really leveled off.
So we're not going to want to keep six.
Maybe we'll keep five or four.
And you know, this one again I'm looking
at the plot and
thinking maybe I'll see five or four but
there's, this is not a great scree plot in
terms of getting easy to.
Interpret.
I'm going to show you the kind of a
typical screen pot that you're hoping to
get that makes your life a little easier,
doesn't always happen with real data but
here's a hypothetical screen pot that I
made these up so
that makes life easy so this one had also
11 total components so they're numbered on
the x axis from 1 to 11 and their
Eigenvalues are Argument on the Y axis so
you can see that first component explained
in a heck of a lot of the variants and
then there's very steeply you drop a to
the next component and
you drop steeply to the next and then at
four you clearly level off so the elbow.
For this one, for this reply, it's clearly
at four.
And then, what people will do is they're
e-,
they'll either choose the, they'll retain
four components.
That is, we are the elbow stars, or
they'll choose,
more commonly, one less than four, so
they'll stop at three components.
So - if somebody were to get data that
looked like this, they might end up
retaining three components or potentially
four, but no more than that.
So that's the scree plot and again it's a
little bit subjective but,
if you look at all of these criteria, the
eigenvalue greater than one,
the total amount of variance explained in
the scree plot, one of,
you know, the combination of looking at
those should give you some sense.
Of where it would be best ,um, to, to make
that cut off, but
also you need to consider the problem at
hand because, in some cases,
you, there's, there might be a construct
that's, you know the sixth component.
That doesn't explain much of the variance,
but
it somehow that construct is of interest
to you.
And you want to isolate it from the other
variables so you might end up retaining
that one just because it's of particular
interest for a particular problem.
So always ,make this judgment in the
context of the particular problem,
the particular goals of your analysis.
Okay, so we've, applied the PCA.
In this case I decided to retain four
components, but just out of curiosity I
also re-ran the model With five
components, and I'll tell you that, what
the difference between those two was just
so you, get a sense of how that works.
'kay, the next step that we're going to
do,
is we're going to apply something called a
Varimax rotation.
So we're going to take our retained
components, apply this Varimax rotation.
Again, it's very easy to do in the
computer,
all of the standard statistical packages
have this build in, so
it doesn't involve us doing any rotation,
or any linear algebra.
But the point of this ,is that it forces
each variable.
So each of my original 11 variables, to
load more strongly on one of
the components and to not load so strongly
on the other components.
And I'll show you how this helps in
minute, but that's going to make our
results more interpretable because it will
be clear that, for example,
fat mass loads on principle component 1
.So when I go to say, what does
principal component 1 mean, it'll be clear
that it has something to do with fat mass.
So, this is a rotation in, that helps us,
purely in terms of an interpretation.
If you didn't need to interpret the
principal com, components for
some reason Your analysis wasn't focused
on that then you wouldn't need to
apply this rotation, but for most examples
in epidemiology, and
medicine we want to actually understand
what those components mean.
So this is very, very helpful.It also
guarantees us that at
the end of the day that our components
will be uncorrelated with one another.
So let me just kind of show you how this
works.
Again, I won't go into the linear algebra,
but Here are the data so
I ran my principal component analysis on
these 11 variables and
this is what I original get before I apply
this very max rotation.
Now ,I just want to point something out
here notice that it
says factor pattern Factor one and Factor
2.
So, I've been talking about Principle
Component 1 and
Principle Component 2, so where did
factors suddenly jump out?
So, I'm just going to tell you that for
the purposes of, today, I'm,
I'm going to be using factor and principle
component interchangeably.
And the reason suddenly rising factor in
our output rather than principle
component, is simply that because in a lot
of their computer packages including SAS
which is what I used here, you often do
your principle components
analysis from within something called a
factor analysis so the algorithm for
principle components analysis is actually
built in to the factor analysis.
If you want to do this varimax rotation,
you usually have to do it.
Out of a factor analysis.
So, hence at the, what we get out of the
end of the day the computer calls it
a factor rather than a principal,
principal component, but
we're not going to distinguish between
these two at all.
There is a, there are some differences
between factor analysis and
principle components analysis, but what we
are doing here is essentially doing
a principle components analysis just from
within a factor analysis.
So what we, what do we get out here.
So we get these weights, so this, these
are what we call the factor loadings what
you're seeing in this chart are the factor
loadings.
So remember that each factor or principal
component is
calculated by doing a linear combination
of all of the original variables so
for example, you're going to take your
android fat ratio.
For each woman you're going to multiply it
times the factor loading, and
you can see here that the factor loading
turned out to be 0.73.
So you take your android fat ratio, you
multiply point, by 0.73.
Now, all of the factor loadings are
going to come out to
be numbers between negative one and
positive one.
So if something's very close to one, that
means that that variable loads heavily.
On the component, if it's close to zero,
it means it does not load heavily.
We would then take our, a woman's lean
mass and we'd multiply it by .39.
We would add those together, so you would
get her principal component 1 is going to
be equal to her android fat, ratio, times
.73, + her lean mass times .39.
+, her fat mass times .85 [SOUND] + her
BMI times
.74 plus her height times .21 and so on.
I won't go through the whole thing, but
what you come out with at the end of
the day is a linear combination of all the
original variables.
But some of the variables are weeded much
more heavily than others.
Now the problem when you look at the
factor patterns here.
When you look at the factor loadings.
If you look at principle component 1, or
Factor 1.
You'll notice that a lot of things load
heavily on factor one.
So a lot of the body composition and body
size, measurements have pretty high
weights and also, the performance measures
have high negative weights,
meaning they're inversely related, they
lower Factor 1.
So that makes it hard to interpret,
cause there's no clear, Factor 1 doesn't
clearly represent any one construct.
But we can apply this Varimax rotation,
and that's what I've done here.
And notice it becomes wonderfully clean,
after you apply this Varimax rotation.
It's very useful.
So, what happens when you apply the
rotation is that
each variable now loads strongly on one of
the principal components but
does not load strongly on the other.
So if you look at the Android fat ratio,
for example.
It has a weight, for principal component
1, of 0.87.
So it has a stra, it's a strong part of
principal component 1.
But then, for the rest of them, they're
very, all the weights are close to zero,
0.1, 0.2, 0.3, those are all fairly low in
the weighted sun.
What that's telling us is that most
android fat,
android fat gets encapsulated mostly in
principal component 1.
And then if you look down across, down the
column here, across a principal component
you'll notice only a certain variables
that load on principal component 1.
And they're all strongly related to one
another.
So fat mass Loads strongly on principle
component 1, as does BMI.
And I've highlighted everywhere where the
factor loading is greater than .40.
That's a little bit of an arbitrary
cutoff, but that's a pretty good.
To show you what, what strongly loads on
each component.
So what does this tell you?
Now, if you look at lean mass it's got
some relationship,
some it contributes something to principle
component 1.
But it's pretty low.
And then the rest of them, and you, maybe
mile time again, is a lit, you know,
contributing something inversely, but it,
none of these are very strong.
And then the rest are pretty close to
zero.
So principal component 1,
we can now say pretty clearly, we can
interpret the meaning.
The meaning of principal component 1 is
that it's body fatness.
So, it's largely representing body
fatness.
How much fat are you carrying.
Android fat again.
It's viseral fat to people who, you know,
tend to have belly fat.
And, BMI is very strongly related to fat.
So, all of these tell you about body fat.
So, now we can Clearly define the meaning
of principle component 1 and
call it something.
It's representing body fatness.
If you look at principle component 2, if
you look down this column,
you'll notice that most of these are
pretty close to zero.
But you get to all of the measures of
running performance and
competitiveness, and all of those have
high weights on principle component 2.
So they are contributing a lot to
principle component two.
So, my all time if it's, if you're faster
then you're going to get a large,
that's going to increase your principle
component 2.
If you run a lot of miles,
if you're running all your intervals at a
faster pace.
All things that indicate competitiveness.
Now, something that's of, of real interest
here, is this last one.
Notice that there's an additional thing
that loads on principle component 2,
which is menarche age.
Menarche age clearly is not directly
related, of course, all
the performance ones or the training ones,
they all go together if that makes sense.
But menarche age also loads on principle
component 2.
In fact it does not load on the principle
component That loaded all the other
measures of menstrual function.
Which is really interesting and gives you
kind of some insight here.
Because is what that's telling you is that
,uh,
menarchy is the age of a woman's first
period.
For this population, which is young
adolescent woman runners,
menarchy age is more strongly tied to her
running performance and
competitiveness than it is to menstrual
function.
Later.
The, this is the rest of the menstrual
variables are related to
how many periods she's having per year
after Menarche.
So, interestingly all of the menstrual
function variables don't load together.
Which is telling you something about,
about this population.
So, I think that's really interesting.
So, that's Principal Component 2,
primarily running performance.
But also Menarche is very tightly linked
to running performance.
Those who start competing early in life,
tend to have a late Menarche.
Principal component 3 is also very
interesting because if you kind of
scroll down, fat mass has a little bit of
a loading on it, but BMI, android fat,
not so much, and then we get down to lean
mass and height.
Lean mass and height load very strongly on
this principal component.
And then the rest of the variable
contribute very little.
So this variable represents body size, how
big you are.
If you're taller and
you're more muscular, you're going to get
a bigger score on principal component 3.
So this represents body size.
And what's interesting here is that all of
the measures that we had about body size
and composition previously conflated body
fatness and body size.
That is, if you were a, a bigger person,
you were likely to carry more fat mass
just because you were bigger.
So ,there was some component of body size
as well as body fatness contained in
the variable fat mass, and similarly, you
know,
BMI, if you're just a kind of a bigger
person, you might have a bigger BMI.
That conflates body size and body fatness.
But now, remember we've come out with
components variables that
are uncorrelated to one another.
So we've isolated body fat mass and mad
that a separate construct.
From body size.
That's going to be really useful because
we can then tease apart the effects,
separate the effects of a body size just
kind of being a bigger boned person,
you got taller bigger person from body fat
and
is how much fat you actually carry on
your, on your body.
So that's nice, we're able to separate
those constructs and
isolate them from one another, it was very
very useful.
And then finally the.
Fourth principal component, I ended up
calling menstrual regularity,
because if you look down, hardly anything
loaded on it,
except these two, variables that were
representing menstrual regularity,
which is the number of periods a women had
in the past year, and the average number
of periods she's had per year since
menarche, those loaded strongly there.
So this is very useful, because now we've
got four variables that
represent different constructs, they are
uncorrelated with one another.
Another.
And also we've gained some insight into
sort of how things cluster, for
example that Menarche age is more strongly
tied to running performance than it
is to menstrual regularity.
Alright.
So
going through our steps here we've done
the first couple of steps, we applied that
Varimax roation, we interpreted the
meaning of the components by looking at
the rotated factor pattern, those pat,
pattern, those factor loading.
And.
And then the final thing we're going to
do is we may then want to take those
components, those new variables,
those four new variables that we
calculated and
do further statistics on those new
variables.
We have four new variables in our data
set.
We can use them to do further statistics,
I just want to point out.
One additional thing is that I mentioned
That I retained,
as you saw in the solution here.
I contained four components in my
solution.
But what happens if I ask for five
components?
What happens if I ask for five components
is that we get a fifth,
all the same of the principal components
stay the same.
Except the fifth component ends up
representing menarche age.
So the menarche age gets separated out and
becomes its
own component separate from menstrual
regularity or running performance.
So that might be useful.
It's useful when it loads on running
performance because it
gives me some insight.
But if I really care about menarche age as
a seperate construct I might want to ask
for five components so that I can actually
look at the effect of menarche age.
Okay, so now we're going to actually use
these components, these new variables,
these four new variables, to do further
statistics.
So what I did here, is that I wanted to do
this, to do a logistic regression.
So what I have here is a binary outcome,
stress fracture or no stress fracture.
These women fractured or they didn't.
So, I applied logistic regression
analysis, and
my predictors are these four principal
components: body fatness,
running performance, body size and
menstrual function.
Newly calculated.
The computer, by the way, will calculate
these for you.
You do not have to calculate out those
linear combinations yourself for
every ,uh, observation in your data set.
You computer will calculate for you these
values of these principal components.
For each woman in the data set and
it's very easy to get that on the computer
you did and take those new variables and
apply them in something like a logistics
regression as I done here.
Now, I'll just mention that because the
principle components,
these four components are uncorrelated
with one another.
Another.
I have thrown them all together into a
multi variant logistic regression just so
I can put everything on one slide.
But in fact, were I to run separate
logistic regressions with
only one principle component at a time,
I'm going to get the same result in terms
of data coefficients and P values.
Because I, there's no adjustment here.
Since nothing is correlated, none of the
variables are correlated to each other,
there's no, I don't really need to adjust
for anything.
I could just run these separately.
Or I can pull them all into a single model
just to save space on this slide.
But just note that's kind of important to
know is that you don't really need to
do a multi-variate analysis now because we
have already adjusted everything,
everything is separate, all the predictors
are separate from one another.
But whats interesting now is to just look
at the results that we got.
Okay, so principle component one, that was
this body fatness,
how much body fat you are carrying.
Independent of your body size.
And what's interesting is if you recall
from a earlier,.
Module.
I used the ,uh, body composition and body
size variables.
And I tried to predict ,uh, stress
fracture.
And what turned out was that if you were.
All the body size and body composition
measures having higher values
was protective against stress fracture.
It wasn't significant for all of them but
all of them were in the protective
direction and body fatness was this,
body fat, fat mass, that single variable
was the strongest predictor.
Was the most protective.
And I mentioned then that, the, the reason
that fat mass might be so
protective in this particular population
Might have to do with the fact, that,
if you have more fat mass you're likely to
have better menstrual function.
And having better menstrual function
protects your bones.
So, what we've done now those is we've
created separate constructs.
A separate variable that represents body
fat that's independent of
menstrual function.
And when I put that into the model what
you'll notice is that fat
body fatness per say without this
mediation through menstral function has
some is still somewhat protective but its
not statistically significant and
the beta is not very big.
In other words, most of the protective
effective body fatness was probably due
to the the was probably due to its effect
on menstrual function that is more fat.
Better menstrual function less stress
fractures So, that's interesting.
We're able to kind of tease apart what's
due to fat mass versus menstrual function.
The second parts of [UNKNOWN] being more
competitive at running, running more, and
sort of not surprisingly, this one has a
positive relationship with
stress fractures, so the beta here is
point-nine, so
that's a fairly big affect size, and the
p-value is statistically significant.
Obviously, if you run more, if you run
harder You're just,
you have more opportunities to get a bone
fracture.
The third principal component, was this
body size, which is just kind of
how big boned, how tall, how big you are,
not how fat you are,
but how big you are, and this one is all,
not quite statistically significant.
The p value is about .07, so it didn't
quite reach statistical significance, but
the beta is about the same size as the
beta for running performance.
It's negative.
So that's saying being a little bit bigger
is actually protective against fractures.
And this makes sense, because, if you have
a bigger body,
you know we call it big boned right?
You, you tend to have stronger bones.
Your bone density tends to be higher.
So bigger bodies you tend to have, better
bone density the stronger your
bones obviously, the less likely you are
to...
To fractures.
So that makes sense and then finally,
menstrual function.
This had a strong negative relationship.
So better menstral function was related to
protection against stress fractures.
This one was the most significant and also
had the biggest beta coefficient.
And that's well known that menstrual
function is strongly related to
bone density and fractures in women
runners.