In this next module, I am going to go over
the mechanics of how to
calculate the Fisher's exact test by hand.
You're not going to have to do too many of
these by hand, but
it's important that you do this at least
once,
to really understand what's going on
behind the scenes in this test.
And also in order to know how to choose
the correct P value from your
statistical output.
So when is the Fisher's exact test used?
The fisher's exact test is used when you
would try to do a chi-squared test that
you have an r by c, contingency table but
you have sparse data, some of your cells
have 001 person in them.
The rule of thumb is that your expected
value in any cell if you go to calculate
the chi-squared and the expected value in
any of those cells is less than 5,
you should prefer to use the Fisher's
exact test.
Now, its actually never wrong to use the
Fisher's exact test.
But you'll see in a minute that it can be
quite cumber sum to calculate out of
Fisher's exact test if you have a large
sample.
Now a days when we have a lot of computing
power so one could argue that you
should always report the P value from the
Fisher's exact.
As long as your computer can handle
calculating it.
They'll be situation when it's just,
there's too many
probabilities to calculate out for the
computer to handle it.
But you know, my, my little computer on my
desktop with Sass with calculate
[UNKNOWN] exact out for relatively large
Sample sizes without too much problem.
But you definitely want to use and report
the fisher's exact,
especially when you have sparse data when
you have large samples, in fact,
it usually doesn't matter.
The p-values come out kind of similar.
This is especially important in papers to
report the fisher's exact,
not only to get the p-values.
Right.
But even more importantly because when you
when you use an exact test and you put
that in the the footnote of your table, it
flags to the reader, hey, reader, I have
sparse data, and you need to consider that
in an Interpreting these results.
So it's kind of like a signal to the
reader that you've got sparce data.
So another important reason to always
chose the Fisher's exact test when you
have sparse data.
I'm now going to go over to just how to,
to calculate a Fisher's exact test by
hand.
You can do it by hand.
It is a little tedious, you will have to
do one for homework just so
you understand the logic of it.
And the best way to illustrate how to
calculate one is just to do an example.
And so, the, the, the story is, where this
Fisher's exact test came from,
and this is the story that Fisher, who was
a statistician.
A very famous statistician who came up
with,
a lot of the statistics that we do today.
That, you know, way back when.
He, had a colleague.
I'm just going to call her Cathy, just to,
to give her a name.
He clai, she claimed that when she drank
tea,
she could actually distinguish whether the
milk had been poured first into the cup,
or tea had been poured first into the cup.
So, in other words, you know?
She could actually sit there [UNKNOWN]
taste different.
It's whether or not you actually poured
the milk before the tea or
the tea before the milk.
That was her claim, in that she could
distinguish this.
So, he wanted to, to test her on this, he
wanted to kind of call her on it.
So, he had designed a little experiment.
The experiment, couldn't involve her
drinking too much tea, it had to have,
kind of, a limited number of, tea cups and
therefore we ended up with sparse data
here.
So, the task I claim.
Fisher designed the following experiment.
So he made eight cups of tea for her to
taste and you can see why we
need to keep this relatively small and why
we're going to end up with sparse data.
In four of those cups, you know,
he poured the milk first, in four of those
cups he poured the tea first and
he just presented her with the eight cups
kind of randomly ordered.
And told her you have to pick out for me
the four in which the milk was
poured first and the four in which the tea
was for first.
And the null hypothesis here would be that
Cathy's guessing abilities are no
better than chance.
So, if she was just guessing what would
you expect to happen.
Well you probably expect her to guess
about two right, just kind of randomly.
The alter, there's actually more than one
alternative hypothesis here.
So just bare with me.
It's a little confusing but.
That the right tail hypothesis is kind of
what you'd expect.
We think maybe she's going to guess right
more than expected by chance.
And she's going to correctly identify the
milk poured cups more than you'd
expect is due to chance.
There is another possibility.
There's another alternative here that's
different than the null hypothesis.
This is what we call the Left-tail
alternative hypothesis.
And this is important because this is
going to be
printed out in your statistical [UNKNOWN].
You have to understand what it is.
There's another possibility here.
She could guess wrong more than expected
by chance.
In other words, she could correctly
distinguish the cups, but, but,
label them in the reverse.
So she could.
Correctly say, hey, these four are,
milk poured first, in other words, she
could get the four that were,
that were she could correctly get the four
that were different than the other for.
But she might say, these are the milk
poured first, but,
in fact, those were all the tea poured
first.
She did actually distinguish the cups
correctly in that case,
except she She didn't know which ones were
actually milk poured for
her, so she was actually systematically
wrong.
So that's another possible outcome that
would not be the null hypothesis.
And we'll calculate p values for both of
those.
So when the, the legend goes that when
this was conducted,
this experiment was conducted, this is how
she did it.
So this is the observed table.
This is the data that we.
You have.
That, this is what actually happened.
So, Fisher, had poured a milk first in
four cups and tea first in four cups.
And Kathy knew that there were four cups
with milk first and
four cups with tea first so she was going
to identify four and four.
She wasn't going to guess them all to be
milk first.
That's was allowed in In the set up here.
So these are fixed.
There's four tea poured first and there's
four milk poured first, and
she has to guess four and four.
When she guesses, what happens is that she
correctly identifies three of
milk poured first, she gets one wrong.
And then, of course the she's going to get
one of the tea poured first wrong.
And 3 of the tea poured first right by
default, so this is a binary situation so
any that she doesn't that she guesses to
be milk poured first can't be
tea poured first and vice versa.
So that's the outcome now we look at that
and
we say well she did you know if we were.
If it was chance you'd probably only get
about two right, but you know,
probably three right might also be in the
realm of what we might expect of a chance.
We might, we might have been amazed has
she gotten all four right.
So, Fisher wanted to calculate a P value
here.
How we are going to calculate a P value
here?
Notice, very sparse numbers, we got a lot
of one cells.
Clearly we don't want to do anything, we
don't want to do a chi-squared.
Which is approximating a normal [UNKNOWN]
binomial.
We want to do an exact probability.
So how do we do this?
So step one of the Fisher's test is
actually to identify the observe table and
all the tables that represent a more
extreme outcome.
Okay, so what does that mean?
So this is the observe table, we just saw
that on the previous slide.
That's what we observe but
remember that the P value is what we
observe Everything more extreme.
Well what is, what would be more extreme
in this case?
Well more extreme would have been she
actually got all four cups right and
none wrong.
So that's what the second table I'm
showing you here,
that's the more extreme table.
And there's nothing more extreme, that's
as, that's as good as she could have done.
Now we can calculate the probabilities
associated with each of these tables.
And this is going to get back to
permutations and combinations from
last term, so if you didn't get enough of
that before, we do it a little bit here.
So we can actually calculate the
probability of each of these tables.
I'm going to show you how it's done.
So here's the probabilities calculated out
and
I'm going to walk you through the logic
here.
So what is the probability of guessing
three right and one wrong?
Okay.
We have to do a We have to do an
accounting problem here.
So what's the probability of getting
exactly three right and one wrong?
Well what's our denominator here?
What are all the ways that she could guess
four cups out of eight cups?
So imagine she's got eight cups and she's
got four stickers with M on them, and
she has to paste the four M stickers on
four of the cups.
And of course, the rest of them would be,
she would be saying were Tea poured first.
So she has to pick out of the eight cups,
any four of them.
As her choices for the milk poured first.
Her guesses.
That denominator, all the ways she can do
that is an 8 choose 4.
There's 8 cups, she can choose any 4 of
them.
That's an 8 choose 4.
So we could do out 8 choose 4,
that would give us the total number of
possible ways she could guess here.
So that's our denominator.
Whi, which, what situations will fulfil
her getting exactly 3 right.
How many different ways can she get
exactly 3 right?
That's what goes in the numerator here.
So here is how she can get exactly 3
right.
We have 4 milk poured first cups.
She has to guess any 3 of them correctly.
So that's a 4 choose 3.
She has to guess one of the tea poured
first cups wrong.
So, that's a 4 choose 1.
So, she gets to choose any of the three
milk cups, but then there were 4
tea cups that she's going to incorrectly
put one of the m stickers on.
So, that's a 4 choose 1.
So, there's 4 choose 3, times 4 choose 1,
possible ways that she can get exactly 3
right and 1 wrong.
So that's the probability of the observed
table.
The probability of the more extreme table
is actually only one way that she can get
them all right, right.
She has to get,
correctly put the m stickers on the
exactly four milk poured first cups.
So the probability for the, for the more
extreme tables is actually fairly easy.
It's the same denominator as e.
Chose four possible ways she could put
those m stickers on the cups.
And she has to get all four milk cup
poured first cups right.
And none of the t ones, you can't put the
m labels on any of the t ones.
Four choose four times four choose 0 is of
course just 1.
There's only one way she can get this
right.
So notice that we would have been kind of
amazed had she gotten all four right.
That p value is very small.
However, the probability of getting
exactly three right is pretty high.
It's not that unlikely.
Somebody could do it just guessing.
So now we're going to calculate all the
different p values that come out here.
And actually when you're first doing
Fisher's exact test what I recommend that
you do Is not only calculate the
probability for
the table that you have observed and the
more extreme tables but
the best thing to do is, I will give you
problems that are pretty small,
is to calculate all out the probabilities
for all possible outcomes.
So here's the probability.
Complete probability distribution where X
is the number of correct
identifications of milk-poured first cups.
She can get four right, which we already
calculated.
She can get three right, which we already
She could have also gotten 2 right, 1
right, or 0 right.
And that goes through all possible
outcomes.
I can calculate the probability for each
one of those tables.
This is a really good thing to do because
it's a little bit of a check To make sure
that you've calculated the probabilities
correctly, cause they better.
You've now accounted for all possible
outcomes, they better add up to one.
And indeed, if you add those up, you'll
notice they add up to one.
The distribution here turned out to be
symmetrical.
I'll warn you.
That in Fischer's exact tests, the
distributions are not always symmetrical.
So just keep that in the back of your
mind.
The one tail test and the two tail test,
the two tail test is not always double the
one tail test.
The tails don't always match.
Now we're going to get a number of p
values out of Sass, or
whatever statistical program you're using.
So the right hand tail probability, that's
literally what sas calls it, is you get,
you add up the 0.229, what you observed in
everything more extreme to the right.
That is her, getting more right.
So 0.229 plus 0.014, that comes out to one
tail p-value of 0.243.
That's our one tail p-value.
Of course we're at the end of the data
that I want to
report a two tail p-value because it's
equally likely that she.
She could have been wrong in the
systematically wrong as I
mentioned before.
Now, sas always also gives you something
else.
It gives you this left handed probability.
We never really use it for anything, but
it's there in the output.
So I just want to let you know what it is.
This relates to that alternative
hypothesis that I mentioned.
Where she's systematically wrong.
So you could also test the probability
that she's systematically wrong.
You could calculate a p value for that.
You would, then, you would add up what you
observed, and
everything more extreme in these being
systematically wrong directions, so
every, the, the essentially the left tail.
So, 0.229 plus 0.514 plus 0.229 plus
0.014.
Our p value here comes out to be 0986,
so clearly we don't have any evidence that
she's systematically wrong.
We get the right hand tail probability the
left hand probability.
And then we want is the 2 sided p value.
Now the 2 sided p value for fisher's exact
test is calculated by adding up
all the probabilities in the distribution.
So here's all the probabilities that are
less than or
equal to the probability of the observe
table.
So that, in this case, is 0.229 plus 0.014
is less than or equal to it.
Plus 0.229 is less than or equal, 0.014 is
also less than or equal.
So we add up those four probabilities.
Here it comes out to a two-sided p-value
of 0.4857.
Now notice that we also, in this case,
could have simply just
doubled the one-tailed probability, the
one tailed p value.
And gotten the two tailed p-value.
However, you're going to see some cases
where the two tailed p-value is
not equal to double the one tailed p-value
because there is,
sometimes, the Fishers exact test does not
have a symmetric distribution.
And the area under one tail might be
different than the area under
the other tail.
So the way to calculate the two-tailed is
just to add up the p-value of
what you observed in all other observed
tables that had equal or smaller P values.
That happens to work out to be double the
one-sided P value here,
but, as you'll see in your homework that
isn't always the case.
That's a hint on your homework, by the
way.
So those are the P values you get out of
SAS again,
you're going to want to report the
two-sided P value at the end of the day.
And I just show you the output from SAS
when I ran this fisher's exact test in
SAS indeed I get a number of P a P values
here so here's that last cited P value I
was telling you about we're generally
going to ignore that.
Here's that right-sided P value he was
talking about.
That's the one-tailed probability we're
also going to ignore that.
The table probability by the way is the
probability of the observed table,
of that one observed table.
I get it we usually are going to ignore
that too but
what we care about is the two-sided P
value which happens to be at the very end
of our output in SAS at least, and that's
the P value that we're going to report.
I want to just show you that I also asked
SAS to run the chi square test for
that two by two table.
So my two by two table here again looked
like this.
I have 3, 1, 1, 3.
I can ask SAS to run a chi square test on
it.
And, and it will run it.
When it did that chi square test were
clearly violating the assumption of not
having sparse data here.
It's probably a bad idea to approximate
here with a,
a, discreet distribution with a continuous
one we get a chi-Square value of 0.15.
You can see that two sided P value of 0.15
is very different tan the two sided P
value we got from the Fisher's exact.
Which tells you that, you know, again When
you have sparse data it can
really make a difference if you correctly
chose the Fisher's exact or
try to apply the Chi-Squared.
Luckily SAS pretty nice, it gives you a
little warning down here.
Says 100% of the cells have expected
counts less than 5,
your Chi-Squared test may not be valid.
So it tries to warn you when you need to
actually use the Fisher's exact.
Again, one could argue that you should use
the Fisher's exact in all cases as long as
your computer can handle calculating it.
You can imagine for large tables.
It has to calculate the observed table and
all more extreme tables.
That's a heck of a lot of probabilities to
calculate, so
it can take a lot of computing power.
Although with modern computers, often
times this isn't an issue.
Just for those of you who were interested
in how to actually get SAS
to do this test for you, I'm showing you
how I entered the data here, and
how I got the Fisher's exact test.
Just for those of you who are interested
and want to try it on your own in SAS.