In this next module I'm going to introduce
Principal Components Analysis.
So Principal Components Analysis is
basically a data reduction technique.
If you've got a sought of larger set of
predictor variables,
many of which might be highly correlated,
It can compress them,
that set of variables, into a smaller set
of variables.
Fewer variables, without losing too much
information from the original variables.
This is very useful to do prior to running
a regression analysis.
Because if you've got a large set of
predictors, a whole bunch of
different variables you've measured, and
you just throw each one of those.
Predictors into a regression analysis.
You have a, you're increasing your chances
of making a type one error,
that is of finding chance,
of things just by chance, you're
increasing your risk of over-fitting.
So compressing your data set a little bit
before putting it
into the regression analysis can be really
helpful.
For that reason, Principle Components
Analysis is just a really cool,
exploratory technique, as well, it just
can help you understand.
Your data a little better,
to pick out relationships between groups
of variables and discover patterns.
And you can kind of do the same thing just
by looking at a correlation matrix, so
if you, ask for a correlation matrix of
all the correlation coefficients between
all the pairs of variables in your data.
Uh,you can kind of scan that and
try to figure out which variables are
related to one another.
And that's kind of effective but
correlation matrix can become unwieldy
really fast.
So if you have just ten variables the
correlation matrix is going to
have 45 correlation coefficients to scan
through and
if you have more than that it's going to
get bigger and bigger.
So principal components analysis actually
is, kind of gives you a synopsis.
Of the correlation matrix.
It reduces the information, it synthesizes
it a little bit, so it's easier to get to,
to figure out those kind of things like
what variables are related and,
and what variables kind of cluster
together.
So it's useful even just to understand
your data better.
Let me just start with a very simple made
up example.
I'm not going to go into all of the
details yet
about Principal Component Analysis.
I want to just walk you through this first
little toy example.
Quickly, just to motivate what you can get
out of Principle Components Analysis.
So, here's some data I'm showing you.
Imagine I gave you this data set.
There's two variables.
There's a variable which I'm calling some.
That's on the y-axis and a variable that
I'm calling first.
That's on the x-axis.
And, if you didn't know, I'm going to tell
you in just a minute what these
variables are going to represent.
But if you didn't know.
What is the underlying structure here, you
would look at these data and
you would try to figure out what is going
on with the data,
and what is the relationship between these
two variables.
Now I'm going to tell you what these data
represent so you'll know the structure,
but in a minute we'll see that principles
of components analysis can kind of
help us tease out the structure if we
didnt know ahead of time...
So I just created this little data set on
the computer.
By saying make x be the roll, I virtually
rolled the die.
So make x be the roll of a single die.
So that's going to be a number from one to
six, the roll of one die, and then y,
the variable that I'm calling sum here,
that's going to be take the value you
got on x and then roll the die one more
time and add the roll of the second die.
So this is going to become a number
between a number between two and 12.
So x is embedded within y cause you're
going to take the,
the value from of x, the roll of the first
die and add it to the.
To the roll of the second die, and that's
how you're going to come up with Y.
So X and Y are correlated here.
They have covariance, they're correlated
because X is part of Y.
And notice that the variables here have
been Z standardized as I've turned them
into Z squared.
So if you're actually looking at the, the
axis here, it ranges from -1.5 to 1.5.
In both directions, and you know something
comparable.
-2 to 2 in the other direction.
So these have been standardized.
You need to standardize your variables
prior to running a PCA analysis.
If I ask the computer to give me the
correlation coefficient,
it turns out to be .71.
That's not quite as useful as seeing.
They are squared so if square point seven
one I get the R squared value and
that comes out to be exactly 50% and
what that's telling me is that 50% of the
variblity in Y is,
comes from X, is explained by X and that
makes perfect sense here right?
Because we rolled two die.
The variation, half of the variation comes
from the variability of that first roll.
So half of the variation of the sum comes
from that first roll.
That's what the R squared represents here.
They share 50% of their variants, these
two variables.
And how can principal components be
applied here.
So the way that principal components
analysis is applied what we're going to do
is we're going to try to extract
information from as much information as
we can from both of these variables.
We're going to try to actually come up
with two new variables.
The first of which is going to extract as
much information as possible and
the second of which is going to, is
going to extract as much information as
possible from the leftover what we didn't
capture in the first principle component.
But basically what we're going to do is
imagine here that we draw an oval,
an ellipse around these data points.
And if I just asked you to.
Find the direction, the line which
represents the maximum variation in these
data.
You could do that by just kind of finding
the.
The axis of the ellipse that's the
longest.
In order, that's what I'm going to do
here.
I may not be drawing this perfectly right
but something like that is going to be
the maximal, the biggest line you can draw
in this ellipse.
That's going to represent the maximal
variation in my data.
If I'm seeing this as sort of a cloud of.
Data points.
I want to find the line that represents
the maximal spread in the data.
The maximal variation.
That's where more variation needs more
information so
I am going to find that line.
This is what we call the first principal
component, that line.
That is a new variable that contains
information from both of the two original
variables and actually contains as much
information as possible, and
what am I going to do with that?
Well, I'm just going to,
I'm going to show you that here on on
again on this graphic here so this Again,
is the first...this is [UNKNOWN] fit on a
computer so it's properly drawn.
So this is the first principal component,
the line in blue.
And the computer found that by finding
that line of maximal variation.
I've also shown you here in red the linear
regression line
between these two variables.
I just want to show you that they're very
close, these two things, but
not identical.
So then we take that.
First principle component.
What are we going to do with it?
Well that represents a new variable.
It's a line, so it's just one dimensional.
It is a single new variable that contains
information from
the two original variables.
What I'm going to do next is I'm going to
rotate my entire scatter plot
here such that the first principle
component aligns with the x-axis.
This just makes it easier.
To deal with because we like we want to
reference everything to
that first principle component.
Its easier to do that if we rotate to that
first principle component ends up
on the x axis.
So that's all I've done on the right panel
here.
So that's the first principle component.
The second principle component Is going to
be a line perpendicular to
the first we always are going to choose a
line perpendicular to the first principal
component now since we're in only two
dimensions there is only one line that
is perpendicular to the first principal
component here so that line and
we don't even have a choice we're just
going to draw the line perpendicular.
Perpendicular.
But if you were in higher dimensions there
would be,
you would choose the perpendicular line
that captured, again, the most
variance in, in the left, in, left, most
leftover variance in my data points.
So when I rotate this graph the first
principal component becomes the x-axis.
The second principal component becomes the
y axis.
So now you can visual
see the two components.
What are the principal component actually
represent here.
[INAUDIBLE] When you rotate the axis here,
what you notice is they have equal
variants.
So there's equal variance in principle
component one as in
principle component two.
They're also uncorrelated as you can see
because they're perpendicular.
So what have we actually done here?
What does first principle component
represent here?
It essentially represents the roll of die
one.
That was the overlap between the sum and
the first variable.
It was the roll of die one.
Principle component two now, rather than
representing the sum,
represents the separate independent role
of the second die.
That's what we've extracted here.
So we've extracted some structure here.
We've totally separated that first roll
and second roll of the die, and what
we find is, of course, as they're, they're
equal things, they're rolls of die.
There have, they each have equal variance.
And if you're doing this in a computer
program,
the computer program will tell you well
the variance,
when you've done this technique, you'll
say, what's the variance of each factor?
So it turns out factor and principal
component I can use interchangeably.
In this lecture.
So, it turns out that remember, what was
our original standard deviation.
The standard deviation of sum was equal to
one and
the standard deviation of of first was
also equal to one.
That's because I standardized the
variables which we're
always going to do before Principle
Components Analysis so the variants,
the standard deviations are one and
therefore the variances are also one.
So the variance is also equal to one for
both of those [SOUND].
So we have a total of a variance of two
and when we.
Extract those two principle components,
it turns out that we have equal variance
in each.
Because the variance of the roll of one
die is equal to the variance of
the roll of a second die.
So we extract and
we found out here that each component
explains exactly half the variance.
Now normally what you're going to see is
that the first component is
going to explain more of the variance than
the second component because
that's what we're after.
But in this case what we really had
structurally underneath here was
just a roll of two die so each of those
explains exactly half of the variance.
So that's just the kind of motivate that
you can pull structure,
you can figure out and un-tingle
correlated variables.
Using principle components analysis.
Now, I'm going to go through in more
detail exactly what's going on with
a little bit more math,using some actual
real data.
So this goes back to the data set that I
was talking about earlier.
I have 91 young adolescent women runners.
And the, we measured a bunch of things on
them included their fat mass, their
weight, their bone density, menstrual
periods, things that were of interest.
I'm just showing two of the variables
here.
It's really easy to illustrate principle
components analysis in two dimensions.
It gets really tricky to draw things in
more dimensions so
I'm going to stick for now, and we'll get
to a higher dimension problem later, but
I'm going to stick for now to two
variables, two dimensions.
So, I have two variables, fat mass and
weight.
As you would expect, fat mass and weight
are highly correlated.
Your fat mass is just exactly how much
the, measured by DEXA, exactly how
many pounds or kilograms of fat you have
versus things that are not fat.
When I plot these two variables in a
scatterplot,
you'll notice that they're highly related.
The higher your weight, Is, weight is on
the x-axis here, the higher your
fat mass is, and I, it's kind of arbitrary
which one I put on x versus y.
We just know that these are highly
correlated.
We, they have, when I calculated the
correlation coefficient here, they have a,
a correlation of 0.86.
In a way, these two variables are almost
completely redundant.
Right, there's fat mass and weight are
very, going to be so
tied together because you have more fat
mass you probably weigh more as well.
One of the things you might do when you
see something like this is
you might say well okay when I go to do my
regression analysis, I'm only going to
look at fat mass or I'm only going to look
at weights since they're redundant,
I really only need one of those.
Variables.
And people do that but its,
you're losing some information when you
just throw in one of the variables out.
You've bothered to measure it, you don't
want to just throw it out.
Also what, more realistically people do is
they put
fat mass into the regression equation and
look at the pay value,
then they weight into the regression
equation they look at the pay value and
they choose the one that's sort of highest
and of course that increases your
chances of type 1 errors, so you got to be
a little bit careful about that.
A better solution.
Would be to say, can I extract as much
information as possible from these two
variables together, from both of these
variables.
I want to create a new variable that
contains information from
both fat mass and
weight, and extracts, as much information
as is possible into this new variable.
More information than either variable
alone.
And that's what we're going to do.
Essentially with principle components
analysis.
So, we're going to create a new variable.
That new variable is going to be the
original two variables -
fat mass and weight.
All that I mean by linear combination.
So we're going to call this variable a
component, call it component one.
Yeah.
All I mean by linear combination is you're
going to take a persons,
a woman's fat mass value and multiply it
by some coefficient and
then some weight and then you're going to
take her weight value, you're going to
multiply that by some weight coefficient
and then you're going to add those up.
When you do that you come up with a single
number that has elements of
both fat mass and weight in it.
And the goal in principal components
analysis is to
extract to get the most information out of
both of those two variables and
the way that we do that is that we find
the Betas,
this is the weights, Beta of f fat mass
and Beta weight here that give
the new variable component one the maximal
possible variance,
that means captures as much of the
information as is available in the data.
Beta.
>> So you literally could imagine, so I
could just you know try,
here's component one, if I put in 0.5 for
fat mass, and I put in you know 0.4 for
weights, and then I calculate that
variable for everybody in my data set and
then I calculate the variance of that
component one in the normal way we
calculate variants for a single variable,
And then I do it again.
I try, oh, let me try something else.
[LAUGH] Now, I'm going to get a variance
here.
Maybe I'm get a variance of 1.4, and then
I try something else.
Let me try 0.3 for fat mass.
You can see that this is not an efficient
way to solve this problem.
0.2 for weight and now, you know, maybe I
get a variance of 1.5.
If I try all possible combinations.
Of the betas.
What, which one combinations is going to
give me the highest variance for
this new variable?
Of course you don't want to try to do that
out by trial and error.
But it sounds kind of like a maximization
problem, so
we can do that out with a little bit of
calculus or
a little bit of linear algebra, and that's
exactly how it's done mathematically.
I'm not going to go into the details here,
but it basically involves a little bit of
linear algebra, which is.
Beyond the scope of this course but all
your trying to do
the end goal here is to get the betas that
maximize the variance.
And rather than trying to actually do out
the linear algebra here.
We can, in a way, solve this problem
pictorially, with a picture.
And so now that's what we're going to do.
We're going to solve this problem with a
picture.
What we're going to do is say, well hey,
here's this scatterplot.
The, the lie, the Component one of the
variant, the component that I can come
up with that has the maximum variance will
correspond to [UNKNOWN] draw an ellipse.
Around my my scatter plot, my data points
and
I find the direction of the of the ellipse
that has the maximal spread.
That will correspond to the line of
maximum variance.
This will be my first principal component.
I'm just trying to find the line that.
It represents the maximal spread of the
data that is my first principal component,
that will correspond to giving the
variable with the maximal possible
variance and then whatever the betas are
that define this line would be
my weights to get component one.
So that's how we can find it sort of
pictorially just conceptually what we're
doing is we're finding that line of
maximum variance.
So that's the first principal component
called pc1 here.
Now principal component one is just a
Single variable.
It is, it's represented by a line, because
it only has one dimension.
When you look at that line in a graphic,
you feel like you're in two dimensions,
right?
Because, if I for
example, take this particular observation,
this woman right here.
And I say, well what's for her value for
principle component?
One, how am I going to find that?
To find that, what I'm asking is where
does she lie along this line,
this line of maximum variances principle
components one line.
Where does she lie on this line?
Well it's actually not obvious where she
lies on this line, right?
Relative to the, to zero on this line.
Where does she lie on this line?
It's not obvious and I, you know, where
does this woman lie?
What's her value for principle component
one?
Where does she lie along this line?
It's not really obvious because we'd like
to have our x-axis, so this is where,
its like we're on a coordinate space here
but it's in the wrong direction.
We'd like to have our x-axis lined up
horizontally we just, it's easier for
us to look at things where the x-axis
corresponds to the horizontal directions.
So what I want to do is rotate this whole
scatter plot such as the first
principal component that line of maximum
variation lines up with the x-axis.
So that's what I've done, that's all that
I'm doing in the right hand panel here.
We've just rotated the graphic.
And we can do this, we can rotate all
these points just with a little bit of
linear algebra or we can just you know
literally rotate the graph here.
So if I rotate this graphic it makes it
really easy to see where what every
woman's value is for the part first
principle component, so
I'll take this woman I've highlighted in
black here.
So in the original scatter plot, she had a
value of negative 1.74 for
her fat mass and negative 1.26 for her
weights.
I should put the x value negative 1.26,
the y value is -1.74 So that was her
coordinates in the original scatter plot.
When I rotate this graphic,
I'm now going to get her coordinates
relative to the first principal component,
and also the second principal component
which is just the perpendicular line here.
So, notice that when I rotate this
graphic, she now has new coordinates.
So, now her x value is just her value on
component one.
That x value actually turns out to be
here.
-2.12.
You can see that in
this new coordinate axis, she falls at
about -2.1, for her x direction.
That's her value for principle component
one.
In the Y direction, she falls at about
-.34.
And that's here value for the second
principle component.
And where did these values come from?
Well, this just came from me solving for
those betas.
So when I solve for principal component
one, the beta for
fat mass turned out to be .707, the beta
for weight turned out to be .707.
So when I want to calculate her value.
For principal component one,
I'm just going to plug in her actual fat
mass and weight.
So I weigh 0.707 times negative 1.26 plus
0.707 times negative 1.74.
That gives me, when I calculate it out, a
value of negative 2.12.
And so that will be her X value in this
new graph or that will be her value for
principle component one.
What does it mean?
Well, this is in standard deviation units.
So she's about two standard deviations
below normal on this
first principle component.
She's very light and petite compared to
the rest of the sample because.
The first principle component here is
representing some combination of
weight and fat mass.
That's the first principle component.
The second principle component is chosen
to be
perpendicular to the first uh,principle
component.
And so in two space, when we have just two
dimensions,
there's only one possible line here, I've
drawn it in, that's.
This is the second principle component.
And that becomes the Y axis in our new
rotated space.
And they'll be some beta coefficients
associated with that
if you plugged them in, you would get
-0.34 for this particular woman.
So now we have just have two new
variables.
Essentially we've got these by finding
this line of maximum variation rotating,
so it lined up with the X axis.
And then finding the, the second principle
component.
Is perpendicular to that, and now we have
two new variables.
The first variable represents some
combination of weight and fat mass,
the second variable represents any left
over variability once you have done
principal of components one.
I just want to say a bit more about the
second principal component.
And I have a clean graphic here.
So, when I'm in two dimensions,
there's only one line perpendicular to the
first principle component.
So that's going to be the second principle
component, and we're done.
However, that's, you know, usually it's
more interesting than that.
So usually, if we're, so say, imagine
you're in three dimensions.
What's the second going to,
principle component going to be when I
start with three variables and I'm in.
Three dimensions.
Well that's going to be, I have to find
the line of
maximum variation that is perpendicular to
the first principal component.
And if I'm in three space, there's
actually many lines I can choose from.
Imagine just kind of rotating 360 degrees
around the first line in space.
You're going to find whatever direction
where the, the remaining where the.
Remaining variance is the largest.
So you have the biggest spread of the
data, I guess.
So it gets more interesting in multiple
dimensions.
But you're always choosing principle
components that are going to
be perpendicular to the la, to all the
other ones.
So for example, if I went, if I was in
really high space.
And I had wanted to go for a third
principle component.
Then the principal component three is
going to be the line of
maximal variation that's perpendicular to
both principal component one and
two and you can keep going.
So you're going to come out with a whole
set of principal components.
At the end of the day,
we may throw some of the ones that some of
the lesser ones away in the end.
Now, but we end up with,
if we start with two variables, we end up
with two principle components.
If we start with three variables,
we'll end up with three principle
components and so on.
Now I just applied the principal
components analysis to the simple data
set, where I just have weight and fat mass
and I've rounded these values.
So here's some of the data.
Here was the weight and fatmass
combinations for certain woman.
Here is their translation into principle
component one and principle component two.
So all of these the.
Two variables when you fat mass get
translated into two new variables,
principle component one and principle
component two and again, we may decide,
and I'm going to show you in a minute,
that principle component one captures
enough of the information of weight and
fat mass that we no longer need principle
component number two and
we just kind of discard that and not take
that.
For, future analyses for further analyses.
Now, these are just new variables,
every woman gets a new values on this, in
this data set.
We can do statistics about these new
variables, so here's some,
I ran some basic descriptor statistics
about my new principle components.
And notice that I get standard deviations.
The standard deviation for principal
component one is very high; for
principal component two, it's very, it's a
lot lower.
And you can see that in a picture, right,
I mean, here's a huge amount of variation
in x and very little variation in y.
Let me just square these,
because it's useful to talk about
variances here, so if I square.
Where 1.36 the variants for
principle component one actually turns out
to be 1.86 and the variants for
principle components so that's principle
component one the variants for
principle component two if I square .378
that comes out to be .14.
So how much variance did we start with in
this problem.
Both variables were standardized, fat mass
and weight.
So the variance for fat mass, was
originally 1.0.
The variance for weight was originally
1.0,
because these were standardized variables.
Standard deviations is one, so variance.
This one.
So the total variance we started with was
2.0.
You add these two together.
What we've done is we've partitioned that
variance into.
We've put a whole bunch of that variance
in the principle component and very lean,
meaning there was very little left over
for the second principle component.
We've we've now taken our, our 2.0, our
variance of two,
and we've divided it into, almost all of
it
went into the first principle component
with a variance of 1.86.
Very little variance was left over, and
in fact if you just divide 1.86, divide
that by 2.0, you'll see
that 93% of the variance is now explained
by that first principle component.
Which means if I throw out the second
principle component, and
I don't use it for further analyses, I've
only lost 7% of the information.
Of the variance in my data.
So that's very useful to understand.
And next I also ran the Pearson's
correlation coefficients,
the correlation matrix between my two new
variables and what do you notice?
So the correlation is exactly zero.
They are completely uncorrelated.
And that's another nice feature.
We end up with at the end of the principle
components analysis,
we've extracted, we've untangled those two
variables.
So they're totally uncorrelated so
principle component two.
Is representing sort of whatever we
haven't.
Different information than principle
component one.
Whatever we haven't explained in that
first principle component.
And I just want to show you because you're
going to see in your output from SAS or
whatever statistical program your using.
You're going to see the term eigenvalues,
don't get scared by that it's not a big
deal.
The eigenvalue Is just the variants that
each one of the new variables.
So, for example, the variants of principle
[UNKNOWN] was 1.86.
For principle [UNKNOWN] one and two, it
was .14.
The Eigenvalue is just the variance of
those new variables.
And Eigenvalue's a term that comes form
linear algebra, so what we did.
In order to get, or to do an principle
components analysis is to
actually take the Eigenvectors of the
correlation matrix so
you've applied some linear algebra to the
correlation matrix, the term Eigenvalue is
in there because it's something we can do
mathematically but it turns out that
that equals, at the end of the day, just a
variance of each of those variables.
Somewhere later in the output at least in
sash you see a little block that says
variance explained by each factor and you
notice those are the exact same numbers so
it's it's giving you a better layperson's
interpretation of those numbers,
you can find that is exactly the variance
explained by each factor.
You notice that I'm sometimes switching
between the terms factor and
principal component.
In fact, a lot of times when you want to
do Principal Component Analysis,
you're actually going to run a factor
analysis.
At least the algorithm in the computer.
It's, Its uh,principle components is often
created as
a specific instance of a factor analysis
so sometimes you'll see that you're
actually doing it within the factor
analysis function so
you might get out things at the end of the
day that are called factors.
So don't worry about the fact that I'm
sort of flopping between those two terms.
All right, so what did we end up with at
the end of the day?
We started with fat mass and weight.
Now we've got two new variables.
Two new components.
Principle components one and two.
What do those actually mean though?
It was easy to figure out what they meant
for the dice example, but
what do they mean for this example?
That's where we have to do a little bit of
thinking.
It's probably pretty easy to guess what
they mean here because we
have such a simple example.
But in the next module, we're going to
talk a little bit more about how to
figure out what the principle components
mean.
So principal component one here is some
combination of, you know,
your weight and your fat mass.
Of course, those two things are highly
related, so
it probably relates the fact that you're
going to have a higher
principal component one if you're kind of
a bigger person, you have more body size,
because the bigger you are, just like
tall.
Big boned, that's going to mean that you
weigh more, and it's also going to mean
that you have more fat mass, because,
just, the bigger you are,
even if you're really lean, you're just
going to carry more fat mass.
It's also, there's also just a dimension
of just how much body fat you carry for
a particular body size.
That's also encapsulated in this principal
component one, so
you're, it means something about that
you're both a bigger person.
And that you have more, you're carrying
more body fat.
Well what is principal component two then
probably relate to?
Well it likely, in this case,
relates to weight really is just fat mass
plus lean mass.
So weight is, you know, one, fat mass is
one part or weight.
The other part of weight that we're
missing,
in a way it's like the dice example,
right?
The fat mass plus the lean mass equals the
weight.
So, the piece that we're missing in that.
Sum, that got you the total weight is the
lean mass, so
probably a principle component two
represents something about the lean mass,
so for a given body size and body fat
level, there's going to be
some variation in the amount of lean mass,
and that's capturing that.
There isn't a lot of variation though,
because remember there's not too much you
know, variability left.
For a given body size and
body fat there's probably not going to be
a whole heck of a lot of.
Variation lean mass.
So it has something to do with the lean
mass.
And again, we're probably not even
going to worry about this one.
For this example we're probably going to
use principal component one for
the rest of our analyses because it
captures almost all of the information.