Welcome to week two of HRP 262.
This week, I'm going to introduce you to
the parametric regression methods for
analyzing survival data.
So last week, we talked about basically
descriptive methods for
looking at survival data.
This week, we're going to delve into
regression.
We're going to start by talking about the
parametric regression models,
which are those that assume some kind of
underlying mathematical function for
the survival times.
We're specifically going to talk about
exponential and Weibull survival models.
Because we are delving into fitting
mathematical Curves,
smooth mathematical curves.
We will have a bit of math this week.
Especially the first three units we'll
talk about probability distributions,
hazard functions and survival functions.
So there will be some math thrown in
there.
So where are we on our little statistical
chart of tasks for time-to-event outcomes.
Again, we cover some of the descriptive
methods last week, incidence rates,
Kaplan-Meier statistics.
This week we're delving into our first
regression technique for survival data.
Specifically, the parametric regression
technique.
Just to give you a flavor for
what I mean by this, so, here are two
survival curves pictured on this slide.
On the left side is the non-parametric
estimate of survival function.
We, calculated this last week.
This was some pregnancy data.
Women getting pregnant.
We calculated the Kaplan Meier curve.
This is the observed survival function,
just what we saw in our data.
That's what you're seeing on the left hand
side of the slide.
On the right hand side of the slide,
what you're seeing is the result of
parametric regression model.
So what we have done is estimated that
survival curve now as
a smooth mathematical function.
And that's the idea of parametric
regression.