In this next module, I'm going to talk
about effect modification,
which is equivalent to the term
interaction.
You'll see that epidemiologists tend to
use the term effect modification.
It's a little easier to talk about one
variable modifying the effect of another,
it's a little easier to talk about
verbally.
But statisticians prefer the term
interaction,
because that's more of a statistical term.
But they're equivalent terms.
So what is an effect modifier?
This is the situation where we have a
predictor and outcome that actually have
different relationships depending on what
level we're at of the effect modifier.
Again, effect modification is also called
interaction.
So the predictor now, come now may differ
in their relationships depending on
where we are depending on the effect
modifier.
Just to say it a little bit more
Statistical terms, what we're looking for
is when the effect size, again, the
relationship between the predictor and
the outcome, is modified, is different, in
different subgroups.
And statistically, that would mean we
would see a statistically
significant difference of the effect
between those different subgroups.
So for example, if you had a blood
pressure treatment that worked
significantly better in men than in women,
we would say that the treatment had an
interaction with gender.
So gender modifies the effect.
Of the treatment on blood pressure.
In this module, I'm just going to
illustrate an interaction with some
examples, we're not going to get into the,
details of how you statistically identify
interacting variables yet.
Here's some data from, one of the national
health surveys.
So this was a study that was looking at
the relationship between being
overweight or obese And mortality.
The outcome variable here is years of life
loss so bigger bars higher bars
are bad that is increasing your mortality
because you have more years of life lost.
The different colored bars here represent
the age at
which you became overweight or obese.
So the thought being that being overweight
or obese in your twenties that might be
worse than if you became overweight or
obese in your thirties forties.
fifties, sixties, seventies.
It turns out that the relationship between
obesity and
years of life lost is modified by both
race and gender, and
that's what's illustrated in these next
couple of slides.
So if you look at white men, and you look
at the relationship, if you're This is 25.
A BMI of 25 would represent overweight.
A BMI of 30 or above would represent
obese.
So basically if you were obese, starting
from an early age.
You know from your twenties or your
thirties or even forties or fifties.
If your obese.
And you're a white man, you are losing
years off your life and, you know,
the worse the obesity the higher this
goes, where you're really morbidly obese,
you're losing a huge number of years off
of life.
If you then turn to look at white women,
however, you'll notice that the
relationship's a little bit different.
So, indeed Women, white women are losing
years off the off of life,
related to being overweight or obese.
But the curve here is not quite as steep,
it's not quite as bad if you're
a white woman to be morbidly obese in
terms of mortality.
And the relationship looks just a little
bit different.
And being, starting the overweight in your
twenties versus your forties in
women doesn't seem to make as much of a
difference as it does, did in white men.
If you look at black men which, what's
interesting is that In fact,.
If you're in your seventies, and
you become overweight or obese, the bars
are below the zero line.
That means you're actually increasing your
life expectancy.
But if you're overweight or obese up in
the, you know, higher ranges.
The years of life lost for a black man who
had been overweight or
obese since their twenties is huge.
It's up here, like 20 years of life lost.
So a much steeper increase here.
And a little bit of different relationship
with depending on when you get.
Obesity or overweight occur.
Then if you look at black women, the
pattern again is very different, and
there's not much increase in years of life
lost until you get to the really,
really high levels of obesity.
So very different relationships Depending
on both gender and race, so
we would say that both gender and race
modify the effect of obesity on mortality.
And equivalently you could also say that
the interaction between race and
BMI is significant and also the
interaction between gender and
BMI is significant, so the impact of BMI.
On mortality differs by race and gender.
Just a couple more examples just to
illustrate and
make sure you're on the same page here.
So here's another example where we were,
we're looking at,
what we're looking at in these graphics is
whether or
not that your education level, this is
quintiles of education.
Whether or not that affects when you get
diagnosed with breast cancer, whether or
not you're diagnosed when the tumor is
local, regional, or
in the black bars here are distant.
So obviously,
with any cancer you want to be diagnosed
when the cancer is still local.
It hasn't spread.
So if we look at white women And we look
across Quintiles of Education.
You can see that as you go up in the
quintiles,
you tend to have more cancers diagnosed
locally,
you tend to have fewer cancers diagnosed
at a distant, a metasticed stage.
So interestingly however, If you look at
black women,
that relationship doesn't seem to be the
true so as you go across quintiles of
education there's not much of a change in
local diagnosis versus distant diagnosis.
I don't know why that would be but for
some reason the relationship between
education and
stage of cancer diagnosis is different
between white and, and black women.
So we would say that there's an
interaction here between race It's
and education.
And a final example, the typical things
that you're going to see that tend to be
effect modifiers or interacting variables.
Age might be one of them, race.
Gender these are sort of the big ones for
women pre-menopausal verses
post-menopausal often makes a difference
so this is an example we're looking at
colon cancer the relationship between
obesity and colon cancer
is different in pre-menopausal women then
in post-menopausal women so I'll just.
going to zero in on some things on the
chart.
So if you look among pre-menopausal women.
Then obesity increases.
About doubles your risk of colon or colon
rectal cancers.
That's for pre-menopausal women.
However if you look in post menopausal
women it's the opposite.
the, for post-menopausal women being obese
is actually slightly protective.
It doesn't quite reach statistical
significance.
But it's a slightly.
Protected or at least unrelated to colon
cancer in post-menopausal women.
Interestingly if you look at breast cancer
it's the opposite.
So for breast cancer obesity is a risk
factor for
breast cancer in postmenopausal women, but
not in pre-menopausal women.
So these are the types of things that are
typical interacting or
effect modifying variables.