In this next module, I'm going to talk
about variable selection in a case
where you're trying to identify multiple
important causal predictors of an outcome.
And there's a really nice discussion of
this in Biddinghoff textbook,
it's very short, so I'd recommend reading
it there as well.
So the ideal situation when we're doing a
medical study is we would like to
have a primary hypothesis of interest from
the get-go.
You, you design a study around that, and
you get your data, you analyze your data.
By doing so, and pre-specifying everything
ahead of time,
having one main hypothesis, you control
your type one error.
Of course the reality is, we often do
that, but in the course of doing
a particular study, we collect a whole
bunch of data that's interesting data and
worth mining for additional information.
But that changes the situation for model
building now because now there's not
necessarily a single predictor of
interest.
We might be mining our data set just to
say,
well what are other predictors of the
outcome.
So we might be interested in multiple
important predictors that might have
a causal relationship with our outcome.
And that's perfectly fine to do.
It's worth doing what we call secondary
analysis like these.
Because we're getting the data are there
and
we want to mine that for useful
information.
However, variable selection in this
scenario becomes much much trickier.
It's a bit of an art.
There are multiple potential approaches
that you can take and
different people will have slightly
different preferences for how to do this.
A lot of it will be guided by some kind of
clinical judgement as well.
So, variable selection is,
as you're going to see in a minute, is
going to be more decision points.
And, when you're doing these types of
analyses where you're screening for
a number of po, potential important
predictors,
you're obviously increasing your risk of a
type one error.
Now, it's generally not recommended that
you somehow try to do some kind of
p value correction in this context.
And that's simply because there's so
many decision points in the model building
process here that it's actually really
hard to say what the true p value is or
the true p value level is.
So hard to attach a, p value adjustment
here.
Rather than doing that we tent to just
want to interpret the results cautiously.
You have to tell your reader that this
came from a data set that was set up
to test something else and that you're
mining it for additional information and
therefore that things have to be taken
with a grain of salt.
That there is going to be some chance
findings expected to arise.
So I thought the easiest way to illustrate
this would be just to
go through an actual example.
So this was a data set, that I was
involved in.
A paper I was involved in a number of
years ago.
You can see that I do a lot of data
analysis on stress factors in runners.
because, I used to be a competitive
runner, and
this is a different data set actually than
I talked about with stress fractures and
runners last week, this was a data set
that came from a randomized trial.
So we have randomized women runners.
To take hormonal contraception or not.
To see if that had an effect on bone
density and stress fractures.
But then after we answered that question,
and wrote up the main paper, here we had
sitting this great data set with all of
these variables that we had collected and
we wanted to say, well, can we identify
other risk factors for stress fractures?
So, this is the secondary analysis from a
randomized trial.
You can see it's a different data set
because my N now is 125.
These were college age women, so
older than the data set that I talked
about last week.
We had a number of predictors that had
previously been linked to
stress fractures, or
that we had some reason to believe would
be linked to stress fractures.
So we had measure bone density on the
women, menstrual function, calcium intake,
injury history, training Body size and
composition age,
all things that we suspected, could be
factors in stress fracture development.
So how do we actually do this model
building this variable selection?
So what's typically done in this kind of
scenario.
Is that we want to screen through a number
of potential predictors, and
a way to do that is to do univariate
analyses, so
to run each predictor with the outcome in
a separate logistic regression model.
Or in this case, we actually have
prospective data, so
Cox regression was run, but it's actually
pretty much the same procedure.
So if we had a logistic model for
stress fracture we would do one variable
at a time.
So here's a predictor that I think might
be related, I put that in a model,
I run a unit variant model.
That gives me a sense, just sort of a
screening of which ones are related to
stress fractures, in the unit area way.
Now there was a little bit of extra detail
here.
Since these data came from a randomized
trial,
we decided that it was important in all
models to take that into account.
So even in the quote unquote unit area
models, or only looking at one potential
predictor at a time, we also had adjusted
for the site in the clinical trial,
which Would be dummy coded as well as what
randomization group the women had been in
just in case there were any effects of
those two things throughout the trial.
So there's a few other things lurking in
the model,
but it pretty much we're just looking at
one predictor at a time.
Those actually didn't have much of an
effect on the estimates.
So here is a variable screen, here's all
the results of the predictors
test one at a time with just these other
two randomized trial details in the model.
So you can see that lots of things, lots
of predictors were tested.
There's a whole bunch of things in this
table, okay.
So we had a whole bunch of variables we
wanted in we thought that,
we thought might be relevant.
We wanted to test them out.
One thing that you'll notice is that a lot
of
the variables are highly related to one
another.
So height, weight, body mass index,
percent body fat lean mass.
All these things are measures of body size
and composition.
We've got a bunch of measures about how
long you've been running,
how much you run.
We've got history of fractures number of
menstrual variable menstrual function
variable a whole bunch about bone density
cause had given that mendesa.
We had a lot of bone density and
bone mineral content which is slightly
different than density, we had that.
We had two measurements related to calcium
intake.
So a lot of these are overlapping.
That means one of the first decision
points that's going to need to
be made here is which if this when they're
highly overlapping and
they both seem to be related to fractures.
Or multiple ones seem to be related to
fractures.
Which of these do we carry over and test
in the final model.
Now I'll just remind you that last week I
talked about
principal components analysys.
And one of the advantages of doing a
principal components analysis was that you
might be able to take some of these highly
correlated variables, and
rather than having to just drop some and
ignore some, you could compress them
into a single variable and take that
forward for regression.
So that is another option that wasn't done
here.
Again, just to show you some language from
how these things are written up in papers.
So in the statistical analysis section in
the,
when the, we're describing how the
multi-variable models work.
How the variables were chosen for the
final multi-variable models.
The first thing that's talked about is
just the fact that
we didn't take forward all of the
variables in table one here.
For the multivariate regression model, we
were choosy about it.
So, various, the various indicators of
bone mass basically,
were all highly correlated.
So, we had bone mass and bone density in
their hip,
we had whole body...it's fine, all these
are highly correlated.
Bone density is highly correlated with
content.
So we selected one of them.
We selected whole body bone mineral
content for
our primary multivariate model.
And why did we do that?
There's some justification.
Notice, this is all just clinical
judgment.
It, there was, first of all, it was
strongly associated with stress fractures.
So we are looking at saying, hey, that
one, it does look like
it has a stronger relation the strongest
relationship with stress fracture.
There were multiple skeletal sites where
stress fractures could occur, so
a whole body bone strength measure might
be the most relevant.
And there's some technical things about
how to
measure bone strength especially when
you're growing, so
there was some reasons for choosing that
one out of the set.
Also, similarly, daily calcium intake and
servings of dairy products were highly
correlated.
We chose dietary calcium intake for the
multivariate model.
Now, if you go back and look at table one,
I'll just highlight here,
if you look at calcium intake and servings
of dairy products.
So calcium intake didn't quite make
statistical significance.
However, servings of dairy products did.
And yet, a judgment was made not based on
the p-value there, but
that dietary calcium is really more
relevant, because that's kind of
what we're after, what we think would be
related to bone density.
So a decision was made to put dietary
calcium forward and
not dairy, without P value shopping.
And finally, lean body mass was so
strongly to bone mineral content that it
was felt that it couldn't be carried
forward, so
it was not carried forward into the
multivariate model.
So there's some choices being made just in
terms among highly correlated variables.
Which ones do we even try out in the
multivariate model And then it's saying
well accordingly here is what we brought
forward for the multivariate model.
age, height, weight, history of stress
fracture, age at menarche,
history of menstrual irregularity.
And, and the ones we just talked about
where,
was, there was some decision point that
had to be made.
And this is along with certain other
variables I don't remember exactly what
those were, I didn't actually do the
analysis here, but
I think out of the ones that you saw in
the earlier table.
Some of them clearly had some relationship
or had, there was some indication of
a relationship with stress fractures,
those were carried forward.
Some clearly were very close to one on the
odds ratio, didn't look at all related.
Those were not carried forward.
And then that's who, what we included in a
multivariate model.
And then we're going to prune some of
those and
only retain some of those from the models.
So what was the decision point there?
So the decision was made to,
that those that were significant at a P of
less than .10 were retained in the model.
Those that had P is greater than .1 were
removed or pruned from the model.
However, there was one variable that's
really relevant to
stress fractures in women, which is a
history of menstrual irregularity.
And, even though P was les, greater than
.1.
A decision was made to keep that in the
multivariate model because the effect
size was actually large and it was
consistent with other studies.
So even though it didn't make statistical
significance in our small study,
we still it was important to keep it on
the model.
So notice how many decision points have
been made here in terms of
the choice of this multivariate model.
And somebody else looking at these data
could have come up with slightly different
choices and definitely could have come up
with a slightly different final model.
But the general procedure of looking at
the univariate analyses and then moving
some of them forward to the multivarieate
anaylysis and then pruning some that
are no longer significant is kind of the
way, the general process that's used.
Here's the resulting multivariate model.
So the things that stuck in the model
again are the P less than .10, were age,
and, and no, this is an interesting point
about presentation of data, but
all of hte relative risks are set up so
they are greater than one.
There was somebody, there was a coauthor
on our page who insisted that
doctors wouldn't understand rate ratios or
risk ratios below one.
They wouldn't understand what that means,
so that we had to make them all above one
by making things like age per year younger
increases your risk.
So the younger you are, the more your risk
is.
I actually don't like that at all, because
I think it's much more natural to
say per year older of age, your risk is
per, your,
your risk is lowered But anyway, this is
what ended up in the paper.
So being younger was protective.
Having a history of stress fractures was
really highly related.
So if you're prone to stress fractures, if
you've already had one,
you're probably much, much, much more
likely to have one in the future.
And these are actually risk ratios, rate
ratios.
So this can be interpreted as a six fold
increase in risk.
The bone density also highly related.
This is per standard deviation lower.
So the lower you are, one state of
deviation lower in bone mineral content.
Where this is associated with a doubling
or tripling of risk.
Dietary calcium didn't quite make
statistical significance.
P is less than 0.10 here.
But having, less calcium in your diet
means more risk.
Age at menarche was significantly related
at p of 0.05.
And then finally this history of menstrual
irregularity.
Notice that, totally not significant but
the effect size is pretty big.
And because it has been pretty well
established in other studies that this is
an association.
We kept this in the model.
Again, many decision points here.
Now I just want to contrast this with, I
actually did an example last week,
essentially, of a multiple important
predictors of variable selection.
When I was talking about principal
components anaylsis.
So I'll just kind of put upon for
principle components analysis here by
showing that the variable selection for
the multivariate model was a heck of a lot
easier in that case.
So just a reminder, I had a different data
set on 91 high school women runners
who had, we had many of the same variables
measured and
one of the outcomes of interest was stress
factor.
Now this was a logistic regression rather
than a Cox regression.
But I, I actually took all of those
multiple measures of
things like body size and composition, and
running performance and
special function and I ran that principal
components analysis
to come up with four components at the end
of the day.
The nice thing about doing it that way is,
the variable selection for
the final logistic regression model was
totally easy.
There was nothing to do really.
Once I have got principle components,
they're uncorrelated with one another.
That means that whether I analyze them by
themselves or whether I analyze them
with other of, other principle components
in the model, I get the same answer.
So, in other words, if I ran this same
regression model with body fat,
in the model and nothing else, I'm
going to get the same beta and
the same p value, essentially, with very
slight change.
If I run body fatness with running
performance in the model and drop body
size and menstrual function, I'm going to
get the same betas and the same P values.
In other words there's really no decision
to be made about which variables
go in the model.
Once I've done principal component
analysis I've already compressed my data I
now have uncorrelated predictors so
I can just put them all in the model and,
and I'm done.
And so it does simplify your life for
variable selection.
I just want to again caution on p value
shopping in this
scenario again many opportunities to go p
value shopping.
You know the more predictors you test of
course we want to test ones that would be
more relevant, But the more you test the
more chances of a type one error.
And you can imagine you know trying lot's
a different combination of models and
trying to optimize the one with the
highest numbers,
Highest number of significant p-values.
Shopping around, just, what is the model
that gives me the best p-values?
That, we don't want to do.
You can see that that wasn't done in the
example I showed you.
And, an automated way to try as many
models as possible until you find the one
with the highest number of significant
p-values is to use those automatic
selection procedures, which we've talked
about before backwards forwards,
step wise, automated regression with the
computer.
And it's probably better to avoid those
for this particular situation.
And there's again, lots of opportunities
for p value shopping,
you want to be very careful that you're
not doing p value shopping.