In this next module, I'm going to talk
about mediating variables.
So a mediating variable, a mediator looks
a lot like a confounder.
Like a confounder it has to be associated,
both with the protector and
the outcome variables.
Unlike a confounder however, it is on the
causal pathway between the predictor and
the outcome.
So it helps to explain why a predictor and
an outcome are causally related.
So that's different than a confounder
because it's on the causal pathway.
I just want to point out though that
mediation and confounding, mediator
variables and confounding variables are
actually identical statistically.
The way that we're going to identify them,
what they do statistically is actually the
same.
So we're really only distinguishing these,
on conceptual grounds.
Statistically, they're going to look the
same, but because we know more information
about the problem, we know about the
biology or about the clinical problem.
We can make a judgment call as to whether
or
not one is a confounder versus a mediator.
So for example in the case I gave in an
earlier module about lung cancer and
drinking and smoking, we decided that
smoking was a confounder.
Smoking is not on a causal pathway between
drinking and lung cancer, so
it's not the case that if you drink, that
causes you to smoke more.
And that's, then smoking increases your
risk of lung cancer.
So there's no causal relationship between
drinking and smoking.
Smoking just happens to be related to both
of them,
there's in fact no causal relationship
between drinking and
lung cancer, the relationship we're seeing
is purely driven by smoking.
So that would be an example of a
confounder.
An example of a mediator would be if you
look at the relationship between
obesity and heart disease, and you look at
the mediating variable of blood pressure.
So obesity probably is causatively related
to heart disease.
Disease and then the variable blood
pressure might be
a mediator of that relationship, if it
might be one of the things that
explains why obesity raises your risk of
heart disease.
So obesity causes you to have higher blood
pressure.
Higher blood pressure puts strain on your
heart and
increases your risk of heart disease.
So, that would be considered a mediating
variable rather than a confounder.
It's not causing a spurious association to
appear between obesity and heart disease.
Rather obesity does have a causal
relationship, is just one of
the ways that the relationship between
obesity and heart disease is mediated.
It's one of the things that explains it.
But again statistically, you're going to
look the same.
So it's all conceptually how we
distinguish those.
I'm just going to give you a couple of
examples of what mediation looks like,
and say a little bit about how we identify
mediators statistically.
So when people are talking of mediation,
they love to draw these nice little path
diagrams and little flow diagrams.
So I think those are nice, I always like a
good picture.
So here's a, an example I picked out of a
recent article on the literature, and
was looking at physical activity as the
predictor, and eating self-regulation,
how well can you self-regulate in terms of
eating as the outcome variable.
And if you look at physical activity,
people who exercise a lot and
you look at people's ability to self
regulate their eating,
in fact you do find an association between
that predictor and that outcome.
And they do appear to be causally related,
not really through confounders but
one seems to have effects on the other.
Now, there might be a lot of.
There are variables here though, that help
to explain how physical
activity regulates eating, and that's what
this picture is showing here.
I'm going to just put this in statistical
terms for a minute.
So, here, look at this, this arrow right
here, which says the total effects path C.
So, this is, image that I were to was to
try to relate physical activity and
eating self-regulation with some kind of
statistical test.
Let's say I did a regression, and I get,
I'm going to just make up a,
you know, a regression coefficient here
for hypothetical.
Just to make it easy, a number that we can
deal with, but imagine that you.
You run a regression.
Physical activity's the predictor.
Eating self-regulation is the outcome.
And the beta coefficient from that
regression comes out to be 1.0,
showing there is a statistically
significant relationship here.
That's the magnitude 1.0.
So we then though, that's our simple
model.
We then go and say well maybe there are
things that explain the relationship.
Mediate the relationship between physical
activity and eating self-regulation and
here's an example.
Perhaps you exercise a lot you improve
your body image which in
turn help you to regulate your eating
better.
So let's say I then add to my regression
model a variable for
this dysfunctional body image investment,
body image basically.
And let's say the beta for that comes out
to be 0.25.
And when I put that in the model, my beta
of the direct effect of between
physical activity and self regulation goes
down, say it goes down to 0.75.
You notice how this body image is kind of
looking like a confounder.
Because when I put it in the model, the
relationship between physical activity and
eating self-regulation gets extenuated.
But it's not a confounder, it's just
explaining some of this relationship.
And, then, let's say I add depressive mood
to the model,
so if you exercise more that improves your
mood that pretty well established and
maybe if you have better mood.
That helps to improve your eating self
regulation.
So let's say I've dumped depressive mood
now, as another co variable in the model.
I'm not saying the beta coefficient for
that, also comes out to 0.25,
and my relationship between physical
activity and
eating self regulation goes down even
more.
Let's say I'm making this you know,
very simple numbers, but lets say it goes
to 0.5.
So essentially when I adjust for mood and
body image, I've cut down, I attenuated
my data coefficient between physical
activity and eating self regulation.
To my 50%.
That leftover effect of physical activity
we're going to call the direct effect.
So I'm going to put this on this dotted
line.
That's maybe the, what we, we, maybe we
have, accounted for
all possible mediators.
But when we account for the mediators we
know about, that's what's left over.
So we would call these the direct effects
of physical activity
on eating self-regulation.
So somehow physical activity directly
affects your eating.
You can imagine exercise certainly has
very profound impact on appetite hormones.
So that might be sort of a direct effect
on eating self regulation or
something of that nature.
But when we put these other things in the
model, we explain away some of
the relationship between physical activity
and eating self regulation.
Because these other variables are
mediators.
So the rest of the relationship between
physical activity and
eating self regulation, was driven by the
changes on body image and
the changes on depressive mood.
But depression and body image are not
confounders, because they're just one of
the ways that physical activity is able to
influence eating self regulation.
Just to illustrate one more example of
what mediation looks like, so imagine
we've got a predictor a parental education
that's my X my predictor variable and
my outcome here my Y is the BMI or waist
circumference of the child.
So there's an idea that if you have more
educated parents it does turn out that
they tend to have, children who are less
at risk for obesity.
And you can imagine that there's a number
of ways that,
number of ways that this relationship
might get mediated.
So again you know you can model this and
if you just put physic parental education
into the model, you'll find a big
relationship between parental education
and the child's weight or over weightness.
But if you start adding other things into
the model there is a lot of
things that can explain that relationship.
So for example parents who are more
educated,
they might be more likely to put their
kids in sports, that helps reduce the BMI.
Parents who are more educated might be
more likely to encourage their kids to
eat breakfast, and that might help keep
the BMI low.
They might be less likely to push sugary
drinks and
that keeps the BMI low and so on.
So again, if you adjust for these other
variables, they will
appear to reduce the relationship between
parental education and child BMI.
But in fact, that's because they're on the
causal pathway between those two things,
so that's a mediation.