In this next module, I'll run through a
quick example of the use of
Weibull regression in the literature.
So, this was a study that was looking at
whether or not being either religious or
spiritual have any relationship to the
onset of depression.
And the outcome of this study was the time
to depression, so
they used survival analysis methods.
These are some data from Canada, there was
about 12,000 people.
They were all verified to be not depressed
at baseline in 1994,
and they were followed during 14 years.
And again, the outcome is time to
depression.
They used Weibull proportional hazards
regression model to model the risk
of depression.
And the, they were most interested in
religious attendance and
spirit, spirituality as potential
predictors of whether or
not you would end up getting depressed.
So, I'll just show you the survival
curves.
These survival curves, as you can see,
they're very smooth.
These come out of the Weibull regression
model that they fit.
And this is the survival curves looking at
religious attendance as the predictor.
So, we have survival on the y-axis
starting at 100% because there's nobody
depressed at the beginning.
At baseline everybody was non-depressed.
And it falls off from there.
You can see the scale of the y-axis, it
only goes down to about 75%.
So, by the end of the study, about 20% of
people had become depressed.
You have 80, 80% chance of not being
depressed by then.
This is time in months.
And there is three curves.
So the top, the bottom curve are the
people who do not attend regular religious
services, and you can see that they get
depressed more quickly, so
their survival curve drops off faster.
The ones who occasionally go to religious
services, they're somewhere in the middle.
And the ones who attend monthly or more
are on the top, having the,
the lowest rate of development of
depression.
It isn't a huge effect, but there is some
separation between those curves.
So, they did find an effect here.
They did not find any relationship between
just spirituality in general and
the onset of depression for whatever
reason.
I'll show you the table that they
presented in their paper.
Again, this is based on a Weibull
regression model, as they indicate here.
So, we'll scroll down to the predictor
they cared most about,
which is this frequency of religious
attendance.
And you can see that the reference
category was those who did not attend,
occasionally had a hazard ratio of just a
little below one.
Indicating a tiny bit of protection
against depression and then monthly or
more had a hazard ratio of 0.78.
So, not a huge effect.
But we would say that the rate of
depression was reduced by
22% in those with frequent religious
attendance, and the P value here was 0.01.
The confidence interval does not cross
one.
So, they did find a significant effect
here.
Just for fun, let's look through some of
the other hazard ratios from their model.
The, again, the spirituality variable did
not come out significant, so
they didn't include it in the table here.
But here's all the other things that they
adjusted for, which could be
potential confounders, of course, so they,
they put gender into the model, so
female gender actually had a higher rate
of becoming depressed some other ones,
education, so if you have a college or
university degree that predicted less
depression over time, so that's good.
If you don't have any history of family
depr of depression in the family,
that's protective.
If you've never had any episodes of
depression before,
that's very protective, as you can see
here.
That's a really low hazard ratio.
Perceived social support was also
protective,
having more social support and, perhaps
you attend religious services a lot,
you have some kind of community and
support there.
The other thing that I'll point out is
that they give the additional parameter
for the Weibull model is 1.68, and you can
see that it is statistically significant,
the 95% confidence interval does not cross
one.
So this is indicating that we probably are
better off fitting a Weibull model
than an exponential here because the scale
parameter clearly doesn't look to be wide.
And this is above one, so it's indicating
that depression is increasing.
The rate of depression is increasing
during the study follow up period.
So, this is just an example of Weibull
regression in the literature.