[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to talk
about two probability distributions that
are often used in survival analysis, the
Exponential and the Weibull.
It turns out that survival times often
follow one of those distributions.
So, to build up to talking about the
Exponential and
the Weibull, I'm actually going to start
with the hazard function.
Every probability distribution has a
hazard function and
I think it's easier if we start by
defining the hazard function here And
then I'll show you how that leads to
particular probability density function.
So, the hazard function as I mentioned
earlier,
is the instantaneous incidence rate.
If the probability that if you survive up
to a particular time, event free,
you haven't had the event yet, it's the
probability that you're going to have
the event in the next, instant and
probably the pregnancy data that we've
talked about earlier is a good example of,
for kind of
putting this into words because women can
only get pregnant once in a given month.
So for that pregnancy data we talked about
earlier,
it would be the probability that if a
woman is,
has remained as still not pregnant at the
beginning of a given month,
it's the probability that she's going to
get pregnant within that next month.
So, that's what we mean by a hazard
function.
We can define it mathematically for those
of you who like this kind of case,
it's just saying this is in, the
mathematical terms.
If you like that words though, the
probability that again, if you survive up
until a time t, that you will succumb to
the event in the very next instant.
And lemmie just review some potential
hazard functions.
What might hazard functions look like?
Well, the most obvious one is that maybe
the hazard function would just be
constant over time.
That makes a lot of sense with something
like the pregnancy data where it's
probably the case that a woman's
probability of getting pregnant in
any particular month is pretty constant
from month to month.
So we could say that the hazard function,
and the way I'm going to represent
the hazard function is I'm always going to
right it as h of t.
All that little t is in there to remind
you that the hazard function itself is
a function of t, and it might change over
time.
Now in the instance and when the example
where it's constant over time, then
the hazard function will just be equal to
the same thing, regardless of time.
And, so, it's going to be equal to some
constant, which I'm calling here c.
c stands for constant.
So it could be constant over time, and
that makes a se, sense with a lot of types
of data,
that the hazard rate is roughly the same
from month to month or year to year.
That's the simplest case.
However, you could imagine scenarios where
the hazard function is increasing over
time.
Maybe it's not constant but
it's increasing in some predictable way
over time.
So a very simple function where the hazard
would be increasing over time is,
is c times t.
So this means that the hazard would be a
function of time.
And as time goes up the hazard function
goes up.
A little bit more general than that we
could define hazard function,
which was c, some constant, times time
raised to a power.
If that power was greater than 0, then t,
there's going to be some, you know,
we're multiplying by something greater
than 0, then,
so this is going to be an increasing
function.
And if k is equal to 1, then we would be
back on this c times t.
So I can draw a little picture here, so if
here's time and here's my hazard function,
which is a function of time, yes, we are
equal to the first one, c times t, it's
going to look like that as we go across
time, the hazard function increases.
And we don't have to have it increase so
quietly so steeply, so
the second equation allows us to have
the hazard function increase less steeply
over time something more like that.
You can also imagine in scenarios where
the hazard function
decreases in some predictable ways.
For example if you had a constant but were
dividing by time and
as time got bigger, as you went further in
time, the hazard rate is going to go down.
Or you can again have a more general
equation which has a constant time
raised to some power.
If that power is negative that puts t in
the denominator and
again overtime the hazard function would
be decreasing.
I told another possibility which is often
the case of real data is that
perhaps the hazard function doesn't have a
smooth mathematical function.
So you can some scenario, I'm just making
this up.
But here is time, here is the hazard
function.
There's nothing that says that it has to
follow a nice smooth function.
With real you know,
things in life, perhaps the hazard
function looks something like that,
some weird squiggly thing that's too hard
to define mathematically.
So we're going to see that eventually when
we get to cox regression.
We are going to try to avoid specifying
any particular destination for
the hazard function because of the fact
that often times it doesn't
follow something that we can easily
estimate mathematically.
So just keep that in the back of your
mind.
This week we are talking about parametric
regression,
trying to actually estimate that hazard
function, but eventually we may try to,
want to try to avoid estimating it and,
and giving it any
particular mathematical form and that's
what cox regression does for next week.
Alright, so, I now just kind of want to go
through an example to
show you how How this works.
When the hazard function is constant what
does that tell us about survival times?
For the pregnancy data, we have this
pregnancy data that I
showed you last week, some women who had
sub-frudoil or
sub-frutile they were given some treatment
they were followed over 2 years.
When we look at that data,
we cal, we calculate an average incidence
rate of 10.4% per month.
In other words, about 10.4%of women who
were at
risk of getting pregnant in any given
month, got pregnant.
Now, for the purposes of just making this,
really, a really simple calculation.
What I'm going to say is that we imagine
we have a case where the hazard rate is
a con, a constant.
And, it's equal to .1 at 10% chance per
month, .1 chance of pregnancy per month.
So, if I were to tell you that every woman
has a 10% chance of getting pregnant in
a given month if she, obviously if she's
not already pregnant, and I were to say,
what's the chance that a woman is going to
survive pregnancy free, she's going to
make it to 6 months without becoming
pregnant or you could equivalently ask
what's the chance that she's going to get
pregnant within the first 6 months?
Your instincts looking at this 10% might
be to do the following.
You might say okay well I want to know the
chance she's going to get
pregnant within 6 months so I'm going to
say she has a 10% chance every month.
I'm going to multiply that by 6 and I'm
going to say that her probability of
getting pregnant within 6 months or less
is equal to,
I'm going to say she has a 60% chance of
getting pregnant and therefore her chances
of the pregnancy taking greater than 6
months is equal to 40%.
That would be kind of you're first guess.
That actually wouldn't be quite correct
though and
I'm going to show you that, why, why that
is now.
You can't just multiply like that because
when you multiply like that,
you forget the fact that every month some
women are getting pregnant.
And that changes the denominator, so let
me illustrate that now.
So this again might, might be your first
instinct, but
it would actually not be correct.
So let's just do a little math out here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I want to calculate the probability that a
women gets pregnant within 6 months or
1 minus half the probability that she
survives pregnancy three past 6
months if the hazard rate is a constant
10% per month.
So, I gotta write down the time, the
hazard,
the number of women at risk of getting
pregnant, once you're pregnant already,
you can't, you have no chance of pregnant
again that's why you have been,
within once you're already pregnant, until
of course that baby is born.
And, incident pregnancies.
I am just going to make this little table,
I think it is easier to keep track of
things, and then women left.
Okay, so here we go.
So, first month happens.
Let's start, to make this really easy
we'll start with 100 women.
So we're make, we're going to put whole
numbers to then start with 100 women.
So, at time point one, the first month of
the study, the hazard rate is 10%.
I'm going to write it as a percent to make
this really easy.
The number of women at risk at that point,
time point is 100.
How many are then going to get pregnant?
Well, we start with 100 women, about 10%
are going to get pregnant so
we are expecting about 10 pregnancies that
month.
How many women are then left and are now
at risk of pregnancy?
Only 90, so 100 minus 10.
Time .2, the hazard rate is still 10%.
We have a constant hazard, so everybody
who's not pregnant now still has a 10% of
chance of getting pregnant in month two.
How many women are at risk now?
Only 90, because some already got
pregnant.
This is what I mean about the denominators
changing.
How many incident pregnancies are we
going to expect?
So how many women are going to get
pregnant then roughly in month two?
Well 10% of 90 is 9.
So we're not expecting 10 to get pregnant
in that month.
But 9, because some of the women have
already gotten pregnant.
That leaves 81 women left.
We go to time point 3 again, the hazard is
still 10%,
we have a constant hazard makes the
problem easy the number of women,
at risk is 81, while 10% of 81 is about 8,
we're going to just rounding here for
ease, to make the point, so 81 minus 8
we'll give us that we have 73 women
left who are still at risk of becoming
pregnant,8 more have gotten pregnant.
Time .4, same hazard rate, 73 women at
risk.
How many pregnancies are we then
expecting?
Well, 10% of 73 is about 7, again, I'm
just going to round for simplicity here.
That leaves us with 66 women who are still
not pregnant.
Time .5, 10%, we're at 66 women.
10% of 66 is about 7, I'm rounding again a
little bit so
that's going to leave me with about 59
women
who are not, sorry, 59 women who are not
pregnant.
And I'm going to keep going here [COUGH]
to month six.
10% hazard, 59 women are not pregnant,
about 6 of them will get pregnant,
so about 10%, that leaves me with a
probability of 50,
that leaves me with 53 women who are not
pregnant.
So notice now that the probability of
getting pregnant within 6 months is
not equal to 60%, which might have been
your instinct here.
It's actually only equal to 47%,
because there is a 47 women out of a 100
who got pregnant within 6 months.
So the probability of not getting
pregnant.
If the pregnancy taking greater than 6
months.
That's kind of our trivial probability
here.
It's 53%.
You had a 53% chance of it taking longer
than 6 months here.
So it's a little counterintuitive, you
kind of have to work it out.
But what I've just illustrated for
you is actually why we're on an
exponential distribution when the,
hazard function is constant, we end up on
an exponential distribution and
that's because the denominators every time
are shrinking as I've shown you here.
So, it turns out when the hazard function
is constant, we are on an exponential.
Remember this number the probability of
surviving pregnancy for
any past 6 months is about 53% and I've
rounded a lot here so
this is going to be a very rounded number,
but I'll show you that when we
pretend we're on an exponential, or we say
we're on an exponential and
I use the formulas for an exponential, it
will spit out the same answer.
So it turns out when the, the hazard rate
is constant, we are on an exponential.
Now the exponential distribution is
actually a family of distributions because
the parameter h changes how steep the
curve is.
You can have various steep exponential
curves that drop really fast, or you can
have very shallow exponential curves which
don't drop as fast, and that all
depends on the value of h, how the hazard
rate, how fast events are occurring.
The probability density function for a, an
exponential is the following.
h, your hazard rate, your constant hazard
rate
The exponential function raised to
negative ht, t here being time.
So that's the probability function if you
wanted to say,
what's the probability of having the event
in any particular month?
So for the pregnancy example, if I wanted
to say, what's the probability that
a woman is going to get pregnant in
exactly at, during the 7 month exactly and
that's a funny question to ask but you
know, if she wants to know she is
going to get pregnant during that 7
months, what's the probability of,
of that specific time point being, when
she gets pregnant.
That's what we mean by a probability
density function.
Once we know we are on an exponential,
we can also define a cumulative
distribution function.
So the cumulative distributive function is
a,
a calculated by taking the inner growth
from 0 to t.
So what's the chance on a particular curve
that I, that takes,
so for example what's the chance that it,
that, you know, I'm going to get pregnant.
What's the probability that I'm going to
get pregnant within 6 months?
So we've put he was 6 months here.
I can calculate if I know I'm on an
exponential,
I can figure out that the cumulative
distribution function.
I'm doing out the calculus here for you,
you don't need to do out the calculus, but
for those of you who are curious, I take
the integral from 0 to t,
t being the time that I want to know
about,
when I take that integral I can show that
cumulative distribution function for
an exponential has the general form 1
minuse raised to negative h and
then t plug in whatever time you are
interested in.
So for example, 6 months.
So if you just apply that here.
Remember for this pregnancy data, we said,
well, what's the probability that I get
pregnant within 6 months?
You can just apply the cdf if we know that
the pregnancy is constant at point one,
10% chance per month.
We can just apply the cdf formula here to
get probability,
rather than us having to do out all the
math like I just did on a previous slide.
So if we just apply 1 minus e raise to
negative.
Now the houser right here is point 1 per
month.
And then we have to make sure we enter
time in months which we're going to at
six months.
We would just plug into that formula.
So if I do 1 minus e raise to negative .6.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So when we calculate this out, this turns
out to be right around 45%.
So not exactly what we got before because
of course we
were doing a bunch of rounding there, but
right about that.
So, we had found about 43%, about a 45%
chance of
getting pregnant within 6 months, and then
what we're usually interested in
when we're doing survival analysis is
actually the survival function.
So the survival function is just the area
to the right, what's the chance of,
not getting pregnant within the first 6
months of it happening, after that
instead of that's just going to be 1 minus
the cumulative density function.
So it's easy to just subtract 1 minus the
cdf and
you can show that that's equal to e raised
to the negative ht, so again if we plug-in
to that e raised to the negative 1 times
6, well that's just
going to be 1 minus what we calculated on
the previous page, it's right about 55%.
So again women have, the constant hazard
rate,
is 10% per month, there's a 55% chance of
surviving pregnancy,
free of not getting pregnant within the
first 6 months.
So that's an exponential function, and
just to show you all of
these together the hazard, the probability
density function, the cumulative density
function and the survival function, all as
functions of time.
I've made graphs where we have a constant
hazard of .1,
just to show you what these all look like.
So the hazard function is here in this
upper left hand panel, so
the hazard function is constant over time,
it doesn't change over time.
That translates to a pdf, a probability
density function,
that looks like an exponential, because
we're on an exponential.
It's not a terribly steep one.
It's a rather shallow exponential.
That corresponds to a cumulative density
function that looks like this,
where women are becoming pregnant and you
can see that at 6 months,
you know, not quite half our pregnant yet,
but if we were to keep going we
would expect about 90% of the women to be
pregnant by about two years.
And then, finally the survival probability
is just like a Kaplan Meier curve,
that's what we're trying to estimate when
we do a Kaplan Meier curve.
And you can see that this is the chances
of remaining pregnancy free or
event free and that one again drops.
It's kind of a complement of the cdf.
So this is just to show you that once you
know one of them, if you know the hazard
then you'll know the pdf, the cdf, and the
survival probability.
You can, you can know the functions for
all of them.
When we do parametric regression, what
we're actually going to be estimating.
Our regressions equation is going to be
centered around the hazard function But
often, and what we want to generate is a
survival function, a survival curve.