[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module I'm going to tell you
about GEE modeling, which is
used to analyze correlated data when you
want to do between cluster comparisons,
within cluster comparisons, or both.
So generalized estimating equations are
used to analyze correlated data
including repeated measures data.
Although I would just want to put the
caveat that this module's going to
focus on when we have data at one time
point.
It gets, adds a layer of complexity when
we want to talk about repeated measures so
we won't get into that in this course.
If you're interested in learning more
about GEE for repeated measures,
I'll be teaching that in the Spring
quarter course, in HRP262.
So GEE models basically just build on
generalized linear models, which is what,
something we've talked about throughout
this course.
They build on those generalized linear
models by actually estimating and
accounting for the correlations in the
data.
So let me just walk you back a step here
and remind you of a few things.
So if we go all the way back to regular
old linear regression,
a regular linear regression model looks
something like this.
We have some linear combination of betas
and
predictors that we're using to predict a
continuous, normally distributed outcome.
Now we often don't really pay attention to
it, but there's something lurking in
the model that we're also estimating
beside the betas and the alphas, and
that's the error.
And we need to estimate that in order to
be able to estimate the standard errors,
which of course give us our P-values.
But there's a couple of very important
assumptions about the error term in
linear regression.
So one of the assumptions is that it's
normally distributed.
That is, the error is normally
distributed, we check that by looking at
the distribution of the residuals and
seeing if those are normally distributed.
So that was an assumption of linear
regression, and
the other assumption is that the errors
are independent.
That was another assumption of linear
regression.
So of course in this term,
we violated this assumption of normality
of errors, because we've been
dealing with outcome variables that are
not normally distributed.
So, we got around that by using
generalized linear models,
rather than regular old linear regression.
That general of those generalized linear
models al,
allowed us to deal with non-normal error
terms, non-normal outcomes.
So for example we did logistic regression
for binary outcomes.
And that model looked an awful lot like a
linear regression model.
The right hand side of the equation is
exactly the same, but
we did this transformation.
The logit of our outcome variable and the
generalized linear model
framework allowed us to incorporate
non-normal errors.
GEE goes one step further.
Because it also takes care of, whether the
errors are independent.
We are no longer, with GEE models,
required to have independence of errors.
So it explicitly models the correlation
structure, and
corrects the error terms for the
correlation in the errors.
Just to remind you, the generalized linear
models we've talked about if you,
if your outcome is continuous, you're just
doing a regular linear regression.
You can think of that as a generalized
linear model where the outcome
distribution is normal and you're not
doing any transformation to the outcomes,
so we say that link function is the
identity function.
We talked a lot in this course about how
to analyze categorical outcomes,
that is binomial or multinomial outcomes.
You do a logit transformation for
those, and for count data we talked about
using poisson regression.
GEE models go one step further and add one
additional thing, to the model.
So for example, here's a logistic
regression model but
in the GEE framework we're going to
estimate an additional set of parameters.
And this is the correlation matrix.
We're going to be estimating something
called the correlation matrix.
That's going to reflect the correlation in
our data.
By estimating the correlation matrix,
we can use that then to correct the the
errors.
To correct our standard errors for this
correlation.
If we don't estimate the correlation
matrix and
we don't correct for it, then our standard
errors are going to be, all be off.
If we do estimate it, then we can get the
correct standard errors.
Now, this is some additional parameters
that we're going to have to estimate.
And it turns out that we often don't
really care too much what that
correlation matrix looks like.
We're not necessarily going to report it
in our paper.
We still care about the betas and the
alphas, but we need to
estimate this correlation matrix in order
to get the correct standard errors.
That's the key here.
We may not be doing anything in terms of
reporting that correlation matrix in
our paper, although we'll look at some
today.
But it's just I, explicitly correcting for
these correlation.
So let me just give you an example of a
very simple correlation matrix.
What do I mean by this?
So, remember we had some data of a
hypothetical trial one,
which was, people were treated in one eye
with a treatment, an active drug, and
in the other eye with a placebo.
And I actually ran the correlation matrix
to see, is eye1 and
eye2, say, left eye and right eye within a
person, are those correlated?
And indeed, we did have a significant
correlation here, as you would expect.
Eyes are correlated within a person.
So this is the correlation matrix.
That's all we mean by a correlation
matrix.
Now, this is a very simple correlation
matrix, but
that's all we're trying to estimate in
gene, in GEE models.
So it's going to be easy when we have a
simple one like this.
You can imagine that if you're, you have a
more complicated situation like,
you of course can't have more than two
eyes on a person.
But if somehow we were talking about
aliens and
you can have four eyes within an alien,
you, you know, then you'd have four cor,
you know, you'd have a four by four
matrix.
And the more things that are correlated,
the bigger, you know, that matrix can get.
If you had four time points, you'd have a
four by four matrix.
So that means there's going to be a lot
more things to estimate if you
want to estimate each one of these
correlation coefficients.
So that's what we're going to be doing.
We're going to estimate this correlation
matrix through GEE.
I just want to point out quickly that
generalized linear models
worked by using something called maximum
likelihood estimation,
that we've talked about in this course.
It turns out that if you have correlated
data, remember, for
maximum likelihood estimation, we've had
to build a likelihood function.
And that was, where we multiplied together
a bunch of probabilities.
So for example in logistic regression,
here's the probability that a particular
person gets the disease.
Here's the prob, probability that somebody
doesn't get the disease.
And we multiply those probabilities
together.
The fact that we multiply those
probabilities together mean that we were
assuming that those observations were
independent of one another.
With correlated data it gets really messy
to specify this probability distribution.
Can be very complicated when some of your
observations are correlated with one
another, it's too hard to specify in the
maximum likelihood framework.
But the quasi-likelihood estimation method
only requires that you
specify the relationship between the
outcome mean and the covariate.
So the mean of the outcome and your beta
coefficient, and
the relationship between the outcome mean
and the, and the variance.
So you don't have to specify the whole
complex distribution, you just have to
say what's the relationship between the
mean and the variance.
So for a Poisson, for example, the mean
and the variance would be equal.
So it has many of the advantages of
maximum likelihood estimation, but
it doesn't require all of the assumptions.
So that's what actually used here.
The actual mechanics of generalized
estimating equations.
What's happening behind the scenes, is
basically that
the computer is just fitting a regular old
logistic regression or
whatever type of model you're using,
Poisson regression, linear regression.
It's fitting the as if to start with
without doing anything to account for
the correlation.
Assuming the observations are independent,
it starts there.
The next things that, that it does is it
calculates all of the residuals.
So remember residuals are just a person's
observed value minus their
predicted value from the model and
usually it, that residual is transformed
into something, kind of z score.
So those residuals represent the errors.
So it uses, the computer's using the
residuals to pick out what actually is
the correlation structure.
Now, if the residuals are independent,
that means we are,
we have independent data.
If the residuals are not independent, what
is the structure of the correlation?
What are the correlation coefficients?
And it comes up with some kind of working
correlation matrix from these residuals.
This is an iterative process, though, so
then it takes that working correlation
matrix, it runs the the model again,
this time accounting for this, cor, these
correlations.
Refits the regression coefficients,
correcting for
the correlations, then it recalculates the
residuals based on this new model.
And there may still be some unaccounted
for
correlation that it's picking up in the
residual.
So it reestimates the working correlation
matrix, reruns the model, recalculates
the residuals, and walks through this
until you get some kind of convergence.
You converge upon a particular working
correlation matrix.
Again, this correlation matrix is really
just a nuisance variable.
We have to estimate it in order to get the
right standard errors here, but
it's not something that we usually care
about.
It's just kind of a nuisance variable that
we have to estimate.
The computer, of course, is going to do
all this for you behind the scenes.
Now one of the things that you need to
know about GEE models is that you actually
have to specify a correlation structure up
front, when you ask to run these models.
The computer needs some kind of framework
of the structure of
the correlation matrix.
Let me just give you an example of what I
mean by that.
A very simple correlation matrix,
imagine I'm going to do something where we
have three time points.
So if you measured an outcome like bone
density at
three different time points you can build
a correlation matrix.
So this would be a person's bone density,
how does it correlate with their bone
density.
How did the bone density at time 1
correlate to the bone density at time 2,
for example.
Of course time 1 is going to correlate
perfectly with itself.
But maybe time 1 and time 2 have a
correlation of 0.95.
And time 1 and time 3 have a correlation
of 0.92.
And 2 and 3 have a correlation of 0.93.
I'm just making these up.
And the correlation matrix is going to be
a, the same across the diagonal.
So, there's a couple of choices you have
for
this, for estimating this correlation
matrix.
A couple of different structures.
So you could actually try to estimate all
of
the individual correlation coefficients.
And you might think, well, why don't we
always do that, right?
That seems perfect.
We just actually estimate the individual
correlation coefficients.
That is what we would call an unstructured
correlation structure,
because you're estimating everything
separately.
The problem with that is, well, for three
time points, or
three, you know, whatever is correlated
here.
It's fine probably,
because there's only three correlation
coefficients that you have to estimate.
But imagine if I had a four-by-four matri,
then it's going to be
four choose two correlation coefficients
that have to be estimated.
If I have a five-by-five correlation
matrix that's going to be five choose two.
All of a sudden, you're going to have too
many parameters to estimate,
and so you're actually not going to be
able to estimate all of those parameters
separately unless you have, you know, just
a huge data set.
So, there are ways to kind of cheat that
and
not have to estimate all of those
separately.
You don't want to use up all your degrees
of freedom on this.
So here's another possibility you could
do.
It's called an exchangeable correlation
matrix.
This is the simplest.
Well, you could just say, well, I know
there's some correlation.
It's not zero.
What, this is what it would look like if
our time points were independent,
if our outcomes were independent.
We'd get, the correlations would all be
zero.
Okay.
That's what we call
the independence correlation structure.
But if we know we have correlation, we
might just say well,
I'm going to assume that all the
correlation coefficients are the same.
So, eh, for the bone density one, we are
saying you know,
they were all pretty close.
And maybe we'll just call it 0.94 for all
of them, close enough.
We're going to estimate a single
correlation coefficient for
all of, of the correlations.
This is what we call an exchangeable
structure.
And that's the one that's mostly commonly
used in the situation where you
have data at one time but not repeated
measures.
And you just have some kind of clustering
in the data.
There's no natural ordering.
And so there's no, you know,
and we probably don't want to estimate
each one separately.
So often, exchangeable is fine.
You do a lot better by saying that there's
some correlation than that there's none.
And so even if we don't get all the
correlation coefficients right,
you do pretty well there.
There are some other choices which I'll go
through.
So, independent means that all the
correlations are zero or
you assume that they're all zero.
Exchangeable means you just estimate one
single correlation coefficient.
That's beneficial because you only use up
one degree of freedom.
Unstructured says you estimate them all,
that might be too costly in tems of
degrees of freedom.
And then these last two are pertinent to
repeated measures data, primarily.
I'll just walk through them quickly, just
to show you that they're all,
there are these, different choices.
And basically, at the end of the day,
we're looking for the simplest structure.
Use up the fewest degrees of freedom that,
that does well in our data.
It turns out, actually, for GEE models,
that if you get the correlation structure
wrong, you don't do too badly,
as long as you're choosing something
called robust standard errors.
The robust standard errors are robust
against misspecifications of
the correlation structure.
So that even though you have to specify it
up front, if you get it wrong, uyh,
you probably, it probably is not going to
be too big of a deal.
All right, so, different correlation
structures.
So this is the independence correlation
structure.
That means that all of the outcomes are
independent.
So that one's easy.
That they're all set to 0.
Clearly, we're talking about,
this week, about situations where we don't
have independence.
So this is what we would need in order to
be able to do regular linear regression or
regular logistic regression.
Presumably, we don't have this if we're
turning to GEE models.
I mentioned the exchangeable correlation
matrix.
Whatever, however many time points or
however many correlated things you have
you're going to be estimating just one
correlation coefficient for all of them.
Well again, that does pretty well because
you're not assuming they're zero,
which is what, which is definitely
problematic.
But as long as they're all kind of similar
or
there's no real pattern to them, you can
do pretty well by just accounting for
the fact that there is some correlation as
opposed to saying there's none.
And it doesn't use up too many degrees of
freedom, so
this is often used for, if you've got data
at one time point.
Like, you have siblings you're looking at,
or two eyes in a person, or case control,
match case control, that is, you're not
talking about repeated measures.
This often suffices.
Unstructured estimates all of the
correlations separately.
If you get four four by four matrix, that
means you're going to have to
estimate four choose two or six
correlations separately.
You can see that if was a bigger matrix,
which it often can be,
you can start eating up degrees of freedom
really fast.
Just to point out that there are other
structures that you can come up with.
Autoregressive is something where this is
specifically really for
repeated-measures data if you're thinking
of the t1 through t4 as four time points.
So again, bone density, measure of the
same person at four time points,
you can still get away with only
estimating one parameter here.
But you raise, you square it and then cube
it.
You raise it to different powers so that
as you go further and
further apart in time, there's less and
less correlation.
That makes sense for
repeated measures because there's some
kind of natural ordering of things.
It doesn't usually make as much sense for
just cluster data at the same time point.
M-dependent is similar to autoregressive,
except rather than taking squares or
cubes, you're just estimating, a single
correlation coefficient for,
time points that are one time point away.
A different one for time points that are
two time points away, and, and, and so on.
So that saves you, again, some degrees of
freedom, but
allows you a little more flexibility than
the autoregressive.