In this next module, I'm going to give you
some mathematical details about two of
the hypothesis tests that you can get out
of logistic regression.
So in logistic regression, the hypotheses
that we might be testing, we might want to
test whether or not an individual beta for
one predictor is significant or not.
That will tell us if
that particular predictor has an
independent relationship with the outcome.
That's one kind of test that we can do.
A second kind of test that we can do is
what's called a global test.
We can look at a set of betas at once and
say whether or not that group of betas,
if any of them, have a relationship with
the outcome variable.
So the null hypothesis for the global test
will be that all the betas are equal to
zero, and if we reject that one, that will
just tell us that at least one of
the betas is predictive, has some
relationship with the outcome.
So I'm going to turn to the first of those
tests first,
which is just something very simple called
the Wald test.
So, the Wald test is going to test the
null hypothesis that a single beta,
call it beta 1, is equal to 0.
And it's very, very straightforward,
because we're just going to take
the beta that we estimated, which we can
get right out of our computer output, and
divide it by the standard error.
I'm not going to make you calculate the
standard error by hand again.
The computer will calculate the standard
error for that beta.
Beta divided by its standard error is a
z-score.
If that z is significant, than that, and
you can reject the null hypothesis, that
tells you that, that particular predictor
has a relationship with the outcome.
The null value of course here, is that
beta is 0.
If there's no association between the
predictor and
the outcome, then the slope will be 0.
In other words, that beta will be 0.
So that's all the Wald test is,
beta divided by the standard error follows
the z-score.
That's, that's it.
Sometimes you'll see,
in some computer outputs, that you will
actually see it as a Wald chi-squared.
All this is is, to avoid negatives, you
can square the z-score, and
you end up with a chi-square with 1 degree
of freedom.
But its no different then just squaring
what we just calcuated and
that of course also comes with the same
p-value.
Again, most of the time you're not
going to be doing this by hand,
the computer will actually calculate the
z-score or the chi-squared for you,
and will give you the p-value.
But that's where that individual p-value
comes from.
Just to give an example here.
Going back to the example I used in the
earlier module that cardiovascular disease
and age.
This was a simple 2 by 2 table.
I can take those values and plug them into
a logistic regression in my computer, and
here's the output that I got.
So, we saw in the last module how to
actually get the betas and the alphas.
So, in this case SAS has estimated for me,
using maximum likelihood estimation,
has estimated the value of the intercept
and age.
The computer has also given me the
standard error.
And I mentioned before that the standard
error falls right off
the second derivative of the likelihood
function.
So that comes out sort of automatically.
We get the standard errors.
If I divide, say the beta, 2.09, by its
standard error 0.5,
I get a value of about 4.
Well, that's the z-score, which we know is
going to be highly significant.
If I square that value of 4, I get a value
of about 16.
That's also going to be highly
significant.
So clearly we, age is very significantly
related to cardiovascular disease.
And very simple.
Beta divided by standard error gives you
this statistic.
Notice that if I go back to the original
two by two table, and
calculate the p-value for an odds ratio in
the way that I told you earlier in
the course, which is just to calculate the
natural log of the odds ratio and
compare that to its standard error, which
is just this 1 over a, plus 1 over b,
plus 1 over c, plus 1 over d, square
rooted.
That follows a z-distribution.
When I calculate that out from the,
directly from the 2 by 2 table here,
I get a z-value of 3.96.
Well, guess what, if you square the 3.96,
you end up with the,
Wald chi-square value.
So the logistic regression here isn't
doing anything more than we
could already do from a 2 by 2 table.
Of course, we're going to want to
eventually add more predictors to the
model.
The next test that I'm going to talk about
is what's called the likelihood
ratio test.
And this is testing the global hypothesis,
the global null hypothesis that all,
a bunch of betas, a set of betas, are all
equal to 0.
So if you reject the likelihood ratio
test, that will
tell you that at least one of the betas is
significantly related to the outcome,
that at least one of them is predictive.
It doesn't necessarily tell you which one,
but
it tells you that a group of betas is
significant or not.
So that's what the likely aim of the
likelihood ratio test is.
And the mechanics of it hearken back to
something I
talked about in the last module,
which was that we can actually calculate
the value of the likelihood function.
The actual probability of our data at its
most at the most likely value for
the parameters.
We can plug those parameters back in and
actually get a, a numerical value, a
probability, for the likelihood function.
And that, we are going to be doing that in
order to perform the likelihood
ratio test.
The way a likelihood ratio test is, again,
works, is,
again we're comparing a group of betas.
So we're going to have what's called a
reduced model and
we're going to have what's called a full
model.
The reduced model will have k parameters
in it, so
maybe it looks like the logit is equal to
alpha plus beta 1 plus beta 2.
The full model will contain all the
parameters that
are in the reduced model plus some
additional ones.
So maybe that looks like logit is equal to
alpha plus beta1 plus
beta2 plus beta3 plus beta4.
And if we do the likelihood ratio test
comparing this reduced and
full model, that will tell us whether
adding 3 and
4 to the model adds anything in terms of
predicting our outcome.
If we compare a reduced model with three
parameters in it, as we see here,
as we see here to a, to a full model with
five parameters in it,
then the difference between those two
models is two parameters.
Our likelihood ratio test is going to be a
chi-square with two degrees of freedom.
So we all,
we have a reduced model with k parameters,
a full model with k plus p parameters.
We're going to end up with a chi-squared,
on a chi-squared distribution with
p parameters, p being the difference in
the number of parameters between the two,
the two in this example.
It turns out that if the null hypothesis
is true, if all those betas are equal to
zero, then the negative 2 log of the
likelihood for
the reduced model, that value of the
likelihood, that probability, divided by
the likelihood for that full model, if you
take the ratio of those two and
then take negative 2 log of that, that
that will follow a chi-squared
distribution with p degrees of freedom if
the null hypothesis is true.
Now, the ratio can be broken down because
the log of a quotient,
of two things divided, is the difference
of logs.
So we can actually take this formula and
make it a little simpler by just realizing
that what we're going to end up with is
negative 2 log of the likelihood of
the reduce model minus negative 2 log of
the likelihood of the full model.
That's the same as the ratio, but it's
easier to calculate, so
we're generally going to just do this as
differences.
That's going to have a chi-square with p
degrees of freedom distribution under
the null hypothesis.
Now I'm going to go through a numerical
example that will illustrate how
the likelihood ratio test works.
So first of all, I just want to start by
showing you that for
that simple 2 by 2 data set, I plug that
into the computer, and
it gives me out automatically something
called the likelihood ratio test.
Notice it says above, testing the global
null hypothesis that beta equals zero.
Well for the very simple example of the 2
by 2 table, the reduced model, so,
SAS automatically gives you a reduced
model where you
have a a model where it only contains the
intercept.
So when you get output from your computer,
that's called the likelihood ratio test.
For the global test, this is testing
whether or
not a model with only the intercept is
different than a model with
all the parameters that you have put into
your, into your model.
So, in this very simple 2 by 2 case, we
only had one beta, and
that was the beta for age.
So, here we are comparing the model with
age to the model without age.
In general, you'll be, the statistic will,
that's automatically calculated, will
compare the model with only the intercept
to the model with all the parameters that
you had put in, all the predictors that
you've put in the model.
So this, in this case, we're only going to
be testing whether or
not beta age is significant is a
significant predictor.
If you had multiple betas you'd be testing
whether that set of betas was significant.
Indeed, we get a chi-square that's very
high here.
The p-value is highly significant, so we
do have evidence that age is predictive.
And we saw that from the individual Wald
test as well.
Let me walk you through the math of how
this works now.
So the Reduced Model in this case is just
the intercept only model.
So what does it mean to fit a model with
only the intercept?
All that that means is that what you're
going to get out at the end of the day is
that alpha will be the log odds of having
the disease in the sample,
not accounting for anything, so just the
marginal odds of getting the disease.
So in the case of that, the cardiovascular
disease example, with age,
we had, these were the 2 by 2 numbers,
just to remind you.
We had 43 people with the disease, and we
had 57 people without the disease.
So the odds of getting the disease
overall, the marginal odds,
not accounting for age, is 43 to 57.
So alpha in this case is just going to be
the natural log of the 43 to 57,
of the odds.
Whatever value that comes out to be, I
think that comes out to be negative 0.28,
so that's what alpha will be in this case.
It relates just directly to the overall
probability,
the overall odds of having the disease.
So that's the reduced model.
We can actually go through the logic of
finding out the,
estimating the, the value for alpha, using
maximum likelihood estimation.
I'm going to just run through this
quickly.
This is what we did in the last module as
well.
But what would the likelihood function for
the reduced model actually be?
Well, for the reduced model, we're not
accounting for age.
There are no betas.
The only thing we have in the model is
alpha.
Everybody just has e raised to alpha.
Everybody who gets the disease, there were
43 of them, has e over 1 plus e.
That's the probability of getting that
disease.
Everybody who doesn't get the disease,
there were 57 of them,
has 1 over 1 plus e.
That's it.
So there's nothing taken to
account except whether or not you have the
disease.
We then take that likelihood function, we
take the log as I've done here,
I'm going to just you're going to just
trust me that that's the correct log, or
you could stop the video and try it on
your own.
We take the log of that function,
we take the derivative of the log
likelihood function, we set it equal to 0.
We solve algebraically to find out that e
raised to alpha is 43 out of 57,
the odds of having the disease, or
0.75, and alpha is the natural log of
that, or negative 0.28.
So we solve and find that alpha is equal
to negative 0.28.
The 0.75, the 43 to 57,
is, again, it's just the marginal odds of
cardiovascular disease.
e raised to alpha gives you the marginal
odds of the disease, and,
if there is nothing else in the model,
that's of the disease in the whole sample.
Now I'm going to take that negative 0.28,
and I'm going to plug it back into that
likelihood function, so that I
can get the actual value of the likelihood
function, the actual probability.
So I'm plugging in the negative 0.28,
actually, what I've plugged in just to
make it easy here was,
I plugged in the 0.75, because that's the
e raised to alpha.
So for those who have the disease,
their probability of getting the disease
was 0.75 divided by 1, 0.75.
We raise that to 43.
Those the probability of not getting the
disease was 1 over 1.75,
there's 57 of them.
We plug that in we get an actual
probability value.
Now notice [LAUGH] that the probability of
having these 43 people having
the disease and these other 47 people not
have the disease, that exact probability,
because there's many, many possible
outcomes here, it's really, really small.
It comes out to be 2.1 times 10 to the
negative 30.
That's a tiny, tiny probabilty.
But that's the probability at the alpha
value that's most likely.
There is so many out, possible outcomes
here,
that the highest possible probability is
still a really small probability.
Just keep that in the back of your mind.
But that's the actual value of the
likelihood.
That's the probability of our data with
the most likely alpha in in it.
Now what about the likelihood value of the
full model here?
So, remember, all that the full model has
in this case is
just an additional beta accounting for,
you're either older or you're younger.
And we already solved for that beta in the
earlier module.
We solved for alpha and beta in the
earlier module for that particular model.
And it turns out that we solved and
found that e raised to alpha plus beta,
that was equal to 21 over 6.
So that I'm just plugging in to
the likelihood that we saw in the earlier
module.
I'm plugging in the value that we saw for
e alpha and e beta.
When I plug in e alpha plus beta or e
alpha for
those who are, who don't have, or who
aren't older, they just get e alpha.
I plug in the rest, you know, these were
the, the values of the 2 by 2 tables.
So I'm just plugging in the most likely
values for
alpha beta into the likelihood function.
And I can actually solve out the actual
value of that likelihood function.
So when I solve that out,
it comes out to be again, a really, really
small probability.
The probability of me seeing exactly the
constellation of events that I saw in
my sample is small, but this,
notice, that this probability is times 10
to the negative 26.
It is higher than the probability that we
got from the reduced model.
And that makes sense,
because age does have something to do with
cardiovascular disease.
So when we account for age in our model,
we are doing better at predicting who gets
cardiovascular disease and who doesn't.
So the probability of our data goes up
when we account for age.
Now, the question for the likelihood ratio
test is, does our
probability go up enough when we add age
or whatever the betas are to the model?
Does it go up enough that it's worth
keeping age in the model?
Have we budged our probability enough?
When you go from the reduced model to the
full model,
the likelihood value will always get
bigger.
But does it get bigger by enough that it's
worth keeping, say, age in the model?
So the likelihood ratio test, then, we get
by just plugging in.
We do negative 2 log the negative log
likelihood for
the reduced model, minus the negative 2
log likelihood for the full model.
The reduced model always has a smaller
probability, but when you take negative 2
log of a smaller probability, you're going
to end up with a bigger value, so
the reduced, the negative 2 log,
likelihood of
the reduced model will always be bigger
than that for the full model.
So we do reduced minus full to end up with
a positive number.
So I've just plugged in
those probabilities that I calculated on
the earlier slides.
Negative 2 log likelihood for
the intercept only model, minus for the
model that included age.
I get values for the negative 2 log
likelihoods.
Notice I get nice whole values instead of
those really tiny probabilities.
I get 136 minus 117, the difference
between those turns out to be 18.7.
The null hypothesis in this case, because
the only difference between the two
models is the beta for age is, is that,
that the beta age is equal to 0.
Clearly this is a highly significant
chi-square, and
so we can reject the null hypothesis that
beta is equal to 0.
We gain something by adding beta to the
model.
Now notice that the Wald test here give us
a very similar answer to
the likelihood ratio test.
The difference is that the Likelihood
ratio test can be used when we
want to look at groups of betas, rather
than a single beta at a time.
And that's generally where we end up using
the likelihood ratio test.
So just to give you an example of where
the likelihood ratio test would be useful,
take the example that we had in a previous
module which was a 2 by 4 table,
cardiovascular disease and four categories
of age.
If we do a fetal logistic regression model
here, what does the model look like?
So its the logit for cardiovascular
disease, that is equal to, and
we're going to have to dummy code race,
because race is a a categorical variable
with multiple levels.
So we're going to have three betas in the
model, because there are four categories.
The refererence group gets absorbed into
the intercept.
I'm going to make the reference group the
white group
here because they have the lowest risk of
cardiovascular disease.
Then I have to have a beta for black,
Hispanic and other.
So I've dummy coded here.
And I've added race in the model as three
parameters.
Notice that sometimes I might want to know
the effects of individual races,
but sometimes I might just want to know
the effect of race overall as a single,
categorical variable.
The Wald test does not give me p-values
for
ind, the Wald test gives me p-values for
individual races.
But it doesn't give me a p-value overall
for
race as a kind of a cumulative variable.
That's what the likelihood ratio test is
going to give me.
So when I run a model, in this case, I ran
a model that contained the intercept and
the three dummy coded variables for race.
The likelihood ratio test statistic that I
get up at the top of my output is testing
the global null hypothesis that all the
betas in the model are equal to zero.
So it's testing whether or not the beta
for these three groups,
whether or not those are equal to zero,
and those betas represent whether or
not these groups are different than the
reference group.
So we're testing, overall,
are any of those betas, significantly
different than the white group.
That's what the likelihood ratio test will
test when we look at
the reduced model here, the intercept only
model compared with the model with race,
the likelihood ratio statistic comes out
to be 14.
I'm not going to through the math on that
but we're going to believe the computer.
And that's a significant p-value.
We've three degrees of freedom here
because the reduced model has
only the intercept.
The full model has three additional
parameters, so
we're going to have three degrees of
freedom.
So what does this tell us?
This tells us that race, overall, as a
categorical variable has some
predictive power in predicting
cardiovascular disease.
That's giving us a slightly different
piece of information that if
we look at the individual Wald p-values
for the individual race groups.
Those individual p-values tell us
specifically which
racial groups are different than the
reference group.
That those are giving us p-values for each
individual betas.
Sometimes they want to get a p-value over
all for a group of betas.
Typically, with a categorical variable
like that,
the likelihood ratio test will give you
that.