In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about receiver operator
characteristic curves, and their role in
logistic regression.
First of all, just a little historical
background here.
The term receiver operator characteristic
did not arise in
the context of logistic regression, it
actually originated during World War II.
So, people had to interpret radar signal
[INAUDIBLE] blips on the radar screen and
had to determine is this an enemy plane or
is this a friendly plane?
The receiver operator characteristics
referred to
the operator's capability to correctly
distinguish between those two.
And of course it would be very important.
Had to correctly distinguish those.
There will be bad consequences if you
misidentify a friendly plane as
being an enemy plane, you might shoot it
down.
And if you misidentify an enemy plane as
being a friendly plane,
then you might miss an important threat.
So there's a tradeoff between those two.
And that's esse, essentially what's
represented in the ROC curve.
So let me just go through how an ROC curve
works.
An ROC curve has on the y axis,
sensitivity.
And sensitivity is a value that ranges
between 0 % And 100%.
This tells you how good you are at
detecting enemy planes.
So if there's 50 enemy planes out there,
and
you correctly identify 45 of them, then
your sensitivity would be 90%.
This tells you whether or not you're
missing a lot of those enemy planes.
On the x axis, we have specificity.
We actually have 1 - specificity.
That's probably for historical reasons
that is was originally set up that way and
we just kind of kept that as the tradition
so it's actually 1 -
specificity but specificity has to do with
false positives.
So how good are you at not, labeling
friendly planes?
As enemy planes.
In other words, avoiding shooting down
friendly planes.
Of course we want to correctly identify
the friendly planes,
to avoid consequences like shooting them
down.
So if there are 50 friendly planes, and
you misidentify one of them as an enemy
plane, but get 49 of them correct,
then your specificity would be 49 out of
50, or 98%.
And the ROC curve Represents the trade
off between sensitivity and specificity,
so your, you can change your threshold for
how stringent you want to be about false
positives or false negatives.
You might really,
really care about at all costs, avoiding
down shooting friendly planes for example.
Then you would want your specificity to be
really high, but
that would cost you some sensitivity.
You might end up missing Some enemy
planes.
And similarly, for some reason you might
decide that shooting down all the enemy
planes is actually more important than
misidentifying a friendly plane, and
then you would want you sensitivity to be
high at the cost of some specifity.
And that's just charted here, those
different thresholds can be represented.
So depending on where you put your
thresholds,
you're going to get different values on
this curve.
So imagine that you just wanted to make
sure that you caught all enemy planes.
You could just say I'm going to shoot down
all planes that up here on the radar.
You, your sensitivity then Would be 100%
right, but your specificity would be 0 so
1 - the specificity would also be 100%, so
in other words if you just said I'm going
shoot down all planes you would be up here
in this in this curve you'd put a dot
there or you might say, I'm just not going
to shoot down any planes, I'm just going
to pretend everything is friendly And
basically ignore it on the radar screen,
and then I would have perfect specificity
because I wouldn't accidentally shoot
down any friendly planes, but I would miss
all the enemy planes.
So I would have zero sensitivity.
So I'd be over here at the bottom left
hand corner.
1 - 100%, of course 0%.
So those kind of represent the Streams and
then you can chart everything in between.
Now if you were really bad at
differentiating you
would end up with a straight line here
between those two points.
So in other words if you were just
guessing.
You looked at the plane and you were just
going to make a Totally random guess,
this is how you would do in terms of
trading off sensitivity and
specificity, be on this, diagonal line.
What we are hoping for, is that you are
somewhere better than that.
So this would be, I'm going to show you a
really good ROC curve to start with.
So this is somebody who does a really good
job, they, the sensitivity Is
almost always 100%, and the specificity is
almost always 100%.
So you, again, 0% on 1 - spec- specificity
represents perfect specificity.
So if you're really, really good at
distinguishing, you're going to,
you're going to be somewhere where You're
very close, to the y axis there.
Now, if you're not so
good at distinguishing, you're going to
look something more like this.
So maybe just a little better than chance,
but not much better than chance.
And then clearly, there's a big tradeoff
here between sensitivity and specificity.
So we're hoping for a very, fat ROC curve.
That would indicate good accuracy.
Realistically, in medical examples, we
tend to see something more like this.
And that's actually a very good one.
And kind of a more typical one might be
something like this.
We can quantify how good our accuracy is
by actually just
Calculating the area under the curve.
The area under the curve if you have or
if know better than chance would be 50%
that's a diagonal line.
As you do better than that you might get
up to the range of 70,
80 90%, ROC area under the curve.
And we're looking for, you know, in that
range.
Just to illustrate exactly how we
calculate an ROC curve,
I'm going to go back to an example that,
that we looked at earlier, which was, from
data on my Stamford students.
I had asked them whether or not they
considered themselves to be book smart or
street smart as a binary outcome variable.
And I wondered if the amount that would be
related to the amount of
homework that they would do every week.
I had kind of thought that maybe if you
considered yourself book smart you'd
someone who did a lot of homework.
In fact, when we looked at these data, it
turns out to be negative.
So, the more homework you do, the less
likely you are to be,
to consider yourself book smart.
So perhaps, people who think they're book
smart feel like they
can get away with doing less homework,
something like that.
however, this was clearly not
statistically signifigant.
So there is not a strong relationship
here.
Although it's slightly negative in terms
of effect size.
This was the logistic regression equation
that we came out with,
when we estimated alpha and beta.
Again, not statistically significant.
I'm going to now show you the ROC curve
that goes with that model.
So this model contains homework, predictin
whether you or
not you think yourself, to be book smart
or street smart.
You can see that this is a really bad ROC
curve.
We have not done well at classifying
people as one or the other.
because homework doesn't really do a good
job.
It's not that strongly related.
So the, again,
I said that 50%, our area under the curve
means you're no better than chance.
Here, you can see that we have an area
under the curve,
which the computer has calculated for us
to be 60%.
And that's really Pretty poor its not
really much better then chance a that's
not unexpected given that our predictor in
this
logistic regression model a was not
statistically significant.
Now the key here is that we may have we
only have one predictor in this model.
But you can imagine that you might have a
model with many predictors.
And this is trying to quantify, if you use
many predictors at once,
how good does that do in terms of the
accuracy of classifying people.
ROC curves are often used in the context
of prediction models.
Clinical prediction rules, which we're
going to talk about.
Later in this course, and you want to know
how well you're able to
classify patients as having a condition or
not having a condition.
60% not so good.
All right, where does this ROC curve
actually come from?
How do we calculate it?
And you notice what we're doing here is
that we have a Series,
sensitivies and specificities.
And if you've ever dealt with sensitivity
and specificity before,
you prbabably saw it in the context of a
single two by two table.
In other words, you saw something like
there's, the, the true positives.
And then there's the test positives.
And people either have the disease or they
don't and they either test positive or
they don't.
And you could calculate sensitivity and
specificity from this 2 x 2 table.
Well, now we're talking about a series of
sensitivities and specificities.
So how is it that they were having.
Many many sensitivities and specificities.
Well, the idea here is that there are,
that homework is a continuous predictor.
And again, if you had many predictors in
your logistic regression model.
You'd have, you'd have many facets, and
many potential, cutoffs for test positive.
So what does it mean to test positive?
Well, it depends.
I could say I'm going to make test
positive be, you know,
10 hours per week of homework.
That is, if you exceeded 10 hours per week
of homework,
then I'm going to classify you as being
somebody who is likely to be street smart.
Or maybe I'm going to make that set
threshold 30 hours.
In other words,
I'm going to calculate multiple different
sensitivities and specificities.
That's what each of those dots represent,
for, with different cutoffs.
for homework.
And in fact, what we use, since there
might be multiple predictors in the model,
is not actual different cutoffs from
homework, but different cutoffs of
predicted probabilities from the logistic
regression model.
So we're going to do is we're going to
calculate everyone's predicted probability
of being book smart in this case, based on
the regression model And based on their
values of homework, or whatever other
predictors we might decide to throw in,
we're going to calculate everybody's
predictive probabilities, and
then were going to make the cut off for
classifying somebody as book smart for
as, for test positive,
we're going to make the cut off being
above a certain predictive probability.
So maybe if you have a predictive
probability of being book smart Smart of
60%, we're going to call you book smart
and maybe if you
predicted probabilities lower than that
we're going to call you street smart, so
we're going to use different predictive
probabilities as the threshold in order to
get multiple sensitivity and
specificity marks, thats the, the set up
here, that's the idea.
All right, just to remind you, how do we
calculate a person's predictive
probability from the regression model,
where does that come from So, hopefully,
you remember that it looks something like
this.
The person's predicted probability has
this e over 1 + e function.
And in this case, we only have a single
beta in the model.
We're plugging in their homework time.
So a p, a person's predicted probability
is a function of alpha beta, and
the actual amount of homework that they
do.
And again, we could have more betas in, in
a regression model.
In this case, we only have a single.
A single predictor.
So just to give an example,
if you're someone who does 50 hours per
week of homework, that's a lot.
We would plug in that 50.
Where does that p = e over 1 + e, where
does that come from?
I'm going to kind of re-drive it here just
to, to jog your memory so
you remember where this comes from So
I'm going to plug the 50 into my original
logistic regression model,
I come out with the logit for this person
and the predicted logit is 0.17.
I don't think in logits, you probably
don't either's, so
we'll going to go a little further, we're
going to exponentiate both sides of
that equation, which is what I've done
here, E raised to 0.17,
that's going to give me the odds P over 1-
p is of course is the odds,
that's the odds of being book smart, the
predicted odds of being book smart for
that person, and then of course I don't
think an odd either, so
we want to translate that back to a
probability so remember to get back to
a probability we can do odds divided by 1
plus odd, that's essentially what this
term over here represents, this e is the
odds, 1 plus e is 1 plus the odds.
So that turns out to be here 1.19, divided
by 2.19.
So this person has a predicted probability
of being book smart of 54%.
Since they do a lot of homework, we're
actually giving them a relatively low
probability of being book smart because of
the inverse relationship here.
Now, as you know.
That, of my Stanford students in general,
about 80% of them would classify
themselves as book smart.
So our predictive probability of 54% is
low in this context because most Stanford
students actually would be very likely to
classify themselves as book smart.
Something on the order of 80 %.So that's
how to do the predicted probability for
one person.
So now I'm going to actually walk you
through the mechanics of
how to calculate all the points of the ROC
curve.
I actually had a computer do this for me
because it's a little tedious.
So here are the data put in a table form
that the,
the computer used to plot the ROC curve
for me.
So what's happening here?
What we were doing again is that we are
putting the threshold for
test positive at different levels of
predicted probability.
We're going to start with the lowest value
for predicted probability in my data set.
So the person who did the most homework
had a predicted probability based on
the logistic regression model of 52% of
being book smart.
And we can represent this row of data as a
2 x 2 table.
And calculate sensitivity and specificity
accordingly.
So We have, in this data set, we have some
people who are truly book smart, and
some people who are truly not book smart.
This is self classification.
My Stanford students tend to consider
themselves to be book smart, so
I actually had 50 people in this data set.
two people didn't answer, there was
missing data.
But 40 out of 48 considered themselves to
be book smart.
And only eight considered themselves to be
street smart.
So those are my, those are the actual
classifications.
Then, what I'm going to do is I am going
to say,
I'm going to classify everybody who has a
predictive probability of 52% or higher.
I'm going to classify them in my test as
being book smart.
So this is my, my.
[UNKNOWN] now whether or you've met 52% or
you were higher than that.
Well that includes everybody in the data
set.
In other words, I'm just going to classify
everybody as being book smart according to
my test.
That means I am going to get everybody who
is book smart correct.
But I'm also going to get everybody who's
street smart wrong.
That easy to, to see that all that data is
an irrocio in terms of correct since I
got forty book smart people correctly
identified as book smart.
However, on the incorrect column,
all eight street smart have been
mis-classified as book smart
What does that mean in terms of my
sensitivity and specificity?
Well, my sensitivity, of course, is 100%,
40 out of 40.
My specificity, however, is 0%.
I've got zero out of eight of the
negatives correctly classified here.
So, where am I going to put a point on my
ROC curve?
So lets go now over to the ROC curve and
we can see that were going to be at 100%
sensitivity.
And, 0% specificity, but 1 - 0% puts me
at.
100% for one minus specificity so I am in
the upper right hand corner I've
put a point in the upper right hand corner
there.
Now I'm going to change my threshold for
the test positives I'm going to now say
I'm going to make a new rule.
I'm going to go to my data set, the next
highest predicted probability was 54%.
So what if I put the, the threshold, the
cutoff there?
So now I'm going to say everybody who has
a predictive probability of 54% or
higher is going to be Is going to test
positive.
Is going to be classified as book smart.
The actual number of people who are book
smart doesn't change, so
the rows will be the same here.
But now, I'm going to classify some people
as being street smart.
And in fact, I got out of the 40 people
who are book smart,
I'm going to misclassify Two of them.
But this doesn't change the classification
at all for the eight who are street smart.
For whatever reason, they are all having
predictive probabilities above 54%.
So now I make a new 2 x 2 table and
I can calculate sensitivity and
specificity on this new 2 x 2 table.
And the computer's actually here,
has gone through and figured out all these
numbers for me.
So I've now classified 38 correctly.
I've classified 8 of the street smart
people incorrectly and
2 of the book smart people incorrectly,
that gives me a sensitivity of about 95%
38 divided by 40 and then for specificity
I'm still at 0%, so how do
I go represent this on the graph Well now
I'm only ay 95% sensitivity which is here,
this line here, and I'm at still
continuing to be at a zero specificity,
so that would put me here on the graph,
that's the next point on this graph here.
Now, in fact, as I go through and
do this logic For increasing, predicted
probabilities for a little while.
What you'll notice is that, changing that
threshold, I,
I remain at a sensitivity of 95%, and a
specificity of 0% for a while.
That's this straight line here.
They don't change until somewhere in the
middle here,
I haven't presented all the data just to
be able to put this all on one slide, so
somewhere in the middle this changes and
I reach a specificity of about 25% while
I'm still at a sensitivity Of 95%.
And then we keep going through an
increasing of the threshold,
increasing the predictive probability
cutoff.
And that is going to get us this ROC
curve.