All right.
Let me show you something a little bit
more complicated.
The exponential is great because it's the
simplest of them.
But let me show one, one step more
complicated.
So, what if we have a hazard function that
was increasing?
And, what if that hazard function was
increasing in a very specific way?
So, what if the hazard function was equal
to point one, like we had before.
So, say a ten percent chance.
But it was a 10% in the first month, and
then let's say,
their, your chances went up with each
sequent month.
So what I'm doing here, is I'm taking
time, and I'm raising it to .2.
This is just arbitrary.
I'm making this up.
But for whatever reason, imagine that
every month there's a little bit more and
more chance of getting pregnant or
whatever the event is.
I, I can't come up with exactly the
scenario here, but
imagine that these women were in this
study had some treatment that was
slow acting and every month the, their
fertility went up a little bit.
So that's what we could, we could use as
the function here.
Lemmie just show you how this would work
again, kind of the same chart as
before it's a little bit more complicated
now because of the fact that the hazard is
increasing, changing over time, but we can
still do this kind of same calculation.
So imagine that that's the hazard rate and
we are starting with a 100 women and
we're looking for the probabilities for
pregnancy within 6 months.
So the number remaining at risk, this is
those that haven't gotten pregnant yet,
the instance of pregancies.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And women to our left.
So again, let's just go through this
calculation.
Sometimes it's helpful to
write something out like this to really
understand what's going on.
So in the first month, the hazard rate is
10%, the time is one, so
1 raised to .2 is still 1.
And so the hazard rate in the first month
is just 10%.
There were 100 women at risk, so
we're expecting about 10 of them, 10% of
100, to get pregnant.
Means 90 are left, that one's easy.
For 10.2, it's just slightly more
complicated.
Which is 10% times month two raised to
0.2.
Well, 2 raised to 0.2 is 1.14,
that gives a hazard rate that's a little
bit higher it's 11.4% so
we're expecting about 11.4% of the other
women to get pregnant that month.
There are 90 women who are still at risk
of getting pregnant.
Well, 11% of 90 is actually still about
10, so
we're expecting 10 to get pregnant, 80 to
be left.
10.3, we do 3 raised to .2, which is 1.24,
giving us a hazard rate of 12.4%.
We are starting with 80 women; 12.4% of 80
is actually about 10, so
now we'd be down to 70.
Month 4, we do the same calculation.
4 raised to .2 is about 1.31, so it's a
13.1% hazard rate.
So you can see that every month the hazard
rate is increasing.
Now you have a 13% chance, if you're still
pregnancy free,
you have a 13% chance of getting pregnant
in this month.
And we had 70 women left, so 13% of 70 is
just about 9, so then we're down to 61.
In month 5, I'm going to just, to keep
things from getting too slow here,
I'm just going to write down what it comes
out to be.
So, 10%.
5 raised to the 0.2 power, that's going to
give me 13.8% hazard, a little bit higher.
61 women left and
so, therefore 13.8% of 61 is about 8 women
who will get pregnant; 53 are left.
And then for month 6, the rate comes out
to be 14.3% we are starting with 53 women,
14.3% of 53 is about 8, again, I'm
rounding just here to keep things simple.
We would then be left with about 45 women.
So that means that 45 women are left who
haven't got pregnant,
that means 55 have gotten pregnant So
the probability of pregnancy within 6
months is now about 55%.
It is higher because every month there was
a little bit more chance of
getting pregnant.
But the probability of not getting
pregnant within 6 months is 45%.
And what I just illustrated for you is
something called the Weibull distribution.
So if you have a hazard function that is
increasing with co, a constant times
T raised to a power, that will follow the
Weibull probability distribution.
So what you just illustrated was the
Weibull distribution.
So let me just write out the Weibull
distribution.
I don't want you to get bogged down.
There is a lot of parameters.
This can look a little complicated.
If you look this up on the internet,
you'll see that everybody uses different
symbols to
represent the Weibull function and they
represent it in slightly different ways.
I'm going to represent it in the simplest
way that I can think of to.
And I don't want you to get bogged down
with the details of the function or
worried about it too much when you are not
going to have to work with really Weibull
directly but I want you to have a concept
of what the Weibull function means.
So, again a hazard function for a Weibull,
this is just a way of
having a Hazard function increase over
time in some smooth mathematical way we're
multiplying by some function of time every
month or every year, every unit of time.
And I just want to show you actually that
the exponential distribution is
actually a special case of the Weibull
distribution.
So the exponential, which I told you
occurs when you have a constant hazard,
well if k equals 1.
And I'm calling k this power here, is
equal to 1, then if I plug in
k I get t raised to 0, so that t just goes
away and I get back to the constant.
So an exponential is actually just a
special case of a Weibull distribution.
Alright, so let me kind of just give you
some examples here for
Weibull hazard functions.
Here is, the Weibull hazard function when
k equals 1.
So this parameter k, what I'm calling k.
And again, you'll see it called different
things in literature, but
what I'm calling k is just a power.
I'm raising to a power in order to have a
way to
multiply something more every month.
If I set k equal to 1, I'm just going to
end up with and I'm using here a c of .1.
What we did before, that them or the
constant hazard is .1 and I'm
not multiplying by anything, every month,
just by 1, that I get a constant hazard.
That's actually just an exponential.
However, if I then set k equal to
something greater than 1,
I'm going to then have, be multiplying by
something that's above 1, and
whet you can see is that I get an
increasing hazard over time.
It's not linearly increasing, because
again, I'm raising by this power here, but
this is one instance of a Weibull
function,
I think I Set k to be 1.2 here, and C to
be 0.1.
Increasing hazard function, but
it's smooth, we can predict how that
hazard function is changing over time.
I could also make k less than 1, and when
I make k less than 1 I'm going to
get something that's decreasing, and they
look, the curves generally look something
like that, but again, depending on what k
and c are, this curve will change.
All right.
So then I took those, once I've
established those Hazard functions I
can then say how that translates to the
probability density function,
the cumulative density function, and
what we really care about here, which is
the survival function.
Again, don't get bogged down in the
formula.
The formula looks rather complex.
Remember that there's a mathematical
relationship between the Hazard function,
the pdf, the cdf and the survival.
I'm not going to make you do that
mathematical work.
I'll show you what the relationship is, at
a future module.
But don't worry too much what I wanted to
show you here is that if k is equal to
1 again, this just goes back down to the
exponential.
So if I plug in 1 and 1 here notice what I
get.
I get c, t raised to 0 which is just 1, e
raised
to negative ct so it just goes back down
to the the exponential.
I was calling the constant h for, before
for hazard ratio I'm calling it c here for
constant but otherwise don't worry too
much about that formula but
it's there just if you want it.
So now, I'm just showing you the
probability density functions as
a function of time, I have the same c, I
think I said c equal to .1 and all of
these, so they all have the same c, but k
is either 1, making this an exponential,
or greater than 1, making this, a positive
hazard over time, or less than 1.
So what you'll see is, that an exponential
curve,
as expected, looks like an exponential
when k is 1.
When k is greater than 1, you get this
probability density function, so,
there's a steep rise in your chances early
on in the having the event occur, but
then a lot of people by the end here have
had the event occur already, so
the probability of having it happen last
month is low just because moth
people have the even early on.
Because the hazard is high.
When we have case last in line the hazard
is decreasing over time.
So, you have allot of chance of having the
even early on because that's when
the hazard is highest.
And then that goes down over time.
The hazard rate is going down over time.
So, less and less a chance of having the
event in the later months.
So that's just what the probability
density functions look like.
The corresponding cumulative density
functions, again,
don't stress too much about the formula
here, but
I'll just show you that this does go
nicely to the formula for
an exponential if I plug in k is equal to
1 So you'll just end up with that and
again, I'm using c here when I used h
before but they're both just constants.
Just to show you a few different
cumulative density functions.
So they all have the same c.
The hazard is just staying the same here
on this left hand panel, so
we kind of have a shallow rise in the
events.
When the hazard rate is increasing over
time notice that the chance of
having your cumulative chance of events
goes up more, much more steeply.
You're getting, to you know, 86, 80% of
the sample,
having the event much earlier than when k
is equal to 1 as expected.
And of course if your k is less than 1,
then as the rate is decreasing over
time in the cumulative curve, it takes
much longer for events to accumulate.
[NOISE] And then finally, the Weibull
survival function.
This is just one minus the cdf.
So, again, the survival probabilities he,
are, these are similar to Kaplan-Meier
curves.
They're looking at survival function so
over time,
with the exponential, it's almost what
you'd kind of expect.
For an exponential, there's a steeper drop
in survival if you
have an increasing hazard.
There's a shallower drop in survival if
you have a decreasing hazard.
All of those again conceptually is what
you'd expect.
[NOISE] And just to show you these kind of
all put together, so
if we have c is equal .1, the constant is
equal to .1, and k is equal to 1,
so the power, we're not raising to any
powers here.
We're on the exponential.
This is the hazard constant the
corresponding pdf which looks like
an exponential function, the cumulative
density and the survival probability.
Therefore we've got this increasing hazard
rate,
you know the hazard rates going up over
time so we have events very early on.
We accumulate events very early and
the survival curve is very steep drops
very quickly.
If we have a decreasing hazard over time
this ones decreasing over time then we
have event early then it drops off quite a
bit, from there it takes longer to
accumulate events because the hazard is
going down every month and
the survival probability, the curve
doesn't drop as quickly.
So that's the general idea of the Weibull
function.
And again, as I mentioned earlier,
hazard functions don't have to follow a
nice mathematical function,
you could end up with one with real data
that looks something funny like that.
At that point, we aren't going to try to
force it to be on a mathematical function.
We're instead, when we do cox regression,
just going to try to avoid estimating that
altogether.
[BLANK_AUDIO]