[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to
introduce the Kaplan-Meier methods.
So, when we have time-to-event outcome
data, and we want to do something that is
mainly descriptive, we usually turn to the
Kaplan-Meier methods.
The nice thing about Kaplan-Meier is it
gives you these beautiful,
intuitive graphics.
And that's why you'll see a lot of
Kaplan-Meier curves in a lot of
papers that involve survival analysis.
They are mainly descriptive.
We can use them to compare groups but we
can't adjust for anything.
So, Kaplan-Meier gives a non-parametric
estimate of the survival function.
And all I mean by that is we're not
going to assume any
particular smooth mathematical curve for
the survival curve.
We're literally just going to look at our
data and
we're going to define the survival curve
based on when events occur.
And just based on how many people survived
past different time points.
So, it's the empirical probability that
what we see in
our data of surviving past certain times.
But the trick is that we have to somehow
account for the censoring.
It would be a really,
really easy to calculate Kaplan-Meier
estimates if there was no censoring.
If there's no censoring, the Kaplan-Meier
estimate just becomes the proportion of
people in your study surviving past, given
a, a different time points.
So, for example, if you started with 100
people and
there were 64 people surviving at age six.
And nobody have been lost,
then the Kaplan-Meier estimate of survival
would just be 64%.
That's just the percentage of people left.
The trick is that, accounting for
the censoring is, makes it just slightly
more complicated than that.
Now, in this module,
I'm going to talk about just drawing a
single Kaplan-Meier curve.
In the next module, we'll talk about
drawing multiple Kaplan-Meier curves for
different groups.
You can get a kind of p-value test called
a log-rank
test to statistically compare different
Kaplan-Meier curves.
Again, that'll be in the next module.
Let me just start here with a really
simple example that
will illustrate how Kaplan-Meier curves
are drawn.
So, imagine that we have a study that just
has five people in the study,
really simple.
It's a one year study.
At the beginning of the study there are
five people alive.
And we'll say that this outcome, the
outcome in the study is death, so
this is a time to death study.
And let's say that the first thing that
happens in this study is that subject
E dies four months into the study.
That means we are going to start by
estimating the probability of
surviving past four months.
Why four months?
Well, that's just what happened in this
study.
The, the curve is only going to be defined
when events occur,
happen to occur in our study.
How we're going to represent that on our
Kaplan-Meier curve.
The Kaplan-Meier curve is going to start
at 100%,
because all five out of five are alive at
the beginning of the study.
We're then going to draw the curve over,
keeping it at a 100% until somebody dies,
until an event occurs.
At four months subject E dies and we're
going to drop the curve to represent that.
The survival probability, the probability
of surviving past four months, which is
what we're trying to estimate with this
Kaplan-Meier method is very easy here,
because we had five people who were at
risk of dying at four months.
One of them died, four of them survived,
so the survival probability here is
just going to be four out of five, 80%, so
that's really simple.
So we drop the curve down here now to 80%.
Representing that our survival probability
has now dropped.
Well, let's say that the next thing that
happens in our study is
that subject A drops out of the study at
six months.
So, at six months, for whatever reason,
we, they were alive,
subject A was alive at six months, but
then they were lost to followup.
We don't know what happened after that.
So, they may or may not have died in the
last six months of the study.
And then, let's say, so they're said to be
censored.
And then, let's say that subject C
actually has an event,
they die at seven months.
So how would we represent that on the
Kaplan-Meier curve?
So turning back to our curve here, we were
at 80%, at 80%, and
then we're going to scroll the curve over.
At six months, subject A drops out of the
study.
We represent that on the curve with a
little tick mark.
We're not going to drop the curve, because
nobody died, there were no events.
But we represent it on the curve with some
kind of little mark, saying that,
hey, somebody was censored.
That means they're no longer at risk of
having the event.
Then subject C dies seven months into the
study.
At the time that subject C died, there
were three people at risk of dying.
Why only three?
Well, one person died at four months, so
they're out of the risk pool.
And then subject A was censored at six
months, so
that person is also out of the risk pool.
So, there's actually only three people at
risk of dying at seven months.
Now, one person dies, two live, so
the chance of surviving is two out of
three, 2 3rds.
So, we're now going to drop the curve
down.
We're actually dropping the curve here
down to 53%.
I'll show you in just a second why, where
that 53% comes from.
But, we dropped the curve because there
was an event and
we are incorporating this 2 3rds
probability, of,
because there was 2 3rds chance of
surviving that second interval.
Now, let's say that subject B and D they
just survive until the end of the study.
So when the study terminates, they're
still alive.
So they're censored one year into the
study.
So, we're going to represent on that, that
on the Kaplan-Meier curve by just kind of
scrolling over the curve to the end of the
study.
And the curve, of course, won't drop
because nobody died.
So, again this is 80% are, and this is
53%.
So, this is a very si, simple survival
curve.
The probability of surviving past four
months,
we would represent that probability that T
is greater than four, that's equal to 80%.
The probability of surviving past seven
months is equal to 53%, and that's it.
So the probability of surviving past one
year, 12 months, is also equal to 53%.
And that's our whole survival curve,
just defined on, at the points at which we
had events.
Now, let me tell you where that 53% came
from.
Why did I drop the curve to 53% here?
So, where that comes from is we have a
rule in
probability that says if we have
independent events,
their joint probability is equal to the
product of their marginal probabilities.
And what we're going to assume is that the
probabilities of
surviving different intervals are
independent of one another.
So, remember that four out of five people
survive the first interval and
two out of three people survive the second
interval.
So to get the cumulative, the total
probability of surviving those first two
intervals, we're going to multiply the 4
5ths times the 2 3rds.
That gives us a probability of 53.3%.
So, we're going to be multiplying across
the different intervals to
get the cumulative probability of
survival.
That's where that 53% comes from.
Now, notice that if nobody had been
censored,
if subject A had not been censored in that
second interval, we would have just been
multiplying 4 out of 5 times 3 out of 4,
which would just have been 3 out of 5.
So, then the Kaplan-Meier estimate would
be easy.
It would just be there was three out of
five surviving it and two people had died.
By changing these denominators, that's how
we're accounting for the censoring.
So again, it's the probability of
surviving the entire year,
taking into the account, the censoring,
comes out to be 53%.
And I just want to show you that
intuitively that's a good estimate here,
because imagine if we didn't know what to
do about the censor.
There's kind of two guesses we could make.
We could say, well, let's say that, you
know,
we're kind of looking at the glass half
empty.
And we say, well, subject A dropped out at
six months.
As far as I know, they're not alive.
So, I'm going to, I only know for sure
that B and D survived the whole year.
So, I'm only going to say that the
survival probability for
the year is 40%, because that's what I'm
sure of, two out of five.
So, I could be kind of pessimistic.
Or, I could become optimistic and I look
at the glass half full and say well, but
yeah, but the last time I saw subject A,
she was alive.
And so I, I'm going to assume she made it
the rest of the year.
And, I'm going to say that the chances of
surviving the year was three out of
five because we only saw two die.
So, I'm going to say it's 60%.
You can see that the 53% is kind of a nice
compromise between those two, right?
It's a little bit bet, somewhere between
40% and 60% and that's what we want.
Subject A, we have some information on
subject A.
We know they were alive for at least six
months, so we want to account for
that and incorporate it in our estimate.
40% is too small, 60% is too high.
53 is a good compromise then.
So that's the idea of the Kaplan-Meier
estimate and the Kaplan-Meier curve.