[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about ordinal logistic regression,
which you can use when you have an outcome
variable that has ordered categories.
So if you have an outcome variable that
has more than two levels and there, the.
Categories are not ordered in any way.
You have to use multinomial logistic
regression but
if your categories have some inherent
order to them then you
have option of running an ordinal logistic
regression.
And that model is also called the
proportional odds model because one of
the assumptions that we are going to talk
about with this model is that, you have to
have what's called proportional odds and
generally what that means is.
That you have to kind of have equal jumps
in risk across the different categories in
order to be able to apply this model.
We'll talk about exactly what that means.
The example data that I'm going to be
using to
illustrate ordinalogistic regression are
the same data that I
use to illustrate multinomial logistic
regression.
It will allow us to kind of compare the
two models.
So, these were some data on 150 college
age distance runners.
The outcome of interest is menstrual
irregularity.
That's a categorical variable because
there are three categories of
menstrual status.
Those are, Eumenorrhiec, which is normal
periods.
Oligomenorrheic, which is kind of a mild
menstrual irregularity,
some irregular periods.
And amenorrheic, which is the most severe
because the women get very few to no
periods at all.
And there is an order in here.
We're going from normal to, kind of,
medium severe, to the most severe.
So this is a ordinal variable, and we can
treat it as such.
The predictor of interest, here, was your
score on an eating disorder questionnaire.
We're abbreviating that as the E-D-I-A.
It ranges from zero to 21 points, and
it measures kind of how disorder the
restrictive your eating is?
So here are the outcomes, and we can, the
what we're going to be doing for
ordinal logistic regression is we have to
think of the outcomes in cumulative terms.
So let me just kind of set up that concept
now.
So here's our three categories,
here's the number of women in each of
those categories.
We can start by thinking about the most
severe category, in this case,
that's the amenorrheaic women.
This is the most severe menstrual
irregularity.
8.6% of my sample falls into that
category.
We could then think, cumulatively, about
being more inclusive.
So coming up with an outcome that,
is more inclusive than just the most
severe outcome.
We can include both the mild and the
severe together.
This is a cumulative outcome becomes I am
including the most severe along with sort
of the next category down.
And we could look at the risks of being in
either of those categories.
That's what we mean by accumulative
outcome.
If we had more than three levels, we could
then go down and include another more
inclusive category until we got you know,
to the reference group.
What we're going to do with this is we're
actually going to build what's called.
Called cumulative logits and that's what
the ordinal regression logistic regression
model relies on is cumulative logits.
So, what do I mean by cumulative logit?
We are going to be fitting logits, as we
do with logistic regression but
we are going to be logit for
the most extreme outcome and the logit for
the more inclusive outcome.
So, the logit for amenorrhea is going to
be the log odds.
Of having amenorrhea, compared with having
anything else.
So comparing the anenorrheaic women to
either oligomenorrheaic or normal.
The logit for any irregularity is going to
be the log odds of having
any menstrual irregularity, that is either
ammenorrhea or oligomenorrhea.
Compared with being normal.
And we're going to be modeling both of
these logits.
And this is, I've just restating in words
there, if you want to see it written out.
So here is what the logistic regression
model is actually going to look like,
we're going to literally model log odds of
amenorrhea.
The log odds of any irregularity.
And remember any irregularity includes
amenorrhea.
I'm going to start this to make this
really simple.
I'm going to start with the intercept only
model.
So there's no predictors in my model.
I'm just fitting a model that contains the
intercept.
In ordinal logistic regression I'm
actually going to be modeling
two intercepts.
One for the most severe category, and one
for the next inclusive category.
And if I had more than three categories,
I'd be.
Estimating even more intercepts than that.
So let me just show you how this works,
because I think it's easy to see with only
the intercept.
So, what is my model going to look like?
So first of all, what's the logit of
amenorrhea of my data set?
If I'm not putting any predictors in my
model,
the logit of amenorrhea just represents
the prevalence of amenorrhea in my sample.
So I had 8.6% prevalence of amenorrhea in
my sample, that's the probability.
I can turn that into an odds by dividing
8.6% by 1 minus that.
My odds is 0.094.
My log odds is therefore the natural log
of that.
So my log odds of amenorrhea in my data
set, not accounting for
anything is negative 2.3.
That's the logit of amenorrhea.
What's the logit of any menstrual
irregularity at all?
Well 33% of my sample has any menstrual
irregularity.
That includes a logit amenorrhea or
amenorrhea.
[INAUDIBLE] The odds, therefore, is one to
two.
The natural log of 1 to 2 is negative 0.7.
So, the logit of any irregularity is
negative 0.7.
If I don't put anything in my regression
model, that's all I'm fitting.
My fitted models will have two intercepts.
The intercepts will be negative 2.36 for
amenorrhea and negative 0.7 for
any menstrual irregularity.
So, that's the model if you didn't have
anything in it at all.
So, that will help you understand what the
intercept means.
Now, lets go ahead and
actually our predictor, this eating
disorder score into our model.
So, now, what is the ordinal logistic
regression model look like.
So, we are going to be fitting essentially
two models.
We're going to be looking at the logit of
amenorrhea and
the logit of any irregularity with
separate intercepts, but
then, what we're going to be doing is
estimating only a single beta.
So, two intercepts but only a single beta.
We're going to estimate one beta.
For eating disorder score.
Notice how this is different than
multinomial logistic regression.
In multinomial logistic regression, we fit
separate datas.
In ordinal logistic regression, we're
going to assume that the beta.
For, for going from having being normal,
to having any irregularity, and
a beta that represents going from have,
being non-amenorrheic to
being amenorrheic, that those betas are
the same, and
that's the assumption inherent in ordinal
logistic regression.
So we have [INAUDIBLE].
Different intercepts but we have a shared
beta.
So, before I actually fit this model I
have a continuous predictor variable so
I need to make sure that it's linear in
the logit in my outcome.
I actually essentially have two outcomes.
These cumulative outcomes so my logit plot
is going to have two lines on it.
If I had a, an ordinal variable that had
four levels to it my lu,
cumulative logit plot would have three
lines and so on.
So let me explain what's going on in this
logit plot.
It's a little more complicated than the
logit plots we've seen until now.
So I have two lines.
So my, my Y axis is logit again.
But the bottom line here represents the
logit of amenorrhea of outcome,
of the most severe outcome.
And is showing you, this is from my
observed data.
So I looked at women as they went up in
their EDIA score.
What did the logit amenorrhea do?
And that's what's plotted here.
It moves around a little bit, because
again these are the observed data.
But you can see the general pattern is
that,
as you go up in EDAI score, you, your
logit of amenorrhea goes up.
It's fairly linear.
It's not a perfect straight line, but I'd
say, as real data go, that's pretty good.
That looks pretty linear to me.
The second line represents the logit of
being either amenorrheic or
oligomenorrheic.
So that's that cumulative logit.
And you can see this, that there's a
similar pattern.
This is the intercept for having any
menstrual irregularities, so
this represents how many people have any
menstrual irregularity at
an edi score of zero.
And as you go up in EDAI score it
generally tends to go up again.
Now, again, there is a little bit of
variation because these are real data but
that looks like a pretty straight line to
me.
For my cumulative logit plot, I'm looking
for straight lines that it's linear in
the logit but I have an additional thing
that I need to check out on this graph.
So the assumption of the ordinalistic
progression model is that there
is a single beta.
In other words, that these lines have to
be parallel,
they have to have the same slope.
We are only estimating one beta for EDIA
so we have therefore
assumed that the slope of these two lines
has to be the same or very close.
So I'm looking at those two lines and
they, those look pretty darn parallel to
me.
So that would indicate to me that we have
indeed met what is
called the proportional odds assumption.
Again it's never going to be perfect with
real data, but
this is hm, about as good as you get.
That would mean that would,
would be fair to estimate one single beta
using all of the data.
I just written out all of that on to a
sliding tissue like to see it written out,
you could pause the video and read those
if, if it helps you.
So because I, I've seem to have met my
proportional odd assumption,
I went ahead and re add a single ordinal
logistic regression in my computer,
Here's the output that I get.
So my predictor is now this eating
disorder score.
I've run an ordinal logistic regression,
so
I'm going to get an intercept, two
intercepts.
And the intercept for amenorrhea and an
intercept for this more inclusive.
Category of any menstrual irregularity.
That corresponds to my logit plot because
I had two different intercepts on my logit
plot but I have only fit a single data for
EDIA.
That also corresponds to my logit plot
because it looks like those
lines are parallel and therefore that it
would.
Would be fair to just estimate the slope
of those parallel lines.
Notice that EDI score is indeed, does have
a statistically significant
relationship with both, amenoria and any
menstrual irregularity.
So that's what our logistic regression
model looks like.
We're going to have one beta but multiple
intercepts, from ordinal logistic.
We can translate that data into odds
ratios, so that,
I've done that here, so we can talk about
the odds ratio for a one unit
increase in this eating disorder score,
that odds ratio turn out to be about 1.13.
So, for every one unit increase in your
eating disorder score, you go up about 13%
in your odds of going from either
oligomenorrheic or
eumenorrheic to being amenorrhoeic.
And you're also going up about 13% in your
odds of going from
having a normal menses to having any
menstrual irregularities at all and
see how we're assuming that those two
jumps are the same.
We can also calculate the odds ratio for a
one standard deviation increase in eating,
eating disorders score, a standard
deviation's about six here, so the odds
ratio looks bigger, so we have a two,
about an odds ratio of about two there.
So again, what that says is that your
chances of going from sort of
normal menses to having any menst,
menstrual irregularity at all, if you go
up one standard deviation in eating.
Disorder score, then you are doubling your
odds of going, of having any menstrual
irregularity, you're also doubling your
odds of going from being in sort of
this smaller category of eumenorrheic or
oligonomerrheic not having the most.
Severe outcome, you're doubling your odds
therefore I'm
going from there to having the most severe
outcome.
And then again we have to assume that
those jumps are equal,
that's the proportional odds assumption.
I've written all of that out on a slide in
case you like to read it written out.
You can pause the video and read it there.
So here's our fitted logistic model.
So this is what our logistic model came
out to be.
Our intercept for amenorrhea was fitted at
negative 3.26.
For any irregularity the intercept's at
negative 1.38.
The beta's are the same, there's only a
single beta so
those lines are exactly parallel.
That beta is 0.1211, it's indeed positive
as we go up in the eating disorder score.
Our risk, or odds, of going to be in
either of these outcomes, goes up.
So that's a positive slope.
That's what we've, that's the ordinal
logistic regression model pictured,
that's what it actually looks like.
We can compare that because we did a logit
plot,
we can compare the fitted model to the
actual data.
And you can see that our fitted model
does, really, pretty well.
It really does capture the pattern in the
underlying data.
Of course, we're smoothing over the fact
that there's a little bit of noise at
the lower EDI score.
Scores, but in general I think that the
fitted model really does look
pretty close to the original data.
So, suggesting that it's a good model.
As with any logistic regression model, we
can then use the model to
get predictive probabilities based on a
woman's eating disorders score.
We're going to get two predictive
probabilities out of the model here.
We're going to get her probability of
being [UNKNOWN] in that
most severe category and
we're going to get the probability of
having any irregularity at all.
To get these predicative probabilities its
our usual equation fro
predictive probabilities.
Except for the amenorrhea equation we're
using the intercept for amenorrhea.
For the any irregularity equation we're
using the intercept for
any menstrual irregularity.
Let me just illustrate by actually
plugging some numbers in.
So imagine you had a woman whose eating
disorder score was equal to nine,
what would her predicted probabilities be
based on the model?
So we would plug in her value of nine, you
can punch that in a computer.
And yo will get out a value of about 10%
so a woman with an eating disorder.
Score of nine is predicted by our model
to,
have about a 10% chance of being
amenorrheic.
Now remember that about 8.6% of my sample
is actually amenorrheic, so
that says that she kind of has a higher
than average chance of being amenorrheic.
Cause she does have elevated EDI score.
We can get her chances of having any
menstrual irregularity again by.
Plugging into this equation.
When I plug in there, I'm going to get
around 42% chance of
having any menstrual irregularity at all,
something like that.
So she has about 42% chance of having any
menstrual irregularity.
What if I wanted to actually get her
probability of,
specifically, having oligomenorrhea?
Well, I could just subtract the 42% minus
the 10%.
This would give me her chance of having,
of being oligomenorrheaic specifically,
that's going to come out to be about
32.3%.
So you can get that chance of being that
specific middle category by subtracting
here.
So I went ahead and had the computer
calculate.
For me predicting probabilities for a
bunch of different EDI score.So here's
the one for nine, which we just calculated
on the previous slide.
Some other ones in between.
The highest possible score is 21.
So if you had a score of 21.
In about 33% chance of being amenorrheic,
43% chance of being oligomenorrheic,
about a 75% chance of being either one of
those and
then a 24% chance of having normal, a
normal period.
so this comes about to be about maybe 76%
combined.
Now we already ran a multinomeial
progression where we also got out
similar predictive probability so I just
want to compare and show you that they.
Come out pretty close in this case.
So here is the results from the
multinomial regression that we ran in
a previous module.
So somebody who has a score of nine has
predicted probabilities again of
about 10%, 30%, 57, 58%, those are very
similar for
21, very similar to probabilities we saw
in the previous slide.
So in this case we get.
Pretty similar results whether we run the
ordinal logistic or
the multinomial relogistic in terms of the
predictive probabilities that tells us
that the ordinal model is probably good
here.
Because we haven't smooth over some kind
of important variations in the data,
it looks pretty similar whether we go into
the fine detail of every category or
we kind of estimate only one single beta.
So the advantage of estimating it with
ordinal edges to regression here is that
the way the multinomial regression worked
we actually had to
estimate two separate betas, one for
amenorrhea, one for oligomenorrhea.
By estimating two betas there was a
smaller sample size used to
estimate either of these betas, we only
had 13 women.
To estimate the beta for amenorrhea.
For example, 13 women who were
amenorrheic, 100 who were eumenorrheic.
That reduces our statistical power, means
our standard errors are going to
be a little bit bigger, our P values are
going to be a little bit bigger.
When we use all of the data, all 150 women
to estimate the, the beta
which was from the ordinal logistic
regression, there was only a single beta.
Then we have more statistical power.
So that means the standard error
associated with this single beta is
going to be smaller than the standard
errors that we got from the multinomial
regression, means our p values are
going to be smaller.
So it does increase your statistical power
if you,
indeed, meet the proportional odds
assumption.
And just to show you graphically, here's
the predicted probabilities,
the cumulative probabilities, as a
function of eating disorder score,
this is what our model predicts if we just
graph out across all the possible scores.
So the blue line represents the predicted
probability of
being amenorrhea equals being in that most
severe category.
The red line here,
represents the probability of being have,
having any menstrual irregularity.
So a, the blue line is sort of included in
this red line.
And you can see that as you go up in
score,
eventually you have more than a 75% chance
of having any menstrual irregularity.
And that's just the, the picture for the
ordinal logistic model.
Now, I just want to mention some other
cases where you
might want to think about applying an
ordinal logistic.
So, a classic ordinal variable is the
likert scale.
Sometimes, on a questionnaire, we'll ask
people did they strongly disagree,
disagree, neutral, agree, strongly agree.
Something like that.
Often times when people.
Do with these datas.
When they get the data in at the end of
the day they just say while I'm going to
collapse everybody.
I'm only going to put people here or here
and
I'm going to rate, run a regular logistic
reg-ration comparing any agreement with
any disagreement or neutrality.
Well that might be appropriate in some
cases.
Especially if you have really small
numbers in some of these categories.
But you are losing information that way
and
it makes you think well why didn't you set
up the questionnaire with only two
questions, if you're just going to collect
the data at the end of the day.
So, if you have a reasonably large sample
size and
you actually have enough people on each
one of these categories, you could
consider doing instead of collapsing,
actually doing an ordinal logistic here.
You'll pull more information out of the
data that way.
What would the ordinal logistic actually
look like just to show you
in the case where we have five levels of
ordinal categorical variable.
We are going to be again thinking about
cumulative outcomes.
We are going to get, kind of get your mind
around this.
The logest is going to be cumulative
logist so we are going to be
comparing sort of the most extreme answer
the strongly agree versus everything else.
So theres going to be a logit that looks
at the probability of being only in
category five versus any of the other four
categories.
But then we're going to have cumulative
logits,
and we're going to get more inclusive.
So then we're going to compare any
agreement at all.
Agree or strongly agrees in the bottom.
Three.
Then we're going to compare the top three,
you know,
neutrality or agreement, to having any
disagreements.
And then, finally, we're going to compare
anything that's
not strong disagreement to strongest
agreement.
So my, our model is going to be combining
all of those.
For comparisons.
And so again you have to make the, you
have to meet the assumption then
that we're kind of having equal jumps
across those different comparisons,
that the odds ratio's going to be the same
in those cases or reasonably similar.
But it's worth considering to see if that
is true in your data if that is
you could do ordinal logistic.
Which has advantages, in that you're
taking in an account.
All these information eon again since
you're only estimating
a single observation or a single beta.
You're increasing your statistical power
compared with.
Somehow doing this with a multinomial
regression.
So just to summarize the advantages and
disadvantages of ordinal logistic.
If you have a case where you meet the
proportional odds assumption,
the ordinal logistic regression has more
statistical power than the multinomial,
logistic regression, because you're using
all observation to estimate a single beta.
Rather than dividing up your observations
into the different categories and
estimating separate datas.
So you do have an increase in statistical
power.
Of course it does require that you meet
this proportional odds assumption.
Its works very well in our example data
test today.
We met that very well but you can imagine
cases where the jumps across different
categories are in fact not equal and that
you wouldn't actually be able to use.
Ordinal logistic in those cases.