[BLANK_AUDIO]
Last week we talked about how to test
whether or not your continuous variable
really does have a linear relationship
with the logit of the outcome.
Which is what the logistic model assumes.
This week we are going to talk about what
to do if your variable does
not have a linear relationship.
So last week I showed you various plots,
logit plots,
which plot the logit of the outcome.
In this case, for this graph of the
outcome here was low bone density.
Against a continuous predictor in this
case the predictor here was
the number of menstrual periods in the
past year.
And in general for women if they are
having irregular periods they have
a higher chance of having low bone density
you can see that here.
As women have more regular periods they
have a lower chance of
having low bone density.
And the relationship here looks nice and
linear, it's really pretty close to
a straight line, so if we were to just put
menstrural periods in the model
without doing any kind of transformation
It seems to nicely fit a straight line.
So that one does look linear in the logit.
In the last module I talked about the,
the data on women runners that I'd been
looking at, and
it turned out that fat mass was protective
against stress fractures in that group.
Again, probably because.
Fat mass increases the period regularity.
And so the graph here is showing the logit
of stress fractures,
that's my binary outcome, and the
predictor here is fat mass.
And this fat mass variable was turned into
Z scores,
as we talked about in an earlier module.
And you can see that, indeed, as women go
up in fat mass,
they seem to go down in their logit of
stress fractures in a nice linear pattern.
So this one would also be, meet the linear
in the logit assumption.
I also showed you last week a couple of
graphs.
We are, we did not meet the linearity in
the logit assumption.
And so here are two examples shown again
here.
So in the last panel this was a study
looking at cardiovascular disease.
So we have the logit of cardiovascular
disease on the y-axis.
And on the x-axis, axis we have smoking.
And you can see that it doesn't have a
nice linear relationship as you
go from being a non-smoker to a smoker.
There's a huge, steep, rise in your risk
of cardiovascular disease.
But then things seem to level off.
They're sort of diminishing returns as you
increase the level of smoking,
you're still increasing your risk but not
quite as steeply.
So it looks like it has a little bit more
of a quadratic relation.
Now this one might be well modeled by
changing your
smoking variable into categories, right?
Rather than modeling it as a continuous
variable,
you might say non-smoke versus light
smokers, versus heavy smokers.
Or something like that.
Now in the right hand panel, I showed you
these data on typhosis, so this was,
the outcome here was Having spinal
curvature, or
kyphosis, after corrective spine surgery
in children.
The age here, the predictor variable is
age, and it's measured in months.
And we saw last week that there's a nice
quadratic relationship here.
The middle ages are at higher risk than
the younger and older ages.
That one was well modeled as a squared
variable because of the quadratic.
So, what do we do when we find that our
predictor variable violates linearity?
We have a couple of choices.
So we can transform the variable
mathematically in some ways.
So I've shown you an example where we took
the square of the variable.
There might be other instances where
taking the log of the variable
accomplishes making it linear with the log
then.
You also might in some cases choose to
break up
your continuous variable into a
categorical variable and
there's a lot of times clinically there
might be some natural clinical category.
So if it doesn't appear to be linear the
log may be treated divided into those
Clinically meaningful categories.
Just to illustrate both of those with one
more example,
here's a data set that was looking at
predictors of low birth weight.
And of course, one of the predictors that
you might expect to to be
a predictor of low birth weight is
maternal age.
however, if you were just to take these
data and throw maternal age into
the model, so we're modeling here the
logit of low birth weight.
But if you were to just throw age in as a
linear variable into the model and
run that model, here's the results that
you get.
So here's maternal age.
Our beta is practically zero and our p
value is totally non-significant.
In other words it looks like age has
absolutely no relationship with
low birth weight.
Now, something seems a little wrong there,
because I think most of us know that
indeed maternal age does relate to low
birth weight.
Well, of course we didn't plot our
variable which is always a mistake.
So now let me show you the plots for this
variable.
Here as I have plotted the plotted the low
gen of low birth weight compared to
maternal age.
And I've done one plot where I used ten
bins and another plot where I used five.
Remember when you are using these plots,
you have to be ale to group people.
To calculate probabilities and therefore
odds.
And so the bin size will slightly,
that you choose will slightly change the
what you see in your graph.
In this case I had a fairly big data set
so
I could easily break it into ten bins and
get a meaningful plot.
But the ten bin plot and the five bin plot
look pretty much the same to me.
I'm seeing a clean quadratic relationship,
where the younger and older ages have
higher risks of low birth weights than the
ages in between, somewhere in the 20s
looks to be about, or about the the mid to
late 20s looks to be the optimal age.
So what do we do?
It's a clearly not linear, and notice.
When I just throw age into the model
without thinking about it, what I'm
asking the computer to do is just to find
the best fit line for these points.
The best fit line for these points is
basically just a straight horizontal line,
and that's why we see no relationship.
That's because there is not a linear
relationship here, but
there is a quadratic relationship.
So, how am I going to deal with this?
Again I might end up just saying, well
it's a quadratic.
So, I'm going to put in the square of my
predictor variable.
So, I tried that.
And indeed when you model it as the
square, so I'm going to
put age in as a linear term and than the
higher order term of age squared.
Notice that both of those indeed turn out
to be statistically significant once I've
got the correct function here.
The only problem with using a square here
is it's a little
bit hard to explain exactly what these
beta coefficients mean,
it's going to be hard to calculate odds
ratios.
It's a little bit harder to explain to
your leader, and so
in this case it might be more natural to
take this graphic and
say well what is it actually mean, what is
the quadratic relationship mean.
It really means that very young women and
very old, well not very old, just older
women reproductively those groups have
higher risks than the, the women in their.
Or 20s who have sort of have more of the
optimum age for reproduction.
So it might be natural actually to divide
this up in to these data,
up in to categories that tells a cleaner
and neater story.
So I then did that.
The categories I chose here are a little
bit arbitrary,
they're sort of based on what I, the
pattern I saw in the graphic, but
you might want to chose sort of clinically
meaningful categories.
But basically had a, you know,
sort of young, pre haven't graduated from
the college age.
And an older age, here, is just above 30.
Which isn't really old but a little bit
older reproductively.
And then the middle age is sort of the
optimal age, it's in between 22 and 30.
And when I compare those three groups in
a, logistic regression.
Dummy coding them.
I end up with that older age versus being
of the optimal age get an odds
ratio of about 2.3, so they have about
double the odds of low birth weight.
And similarly, the young age versus that
optimal middle age also has an odds
ratio of about a doubling of the, of the
odds of low birth weight.
So it may be conceptually preferable, in
this case,
to divide that continuous variable up into
categories.
[BLANK_AUDIO]