Welcome to unit nine, which is the final
unit of this course.
I've kept this unit a little bit shorter,
just to make sure you have some extra time
to study for the final exam.
So this week, we're going to wrap up the
course by talking about
the regression methods that are used when
you have correlated observations.
And these are conditional logistic
regression and GEE modeling.
Let me go back to the chart of statistical
tests that I showed you at
the beginning of this course.
I'll just show you now that we have
actually covered almost all of these at
this point.
So in the first week of the course we
covered a number of tests that were
non-regression methods, we then spent many
weeks covering logistic regression, and
last week, additionally, I told you about
multinomial and ordinal
logistic regression, which are just
alternate versions of logistic regression.
Last week, I also told you about a, an
entirely different type of
outcome variable that you might want to
add to your chart as another row.
Which is, when you have count data as your
outcome.
You have count outcomes you probably
going to want to use poisson regression or
negative binomial regression as we talked
about last week.
The test that we haven't covered yet
that we are going to get to this week are
conditional logistic regression and
GEE modeling, again these are regression
techniques for
when you have correlated observations.
Before I jump into these however I thought
it would be fun to start this week
with a little preview to the final exam,
since that's coming up soon.
So I took two questions off of a previous
year's final exam just to
give you a sense of the types of questions
I might be asking.
If you want, feel free to pause the video
and attempt this question on your own.
I'm now going to just walk through it.
So this was a study cross-sectional study
of people,
they were looking to see about skin
wrinkling.
And wrinkles was measured on a scale of
one to six,
so this an ordinal outcome variable.
That's a hint that's going to help you get
the right answer here.
They wanted to say whether or not your
occupation, if you work outside or
indoors and outdoors, or only indoors,
does that contribute to wrinkling?
So here's some SAS output, and this is
something I might do on the final exam is
just to give you some out put from SAS,
from SAS, and have you interpret it.
So the question, this question is asking
you what type of analysis did
the authors want to generate this output?
So you look at the output,
you'll notice that they're five intercepts
in this model.
So that's a clue that this either going to
be ordinal logistic regression or
multinomial logistic regression.
And I was very kind when I made this
question because I
didn't even put multinomial as a, as a
choice here.
So you can actually get this down to
ordinal logistic regression pretty easily.
However, what if I'd also given the choice
of multinomial logistic regression?
How would you know that this was ordinal
and not multinomial?
Well, you'd know that because there's only
a single beta estimate,
a single beta parameter, for each of the
predictors in the model.
So that's how you can tell that this is
ordinal logistic, rather than multinomial.
Here's the second question again, if you
want to pause the video and
try this on your own, it'd be a good
practice for the final exam.
If not, I'm just going to walk through it.
So this question was asking you to
calculate the predicted probability of
having severe skin wrinkling for somebody
who works outdoors.
So we're going to be calculating a
predicted probability based on the model.
Now this one's slightly tricky, because
you have to figure out,
which intercept am I going to be using
here and which beta?
So, we know, of course,
that the predictive probability from
logistic regression always looks like
e raised to something over 1 plus e raised
to something.
But then we have to fill in that something
here.
So the trick here is that the wrinkle
outcome was again an ordinal variable.
It went from no wrinkling all the way up
to severe wrinkling, and
severe wrinkling is the smallest category.
Remember that ordinal logistic regression
is cumulative.
The very top category is the severe
category.
So you know that,
that category is going to have the fewest
number of people in it.
What's a little tricky, is that when SAS
actually puts the outmake as the output,
it just calls them intercept 1, 2, 3, 4 or
5, but that 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5 don't
necessarily correspond to the numbering
that was used for the actual variable.
They're just labeling them as they come.
So you actually have to look at the
intercept values and
figure out which logit value here
represents the smallest group, and
that's going to be the smallest logit.
That would represent the smallest
percentage of people.
You know that a percentage that's,
a logit that's negative, is going to mean
less than 50%.
So that's going to be the smallest group.
We're going to be using that intercept,
and
then the predictive variable here is a
dummy coded variable.
This person that we want to get the
predicted probability for
had an outdoor job.
So we're going to using the beta of 0.8817
they did not have a mixed job.
So we're going to just plug in now the
intercept for
this person and their beta coefficient.
It's dummy coded, so you're just
multiplying that beta by one.
You are going to need a calculator
available for the final exam so
that you can plug and chug simple numbers
like this.
So if you plug this into a calculator and
you calculate it out, it comes to out to
be about 40%.
So the correct answer here would be a.
So that's just a little preview to the
kinds of things that might show up on
the final exam.