In this next module I'm going to tell you
more about propensity scores.
So we already talked about how to
calculate them,
now I'm going to show you how to use them.
So there's three ways to use propensity
scores: stratification, matching, and
statistical adjustment.
I'm going to show an example of each of
these.
So first of all stratification.
We can stratify a propensity score the way
we would stratify on any confounder.
So, for example, in the rehabilitation
study,
the author stratified on quintiles of
propensity score.
So people who were in the lowest quintile
were only compared to
others who were in the lowest quintile of
propensity score.
Because we've done stratification, the
Mantel-Haenzel methods apply.
And you can see there, they had a nice
figure in their paper.
Again, we were in this study comparing
rehabilitation to getting no
rehabilitation in nursing homes.
And what you can see in this figure here,
is they're showing you the relative risk
of getting discharged to the community.
That's a good outcome.
That means you got out of the nursing
home.
That's what we want.
Over here, we see the quintiles of
propensity scores.
So there was obviously five quintiles from
lowest to highest.
And then they show you overall, what is
the relative risk for
comparing rehabilitation to no
rehabilitation for community discharge.
So because we done the stratified
analysis, we can apply the Mantel Haenszel
methods, we can calculate the Mantel
Haenszel summary risk ratio and
that's what this 1.58 is.
That's the overall, the summary, so after
adjusting for quintile of propensity
scores, rehabilitation, indeed, was still
associated with significant benefit.
The relative risk is 1.58, meaning that
they were 58% more likely to be discharged
to the community if they had gotten the
rehabilitation versus if they had not.
Now, there was something else interesting
in their analysis however which you
can see in the picture here.
So they found a significant interaction.
In other words the [UNKNOWN] test here.
Would have come out statistically
significant.
And you can see that in the picture.
So if you look at the lowest quintiles of
rehabilitation,
these are the people who are the least
likely to get rehabilitation.
There indeed seems to be a benefit.
50 percent, 50 percent,
even a doubling of your chances of getting
out of the nursing home.
However, if you look at the two highest
quintiles of propensity scores,
these are the people who are the most
likely to get rehabilitation.
There was much less benefit, particularly
in the highest quintile.
The the relative risk here was 0.9, no
benefit.
So what is that telling you?
So that's telling you how we decide who
gets rehabilitation is
really screwed up, right?
Because the people who are most likely to
benefit from the rehabilitation,
are actually the people who are least
likely to get it.
So that's a really interesting insight
that came out of
using the propensity scores.
So that was stratification.
Now propensity score matching.
So propensity score matching works in the
following.
We often do a one to one matching, so you
would find somebody, say in
the Ross group, who had a propensity score
of point six and then you would try to
find somebody in the mechanical valve who
had a similar propensity score.
We can't always match them exactly.
But how do we actually achieve this
matching in practice?
In practice there are,
there are a couple of different algorithms
that might be used.
I'm just going to mention the
nearest-neighbor one.
It does take some work to actually match
these,
because you can imagine that there are
often cases where there's only
a match within a certain range, not an
exact match.
So, how does the nearest-neighbor matching
algorithm as
an example, how does that work?
That's what they used in the Ross study.
So, here's what they did.
First of all, remember we had only 406
mechanical valve patients.
We had about 900 Ross patients.
So what they did is they tried to find a,
to match a Ross patient to a every
mechanical valve patient.
So they first randomly ordered the
mechanical valve patients.
Then they start with the first one who
came up on top on that random ordering.
They look at the propensity score, and
they try to find, they go through all of
the patients of the Ross patients, who are
all still available at this time.
And they find the person with the closest
propensity score from the Ross group.
So, maybe on that very first person,
there's a, you know,
the mechanical valve person has a
propensity score of 0.4,
the Ross, they can find a Ross patient
with a propensity score of 0.41.
Pretty close.
And then they keep going down the list,
and
of course there's fewer and fewer choices
out of that Ross list eventually.
So as they go down the list, they may have
to allow the valves,
the the differences between the two, the
two to be a little bit bigger and bigger.
And in fact they let it go up to as big a
difference as 25 percent, so they would
allow a match that where the mechanical
valve say, had a propensity score of
0.2 and the Ross patient had a propensity
score as big as .55, 55 percent.
And after, once they couldn't find the
way, any matches within 25 percent,
then the patient was left unmatched and
they were excluded.
They were just, they simply didn't have a
close enough match in the data set.
And in fact, even with a fairly liberal
criteria of a 25 percent difference,
they can only find matches for 253 of the
original 406 mechanical valve patients.
So they ended up in the match cohort with
a data set of about 500 total people.
Whereas in the original cohort, there was
about 1,300.
So, a lot of people that couldn't be
matched here.
Then they took the match cohort and they
ran a survival analysis.
So this is just a Kaplan-Meyer curve so
it's unadjusted.
In blue we have the Ross patients in red.
We have the mechanical valve patients,
the smaller dotted lines is to represent
confidence intervals.
You can see the confidence intervals are
highly overlapping.
There weren't that many deaths.
So there was a 97 percent survival in the
Mechanical Valve versus 95
percent in the Ross procedure, the p value
is completely non significant.
So remember that Ross patients, in
previous studies,
had been shown to do better in terms of
survival but once we account for
all these differences between Ross
patients and
Mechanical Valve patients They actually
don't seem to have any survival benefit.
If anything they do a little worse.
And this is just showing the results from
a cox regression.
So, they then took the matched cohort and
they ran it in a regression analysis,
which is going to give us a fairly similar
answer to the Kaplan Myer, but
they adjusted for a few things.
You can see there were very few deaths.
But the hazard ratio comparing Ross to
mechanical valve came out to be 1.86.
So hazard ratio is just very,
is a type of relative risk, so we can
interpret it in the normal way.
The same p value from Cox regression, same
as the log rank test, came out to be 0.29.
So, no differences between the groups,
if anything, the Ross patients are doing
worse.
Now, you have to make some choices with
the matching.
Because not everybody's going to have a
perfect match.
So you have to allow some inexactness in
the matching.
But if you allow it to be too far apart,
like if
you allow somebody with a score of .2 to
be matched to somebody with a score of .9,
obviously there's, you're going to bring
back in the confounding.
So the more inexact you're matching, the
more the confounding.
However you have to trade that off between
having incomplete matching.
So they weren't able to find matches for
about 150 patients in the raw study.Um,
they already had, made the matching up to
25 percent difference between patients.
And that's pretty big.
So, they cut it off there,
but if you make it to exact, if you
require the matching to be too perfect,
then a lot of people are going to be
thrown out of the data set.
That's going to decrease your sample size
and
your statistical power as well as
generalizability.
So, there's a trade off between those two.
Alright, so then the other thing to point
out here is we have matched data.
We have matched pairs.
So of course, when I told you that when we
have matched pairs,
then you have a correlation in your data.
So you should probably analyze the data as
matched pairs and
take into account that correlation.
I'll just note that there is some on-going
debate about this issue
in the statistical literature.
For now, I'd say, you're on the side of
actually accounting for the correlation.
The debate is around the fact that, people
can, two people can have the same, or
very similar propensity scores, but
they have very different underlying
characteristics, so they really may not be
that correlated on Most of the factors
that determine the propensity score.
So the final thing that we can do with the
propensity scores is
just put them into a regression model like
we do with any other confounder.
The nice thing about the propensity scores
is it's only one variable as opposed to
a whole set of confounders that we might
have to adjust for.
So it's a little bit more efficient.
And it would look like we're going to
take, make a regression model,
here's our outcome.
We're going to have the treatment as the
main predictor in the model, but
we're only going to adjust for propensity,
or maybe a couple of other covariates for
some reason we might additionally want to
adjust for.
That's going to be a parsimonious model,
as opposed to if we had taken
all the original co-founders that went
into calculating this propensity score and
adjusted for those.
Now I'll tell you that, if you run the
model where you adjust for
propesity score, and then you go and
run the same model, except you have your
treatment variable in there,
and instead of propensity score, you put
in that original set of covariates.
That you used to calculate the propensity
score.
Might be a big set.
But assuming that you have enough degrees
of freedom to fit that in your model,
you'll actually get very similar results
for the treatment effect.
So in other words, adjusting for the
propensity score has a very similar effect
as adjusting for all the original co,
confounders that
went into the propensity score, as it
might not surprise you to hear that.
But it is more efficient, because it's
only one number.
Now, when we the propensity score in the
model,
all of the usual assumptions apply, it's a
continuous variable so
therefore, we're assuming that it's linear
in the logit.
We're going to want to check that
assumption.
If we just throw it in the model, we're
also assuming it doesn't interact with
the treatment we saw in the rehabilitation
example that there was an interaction.
Between the treatment and the propensity
score, so
if there's some reason to suspect that we
might want to test, add
an interaction term in the model between
the propensity score and the treatment.
And see if there's an interaction,
if there's some reason to suspect there
would be one.
And as I mentioned before, statistical
adjustment with a propensity score is
actually very similar to adjusting for all
the covariants that were used to
Calculate the propensity score but the
benefit really is efficiency so
if you don't have a with a small sample
size, don't have a lot of events, and
you can't put too many confounders into
the model, you can't estimate too
many parameters, that propensity score
again is only one variable.
Just to give an example in that raw study
In addition to the matched analysis I
already showed you, they also did an
unmatched analysis.
They took the original cohort, remember we
have propensity scores on everybody,
even people who we weren't able to find
matches for.
And they ran a regression analysis.
This just happens to be cox regression,
but That doesn't matter,
our outcome here is death.
We put the treatment in as a predictor in
the model,
cause that's what we care about, and then
we adjust for the propensity score.
So the propensity score becomes a
continuous predictor in this model.
Now here's what's really interesting, when
they did this they start,
they stuck with the unmatched cohort, the
effect for
the Ross procedure versus the mechanical
valve, the hazard ratio,
the relative risk for death was 3.64 and
it actually was statistically significant.
So in the, this analysis, even after
adjusting for propensity score,
the Ross procedure actually looks more
harmful than the mechanical valve.
Now, this was a secondary analysis, the
matched analysis was the main one, and
the authors thought, perhaps this was
driven by the fact, this finding was
driven by the fact that, if you look at
the distribution of propensity scores, for
the Ross patients, it was pretty skewed,
it had a long right T And
so, that's skewness might be driving this
hazard ratio.
There may not have been any matches, any,
anybody similar to all of these people in
the tail, may not have had any similar,
people in the mechanical valve group, and
you can't really adjust there for, for it.
So we saw in the match analysis that there
was probably just Some people who
don't have a good comparator,
therefore you can't really completely
adjust for confounding here.
And so something's going on that's a
little funny.
But if anything, the Ross procedure is
worse then the Now I've told
you that propensity scores do not take
care of unmeasured or
residual confounding in the same way that
randomization does.
So to try to deal with a mis-measured
confounders especially if there's
something really important counfounders
that for whatever reason if you're doing
the retrospective core study, maybe those
data points, variables worked.
Measured originally, you just don't have
access to them.
something, people will do something called
a propensity score calibration.
I'm just going to briefly mention it here
just so you're aware of it.
So you could go and
take a subset of the original sample and
measure more carefully.
Detailed information on the confounders
that you care about on that sub-sample.
And you can use that information then to
exprapolate back to the entire sample,
without having to measure the more
detailed confounders on everybody.
Of course saves you time and money.
So you use this information to
statistically adjust for
these additional confounders in the
propensity score estimates of
the full datas that we calibrate those.
So taking into account that you know,
there's a certain profile of
person You go and measure the confounders
on some people.
We can predict the values of the
confounders for the rest of the data set.
We can use that to therefore adjust the
propensity score accordingly.
Then these corrected calibrated propensity
scores would be used in further analyses.
And they've taken into account these other
confounders to some extent.
I just want to end here with a little
summary of,
what are the advantages and disadvantages
of propensity scores?
So first of all, one thing I really like
about the propensity scores is it
just forces the researcher to think about
the problem of confounding by indication.
For observational treatment studies this
is such a red herring that anything that
gets the research really, researcher to
focus on that carefully is, is good.
We've already talked about where we can
reduce a large set of confounders to
a single intuitive variable which is very
helpful.
We can figure out, it reveals when there
are subjects that really,
truly can't be compared.
Or even whole groups, whole treatment
groups that you really can't compare.
It optimizes stratification and matching
as we talked about.
And, it makes statistical adjustment for
a large set of confounders possible when
you don't.
Really have enough data to fit a
regression model on so many variables.
Now the disadvantages of propensity scores
are,
as I keep saying, they're inferior to
randomization.
So they don't solve the problem of either
residual or unmeasured confounding.
However they might give researchers or
readers a False sense of security,
because you kind of feel like you've dealt
with this confounding pretty well and
you might forget about the fact that it
doesn't totally take care of confounding.
So you might get a false sense of
security.
It's not as good as a randomized trial,
and
don't, don't let your reader think it is.
also, as I've mentioned, you don't really
get a different answer.
There's not too much benefit over
traditional statistical adjustment.
In other words, if you just threw all of
the confounders into a regression model,
and adjusted for
them, you'd probably get the same beta and
p value for the treatment effect.
As if you just put the one propensity
score into that regression model.
So adjusting, statistically adjusting in a
regression model for
that propensity score doesn't really gain
you much unless You're limited in
how many confounders you can put in your
model.