Now let me me just show you with a simple
example here how these two models work.
So recall that we had some data on from a
pregnancy study.
So 38 women, who didn't have great
fertility,
were all given a treatment for fertility.
They were followed for up to two years to
see if they got pregnant.
So the outcome here was pregnancy.
And when we look carefully at that data It
did kind of look like the hazard rates
were pretty similar from month to month
fairly constant.
That would imply that an exponential model
should be a good fit.
And we can actually do a little bit more
diagnostics to
see if indeed that's the case.
It's actually difficult to take from data
and directly plot the hazard function.
There are ways to do it.
But they are all require a little bit of
hand-waving.
A little bit of assumptions to do it.
So rather than trying to directly plug the
hazard function, what I am instead
going to look at something that's simpler,
which is to get accumulative hazard plot.
And the reason that I can use the
accumulative hazard plot,
is that we have a direct relationship
between the hazard function and
the survival function shown over here in
blue.
I showed you this in an earlier module.
So it turns out if I take my Kaplan Meijer
estimates of survival and take negative
log of them, that that represents the
integral under the hazard function.
The area under the hazard function curve.
Well, if you have the area under a curve.
That is a straight line.
That indicates that the underlying hazard
is, a constant.
So, if the cumulative hazard function,
follows a straight line,
is linear, that would indicate a constant
hazard.
And, if you look at here, these are real
data so
it's not perfectly linear, but this looks
pretty close to a straight line.
So that's indicating to me that probably
the underlying hazard function is
indeed a constant.
So probably an exponential model is
going to be a good fit here.
So I went ahead and put these data, into
my computer and
ran an exponential regression and here are
the results.
So, again, the exponential model,
we're modeling the laog, hazard, as alpha
plus some betas.
In this case I have no predictors in the
model.
I'm just estimating the intercepts.
So, I get that the intercept is equal to
2.2858.
Here.
And this is not a terribly interesting
model,
because again I don't have any predictors
in it, but
I just modeled the underlying function
here, the baseline hazard function.
And because I'm working in SAS, I have to
know that to get the hazard function,
of course I'm dealing, I've modeled the
log hazard, so
I'd have to exponentiate both sides here.
>> So I would have to exponentiate my
alpha to get the hazard function, but
because I'm dealing, I'm working in SAS.
>> I also first have to know that I need
to negate that alpha before I
exponentiate To get the correct hazard
function.
And it would be clear if you exponentiated
the positive number here,
the answer would make no sense,
so just something to keep in mind to keep
track of those negative signs.
If I exponentiate negative 2.2858, I will
get the hazard rate,
the constant hazard rate, and when I do
that I get a value of about ten percent.
If you recall back to the pregnancy study
when we estimated the average
incidence rate across the whole study, it
was right about 10%.
About 10% chance of pregnancy per month,
given that you hadn't got pregnant in
previous months.
So that seems about right.
Now I want to point out a few things
about, over here about the,
what are called the fits statistics, that
we can get for the overall model.
So because we're doing maximum likelihood
estimation,
we can get a negative two log likelihood.
Hopefully you're familiar with that
already, but basically all we're doing to
get this value is we're plugging back in
the fitted value for
the intercept here, 2.2858.
And any other fitted values, fitted
parameters, we're plugging those back in.
We're actually getting a, a value for the
probability of our data.
That number might come out to be very,
very small cause there's lots of different
configurations that could have
happened in our data, but we're getting
that probability back out.
We take negative two log of it which makes
it, you know, some kind of whole, positive
number, something we can deal with better
than a teeny, tiny probability.
Because we're taking the likelihood as a
probability, so
it's something as a fraction and then we
take negative two log of that.
That's going to mean that the higher the
probability the smaller the negative 2
log likelihood.
So, making our data have a higher
probability is
going to give us a smaller negative 2 log
likelihood.
I want to point out some other statistics
that are directly related to
the negative log likelihood, that we
haven't talked about before but
that can be used to compare different
models, even unnested models.
And that is the AIC criteria, and the
AICC.
So the AIC criteria is something called,
and I'm going to pronounce this wrong,
probably, but something like Akaike, the
Akaike information criteria.
Excuse if my pronunciation is not quite
right there, but
this is another way of telling us how good
our model is, so
that we can again compare between
different models.
Say a model that is an exponential or
a model that has an additional parameter
for the weigel.
What is this AIC criteria.
That it's nothing too, different than the
negative 2 Log Likelihood.
It's just the negative 2 Log Likelihood
plus a penalty for
the number of parameters that you have in
your model.
So every time you put more parameters in
the model, your likelihood always go up,
meaning your negative 2 Log Likelihood
will always go down.
It will always look better.
But, of course, you can stuff your
parameter with,
your model with too many parameters and
just over fit it.
So the AIC give an explicit penalty for
the number of parameters in your model.
So you're just going to take the negative
two log likelihood and
you're going to add to that 2 times p.
And p is the number of parameters in the
model.
In this case we only have one parameter
that we fit in this model,
just one intercept, so we're just going to
be adding two.
To the negative 2 log likelihood.
So, the negative 2 log likelihood was
101.632.
We add 2 to that.
103.632 is the AIC.
The nice thing about the AIC is because
we've controlled for
the number of parameters, you can take
that and
compare two models that don't necessarily
have to be nested,
and whichever one has the smaller AIC,
would be considered the better model.
And you can see that, you know,
in the SAS output it even tells you
smaller is better.
So it's very helpful so you won't forget.
You want, you actually want the smaller
number here.
And in fact what we tend to use is
something called the AICC
that's a little bit preferred.
You can see they're not very different
here but
the AICC has even an additional penalty
filled in for
the fact that we have a finite sample
size, sometimes a small sample size.
And so you can see that there's a teeny
tiny additional penalty here that the AICC
is slightly bigger then the AIC an
additional penalty here.
So we're going to use these fit statistics
to compare different models.
So I went ahead with those data and then
tit, took the same data and
fit a Weibull model.
And so we're estimating one additional
parameter here and we get our intercepts,
so again the Weibull model As the
intercept plus this additional
parameter for telling us how our hazard is
changing over time.
And you actually get two things in the
output.
First, you actually get something called
the scale and something called a shape.
The shape is just the power that we've
raised t to.
But they also give you the scale, which is
just the reciprocal of the shape.
So what you're seeing in the SAS output,
one is the reciprocal of the other so
it doesn't really matter which one you
look at.
We're probably talk mostly about the scale
parameter, but
that's just the reciprocal of the shape
parameter.
If the scale parameter or
the shape parameter is one, remember this
is like the k I was talking about before,
if that's equal to one then we're back on
an exponential distribution.
You can see that they're very close to one
here, so we're probably, there's probably
nothing to gained by adding an additional
parameter for the Weibull model here.
And you can see that also with the fit
statistics.
So recall that the negative 2 Log
Likelihood for
the exponential model was equal to, I
think, 101.632.
And it got just a teeny bit smaller when
we
added the additional Weibull parameter in
there.
But it's hardly very different.
Remember to, compare two models,
two nested models You can subtract the
negative 2 log likelihood for the,
from the smaller model minus the negative
2 log likelihood for the bigger model.
That should follow a pi square.
Here, that pi square value's going to be
extremely small.
You know that's not going to be
statistically significant, so
we have no evidence that that additional
parameter adds anything to the model.
Or, even easier, you can just look at the
AIC.
Remember, smaller is better.
Well the AIC was 103 point something for
the exponential model, and
same with the AICC was about 103 point
something.
Well here, clearly they're bigger,
105, because we're putting an additional
parameter in the model,
we get that penalty without much gain in
the likelihood.
So this is telling us that probably the
exponential is the best fit here.
And just to show you what we've actually
predicted.
[COUGH] When we do parametric regression,
we actually specify the entire survival
function.
So I've actually gone ahead and plotted
them here.
So here is the survival probability on the
Y-axis.
[NOISE]
And here's time on the X-axis.
And, on the left,
I'm showing you the Weibull model, as used
in the Weibull model.
And on the right, I'm showing you the
exponential model.
You can see that they look very, very
close.
There's hardly any difference between the
two.
and compare those two to the Kaplan Meyer
curve.
They look, they're basically a smooth
version of the Kaplan Meyer curve.
We've assumed a nice, smooth mathematical
function there.
Just for fun, let me show you one more
example.
So remember that we had this data about
longevity in 1669, it wasn't so
good people were dying pretty early.
Well I, just have the,
the curve here I don't have the exact data
of exactly when people died.
But just based on this curve I made up a
data set so,
I know that 36 people died between zero
years and 60 years, so
I just kind of put them somewhere in
between those time points.
So I made up a data set that's based
roughly on this curve here for
100 people time to death in 1669.
So using this little data set, I drew a
Kaplan-Meier curve.
You can see that that looks very similar
to the actual curve that was drawn on
these data.
So here's the Kaplan-Meier curve from
these data I then
plotted the cumulative hazard function to
see if that can give
me some clue about what the hazard
function looks like, and indeed,
the cumulative hazard function here looks
like a pretty solid straight line.
It looks nice and linear, so
that's indicating that probably that this
is well modeled by constant hazard.
That's kind of interesting, because
nowadays, you know,
your hazard of death probably goes up as
you age But back then you
kind of have a constant chance of death
every year, because there were so
many things that could affect young people
as well as old people.
So this appears well modelled by an
exponential model,
because we have a constant hazard.
So if we're to had it fit these data into
an exponential model,
here the result again, there is only one
parameter here I'm just estimating that,
single survival curve for everybody.
And the intercept here came out to be
2.8785.
If I want to say, well what is that
constant hazard?
What was your chance of dying every year
in 1669?
Well, I would just exponentiate negative
of the intercept, so negative 2.8785.
The constant hazard rate was 0.056, so
people
living around that time had a 5% or 6%
chance of dying every year, not so great.
But that's the exponential model that I
fit, and then I went ahead and
since I've, I've, again, set the entire
model.
I can dry out what does that smooth
survival curve look like.
And here it is.
This is the survival curve that comes from
that model.
I get this nice smooth mathematical curve.
And, again, you can see survival was not
very good at that time,
because that curve is dropping off pretty
steeply.
[BLANK_AUDIO]