In this next module, I'm going to show you
how to control for
confounding using stratification.
This will get us into the Mantel–Haenszel
statistics.
So, getting back to the example that I
introduced in the teaser for
today, this makes a good example for
illustrating controlling for
confounding by stratification.
So, again, this example was looking at
potential gender bias in
graduate school admissions at Berkeley.
This is hearkening back to the 1970s,
but, people were worried when they saw
this data.
There was even a lawsuit and things like
that.
but, if you look at the data here, this is
some data that somebody compiled for
one of the years of admission.
The females were applying in fewer numbers
than men.
But, indeed, women were 25% more likely to
be denied admission than men and
that was the concern.
However, if you think about this example
carefully, especially back thinking about
in the early 1970s, there is an important
potential confounder here.
You have to look at what departments women
and men are applying to.
Especially back in the 1970s, there was a
big difference between where men and
women were applying and that might
influence denial in admissions rate.
And, indeed, that's what somebody went
back and did with these data.
So now we're going to stratify the data by
department,
by program that people were applying to.
And I've kept the programs anonymous, so
we won't, criticize any departments.
But you can kind of guess what these
departments might be.
So the first stratum is program A.
And what you look, can see when you look
at the data is that men were much,
much more likely than women to apply to
program A, whatever program A happened to
be, maybe it's something like mathematics
or engineering back in the early 70s.
You can see, though, that once you look
only within program A,
women were no less likely to get admitted
than men.
In fact, the risk ratio for denial of
admissions for women versus men is 0.46.
What that tells you is that, actually,
women were a little bit less likely to be
denied and that's actually statistically
significant within this strata.
So once you drill in on program, you're
seeing a different picture.
However, of course, there were very few
women that applied to this program, so
though, even though a lot got in, it still
doesn't represent a huge, number of women.
If you look at program B, you'll notice,
again, very few women applying to this
program.
It's a relatively easy program to get
into, though.
More than half of the people who apply are
getting in.
And that was similar, and stratum one was
also reasonably easy to get into.
But you can see that, again,
women, if anything, are slightly more
likely to get in than men.
The, there appears to be not much of a
difference here.
If anything, the risk ratio is slightly in
the favor of women.
But easy department to get into relatively
speaking, but
many, many more men are applying than
women.
You could see how this might create a
spurious association.
Now, turn to program C.
This program looks a little different.
Program C is dominated by women.
Many more women are applying, 593 versus
325.
Many more women are applying than men.
However, it's a relatively hard program to
get into.
So, for whatever reason,
many more than half of people who apply
are getting denied admissions.
So, a harder program to get into, but more
women are applying.
If you look at that risk ratio,
however, gender doesn't seem to make a
difference on admittance within program C.
The risk ratio is 1.05, men and women are
equally likely to get in.
If you then go to program D, women and men
were about equally likely to apply.
Again, the risk ratio is 1.02.
So not much difference in admissions
between men and women.
This was another department that was
relatively hard to get into.
If you look at program E, this one is
again dominated by women, but
hard to get into.
So women are applying to the harder
departments, basically.
393 women versus 191 men.
A lot of people getting denied.
289 denials.
147 denials for the men.
Most people are getting denied.
So hard to get into, but no real
difference between men and women.
That might be something like education or
English.
Program F, pretty equal numbers are
getting in between men and women and
this one pretty equal numbers are
applying.
Pretty equal numbers are getting in.
This apart, department was really hard to
get into.
Very few people got into it.
But women were no less likely than men to
get in.
The risk ratio in this stratum was 1.01,
right around no.
So, there were, if you look across these
six departments, you can see that if
you just report the crude, the unadjusted
risk ratio, not accounting for
programming, it looks like women are more
likely to be denied admissions.
But when you go and look at the stratum
specific relative risks,
the risk ratios, the picture is very
different.
In fact, in all cases, the women are just
about equally likely as the men to get in.
And there's one program where that's not
true, but, in fact,
the women were more likely than the men to
get in.
So the association that we were seeing in
the crude risk ratio just had to
do with the fact that women were applying
to the harder departments to get into and
men were applying to the easier
departments to get into.
Now, that's pretty much the story we can
now apply some formal statistics to
the story though and this brings int he
Mantal-Haenszel statistics.
So there's a couple of different
statistics that we're going to talk about.
So there's something called the
Mantal-Haenszel test of independence.
This is a chi-squared test.
The null hypothesis here is that the
predictor and the outcome
are independent after controlling for or
conditioning on the confounder.
So once we adjust for
program, is gender and, denial of
admissions, is, are those independent?
The null hypothesis is that they're
independent, and
when you do that statistic, it comes out
to be a p value that is non-significant.
So we have no evidence that those things
are not independent.
So we, we're not going to reject the null
hypothesis there.
It looks like they are unrelated.
We can calculate the p value test, but
then it's also nice to always be able to
provide an affect size.
So we're going to provide an affect size
by calculating what's called
a Maentel-Haenszel summary risk ratio.
All this is, is it's taking the
stratum-specific risk ratios that we
just calculated and it's pooling them.
And it comes out here to be 0.95.
Now, if you were just trying to come up
with the statistic on your own,
you might think, well,
the easiest way to do this is to just take
six risk ratios from the six strata.
Add them up and divide by six.
In other words, average them.
And that's almost what we do to pool them.
Except we want to do one little other
thing in here, which is we want to
give a heavier weight to the strata that
have a bigger sample size.
So whichever strata have more people in
them,
that should have a slightly heavier weight
on the risk-ratio estimate.
So what we do is we do a weighted average
of these risk ratios and
I'll show you the formula in a minute.
When we do that here, though, we come up
with 0.95.
The confidence interval's quite tight
around one.
That's showing you and then you can kind
of,
if you eyeball these risk ratios, it looks
like 0.95 would be a good pooling.
A good summary risk ratio.
So, again, this we would call "adjusted
for program".
When the risk ratio is adjusted for
program, we're finding no difference
between men and women.
This tells us that we thought we saw an
association between gender and whether or
not you were denied admission to Berkeley,
but, in fact, once we accounted for
confounding by program, that, association
completely disappears.
Our p value is non-significant and our
risk ratio is very close to one.
Now I'm just going to walk you
through the actual mathematical details of
these tests.
So we're going to start with the p value
test,
the Mantel-Haenszel test of conditional
independence.
This is actually a chi-squared test.
Sometimes it's called the
Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel statistic.
Sometimes an additional statistician's
name is thrown on the front.
I tend to be lazy and just call it
Mantel-Haenszel because it's shorter, but
you'll see, for example, in SAS, you have
to ask for the CMH statistic.
So the C is the Cochran.
So you'll see it both ways.
So I just want to point out you might see
it, as Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel.
Those are the same, though.
Again, the null hypothesis for this test
is that the predictor and
the outcome are independent after you've
accounted for the confounder.
So when conditioned on the confounder.
So, again, null hypothesis, that after
conditioning for
the confounder, the predictor and the
outcome are independent.
We can see that mathematically, so what do
we mean by statistical independence?
I've gone over this before, but
by statistical independence, we mean that
the joint probability of A and
B is equal to the product of the marginal
probabilities of A and B.
That's what we mean by statistical
independence.
All we're saying here is that you have to
first condition on the confounder whether
or not somebody has the confounder, if you
have a binary confounder,
as I'm showing here.
Once you condition on a confounder, then
statistical independence between A and
B holds.
That's the null hypothesis, and indeed we
saw here that when we
run the Mantel-Haenszel Test, we have no
evidence against that null hypothesis.
It, indeed, looks like they're independent
after we control for program.
Let me walk you now through all the
nitty-gritty mathematical details.
I am probably not going to make you do too
many of these by hand, because,
as you'll see, they're a little tedious to
calculate.
But I actually think it's important for
you to look into the black box here and
know what's actually happening, in terms
of calculations in this statistic.
It'll give us a little bit of insight into
the statistic to see what's going on.
It's also useful to just go through the
math here because the Mantel-Haenszel
test, we're applying it here to the
context of confounding.
But the Mantel–Haenszel test actually has
a broader application,
it's more general than that.
It's going to come up again in the Spring
term when we
talk about Kaplan-Meier statistics, so
the log rate test is actually a
Mantel–Haenszel test, same formula.
It also comes up in meta analysis, that
that gets applied to meta analysis,
that same formula.
So it's just worth you having gone through
this formula once or
twice and having a basic understanding of
what's going on here.
So let me just walk you through that, that
nitty-gritty details here.
So how do we run this test?
By hand.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to divide our
data up into the different strata.
So, by k here I mean just the number of
strata.
So there's k strata, in the Berkeley
example, there were six strata, so
k would be equal to six.
We start with, say the first stratum and
we look at,
we make a two by two table for that first
stratum as I did in the Berkeley example.
We can call those cells a, b, c, and d.
Usually, the a cell we call that, you
know, the disease exposed cell
which just means, you know, denial and
gender, the two things we care about.
And then in Nk here,
I'm going to use to represent the total
number in a particular stratum.
So we start with, say, the first strata.
And what we're going to plug into this
formula here is we're going to look at
the observed number in cell a.
Technically, we could've chosen to focus
on any one of these four cells and say,
"A, a is the most interesting, we're
going to use a".
This table has only one degree of freedom,
though,
so any of the other cells would give us
the equivalent answer.
So we're going to plug in the actual
observed number, so
this is the observed, the observed number
for
cell a in stratum k, that's all that
little subscript k means there.
We're going to do that first.
Then we're going to calculate the expected
count for that cell.
And we're going to do that in the exact
same way we've done when we've
talked about chi-squared tests.
So, to calculate the expected value of a
in a particular stratum,
we're just going to do the row one, the
row times the column,
total divided by the total in that
stratum.
That will give me the expected value of
cell a,
as we talked about when we talked about
the chi-squared statistic last week.
So I calculated that expected value.
I plug that in here and then,
notice, I am going to view this as a
summation sign here.
So I'm going to be doing this for all six
strata, or all K strata, if we want to be
more general, and I'm taking the observed,
I'm subtracting from the expected.
And then I'm adding all of those observed
minus expecteds up across all the strata,
and then I'm squaring that after the fact.
That's the numerator.
What's the denominator?
The denominator is calculated by typing
the variance of a.
Now I haven't told you how to calculate
So I'm going to give you the formula now.
Again it's a little bit tedious, but
basically we're going to calculate this
variance term for every strata and then
just add them up.
That becomes the denominator.
So here is the formula for the variance.
I'm showing you the expected value formula
here,
I've already talked about that, and here's
the formula for the variance.
It looks rather cumbersome, but this is
just row one times row two,
times column one, times column two,
divided by n squared, times n minus one.
And we do this again, specific to each
strata.
A little tedious to calculate.
I'll just tell you where this comes from.
We happened to have a situation here where
we ha-,
we are on a hyper-geometric dias-,
distribution.
That distribution comes with a variance.
And that's the variance for that
distribution.
I won't go into more detail on it,.
You're not going to have to do too many of
these by hand, fortunately.
But that is the variance of a.
So we're going to add those all up.
That makes the denominator.
This turns out to have a chi-square with
one degree of freedom distribution under
the null hypothesis.
Why is this a chi-square with one degree
of freedom?
I'm going to take a few minutes now to
just explain why this is
a chi square with one degree of freedom.
If your head is swimming with summation
tides of this,
really, just you don't care about this
mathematical detail,
it's not absolutely essential, you can
scroll forward on the video if you want.
But I just think its really cool to point
out exactly why this falls at
chi-square with one degree of freedom.
This gets a little bit mathy, but I think
is interesting to see walked through.
So where does this come from?
How come this statistic comes out to be a
chi-square with one degree of freedom?
Well, I'm just going to rewrite this
formula a little bit for you.
So, I'm going to take everything in this
square and
just leave this square for the moment.
If I'm just kind of looking at this, what
I'm
doing is I'm adding up the observed minus
the expected in each cell, each stratum.
But that's the same as just adding up all
the observed and then subtracting from
the sum of all the expected, right, I can
distribute this summation sign.
So I, another way I can write this is I
can just say that this
is the sum of the observed cells across
each, observed cells A's across each of
the different strata if I just add them
up, so it's a sum of A's.
That's my observed.
And then I'm going to rewrite my expected
term a little bit.
So I have a sum of expected values here,
but hopefully you know from a previous
statistics course that the sum of expected
values is the expected value of the sum.
OK, just bear with me for a minute more
here.
So we've got an observed minus and
expected.
If I just say, you know, that the sum of a
is the thing I care about,
I have an observed minus and expected in
the numerator.
And then what about the denominator?
Well, hopefully you remember from a
previous statistics class that the sum of
variances is the variances of the sum, if
you have independent things,
which we do have here.
So I can rewrite the denominator also as
the variance of the sum of a case.
So now we've got an observed minus an
expected squared divided by a variance.
Well, that happens to have a chi-square,
with one degree of freedom distribution.
And I can show you that very easily by
just reminding you that,
if I square root everything, I should end
up with a z-square.
So I'm now going to take the square root
of this whole term.
So I'm going to get rid of the square on
the numerator and
I'm going to take the square root of the
denominator.
So what do I have now?
I've got a sum of a, that's my observed,
minus the expected value of
that same quantity divided by the standard
deviation of that same quantity.
So I have an observed minus an expected
divided by a standard deviation.
Well, we know that an observed minus an
expected divided by its
standard deviation is just a Z statistic.
That's just a standard normal.
So we've proven that this is actually just
a Z square, but I told you last week
that if you square a Z, you end up on a
chi-square with one degree of freedom.
And so that's why this is a chi-square
with one degree of freedom.
So, again, a little bit of mathematical
detail there, but
I think useful to kind of think that
through.
Now, I'm just going to actually plug in
numbers into this formula.
You'll see that I got a little bored of
plugging in the numbers.
So, yeah, you have to back to the slides
where I give the actual numbers in all of
those two by two tables, the, you know,
first cell a, was 19 and so on and so
forth.
I started plugging them in and then I, it
was rather tedious.
So I have to admit that I didn't actually
plug and check all these numbers.
I put the data into SAS, and I let SAS
calculate out this chi-square for me.
SAS spit out 1.49.
I'm going to trust that SAS did the adding
and subtracting correctly here.
So I have a chi-square with one degree of
freedom.
My value comes out to be 1.49.
I could take that and go to a chi-square
chart, or,
of course, in SAS, I'm also going to get
the P-value spit out to me,
so SAS told me that corresponding P-value
is 0.22.
I'll just point out that you won't really
need to go to a statistical chart here to
know that this is going to be
statistically significant.
So you know a chi-square with one degree
of freedom is just a Z square and,
if I square root 1.49, I'm certainly
going to come up with something that's
less than 1.96 and we know a Z of 1.96 is
the cut off for statistical significance.
So that's one way to know that this is not
going to be significant.
You can also reach for what I talked about
last week, that a chi-square with one
degree of freedom, the expected value's
going to be one, and the variance is
going to be two times the degrees of
freedom, so that's going to be two.
So if the expected value here is one and
the variance is two, that means the
standard deviation's about 1.7.
We know that 1.49 is not going to be
anywhere near the tail of
that distribution.
So it's clear that that's not going to be
statistically significant.
Indeed, the P value comes out to be 0.22.
We have no evidence that gender and
admissions are related,
after adjusting for program.
And, agan, I got SAS to do this for me.
So, in SAS,
it's just the first row of this output of
the Mantel-Haenszel Statistic.
There are slightly different versions of
the Mantel-Haenszel Statistic, but
you can see that here, this simple case,
everything comes out the same.
We're just going to pick the first line
there.
Now, let me tell you how to calculate that
Mantel-Haenszel summary odds ratio or
risk ratio.
This, of course, only applies to two by
two tables because we can only calculate
risk ratios or odds ratios from two by two
tables.
So, a little caveat here.
We want to calculate summary odds ratios
if the relative risk,
the risk ratios of the odds ratios are
homogenous across the different strata.
That, it wouldn't, it wouldn't seem really
fair to pool them,
if there was interaction going on or
effect modification going on here.
In other words, if the relationship
between the predictor and
the outcome was different in different
strata, it doesn't seem like it would be
fair to pool them to come up with a single
summary odds ratio or risk ratio.
So we're, in a minute I'm going to show
you how to evaluate whether or
not we have interaction going on.
If we don't have interaction going on,
then it seems fair to pool them, so how
are we going to pool them?
So here's the formula [SOUND] that we're
going to use to pool them.
it's, again, a little tedious to
calculate, but
not too hard to understand, so we're just
kind of walking through what we're doing.
It's just calculating weighted average.
I'm going to start with the odds ratio
because the odds ratio,
is slightly simpler.
So what are you looking at here?
So what we're doing in the numerator is
we're, again, summing up over k strata.
So we've got, in the Berkeley example,
we have six strata, we're going to sum up
over the six strata.
So k just represents the number of strata.
The Ti I'm using to represent the total
sample size in the ith stratum, and
that's what I was calling nk before.
Same thing.
So that's the total sample size in the ith
stratum.
So we're just going to go through and
we're going to, in the numerator, we're
going to add up for each strata.
We're going to start, say, with the first
stratum, we're going to do a times d,
which is the numerator when odds ratio.
But then we're going to weight it by
dividing by the total number in that
strata, whatever that number happens to
be.
And then we're going to do that for all
six stratum and
add them up, that constitutes the
numerator.
We're going to do something very similar
in the denominator but
we're going to use b times c which is the
denominator of.
An odds ratio.
And you'll see that if you look at the
formula for
an odds ratio, it looks very similar to
the formula here,
we're just weighting by the size of the
strata, and averaging over all the strata.
So that's how you calculate the
Mantel-Haenszel summary odds ratio.
At the end of this module,
I'll walk you through an actual example if
you want to see some numbers put to that.
Now, the Mantel-Haenszel summary risk
ratio is only slightly more complicated.
So, the Mantel-Haenszel summary risk
ratio.
We're, we're going to do the same kind of
thing.
Except now you can see that the numerators
are slightly more complicated here.
W're going to take a in the first straum
for exmpale and
multiply it times the total number of
unexposed c plus d.
And then but again we're dividing by to
wait by the total in the stratum.
We're adding up over all the different
stratum.
But where does this a times c plus d comes
from actually.
If you look at the formula for a risk
ratio, it falls out on that pretty easily.
So coming to the risk ratio, we want to
know,
what is out of everybody is exposed?,
what percent that the disease.
So that's just a divided by a plus b.
For the denominator we want to know how
many,
what percent got the disease out of
everybody who was not exposed to that.
That's just c divided by c plus d.
Well if you slightly rearrange this
formula.
You end up seeing that that's equivalent
to a times c plus d in the numerator,
divided by c times a plus b in the
denominator.
And that's where we're getting these
numerators.
And the rest is the same.
We're just going to plug into that as we
would do with the odds.
Ratio.
Again,
I'll walk you through in a miracle example
in a minute.
You won't have to do too many of these by
hand.
But it's good to just see where it comes
from.
So here is, I'm actually going to walk you
through [SOUND] plugging in the data for
Berkeley example.
This wasn't too hard.
I actually went through and plugged in all
the numbers.
In the first stratum, for example,
19 was your" a cell," 933 was the total,
and 825 was the,
in this case, the total number of men who
had applied to that program.
You're going to do that for all six
strata.
And then add them up for the numerator.
Similar to for the denominator.
And when I this all, it comes out to be
0.95.
I'm not going to give you the formula to
get the confidence limits.
I am, it's it's obviously if it's this
hard to calculate the risk ratio itself,
it's going to be even more complicated.
To calculate confidence limits by hand,
you're not going to have to do that by
hand.
I'm going to allow the computer to do that
for me.
Luckily we have computers to do that for
us and indeed if I ask for
the Mantel-Haenszel summary statistics,
what I'm going to get here.
Is I'm, I want the cohort one because
that's the risk ratio I,
I don't need the odds ratio here because I
don't have a case control study.
I get that 0.95 which I just calculated,
and my confidence limits turn out to be
0.87 to 1.03 pretty tightly around 1
because they have fairly large numbers and
clearly it Includes one so this is not
statistically significant.
If you're just curious what else is in
this chart here.
This logit here just means that sas
actually went ahead and
ran a logistic regression to adjust her
program.
Something we're going to do pretty soon.
And it's spitting out the results from
that logistic regression.
we're, we don't, we're not going to choose
that from the output here.
But just notice that we can also adjust
for her program.
For the confounder by regression by
logistic regression.
Which.
We're going to do in the upcoming weeks.
Alright, so just to summarize, we started
with an adjusted risk ratio of 1.25.
It looked like being a woman was going to
to decrease your likelihood of
getting into [SOUND] Berkely Graduate
School.
The stratum specific relative risks are
shown here.
We saw that once we looked in individual
programs,
it didn't look like there was much of a
relationship.
Between gender and your admissions.
Except potentially [SOUND] in the very
first round where it looked better to
be a woman in that case.
When we calculate that [UNKNOWN] risk
ratio it comes out to
be very close to one.
Now the question that we haven't dealt
with that we need to deal with.
And I've pooled the risk ratios as if we
have
homogeneity across the different strata.
In other words, as if we don't have any
interaction or
affect modification going on here.
But you'll notice that one of the stratum
does look different.
So potentially we may have a significant
interaction by program here, so
we need to actually evaluate a test for
that.
So how do we test for effect modification
or interaction?
So in the case of just looking at
stratified contingency tables,
the test that we're going to use is
something called the Breslow-Day test
for homogeneity.
The null hypothesis here is that we have,
do not have interaction, so
that the, that is that the risk ratios or
odds ratios are homogenous.
Across the different strata.
If we reject this test, if we reject this
null hypothesis then that would indicate
that we do have interaction.
I am not going to make you do the
[UNKNOWN] test by hand.
The formula is rather complicated.
It's even worse that I've kind of
summarized it quickly here, but
it's even worse than this.
You're not going to have to do it by hand.
But it's just evaluating whether or
not the effect size is the same across the
different strata.
If the [UNKNOWN] comes up significant then
we do have effect modification.
So what happens here?
Well, I ran this in SAS, I did not do this
by hand, I ran the reso
day test in SAS and the p value d comes
out significant for the Berkeley example.
So it turns out that program, what
department.
You're applying to.
That variable is both a confounder and an
effect modifier.
And this can happen, and that's important
to really understand,
is that variables can be both confounders
and effect modifiers.
And that is what happened in this case.
So argueably, because cell a is different
than the other strata,
we might not want to report a, a pooled.
Risk ratio here because we'd be missing
something of an important effect.
So if you look again look at the stratum
specific risk ratios,
probably these all look homogeneous.
This one looks different.
And indeed, the Breslow-Day test rejects,
saying we have interaction by the program.
The program modifies the effect of gender
on admissions because this
one program looks different than the
others.
So combining the risk ratios into a single
summary risk ratio might
actually obscure that there's a pro female
bias in program A.
We're missing some things.
You always want to make sure you test for
interaction.
And if there is interaction, you probably
want to just report
the stratum specific risk ratios instead
of reporting the pooled one.
I just want to end here with another
example where I
actually go through a case control study,
just to show you how to
actually apply the Mandel Hansel odds
ratio formula numerically.
So just to give you some example data from
a case control study,
here's a study that was looking at whether
or
not, if your spouse smokes, does that
increase your risk of lung cancer?
So if you don't smoke but your spouse.
Spouse does, does that increase your risk
of lung cancer.
They did this as a case control study
because lung cancer is relatively rare,
so it's much more efficient to go out and
find lung cancer cases and
then compare them to controls.
This was done across multiple countries,
however.
And there was some concern that they might
be confounding by country,
because if you are in a country with
[UNKNOWN] with very high air pollution, or
with very high background rates of
smoking.
Perhaps whether or not your spouse smokes
doesn't make a big difference on your
lung cancer risk, whereas if you're in a
country with low background rates of
air pollution and smoking maybe it makes
more of a difference.
.
That was the thought.
So we have to consider potential
confounding.
Country.
So, here's the stratified analysis.
When you look at the individual countries
in
the strata from the individual countries,
actually,
the odds ratio comes out to be very
similar across all three countries.
It does indeed look like spousal smoking
increases your risk of
lung cancer a moderate amount.
Not a huge odds ratio.
Ratios, but somewhat.
And it looks pretty similar across the
different countries.
So the odds ratios are 1.5, 1.6, and 1.3.
In my mind, those effect sizes are pretty
similar.
And I'm not going to expect the [UNKNOWN]
test to come out significant here.
Those look fairly homogenous.
Do this.
Now I went ahead and ran all of these
statistics just for practice here.
So I ran the Cochran Mantel Haenszel test
of conditional independence.
This is the chisper test.
The null hypothesis here would be that
spousal smoking is unrelated to lung.
This comes out statistically significant.
.0196.
So therefor we have evidence that
spousal smoking is actually.
Actually related to lung cancer.
It does appear to increase your risk
somewhat.
Then I ran the Breslw-Day test of
homogeneity.
This one comes about to be
non-significant.
The P value's .88.
Well, that's expected, right,
because the odds ratios look pretty
similar across the different strata.
We don't have any evidence of interaction
by what country you're in.
That would mean that it's probably okay
to.
Calculate a summary odds ratio here.
So now I'm just going to walk you through
how to calculate that summary odds ratio.
I'll show you the SAS output, because I'm
not going to do the confidence limits by
hand, so when I do this in SAS the summary
odds ratio is about 1.38.
The confidence limits go from 1.04 to
1.82,
in other words, 1.0 is not within the
confidence interval.
This is a statistically significant odds
ratio.
I'm just going to walk you through how to
numerically how to
plug into this formula just so you've seen
it once so
here it is again the Mantel-Haenszel
summary odds ratio formula.
To plug into it I've put the data from the
three a strata here so
you can see how I'm plugging into this
formula its not too terribly hard.
So for the first strata, there was a total
of 364 people in that first strata.
To do A times D is just 73 times 82,
divided by the total which was 364.
We do that again for
the second strata, 19 times 16 divided by
total in that strata, which was 78.
And so on, and so forth.
You just plug into that formula.
When I do that I come out indeed with a.
Odds ratio of about 1.38.
And that actually makes a lot of sense,
right?
If you think about, we had odds ratios of
about 1.5, 1.6, and
1.3 from the, the three countries.
The biggest country was the US.
That's quite a bit, has a quite a bit
bigger sample size, so
we think that the weighted average should
be a little closer to the US value of 1.3.
But it's going to be a little bit higher
1.3 because the other countries had
slightly higher values.
So 1.38 makes good sense as being a
reasonable summary odds ratio here.
And I'll just end by saying that you're
not going to see a lot of
Mantel-Haenszel statistics in a lot of
papers.
You're probably not going to end up
publishing a paper that
uses Mantel-Haenszel statistics.
That's simply because we can do most of
the adjustment for confounding and testing
for interaction within a regression, which
is what we're going to do in the next.
Next couple of weeks.
But I still think it's actually useful to
walk through the Mantel-Haenszel test,
because sometimes it's actually nice to go
back to looking at
something in a stratified analysis.
It's a little bit more hands on and
a little more intuitive than just throwing
things in a regression.
As I mentioned earlier, also,
the Mantel-Haenszel test is more general
than just controlling for confounding.
So it's going to come up in some other
contexts.
And then, finally.
I think just looking through the
Mantel-Haenszel and
the stratification picture gives you
an intuitive sense of how we adjust for
confounding.
How we adjust for confounding is actually
simiilar in the regression picture.
So in the stratified analysis,
what we're doing is we're saying we're
going to hold smoking [UNKNOWN].
We're only going to compare smokers to
smokers.
And we're only going to compare nonsmokers
to nonsmokers.
When we then move to continuous
confounders, which we will do in
the regression picture, it's going to be
very similar, except,
when we're talking about continuous
confounders, what we're literally meaning,
that, mathematically, what we're Staying
in the regression model is something like.
If I'm adjusting for age for exmaple.
I only want to compare twenty year olds to
twenty year olds.
Or I only compare 21 year olds to 21 year
olds.
Of course your dataset may not have a
whole bunch of twenty year olds or
it might not have a bunch of 21 year olds.
So you're not litereally comparing them
form year sample, but
your mathematically setting up a model.
That allows you to say I only want to I
want a whole age fix, and
only compare people of the same ages.
Essentially that's what we're doing in
regression to sort of
we're taking the limit of what we were
doing in the stratified picture.
So it's kind of nice to see the, the
stratified methods first because what
we're doing in the regression is actually
very similar but just a.
Its a taken a a step further.