So, that's all there really is to the
multinomial logistic regression.
But now we want to tell you a little about
the map behind it and what the likelihood
function actually looks like to help you
understand it a little bit better.
So, we call that,we have
learned previously about the binomial
distribution.
So if we had a variable that was
distributed in a binomial distribution
with an N, of a sample size of N and a
probability of a positive event of
P then the probability that we would get
exactly X positive events was equal to n,
choose x, p the probability of a positive
event raised to
the number of positive events, and then
one minus p raised to n minus x,
so you've seen that probability
distribution before, the binomial.
The multinomial I'm going to show you in
just a second here,
looks an awful lot like a binomial.
It's just a generalization of the binomial
distribution.
So that we are no longer constrained to
having two potential outcomes.
We now can have three outcomes or four
outcomes.
I'm just going to show you the the formula
when we have three outcomes.
It gets a little bit cumbersome after you
get more than three.
But let me show you now the probability
formula for three outcomes.
So for on a multinomial distribution,
there are more than two possible outcomes.
So let me just give an example.
Imagine we're in a room of 100 people, and
we know there's going to be
some democrats, some republicans, and some
green party members there.
And we know what tho,
the probability of each of those different
types of people is going to be.
So in this case, my.
I have 100 trials, my n is 100, and let's
say I want to know what is
the probability that I get exactly 45
democrats in the room.
Exactly 40 republicans, and exactly five
green party members.
That's one potential outcome in this room
of 100 people.
There's a lot of possible outcomes, so
the probability of this exact outcome may
not be very high.
But what is that probability?
So, according to the multinomial formula
it's going to be n
factorial divided by x factorial, x is
going to be 45 for the democrats.
Divided by y factorial which will be 40
factorial divided by 5 factorial.
So that looks an awful lot like the
coefficient like a regular old binomial
which was just n factorial divided by n
minus x factorial divided by x factorial.
So that was the, the coefficient from a
binomial.
We've just expanded that to have more than
two possible outcomes in the denominator.
That coefficient will then be multiplied
by the probability of being a Democrat,
whatever that is, raised to 45 so that
that's number we actually saw.
Times the probability of being a
Republican raised to 40 and
then times the probability being a green
party member.
These three probabilities have to add up
to one.
So, the probability of being a green party
member is going to be
1 minus the probability of a being of a
democrat minus the probability of
being a republic and we are going to raise
that to five.
That will give us the exact the
probability of getting exactly 45
democrats, 40 republicans and five green
party members in that room of 100.
I don't expect you to calculate
multinomial probabilities by hand, but
I just wanted to show you that it looks an
awful lot like the binomial formula.
So it should be a little bit familiar to
you.
Well, the way that we built the
likelihood.
Function for regular logistic regression
was just based on binomial probability.
Similarly, we're going to be building the
likelihood function for
multinomial logistic regression, built
based on multinomial probabilities.
That's the idea.
But let me just review for
you, because this is good review.
What does the likelihood function look
like when we're
just talking about regular binomial
logistic regression?
So go back now to the two models that I
talked about.
So let's just for a minute talk about
we're going to be fitting two separate
likelihood functions when we talk about a
series of binary logistic regressions.
We'll be fitting a likelihood for model
one, and that's an outcome of [UNKNOWN],
and we'll be fitting likelihood for model
two, that was [UNKNOWN].
So we'll actually have two separate
likelihood functions that we'll have to
solve separately.
That will look a little bit different from
what we see in the multinomial case.
But for model one we have to we're, we're
trying to estimate the intercept for
the [UNKNOWN] outcome and the beta for the
[UNKNOWN] outcome.
And that's what we're trying to estimate.
We do that by fitting a likelihood.
What's going to go in the likelihood?
So the likelihood, the term that's
going to go in the likelihood for
all [UNKNOWN] is the exact same
probability term we've been dealing with
all along here.
It's going to look like the following.
Right, so that's the predicted
probability that a woman will have
amenorrhea.
So all 13 women who have a amenorrhea,
they're going to get
a term in the likelihood that represents
the probability of having amenorrhea,
cause they actually did have it.
Of course the terms are all going to be
slightly different for these 13 women,
cause we're going to plug in their
individual EDIA score.
Some of them may have the same value
there, but
some of them may have different values.
Those women get those terms in the
likelihood.
If you're unamenorrheic, you're going to
get a term in the likelihood that
represents the probability of not having
amenorrhea, and that's going to look like
the following predicted probability that
we've again seen before.
Same denominator, but we have a one in the
numerator.
So that represents the hundred women who
were eumenorrheic,
who did not have amenorrhea.
We'd be plugging in again their individual
EDIA values.
We're going to end up here with 113 things
multiplied together,
we will then solve that likelihood, or the
computer will solve that likelihood to
find out the exact values the best, most
likely values of the intercept and better.
We've all, we've seen this before, this
should be just review.
Coming over here, when we fit this model
for
oligomenorrhea The likelihood function is
going to look like the following.
We're fitting an intercept for a oligo
amenorrhea and
a data for a oligomenorrhea.
All the 37 women who are oligomenorrhea
when
in this data set will get a term that
looks like this in their likelihoods,
because they actually do have the outcome
of oligomenorrhea.
And all the women who are umetiquerial
get a term where there's a one in the
numerator, but the same denominator.
And of course, again, there's going to be
137 terms,
things multiply together in this
likelihood function.
Each women cancer own EDAI value plugged
in but we'll
use this likelihood on the computer, well,
to solve for the alpha and the beta here.
So, that's just review.
Now, lets turn to what the likelihood
function looks like for
the multinomial case.
In the multinomial case,
there are three types of terms that are
going to go in the likelihood.
The term for the amenorrheic woman is
going to look different for,
from the term from, for the
oligomenorrheaic women and
it's going to look different from the term
for the eumenorrheaic women.
And I'll be representing the interseper-,
remember,
trying to estimate two intercepts here,
one for amenorrhea, one for
oligomenorrhea, and two betas, one for
amenorrhea and one for oligomenorrhea.
So four things we're trying to estimate.
So what is the term for the amenorrheaic
women going to look like?
So first of all, let's do the denominator.
In the denominator, we're going to put the
following: e raised to al,
alpha a plus b the 8 times, eba, ebai,
that's your score.
That's one terminated denominator.
That represents the odds being
amenorrheic.
We are also going to put in the
denominator the odds of
being oligomenorrheic.
And then, we are going to put a one.
Basically now we have three things in the
denominator.
This represents your odds of being
eumenorrheic, of being oligomenorrheic,
and being amenorrheic.
You have to be one of those three things.
So to get the probability that you're one
of these three things, the probability of
being amenorrheic, we're just going to
move up the term that represents this,
these types of women in the numerator.
So, the amenorrheic women will get the
following.
The, it looks a lot like the probabilities
that we were fitting for
regular logistic regression but
we have three things in the denominator
now and three traces for the numerator.
The amenorrhea women, their probability
would be e raised to alpha a,
plus beta a, times their edi score, over
this denominator.
That's for the amenorrheic women.
There's 13 of them.
The oligomenorrheic women, they're
going to have the same denominator, so the
combination of these three types of women.
But in the numerator, they're going to get
the term
that represents the oligomenorrheaic
women, this is the odd of oligomenorrhea.
So that, if you divide this by the
denominator you get,
you're going to actually get the
probability of being oligomenorrheic.
All the women who are oligomenorrheic,
they are 37 of them will get this term in
the likelihood of course with their
individual scores plugged in.
The eumenorrheic women will have the same
denominator but
with a one in the numerator.
So those will be all
the different terms in the likelihood.
So now there's three kinds of terms in the
likelihood.
We're going to use that likelihood to
again solve for those alphas and betas.
Now the one thing that's a little bit
different here than what I showed you on
the previous slide, is that we've had, we
have an additional constraint that's been
applied by putting all of these women
together in the same model.
And that constraint is that we have our,
we know the probability of being
amenorrheic Plus the probability of being
oligomenorrheic plus the probability of
eumenorrheic, that has to sum up to one.
That's a constraint that didn't exist when
we ran separate models.
When we ran the separate models,
then the probability of being amenorrheic
plus the probability of eumen,
being eumenorrheic had to add up to one in
the first model.
And then separately the probability of
being [UNKNOWN] plus the probability of
being [UNKNOWN] also had up to had to add
up to one in their own model but
their was no constraint on all three
probabilities.
So that's why when you run everybody
together in a single multi
nomial regression you actually do get
slightly different values because of
this additional constraint but that's what
the likelihood function looks like.
I just want you to see it.
So that you have some picture of what's
going on behind the scenes and
what's slightly different about doing
multinomial logistic regression
than regular logistic regression.
Also, you need to know these terms in the
likelihood because in order to calculate,
to be able to calculate individual women's
predictive probabilities.
So, we are now, we are going to actually
calculate predictive probability.
For each woman.
Every woman gets three predicted
probability because there're
three possible outcomes now.
So what's the predicted probability of
being amonorea?
Well, that's just the, the term that I
showed you from the likelihood from
the previous slide except yeah, we've
actually fit the model.
We actually know what the alphas and the
betas are.
So the alpha for the intercept for the
amenorrheic women is negative 31.9.
The data was 0.1656.
So, I just actually plugged in the actual
values for the alphas and the betas now.
This will give me the predictive
probability of the amenorrheic.
The next term will give me the predictive
probability of being oligomenorrheic and
the last one will give me the predictive
probability of being eumenorrheic.
Let me just actually plug in a particular
score, edi score to show how this works.
So say that a woman has an eating disorder
score of nine we would plug her
value into each one of these terms to get
her predicted probabilities.
For all three possible outcomes.
When I plug in nine to the term, the
predictive probability being amenorrhea,
I get a value of about 10 or 11%.
So she has a 10 or 11% chance of being
amenorrheic according to our model.
She has a 30 about 31% chance of being
oligomenorrheic.
According to our model and about a 58%
chance of being eumenorrheic.
Now, notice if I add up those three
probabilities, they will have to sum to 1.
So, that's that additional constraint in
there.
Now, just to show you in the actual data
set when we are not accounting for
the eating disorder score.
Well remember there was a 13 out of a 150
women who are a,
amenorrheic and 24 out of a 150 women were
eumenorrheic.
So, so about 8% for amenorrheic and about
24% oligomenorrheic.
So if you knew nothing about the women,
your, the predicted probability for
a random woman where we didn't know her
eating disorder score, her probability of
being amenorrheic would be about eight or
nine percent and her probability.
being, amenorrhea could be about 24%.
Now, this woman because she has a, an
elevated score.
She has a higher predictive probability of
having one of
these menstrual irregularities.
Now, you are not going to have to
calculate these predictive probabilities
by hand.
Obviously, it's a little cumbersome.
But the computer will go through and will
calculate these predicted probabilities
for every woman in your data set and so
I've done that here and
I'm just showing you a subset of the
predicted probabilities so
woman who had EDIA scores of nine had
these predicted probabilities which I
just showed you on the previous slide.
Women who had edi scores of 11 would have
even higher predictive probabilities of
being either amenorrheic or
oligomenorrheic.
Lower probability of being in the
reference group.
And so on, if you go down to the highest
possible eating disorder, which was 21.
Those amen would have three, 32% chance,
almost a third chance
of being amenerrheic of 43% chance of
being oligamanerrheic only less than a 25%
chance of having a normal period of your
score is so high on that eating disorder.
Scale.
We can then take the predictive
probabilities and
then actually graph them.
And I think the graph is very visually
useful.
So what this graph is showing you is here
is the EDI,
the eating disorder score on the X axis.
It goes again from zero to 21.
On the Y axis we're showing, all the
predicted probabilities,
[SOUND]
for the three groups.
So, this is your predicted probability.
eumenorrheic your predicted probabiliy in
red, of being oligomenorrheaic.
And your predicted probability in blue.
Of being amenorrheaic.
So if you have a very low eating disorder
score, if you have a score of zero,
you have a very low probability of being
amenorrheaic,
still some probability of being
oligomenorrheaic, but
not high, and you're most likely going to
be, have a normal cycle.
As you go up in EDIA score,
what you see happens is there's a drop in
your chances of having a normal cycle.
There's an increase in your chances of
having one of these two
menstrual irregularities, but you'll
notice that the curve for amenorrhea goes
up more steeply than the curve for
aligametareia that's because there's
a tighter relationship between this eating
disorder score and your chances of being
amatareiac than there is between the score
and your chances of being aligamaneriac.
So this is just a nice way to kind of
visually summarize our logistic or
multinomial logistic regression model.
[SOUND]