In this next module,
I'm going to review the statistical test
that we can use when we want to analyze
data in the two by two table specifically
when we have independent observations.
Uncorrelated data.
That's the most common situation.
So, on this module, I'm going to be
talking about the risk difference and
relative risks, that is odds ratio and
risk ratios, as well as the chi-squared
test because,
of course, the chi-squared test can also
be applied to a two by two table.
The example I'm going to be using for this
module, there's some data that comes from
a randomized control trial of probiotic
supplementation during pregnancy.
So, pregnant women were supplemented with
probiotics, or given a placebo.
And the idea was that this might prevent
eczema in the infant.
So after the infant was born,
they might be less likely to get eczema
during the first year of life.
So, that's the data that's shown here.
This table's got a lot of stuff in it, so,
what I'm going to do for
now is just zoom in on the unadjusted
part, just kind of the raw numbers.
So, the outcome here was a binary outcome.
The infant either got eczema, some point
during the first year of their life, or
they did not.
We had two groups: a probiotics groups,
that where the mother got the probiotics
during pregnancy, or a placebo group.
There were 33 in the, in the probiotics
group and 35 in the placebo group.
And you can see, if you just look at the
raw numbers here, that indeed, fewer
infants in the probiotics group got eczema
sometime during the first year of life.
The p-value for the difference here is
0.029.
I'm going to walk you through where that
p-value comes from now.
So we can put these data into a nice
little two by two table.
Everything in this module is going to be
about analyzing data from a simple two
by two table.
So we have a Treatment group and
a Placebo group, and the infant either got
eczema or they didn't.
So two binary and, binary outcome of
binary predictor here.
You can see that 36% of it treatment group
got eczema versus 62.9% of
the placebo group.
If we want to compare those two numbers,
those two proportions or
risks we're going to do what's called a
difference in proportions z test.
You might also call it a risk difference.
So this is very simple, we just.
We have a two observed proportions, and we
want to compare them and to see whether or
not we can reject the null hypothesis that
those proportions are equal.
Difference in proportions follows a normal
distribution so
we are going to be calculating a z square
here, so
that's the z squared because we know that
proportions follow a normal distribution.
We're going to just be putting in
the numerator here the observed difference
that 36% versus the 63%.
That's what we observed we're going to
compare that to this standard error of
the difference.
The standard error of the difference is
this formula here.
Hopefully this is familiar to all of you.
It just comes from the fact that we have
proportions coming from two roots.
That's why we have sort of two items here
under that square root.
And then the variability,
the standard deviation of a proportion is
related to p times 1 minus p.
Now, a small little subtle note in here
for our hypothesis test,
we're going to use what's called p bar.
That's just the pooled proportion.
All that means is it's nothing
complicated.
It just means we're going to look at the
total proportion of people who had
the outcome in our total sample, ignoring
group.
In other words, how many infants, overall
got eczema?
In this case, it was 34 out of 68 infants
got eczema, so
our pooled proportion in this case, is
just 0.5.
The reason we use a pooled proportion is
because our null hypothesis
here is at the.
Two proportions are equal,
therefore we're assuming that there's a
single proportion here.
When, we don't have different proportions
in the two groups,
we're assuming they're equal, therefore we
can just pool them and plug in p bar here.
That gives us a z score.
We can then look up the p-value that goes
with that.
So that's to test the hypothesis of
whether or
not the, those two proportions are equal.
We can also build a 95% confidence in all
for the difference in proportions.
We do that by, take the point estimate,
the observe difference in proportions
which is about 0.6, 0.5% here.
Add or subtract 1.96.
The 1.96 comes from the fact that we're on
a z distribution.
And then we multiply that by the standard
error.
A small subtlety here is that notice when
I'm doing the confidence interval.
I'm plugging in the individual proportions
from the individual groups.
So notice that these proportions are the
actually the observe proportions in
each group.
I'm plugging in the different proportions.
The 30.
6% versus the 63% here.
Rather than the pooled proportion.
Simply because we have no assumption when
we're building the oncifdance interval
that those two proportions are going to be
equal.
Now if you plugin the pool proportion here
on
the observe proportions in the hypothesis.
It's not going to make a huge difference
in your estimates.
It's only going to make a subtle tiny
little difference.
And for the most part, after this week,
you'll just be doing this on a computer.
And the computer will take care of that
detail for you.
But I just want to point out that subtle
difference here.
So I, I want you now to go ahead and run
the hypothesis test.
Calculate the z score.
That z score should, of course, come out
ca-, correlating to a p value of 0.029.
Calculate the z score here for the
difference in proportions.
I actually want you to pause the video and
try this on your own.
And then restart the video and I'll walk
you through it again.
I'm assuming that this is largely review
for most of you.
Alright, so this is fairly straight
forward.
Again, we are just going to apply that
formula where we are calculating a z
score based on our observed difference.
So our observed difference is 62.9% minus
36.4%.
I'm putting the larger group first, just
so
that I don't end, end up with a negative.
It doesn't matter whether you make it
negative or positive.
So I'm avoiding dealing with the negative.
And then my standard error is going to be
p times 1 minus p.
Again I'm going to use the pooled
proportion.
Just half the infants got eczema overall.
So that's 0.5 times 1 minus 0.5 divided by
the sample size in one group
plus 0.5 times 1 minus 0.5 divided by the
sample size in the second group.
If you just run through the actual math on
that, crank that into a calculator,
you'll see that the z score comes out to
be 2.18.
We call know that if the z score's above
1.96.
That's going to be statistically
significant at the point of five level.
Indeed, if you go to a z calculator, you
will,
in fact, find that the p value that
corresponds to a z value of 2.18 is 0.029,
exactly what the authors reported in their
paper.
That's the two tail p value, and of
course,
we're going to want to use the two tail p
value here, because there's no reason.
That the probiotics couldn't of actually
increased the risk of eczema that could,
that's biologically possible.
Now, I'm just going to show you some
output from a computer program.
I plugged these data into SAS and just to
show you what you get out of SAS,
the key value that's associated with a
difference in proportion.
Now notice that where I'm actually getting
this out of
this SAS output point is chi-square.
It doesn't say difference in proportions
z-test, but
notice the p value is exactly the same as
we just calculated.
In fact, mathematically,
the chi square test from a two by two
table is mathematically equivalent to
the difference in proportion z-test that
we just did.
So we will get exactly the same p value.
So in fact, in sas there's no separate
line for
that, you just take the p-value from the
chi-square.
Alright, now I want you to attempt to
build the 95% confidence interval for
the risk difference using the formula that
I already gave you.
Again, pause the video, see if you can do
this on your own, because again,
this should be review, and then restart
the video and I'll walk you through it.
Okay, so to build the 95% confidence
interval here,
we're just going to use the observed
difference in proportion, which was 26.5%.
That is if I subtract 62.9% minus 36.4%.
I get 26.5%.
That's the risk difference.
The absolute risk difference between the
two groups.
I'm going to add and subtract from that
the 1.96 from the 95% confidence interval.
Times the standard error.
The standard error here.
Again, I'm going to plug in just the
observed proportions in each group.
So, 1 minus 0.364 and
the treatment group divided by 33.
Plus 0.629 times
1 minus 0.629, divided by 35 for the
placebo group.
If you crank out the math on that, this.
Standard error comes out to be about
0.117.
And so you add and subtract that from the
26.5%.
You end up with a confidence interval of
3.6% to 49.4%.
So indeed that confidence interval does
not cross zero.
So we're 95% sure that the true value is
not zero.
So in other words,
we can clearly reject the null hypothesis
that the two groups are the same.
If you want to get this in SAS, you can
ask for the risk diff option, and
it will actually give you you can see at
the bottom here, the difference in risk.
And the conf-, the standard error and the
95% confidence interval,
these are exactly as we calculated in the
last slide, except for
that their SAS goes out to a few more
decimal places.
I'll just note that SAS says something
about it
being an asymptotic 95% confidence limit.
All that means.
Is that we are assuming that we have a
large enough sample that it's okay to
approximate the binomial with the normal.
That's essentially what we're doing when
we calculate standard in
the way we just did in the last line.
That's probably fine here.
Our sample isn't terribly small for much
smaller samples you're
going to want to instead use what is
called an exact 95% confidence limits.
That simply calculates the confidence
limit based on the exact
binomial probabilities rather than doing
any approximation.
SAS does not give this to you if you don't
ask.
I didn't ask here, but in cases where you
have small,
much smaller samples, you might want to
ask for those exact confidence limits.
I want to also show you that you can also
use a chi-squared test to analyze a two by
two table.
I'm, again, assuming that most of you have
seen a chi-square test before, so
this would be largely review.
So, how do we do a chi-squared test for a
contingency table?
We need to calculate, we have the observed
table on the top here.
We need to calculate the expected counts
in order to run a chi-squared test.
So where do those expected counts come
from?
Well, the null hypothesis here is that
which group you're in, treatment versus
control, is unrelated, is independent
from, whether or not you get eczema.
So we can say that there, the two, our two
variables, call them A and B.
So A being what treatment group you're in,
B being whether or not you get eczema.
So we're going to say that those two
variables are independent of one another.
And in statistics, being independent means
statistically,
that your joint probability, the
probability of both of
those things happening is equal to the
product of the marginal probabilities.
That's what statistical independence is
defined as.
So in other words, if these two variables
are independent, then the likelihood that
you have both things happen that you're
both in the treatment group and
that you get eczema.
Should be equal to the probability of
getting eczema overall,
the marginal probability of getting
eczema, tied up time,
times the marginal probability of being in
the treatment group.
So that's the, the theory that we're
going to use to
calculate the expected values here under
the null hypothesis.
So, if the null hypothesis is true, and we
do indeed have independence,
then it should be the case that your
chance of being in this cell,
the treated and get eczema cell should be
equal to 34 out of 68.
That's your marginal probability of
getting eczema.
Where did I get that?
That just comes right from the margins.
Times your chance of being in the
treatment group was actually 33 out of 69.
The two groups were not.
Completely even here, there is a slightly
different sample size.
So, if we multiply those two probabilities
together,
that should give us the probability of
being in this particular cell,
what we call cell A, the treated plus gets
eczema group.
Now, in, for
doing chi-squared tests we actually don't
want the probability we want the counts.
So what I'm additionally going to do here
is I'm going to multiply by 68
by the total count.
If I multiply that probability by the
total count,
I'm going to get the count for that cell,
the expected count for that cell.
Notice one of the 68s will cancel.
So a very simple way to get these expected
values is just to take the row total and
the column total, multiply them together,
and then divide by the total sample size.
If you do that math, you get a value of
16.5.
So our expected value under the null
hypothesis,
if there's no relationship between
treatment and eczema, is 16.5.
Now notice that I don't have to do any
more multiplication.
To fill in the rest of this table.
So the marginal totals are fixed.
Those are not allowed to change.
The ones I've filled in,
the 16.5, I can subtract 34 minus 16.5 to
get this cell should be 17.5.
And then I subtract 35 minus 17.5 to be
able to fill in this cell.
And finally I subtract 33 minus 16.5 to be
able to fill in that cell.
So this table has what we call one degree
of freedom only.
That all that means is by the time I've
multiplied out to figure out one cell,
the rest of the cells are fixed, they
can't be anything else,
because of the fact that the marginals are
fixed.
So, this table only has one degree of
freedom which means I save myself work
cause I only have to really do any work
for one particular cell.
So those are the expected values for that
table, we're then going to
apply the chi-square formula, to compare
the observed in the expected cells.
Notice that you know, there's a few more
people in the treatment,
there's, you know, in the expected value,
the treatment in eczema group has 16.5.
We actually observed only 12.
So there's a little bit fewer people in
the,
infants in the treatment group with
eczema.
So it's a little bit different than the
observed.
Is it enough to be statistically
significant?
And we can answer that question by
applying the chi-squared formula, so
this is just if we're going to add up for
all the sales observed minus expected
squared divided by the expected.
And I went ahead and
plugged all those numbers in from the four
sales on the previous slide.
When you calculate that out, you get a
value of 4.77 for the chi-squared.
This is a chi-squared with one degree of
freedom for the reasons I just mentioned.
Just know the other way to know the
degrees of freedom.
For a contingency table is, you do, rows
minus 1 times columns minus 1.
In this case, we have two rows and we have
two columns,
because it's a two by two table, so our
degrees or freedom will be 1.
So that's your shorthand for figuring out
the degrees of freedom.
Achi-square with one degree of freedom, if
that value is 4.77,
if you go look that up in a.
Chart a chi-square chart you will find
that you get a p value of
exactly 0.029 exactly what we got from the
difference in proportions test, and
notice that if you go back and look at the
z value.
That we got from the difference in
proportions test.
That was 2.18.
If you square that,
you get exactly 4.77 with a little there
may be some rounding error in there.
So, the chi-square with one degree of
freedom comes out to be exactly the square
of the z statistic that we calculated from
the difference in proportions.
In fact, you can prove that those tests,
even though the formulas look
very different, they're mathematically
equivalent,
the chi-square is just the square of
disease statistic.
They're mathematically the same.
And just as a note, the chi-square
distribution in fact, if you take the z
distribution and you square it, that is a
chi-square with one degree of freedom.
And I'll talk a little more about that
when we get to the module on chi-squares.
But just note a chi-square distribution is
defined as a chi-square with one
degrees freedom is defined as a standard
normal variable squared.
So there's a direct relationship there.
And again, the chi-square test for a two
by table,
mathematically equivalent to the z test or
that the difference in proportions.
And so that's why in SAS we actually just
use the p-value from the chi-squared test.
So again, here is that p-value from the
chi-squared test.
It comes out to be 0.29.
We already saw this output.
Now, other things that you can calculate
from a two by two table that I need to
mention, what we've calculated so far are
absolute risks differences.
We've looked at the absolute of eczema in
each group.
Arguably the absolute risks are more
relevant.
To patients and to people, it, people can
understand the absolute risks
more easily and they're less likely to be
misleading.
So I encourage people to report absolute
risks in their papers whenever possible.
However, if you look at the medical
literature,
in fact you'll much more commonly see the
relative risks reported.
Things like risk ratios and odds ratios,
so
I'm going to talk a little bit about what
those are.
Again, I'm assuming you've seen these
before so
I'm going to go through this rather
quickly.
So, what is a risk ratio?
A risk ratio is just a ratio of two risks,
so it's very, very simple to calculate.
We're just going to take the risk of
getting eczema in the treated group,
that goes in the numerator, we're going to
compare that to the risk of getting
eczema in the reference group, the control
group that goes in the denominator.
That gives us a relative risk of 0.58.
That's interpreted as we can say there's a
42% decrease in the relative risk Risk, of
getting eczema if you were in the treated
group versus the control group here.
I'm not going to go through the math on
how I
calculated the 95% confidence interval.
It's, it's not hard to do, but
it's a little tedious, so we'll just let
the computer calculate it out for us.
I'll just note that the 95% confidence
interval here.
Does not cross one, and for
a risk ratio, a value of one would
indicate no difference between the groups.
That's the null value.
So, the fact that it doesn't cross one
tells you that it's going to be
a statistically significant risk ratio.
Risk ratio is very straightforward, makes
absolute sense in the contexts of
these data that we're looking at to report
the risk ratio.
However, when you actually go and look at
the table that I showed you earlier,
we're going to look at it more detailed in
a minute.
You'll see that authors don't report the
risk ratio,
they report something called the odds
ratio.
Now the odds ratio is this very funny
measure that is going to come up,
all the time in the medical literature, as
well as, in this class, for
reasons I will get to.
The odds ratio is literally a ratio of two
odds.
So, what's an odd?
An odd is the risk of something happening,
divided by the risk of it not happening.
That's what an odds is.
Probability divided by 1 minus the
probability.
So in other words, if the risk of
something happening is say 25%,
then your odds is going to be 1 to 3.
There's one chance of it happening for
every three chances of it not happening.
So it's the probability divided by 1 minus
the probability.
So, 25% divided by 75%, or 1 to 3.
So we're going to make a ratio of two odds
here.
So what are the, what's the odds of
getting eczema in the treatment group?
Well, the risk of getting eczema in the
treatment group is 36.4%, so the odds of
getting eczema in the treatment group is
going to be the probability of getting it
divided by the probability of not getting
it, which is 1 minus 36.4%.
Again, very funny measure, most of us
don't think in odds.
Odds happen to have some nice mathematical
properties,
however, which is why the odds ratio comes
up.
So, the numerator is the odds of getting
eczema for the treated group.
The denominator, similarly, is the odds of
getting eczema in the control group.
So, 62.9% divided by 1 minus minus that.
When you calculate that all out, you get
this value 0.34.
What does that value actually mean?
Well, you would interpret this, as a, 66%
decrease in the relative odds.
Of getting eczema.
And if you tell that to a patient, if you
tell to that a person, you know,
you're going to decrease your odds by 66%,
nobody is really going to know what you
mean by that.
Most of us are use to thinking in chances,
probabilities or risks, not in odds.
So this can lead to some the odds ratio
can lead to mis-interpretations.
It can be misleading.
Because you might see this 0.34 and
think that that means a 66% decrease in
your risk, but it does not.
I'm going to talk more in the next module
about being careful about
interpreting odds ratios.
Notice the 95% confidence interval for the
odds ratio is also here.
I'll show you in the next module how to
calculate that.
But again, it does not cross one,
that tells you that it is statistically
significant.
Now again, you're probably wondering,
if you've never seen odds ratios before,
or even if you have seen them,
you're probably wondering why do we ever
use odds ratios?
Well there, there's some, there are some
reasons for that.
But what I'll show you.
This is by the ways where you get this in
the SAS output though.
Just to show you that you
can get a computer to calculate these
things for you.
The computer, SAS automatically calculates
for
you the odds ratio as well as the risk
ratio.
It even tells you, well gee, you know,
you really only need the odds ratio if
your dealing with a case control study.
For a two by two table, but it gives you
those confidence limits so
it saves you having to calculate those by
hand,
again SAS has gone out to a few more
decimal places here.
I'll also just provide for you for those
of you who are interested,
the SAS code that I used to generate the
output in this module for
those of you who are interested in trying
this in SAS on your own.
Here is SAS code.
I've actually entered the data as grouped
data so
all that means is notice that I only
really entered four lines of data code.
There's only four different types of
infants in this study.
And I've entered it as grouped data by
just giving it count so
I don't have to type this line 1112 times.
That's just a shorthand in SAS, or any
statistical program, for
entering data that's from, you know, a
contingency table.
So I'm just going to put that up there for
those who are interested.
I don't want to dwell on it but
getting back now to that data from the
actual paper.
So here's that table three from the paper
again.
We already looked at the unadjusted
numbers, but
now I want to look at the highlighted area
here, the adjusted numbers and
this is where an odds ratio suddenly pops
up.
So, OR here stands for odds ratios so
that.
This is adjusted odds ratio.
So notice that even though it would make
total sense here to report a risk ratio,
because we've got risks, what you, in
fact,
what the others have in fact reported is
an odds ratio.
The reason they did that -
you can see the reason in the footnote for
this table, they say the p-value was
calculated by multivariable logistic
regression analysis.
So, the reason there's an odds ratio here
is because the authors have
a binary outcome and they want to adjust
for some confounders.
To do a statistical adjustment, we have to
use regression.
And the typical regression that people use
when you have a binary outcome,
is logistic regression.
Logistic regression is what we're going to
focus on a lot in this class,
but when you do a logistic regression,
what it gives you out at the end of the
day are odds ratios.
It does not give you risk ratios,
it gives you odds ratios, there's
mathematical reasons for that.
But the upshot is, because lots of people
do logistic regression,
there are lots of odds ratios floating
around in the literature and
we have to be very careful again about how
we look at these.
The reason the odds, this was a randomized
trials so,
arguably, the authors probably shouldn't
have needed to adjust for
confounding but perhaps they've adjusted
for antibiotic use.
Breastfeeding and caesarean section
perhaps those were slightly imbalanced in
these two groups since it was a small
randomized trial.
When they do the adjustment the odds ratio
goes down slightly so
the unadjusted odds ratio was 0.34.
It goes down to 0.24 when you adjust for
these other things.
The p value is about the same as before.
So we end up with an odds ratio and
again you have to be careful about you
interpret this.
So, you wouldn't want to look at this odds
ratio and
say, oh, well that means that after
adjusting for
these confounders there was a 76% decrease
in the risk of eczema.
This is a 76% decrease in the odds of
getting eczema.
Which, again, is a really hard thing for
us to understand intuitively.
All you have to do is look at the risks.
It's really a halving of risk, right?
The risk goes down by about half, from
about 63% to 36%.
So clearly, not a 76% drop in the risk.
76% drop in the odds, whatever that
exactly means.
Now, you might wonder, if you're looking
at this, you know,
adjusted odds ratio and say, well,oh,
well, maybe it's.
It's the fact that we've adjusted for
things.
Maybe that makes the relationship
stronger, and
in fact, if we adjusted these, you know,
the risk ratios somehow, that the risk
ratio would also appear much smaller.
In fact, that's not the case, and you can
show that, because of the fact that
the odds ratio and risk ratio have a
direct mathematical relationship.
So there's a little formula you can use,
if you were in HRP 259,
you've already done this before.
But there's a little formula you can use
to convert back the odds ratio from
a logistic regression,back into a adjusted
risk ratio.
Just using the mathematical relationship
between those two quantities.
I won't derive it for you here.
But it's fairly easy to apply.
So, we're just going to plug it, in this
case, to this formula.
The observed odds ratio is 0.243.
Now we have to plug in the risk, or
prevalence, of the outcome in the
reference group.
So in this case, the reference is that
control group.
62.9% Of them got eczema, so we plug in
the 0.629.
When you do that, you get that the
adjusted risk ratio is 0.46.
Remember, the unadjusted was 0.58, if we
just.
Just divided the the two percentages in
the two groups.
When we adjust it goes down slightly to
0.46,
but it's still about a halving of risk.
The risk is cut by about in half.
So it's the odds ratio again, of 0.24, is
very misleading.
You would not want to say that the risk is
reduced by 75% here.
The correct interpretation is that the
risk is cut in half.
And I'll talk a little bit more in the
next module about correctly interpreting
odds ratios.
Again, we're going to see odds ratios a
lot in this course,
simply because of the fact that we're
doing a lot of logistic regression.