[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to review
the concept of correlated data.
I'm also going to introduce the two simple
example data sets that
I made up to illustrate the concepts this
week.
So first of all, how do you know if you
have correlated data?
The first step in determining that,
is that you have to figure out what is the
unit of observation?
Often-times that's obvious it's just a
person.
Oftentimes we're just doing studies on
individual people, but
that's not always the unit of observation.
Some studies might be focused on limbs or
hands or knees or eyes.
Or, if you're doing a split phase trial in
dermatology, half a face, or
a whole clinical center rather than an
individual.
So you need to determine that first,
before you can figure it out if the
observations are correlated.
Then you're going to ask yourself,
are these observations independent or
correlated?
Independent observations are, of course,
unrelated.
Oftentimes, this is different, unrelated
people, but
again, that doesn't always have to be the
case.
Correlated observations have some
relationship to one another.
The most common source of correlation is
repeated measures data,
where you take the same person and measure
them over time.
Obviously since it's the same person at
multiple time points,
that person's going to be correlated with
themselves over time.
But you could doing a study also where
you're looking at two legs, or
two knees, or two eyes from the same
person.
Or you might be doing a matched case
control study, where each case and
control are one to one match to each
other, and therefore are correlated.
Now I just want to point out that this
week,
I'm going to be talking about methods for
analyzing cross-sectional correlated data,
so I'm not yet going to get into the
situation when we're dealing with
repeated measures, that is things over
time.
So if you want to learn about repeated
measures,
that's what's going to be covered in a lot
of detail in the spring
quarter course HRP262.
So it turns out that adding time to the
picture does complicate things, and
so well we'll get into that, we'll delve
into that in the spring.
For today we'll stick with cross-sectional
examples of correlation.
Now I told you before that there are two
possible consequences of
ignoring the correlations in, in your
data.
So if you're doing what are called
within-person or
within-cluster comparisons, and
you ignore the correlations, you're going
to end up with p-values that are too big.
You're going to be overly conservative.
However, if you are doing between-person
or between-cluster comparisons and
you ignore the correlations, your p-values
are going to end up too small.
They're going to be too optimistic.
So I've, I've told you this before, but I
thought it might be helpful to actually
draw out a picture of this just to make
sure we're all clear on what I mean here.
So I'm just going to draw a picture of
some possible data.
[NOISE]
So the dots here represent observations,
and I'm going to color the different
clusters with different colors.
So here's some datas that are somehow
clustered,
there's somehow a relationship between the
points in these different circles.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So these, this could represent maybe
you've done a match case
control study where each case has been
matched to three controls, and
each of these circles might represent
different matched strata.
Or maybe you've done a family study where
these dots represent siblings from
different families.
Or maybe you're looking at some kind of
dermatology study and
these dots represent lesions from the same
person.
All of those are possible scenarios that
could generate data that look like this.
So when we talk about within cluster
comparisons, what we mean by that is,
imagine you have a case where different
observations, or different people,
if you have people, within a cluster, have
different exposures, or
different treatments.
They differ in some way.
So imagine you're doing a tree you know, a
randomized trial, and
some people within a cluster get the
treatment, and some people don't.
So it might look something like this.
This could be a treatment in a randomized
trial,
it could be different exposures in an
observational study.
If you want to do a within-cluster
comparison, what you're doing is,
you're comparing people who have the
predictor or exposure or
treatment of interest within a cluster to
other people in the same cluster who do
not have that exposure or predictor of
interest.
Because people within a cluster are
similar to one another, this helps to
reduce variability, noise, because you,
you're not worrying about some of the,
you know, some of the confounders are
going to be controlled for, for example.
You're only comparing people who are
similar, or
observations who are similar to one
another.
So you could do these within-cluster
comparisons.
And that looks like that, and of course
then, the statistics that we
use here are going to somehow aggregate
over all the different clusters,
these within-cluster comparisons.
So this would be things like your paired
t-test or your McNemar's test.
If you have data that look like this, and
you're doing some kind of
regression modeling, you can actually go
one step further.
So when we talk about GEE modelling, I'll
mention that you can both look at
within person comparison or within-cluster
comparisons, and between-person or
between cluster comparisons.
So in other words,
you could not only compare if you're doing
regression modelling, you could not
only compare within a cluster, but you
could also compare treated people to
untreated people, across different
clusters.
So that, it, it is possible to do both
between cluster and
within cluster comparisons in the same
data set, but
you have to be using some kind of
regression, like GEE Modelling.
We'll talk a lot about that in the spring
term.
But now for the moment imagine that you
have the following situation.
A little bit different set-up of your
data.
So imagine.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You have, again, clustered data, but
different people, or
different observations within a cluster,
all have the same level of the predictor
that you are interested in.
So maybe it's a cluster randomized trial.
And clusters are randomized as a group to
a single treatment.
If you have this situation, where
everybody has the same exposures or
treatments within a cluster, then you
cannot do within cluster comparisons,
right, because everybody's at the same
level.
So the only thing you can do with these
data is to do between cluster comparisons.
You would compare people who got one
treatment,
to people who got a different treatment
across different clusters.
So that's the idea of between cluster
comparisons.
So if it helps you to kind of draw out
this picture that might help, you know,
to, you to kind of get this idea, and
I'll try to draw out pictures as we go
through this week.
So I made up two hypothetical data sets,
they're very simple.
But I think sometimes having a simple
example helps when you're starting to
learn a method, so we'll just, it's an
easy example to get your head around.
So the first made up data set,
the hype, is a hypothetical randomized
trial of some kind of eye-disease.
And the researchers here assigned 50
patients with bilateral eye-disease,
meaning that they have disease in both
eyes, to receive a drug in one eye, and
a placebo in the other eye.
And it's probably randomly assigned which
treatment, or
which eye, the treatment goes in, left or
right.
And let's say the outcome here is
something very simple.
And your, you have a success if the
symptoms in
the eye improve by more than 50%, and it's
a failure if they don't.
So it's a simple binary outcome.
Now clearly the unit of observation for
this data set has to be the eye, right?
It can't be a person, because each person
has
been given two different interventions, so
we have to look at unit of eye.
And of course, these observations are
going to be correlated,
because eyes within a person are
correlated.
Now I made up some, you know, outcome data
here.
Again, these are hypothetical data, but to
illustrate a point.
And then I analyzed the data ignoring the
correlations, just to start with,
to show you what happens.
So I've ignored the correlations and
pretended,
in essence, that I've just got 50
drug-treated eyes and
50 placebo-treated eyes, and there's no
linking between them.
It's just like I have 100 independent
eyes.
I applied a Chi-square test here, and the
p-value came out to be 0.07.
So this would be the incorrect analysis,
because of course we are ignoring the
correlations now.
But notice the p-value comes out to be
0.07.
It turned out that there were 32
drug-treated eyes that improved versus 23
placebo-treated eyes that improved.
And if you just compared that 32 out of
50, the 64%, to the 23 out of 50, the 46%,
with a Chi-squared, it doesn't quite come
out to be statistically significant.
But something not right here, because we
haven't accounted for
the fact that, hey within a person the,
the eyes are related to one another.
Somebody who is likely to have a good
outcome in one eye is also likely to
have a good outcome in another.
And again by actually accounting for the
correlations, since there's going to
be a lot of variation across different
people, by only analysing within
a person we're reducing variation, we're
going to improve our p-value.
So you all know how to analyze these data
correctly, already.
We don't really need to do a regression
here.
I've already shown you that you could
apply McNemar's test.
So just a review, how does McNemar's test
work?
McNemar's test is just a b minus c
squared, divided by b plus c, b and
c are representing discordant cells.
So this is people where the one eye
improved, but
the other eye didn't improve.
And if the treatment works, we'd expect
that in most of those discordant cases it
would be the treated eye that improved and
not the placebo.
So we can just apply McNemar's formula
here.
It would be 13 minus four squared divided
by 17.
That will have a Chi-square distribution
with one degree of freedom.
If you go and calculate that out and
look up the p-value, it turns out to be
that the p-value is .029.
So it actually gets smaller when you
correctly account for
the correlations here.
And just to put a little picture to this,
I can draw these little graphics again.
Now these dots actually represent eyes.
And what's happened here is we've treated
one eye, but not the other in a person,
and, of course, then we can do within
person comparisons of the eyes.
That's what McNemar's test does.
I then made up a second hypothetical data
set.
It's very similar to the first.
The only difference is, we again have 50
patients with bilateral eye disease, but
the difference here is that every patient
is going to receive either the drug or
the placebo in both eyes.
So the same thing is happening to both
eyes within a person.
So again, to draw my little picture.
[NOISE]
A single person receives the same thing in
both eyes.
And so, of course,
then all we can be doing is doing between
person comparisons here.
Now, again, I made up some outcome data.
So these are made up data, but imagine
that these are real data.
And then I analyzed them, to start with,
the wrong way.
So I ignored the correlations.
I just applied a Chi-square test, ignoring
the correlation.
I'm pretending as if I have 50 drug
treated eyes and
50 placebo treated eyes that have no
relationship to one another.
It turned out that here 27 of the drug
treated eyes improved,
versus 17 of the placebo treated eyes.
And if you just apply a Chi-square test,
you get a p-value of 0.046.
Now what's happening here is that that
p-value is going to be too small,
because what's happening here, so you
kind of go back to the picture.
If a, a particular person, you know,
improves in one eye, they're more likely
to improve in the other eye.
The eyes are related to one another, so
we're kind of over counting people,
therefore our p-value, our sample size in
a sense is overly optimistic and
our p-values are too small.
So now let me show you the correct way to
think about the data.
And to analyse these data, I actually went
ahead and
applied GEE modelling, which I'm going to
get to in a future module.
But here's kind of the correct way to
think about the data.
It, I grouped people now here, according
to person, so the level of analysis here,
the unit here is now a person; rather than
an individual eye.
So on the active drug, it turned out that
there were 11 people
where both eyes improved, five people
where one eye improved and
nine where, neither of their eyes
improved.
In the placebo group, there is six where
both eyes improved, so
somewhat less five where one eye improved
and 14 where no eyes improved.
And so this gives you a better sense of
there's really a difference of
kind of five here, not a difference of
ten, right?
To analyse these data properly we actually
have to apply this GEE
modelling technique, which I'll give you
the details of soon, but
let me just give you the results of that.
So this is just showing you the results
from your hypothetical trial.
Again 17 out of 50 improved among control
eyes and 27 out of 50 among treated eyes.
If you just play a Chi-square, ignoring
the correlation,
you get a significant p-value.
When you correct for the within-subject
correlation, and by applying this
generalized estimating equation, or GEE
model, you get a p-value of 0.11.
So notice that the odds ratio is the exact
same.
It doesn't affect the point estimate, but
it affects the p-value.
And so in fact,
we have been overly optimistic here by
applying the Chi-square.
Once you correct for
the within subject correlations, it's
actually not statistically significant.