[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to show you
how to evaluate confounding in
the framework of regression analysis.
I'm also going to tell you a little bit
about residual confounding.
So first of all,
it's important to understand that when we
evaluate confounding within regression
models we need to focus on the effect
sizes, the betas and not on the p-values.
You almost want to exclusively focus on
those effect sizes.
When we talk about interaction, for
interaction we are actually going to
focus on p-values but for confounding the
effect sizes are what matter.
And here's the rule of thumb.
The rule of thumb is not set in stone.
But a general good rule of thumb is that
you would identify a variable as
a confounder if it changed the beta, the
effect size,
relating the predictor and the outcome,
the coefficient, by more than 10%.
So if you have a model where there's, you
know,
there's a beta for the predictor in the
model.
And then you add the confounder to the
model, and
the beta for the predictor changes by more
than 10%.
When you add the confounder, that would be
considered that,
then this would be considered a
confounder.
If adding the confounder doesn't really
affect the beta for the predictor.
Then this third variable would not be
considered a confounder.
Now I'll just note that this rule of thumb
doesn't really work very well if
you're talking about betas close to zero.
So if the beta between the predictor and
the outcome is already close to
zero it's very easy to change by 10% if
your already close to zero.
So if your at 0.01 10% of 0.01 is very
small.
So this really works for
talking about things that have a beta
that's not the null value.
When you get to betas close to zero,
you are going to have use your judgement a
little bit.
It's not, the 10% rule is not going to
work there.
The example that I'm going to use to start
with here is
this example of gender bias in admissions
are Berkeley.
So this example was from some data.
This was collected in the early 1970s at
Berkeley and this was looking at
whether or not there was bias against
females in graduate school admissions.
And somebody just looking at the crude
data overall concluded that
there was indeed a bias against women.
And here are just the data presented to
the two by two table.
Fewer women were applying than men.
But women were also getting denied
admissions at a higher rate.
If you calculate the risk ratio, women
were 25% more likely to
be denied admissions to Berkeley gradate
school than men.
And that was, indeed statistically
significant.
However, that's the crude data, but
there is an important confounder lurking
in the background here.
So let's start by just running the model
where we put gender in to
the logistic regression model as the only
predictor.
So here is the model with only age in the
model.
So if we just say, does gender predict
whether or
not you're going to be rejected from
Berkeley graduate school.
Indeed, you can see that indeed,
there's a very strong relationship between
your gender, and being rejected.
And the p-value is very strong here.
We have a very positive association with
gender here.
One is equal to female.
I should clarify, so a positive
relationship means that
women are more likely to be rejected, the
outcome here is being rejected.
The risk ratio as we saw in the last time
was 1.25.
We are doing logistic regression, we get
out an odds ratio, not a risk ratio.
So the odds ratio comes to be 1.84.
Of course that's the increase in your odds
of being rejected, not your risk.
But anyway, with nothing else in the model
age looks very predictive.
But there's a confounder here.
So the confounder here is that especially
back in the 1970s women and
men applied to very different departments.
So women it turned out where applying to
departments that were
very hard to get into in high numbers.
Whereas men tended to apply to departments
that for
whatever reason were easier to get into.
If you looked within a particular
department the admissions rates for
men and women were actually very similar.
It's just that there's a confounder here,
women are applying to things,
to departments that happen to be hard to
get into
Men are applying easier ones to get into.
So what we are going to do is we are going
to adjust for
program in our logistic regression model.
Program or department, and the programs
labeled as A B C D E and F.
There were six programs.
In the data sets six programs were
represented.
Essentially departments.
This is a categorical variable.
So there's program A, B, C, D, E and F.
How do we represent categorical predictors
in regression?
We're going to have to dummy code them, so
that's what's represented here.
There are, there was six categories, six
programs.
Then we're going to get five betas in the
model.
Why five betas?
Because the reference group is going to be
absorbed into the intercept.
So, the reference group here turned out to
be program F.
That just happens to be because the
default in my the computer program I
was using, SAS, the default is to use the
alphabetically last
value as the reference group.
Of course I did change that,
but it's kind of arbitrary, which one I
pick to be the reference group here.
So come, this is going to tell me that
indeed there is
a strong effect for program.
These p-values represent the comparison
between these individual programs with
program F.
But certainly at least compared to program
F,
these other programs both have a very
strong difference from program F.
There seems to be an important effect here
of program.
But here's what we want to focus on in the
concept of adjusting for confounding.
So notice what happened the estimate from,
for gender.
The estimate for gender, the beta for
gender was about 0.60,
maybe 0.61, before we adjusted for
program.
After we adjust for program that data
coefficient actually
becomes slightly negative, it goes down to
0.099.
That is clearly more than a ten percent
change So
program would absolutely be a confounder
in this context.
And, it, clearly we need to keep program
in the model, because when we adjust for
program it completely changes the
relationship between gender and
admissions to graduate school at Berkeley.
So, there are, again our general rule of
thumb for
confounding is if we changed the data by
more than 10%,
this, this clearly does that, then we're
going to consider it a confounder.
So program is a confounder in this
context.
Now, I want to go one step further here.
It also happens to be that program is not
only a confounder, but
it's also an effect modifier.
So it happens to be in this data set that
the program.
You can have variables that are both
confounders and effect modifiers.
In fact, program is also an effect
modifier and
I just want to show you that here.
We're going to talk about interactions
very soon, so
I just want to kind of set up that idea.
How would I test for an interaction
between gender and program?
Well you can see that the model is getting
rather complex, but
all we have to do to test for interaction
is to multiply gender times program.
That's how we test for interaction.
That's called an interacting variable.
Now, because there are five programs.
Well, there's six programs, but
five programs represented as betas in the
model.
What we end up with is that when we add an
interaction term here,
because we are interacting with a
categorical variable,
we actually end up with five betas for
interaction.
So now we've got five betas for the main
effect for program, and
five betas for interaction.
So what you can see here is that, in fact,
some of the interaction terms,
specifically term, the interaction between
gender and
program A, that one came out to be
statistically significant.
So it turns out that in this case that
program A actually is
more likely to admit women than they are
to admit men.
So the other programs were all pretty
even, but
program A in particular had a higher admit
rate for, for women.
So we have some interaction going on here.
So I just want to point out that you can
also have something that's
both a confounder and a interaction and
the interacting variable.
And I want to show you how you might want
to use the likelihood ratio test here
when talking in particular about the
interaction between gender and program.
You might just want to report this p-value
and
say hey, program A is different from the
rest.
But sometimes we also like to just report
an overall p-value for
the interaction between gender and
program, and not get into the fine level
of detail of individual categories.
So sometimes with a categorical variable,
we want to just report what's called the p
for interaction, which is just to say
overall is there
any interaction between gender and the
categorical variable of program.
And this is where we can use a likelihood
ratio test,
which we've talked about already.
This is a good use of the likelihood ratio
test.
If you wanted overall p for interaction,
what you can do is compare a model that
contains the interactions with,
between gender a program and to a model
that, it doesn't have those interactions.
And, that you can compare with the
likelihood ratio test because
it's actually a group of betas that you
have to compare at once.
So, I ran the model with the interaction
term, that's of the model I just
showed you, my negative 2 Log likelihood
here turned out to be four 4856.
When I then take the interaction term out
and I run the model
without the interaction, my likelihood, my
negative 2 Log likelihood goes up.
Remember this is the reduced model.
[SOUND] And this is the full model.
The reduced model will have a smaller
likelihood but
therefore a bigger negative 2 Log
likelihood, and
the full model will have a smaller value
for negative 2 Log likelihood.
Remember that if we wanted to say whether
or not adding that interaction term which
comprises five variables, whether or not
that adds anything significantly to
the model, we can do that by using a
chi-square.
This is a chi-square with five degrees of
freedom,
because we have five interaction terms in
the model.
It's a six level categorical variable, we
end up with five terms in the model.
So we have a chi-square with five degrees
of freedom.
The negative 2 log likelihood for the
reduced model is this, for
the full model is this.
We just subtract those.
We get the, we have a chi square, with
five degrees of freedom,
with a value of 20.
We can then look to see whether or not
that comes out to be significant.
Indeed I'll show you in a minute, where I
got this from.
But the p-value here come out to be
significant.
So, the expected value here is five.
And, the P-value does indeed come out to
be significant.
So, that's telling us that the P-value for
interaction,
over all adding the interacting term to
our model, improves our model.
So, in case you don't want to get into the
fine level of details of which particular
interacting terms came out significant,
when you have have a categorical variable.
This is a way to just report an overall p
for interaction for
that entire categorical variable.
Just as a quick reminder, to get the, the
p-values that go with a chi-squared test,
you can plug in to one of these online
calculators.
I did that here.
The computer told me that my P-value for
here is 0.0013.
I did have to do this leg work on my own.
I actually had to run the model in my
computer program,
get out the negative 2 log likelihood for
one model.
And then run the model with or the
interaction term,
get the negative 2 log likelihood out for
that.
And then I had to subtract those negative
2 log likelihoods myself, and go and
get the p-value myself.
So sometimes you actually have to do that
legwork by hand.
It's not automatically built into your
computer package to do
the comparison of a reduced and full
model.
The automatic one that the computer
package will give you is the intercept
only model compared with a full model.
This is comparing slightly different so
again I had to do that legwork on my own.
I just want to give you
a second example of confounding here just
to throw out another example.
So this was from a study well, it was
looking at whether or not maternal smoking
was going to change your risk of having a
baby with Down's Syndrome.
This was the American Journal of
Epidemiology a number of years ago but
I really like this example because it's
going to also illustrate the concept of
residual confounding, which we'll get to
in a minute.
But the crude odds ratio here, so when you
just look at,
the outcome here is Down's Syndrome, the
baby has Down's Syndrome or not.
The predictor here is whether or not the
mother smoked during pregnancy.
And if you just look at the crude odds
ratio,
it indeed comes out to be significant.
This confidence interval does not cross 1.
It's actually significant in the
protective direction.
So it looks like, if you don't adjust for
any confounders,
that maternal smoking reduces your risk of
getting Down's Syndrome.
Now, it's very hard to come up with a
biological story here,
that that could somehow be causal.
We know that in general,
smoking tends to cause DNA damage, DNA
damage, would relate to Down syndrome.
Perhaps you can come up with a causal
story here, but
it's more likely that this is due to in
confounding and indeed it was.
So that's the crude odds ratio.
But then, think about potential
confounders here.
The big confounder here, the most
important one turns out to be age.
And that's I like this paper because they
did a lot of nice graphics and
it's well pictured here.
So here is showing you on the left hand
figure, this is showing you
the relationship between maternal age and
the rates of Down's Syndrome.
So as you all probably know, as maternal
age goes up especially as you
get to 40 and above, there's a really big
increase in the risk of Down's Syndrome.
So you can see that there's a strong
relationship clearly between age and
Down's Syndrome.
You turn over to age and
smoking though, the predictor here, age is
also related to the predictor and
it's a pretty strong relationship so
younger women smoke much more.
Are much more likely to smoke than older
women.
So as you get older, you're also more,
you're more likely to
have a baby with Down's Syndrome, but
you're also less likely to smoke.
Hence we end up with this spurious
association between maternal smoking and
Down's Syndrome.
So what the authors did here was then to
adjust for various things.
So here they're adjusting for various
things.
I'm just going to focus, for the moment,
on the, the most adjusted model.
That's the one at the end.
So when they adjusted for everything that
they needed to adjust for, the most
important one being age, the crude odds
ratio, the odds ratio now is exactly 1.0.
So there is no association between
maternal smoking and
Down's Syndrome once you've accounted for
the confounders here.
And you can see that we started with an
odds ratio of 0.8.
We have changed clearly by more than 10%,
we now are at an odds ratio of 1.0.
And again I pay attention only to these
effects then and
not to the statistical significance here.
I usually like to apply that 10% rule to
the betas rather than the odds ratio.
So if you wanted to you could convert the
ln of 0.8 here and
then of course ln of 1 would be 0.
And you can compare whatever this value
turns out to be to 0, rather comparing
the odds ratios, but clearly we have a
major change in the effects size here.
So that's how we ach, evaluate confounding
in, in the context of regression.
What's interesting about this particular
example,
one of the reasons I like to actually use
this example, is that the authors made
of point of illustrating something called
residual confounding.
And it's very important as we start
talking a lot about statistical adjustment
for confounding, it's really important to
keep in the back of
your mind that adjustment for confounding
is not a panacea.
You can not adjust away all confounding.
And that's kind of illustrated here.
So this first regression analysis was
actually included in the paper just as an
illustration of residual confounding.
What they did in that very first
regression analysis is they
modeled age crudely.
They put into their regression, as a
predictor,
you're either younger than 35 or you're 35
and older.
So they modeled age as a binary predictor.
When they do that, we are indeed
attenuating the odds ratio.
It's going from point 0.80 to 0.87.
But, we are not completely wiping out the
effect of confounding by maternal age.
And that's illustrated as well by this
second regression analysis.
Because this also includes age as a binary
predictor.
But it also adjusts for
all the other things that we're eventually
going to adjust for, race and parity.
What this shows you is that just putting
age in
as a binary predictor does not take away
all of the confounding.
When in the last model the authors finally
put in the exact year of maternal age,
then all of the confounding is removed.
But, this is illustrating the point that
when you put in predictors that
are imprecisely measured,
which is often times we are not measureing
things precisely.
then, there was going to be some leftover
confounding.
Finally, at the end here, they were
actually, I mean,
age is one of the things that we are able
to measure precisely.
You can get birth dates.
So once they finally put in age as an
exact birth date,
the exact age, then finally they were able
to adjust away for all the counfounding.
But for most predictors, for
most confounders we don't measure them
precisely and we don't
measure the predictors precisely and then
the outcomes precisely in a lot of cases.
So the problem here is that because
there's error in the various measurements,
statistical adjustment is imperfect.
And that's what we call residual
confounding, and it comes up a lot.
You really cannot completely wipe out a
confounding simply by adjusting for
variables in multiple regression,
unless you had somehow measured the
variables completely with zero error.
We did it probably in the last example.
Down Syndrome is pretty easy to measure to
get, I mean that's a very easy to measure.
We can probably get a good gauge of that.
Smoking is relatively easy to measure
although there might be some confounding,
some leftover confounding with smoking
because we're not going to measure that
totally precisely.
But age is going to be measured precisely.
So we were able to wipe out most of the
confounding in that example.
But I'll just tell you that residual
confounding comes up
a lot with observational studies.
You say, oh I've adjusted for
smoking, I've adjusted for age, therefore
I've taken care of those.
They're all done with.
There can't be any confounding by those.
But in fact that's not true.
If you've measured your confounders at all
imperfectly or
if you've measured your predictors or your
outcome at all
imperfectly it's impossible to completely
adjust away all the confounding.
In most cases you end up with some
leftover or residual confounding.
And my favorite example to illustrate that
is an example that was
in the American Archives, the Archives of
Internal Medicine a few years back.
Made a lot of headlines in the news media.
I've shown this table before.
I just love this table as an illustration
of why confounding occurs, or
why we have to worry about confounding.
This was a study that was looking at, I'm
just showing you the men here,
that was looking at red meat eating, and
whether or not that related to mortality.
And they classified men into different
quintiles of red meat eating,
Q5 being the highest red meat eater.
And I've shown this before, but if you
look carefully at this table, all the,
the risk factors for for, you know, all
the bad health behaviors and
risk factors go up as you go up across the
different quintiles.
So as you go up, your BMI increases, as
you eat more red meat, you're,
you're more likely to be a current smoker.
You're less likely to exercise, you're
more likely to eat a lot of calories.
So basically, people who eat a lot of,
especially men here, who eat a lot of red
meat, tend to be risky in many ways.
They have,
they just have bad health habits, maybe
they're more risk-takers in general.
So this paper was attempting to say,
what is the precise effect of actually
eating read meat with mortality.
And, so they said, we're going to try to
adjust away for all these confounders.
We're going to throw BMI in the model,
we're going to throw smoking in the model,
we're going to throw exercise in the
model,
we're going to try to adjust away for all
those things.
So I'm going to show you the, the results
of this from this study.
So this is showing you the mortality
risks.
These are relative risks, something called
hazard ratios.
This actually came out a Cox regression
and not logistic regression but
residual confounding applies to all types
of regression.
So what you're seeing here is that for,
let's start with overall mortality, and
actually let me zoom in a little bit here
so
it's easier on small screens to see this.
So, we're going to start with all caused
mortality.
The reference group is the lowest red meat
eaters.
The Q5 is the highest red meat eaters.
And they're showing you the risk, the
relative risk, and this is called hazard
ratio, but it's just like a risk ratio, as
you go up across the different quintiles.
So the basic models then adjusted for too
many things, and
indeed you're seeing a nice increase in
mortality as you're eating more red meat.
Then they do an adjusted model.
They're trying to adjust for
all these things that are different about
heavy red meat eaters.
And what you'll notice is that as we
adjust esp,
with especially in that last Q5 quintile.
That when you adjust, you started at 1.48.
When you adjust for all these things
indeed, indeed the effect gets attenuated.
It gets closer to one.
So it, it's really, after you adjust for
everything, a 31% increase in the
mortality risk or rate.
And then, but what's interesting here is
you might have just stopped there and
said okay, well we adjusted for BMI, we
adjusted for exercise.
The authors did a great job adjusting for
everything they possibly could.
It was a nicely done study.
You might just stop there and say, I've
adjusted for everything, and
it's still an elevated risk, it's still
statistically significant.
Aha!
Red meat eating is bad for you.
And that's indeed what the conclusion of
this study was.
It was widely reported in the media.
What's interesting, though, is if you
delve into the specific causes of death.
If you look at cancer mortality.
Okay, cancer mortality elevated, also
elevated in
that heavy red meat eating group, and
again adjusting for the confounders does
attenuate that effect somewhat, but it
still remains even after adjustment.
1.22 for cancer mortality, 1.27 for
cardiovascular disease mortality.
But here is where it really gets
interesting.
So they also put in there mortality from
injuries and sudden deaths.
They also looked at that.
That's a category of, of things that
people might die from.
So this includes things like gunshot
wounds, and car accidents.
Those would probably be the most common.
So what's interesting here [LAUGH] is that
if you look at the risk ratio,
the relative risk here between high red
meat eating compared to
the reference group of low red meat
eaters, it's also elevated.
It's, the magnitude is almost identical to
the increase in risk for
cardiovascular disease and for cancer.
So that's really interesting because if
you start make a causal story here,
how does red meat, heavy red meat eating,
how does that increase your risk of car
accidents and gun shot wounds?
Well, the, the logical answer to that is
it probably doesn't.
So what we're seeing here,
this 1.26 is almost certainly the result
of residual confounding.
Heavy red meat eaters tend to be people
who have a lot of risky behaviors.
They probably take a lot of chances.
They might own guns and, you know, drive
too fast.
Might drink while driving.
The kinds of things that increase your
risk of this type of death.
And notice that when we adjust for
confounding here there's no change.
So you had 1.24 before adjustment for all
the confounders And 1.26 after you adjust.
That's telling you that there's just
something inherently risky about red meat
eaters that we are unable to capture with
the confounders that we've measured here.
And that leads me to believe that the the
relationships detected here between cancer
mortality and cardiovascular mortality,
which are about the same magnitude,
1.27 and 1.22, that that, those also might
just be due to residual confounding.
Heavy red meat eaters just do a lot of
things bad, and
that increases their risk of mortality.
But it might not be that it's because red
meat eating,
per se, has a direct effect on mortality.
All other deaths, also which is sort of a
catch all category, also is elevated in
a way makes you suspicious that there
might be residual confounding.
And some people actually wrote letters to
the editor on this particular one,
worried about the, the issue of residual
confounding.
And just to help you recognize when there
might be residual confounding.
If you're talking about a binary
predictor, like, you know,
you're a high red meat eater or you're
not.
Incomplete con, adjustment for
confounding can generate spurious relative
risks in the range of 0.6 to 1.6.
So notice the, the relative risk we were
talking about with the red
meat eating example, was about 1.2, 1.3,
in that range.
So these are small effect sizes.
For the Down Syndrome example the effect
size was .8, so
those were both within the range of 0.6 to
1.6.
And statisticians have done simulations
where they actually show
that residual confounding can cause
spurious associations in that
general relative risk range, 0.6 to 1.6.
In other words, if you see an effect size
of two or three in your data set,
that is usually beyond what residual
confounding can cause.
So residual confounding is kind of limited
in its scope.
But if you pick up a lot of observational
studies and papers in the literature,
you will see plenty of risk ratios and
odds ratios that are 1.3, 0.8, 1.4.
These are the, the when the effect sizes
are this,
this small, this is where you start to
worry that there might be residual
confounding that can completely explain
the association that you are seeing.
I've given you examples here where the
residual, failure to,
to completely, perfectly adjust for
confounding creates spurious associations.
however, it can also go in the other
direction.
Residual confounding might also obscure
relationships.
It's causing you to miss associations.
So you might end up with a risk ration of
1.0 when the true risk ratio is
0.8 because of residual confounding.
Those examples are actually much harder to
find.
They're much harder to uncover.
But they can happen.
So just keep in mind that it can go either
way.