Welcome to week six of the course.
This week we're going to continue our
discussion of building regression models.
So first of all, the specific steps that
you take when
you're building a regression model depend
heavily on the end goal of your analysis.
And we can divide those goals broadly into
two groups.
Explanatory models and predictive models.
A lot of the things we've been talking
about up to now have had to
do with explanatory models.
For example, testing for
confounding is most relevant in the
context of explanatory models.
This week I'm going to focus on therefore
the steps of variable selection for
explanatory models.
Next week however, I'm going to focus on
predictive modeling.
You'll see that a lot of the choices you
have to make are actually different for
predictive model, so
it's very important to know which one of
those camps you're in.
I'm also going to talk a little bit today
about missing data.
I alluded to missing data last week.
I'm going to give you some specific
strategies for dealing with missing data.
Again, we're going to talk about variable
selections specifically for
explanatory models this week.
And we're also going to talk quite a bit
about something called propensity scores.
Propensity scores in essence are another
data reduction technique, but
this is a data reduction technique
specifically for your confounders.
And it has some really useful
applications,
especially in treatment studies.
This week we're going to be talking about
model building and variable selection and
there's a temptation when you're building
models,
you're going to see that model building is
a bit of an art.
There is not an exact science to it.
I can't tell you the three steps you have
to do,
often different people will have slightly
different ways of doing this.
And there's a temptation to do something
which people have called P-value shopping.
And I just like this term P-value
shopping.
I was looking to see if I could find a
cartoon that somebody has
drawn on P-value shopping, I didn't quite
find that but
I found a couple of other good cartoons on
P-values shown here.
But basically the idea of P-value shopping
is this, when their are many
decision points in building a model, there
is some temptation to just say well,
especially if I've got a predictor that I
really hope comes out to be significant.
There is some temptation to say well I'm
going to try this model and
I'm going to try putting this confounder
in and taking this confounder out and
I'm going to try changing how I'm modeling
my predictor variable,
I'm going to try the model without this
particular outlier.
I can try all these different things and
of course the P-value for the predictor I
care about is going to change somewhat in
all of these different models.
So the idea of P-value shopping is that
you're going around and shopping until you
find the smallest one and, of course, that
is not a great idea because that is
certainly going to increase our chances of
making a type one error.
So we'll talk more about that later this
week.