In this next module, I'm going to talk
about what a confounding variable is.
So, a confounder is a variable that
is associated with both the predictor and
the outcome.
but it is not on the causal pathway
between the predictor and the outcome.
So this would look something like,
you've got a third variable that's related
to both the predictor and the outcome.
The predictor and the outcome maybe aren't
related to each other.
But because they're both related to the
confounder,
you see a spurious association between the
predictor and the outcome.
That's one thing that can happen with
confounding Confounders can
also obscure relationships.
So perhaps the confounder is inversely
related to either the predictor
and the outcome.,
And it might actually mask a relationship
between those variables,
it might cause you to miss seeing a
relationship.
So both of those things can happen.
Confounding is best illustrated with some
examples.
So I'm going to start here with basically
the reason that confounding exists,
is that risk factors tend to cluster.
People who have bad health habits in one
domain,
tend to have bad health habits in a lot of
domains.
For example.
And this is really well illustrated by a
study that
looked at red meat intake and mortality.
And this is just the descriptive table,
the table one from that study, looking at
the men.
And I think this is a really nice table to
look at,
because it just shows you how clustered
risk factors can be.
So this study was looking at Quintiles of
red meat intake, so
they divided the men up into quintiles of
red meat intake.
Q1 is the lowest quintile, the lowest red
meat eaters, Q5 is the highest quintile,
so the, those who are eating the most.
Red meat.
And if you kind of scroll down this table,
it's
just showing you basic characteristics,
but go to exam, for example to BMI.
This of course is a risk factor for poor
health outcomes.
If you look at BMI, starting with Q1, the
first quartile,
the first quartile, the BMI, the average
BMI is 25.9.
And as you go across the quartiles it goes
up Just beautifully across the,
I'm sorry, across the quintiles, until you
get to the highest quintile of meat,
red meat intake, and BMI is up to 28.3.
You look at smoking, so not too many
smokers, current smokers in the,
in the lowest meat eating group.
As you go up across the quintiles of meat
eating.
Eating, red meat eating it goes up just,
you know, 4.9, 7.6, 9.9, 11.4, 14.8.
It just goes up so beautifully, all of the
bad habits go up,
as you go up across the quintiles of red
meat eating, and you can
see that with some of the other factors
that are listed in this table as well.
This just goes to show you that people who
have a one bad health habit,
such as eating red meat tend to have lots
of other bad habits,
such as smoking, being heavier, not
exercising.
That makes it really difficult in
observational studies to tease out,
is it red meat that is causing them to die
earlier, or is it these other factors, or
is it a combination of all of them and
part of what we're going to try to do in
this course.
is to build regression models that try to
tease out exactly what is
the causal factor.
But I just want to start by letting you
know that that is
actually a very hard thing to do.
We're going to try to do statistically,
but
it's difficult because these things
cluster so strongly.
That's why confounding arises.
Now let me give you just a simple
hypothetical confounding example.
This is sort of a prototypical example of
confounding.
So, imagine you go out and do a study and
you look at heavy drinkers compared to
people who maybe light or non-drinkers.
And you look at the incidence rates of
lung cancer among
drinkers versus non-drinkers.
You will actually find that drinkers get
lung cancer at
a much higher rate than non-drinkers or
light drinkers.
So you might therefore conclude that
alcohol raises your risk of lung cancer.
And that wouldn't be totally unreasonable
because we actually do know that
alcohol increases the risks of certain
cancers, such as breast cancer.
That's pretty well established.
However, it turns out that in this
particular case for lung cancer,
alcohol actually is not biologically
related to lung cancer, as far as we know.
It appears that those are not related
causally.
Of course, there is a very important
confounder,
a third variable lurking in the background
here.
So, heavy drinkers also tend to be
smokers.
And, we know for sure that smoking is
strongly related to lung cancer.
So smoking in this picture is the
confounding variable.
So you see that smoking is related both to
alcohol and
to lung cancer, but it's not on the causal
pathway between those two,
because in fact, alcohol is not causally
related to lung cancer.
The association here was completely driven
by confounding with smoking.
And I think it's helpful sometimes,
to just put some hypothetical numbers, to
illustrate this with some numbers.
So what would it look like in terms of
numerically,
what does a confounder look like?
So I just made up just some hypothetical
numbers here.
You can see they're made up, because there
are a lot of zeros.
But just as a simple example, imagine that
you went out and did a case control study.
You sample 100 lung cancer cases and 200
controls who don't have lung cancer.
If you then asked about, who's a drinker,
say a heavy drinker versus a non or
light drinker.
You would actually find that indeed,
more of the lung cancer cases had a
history of heavy drinking.
And I've illustrated that numerically
here, so in this particular example I said
50% of the cases are drinkers versus only
25% of the controls are drinkers.
So you can see that there is a strong
relationship here.
This is a case control study, so just to
review from last week,
we could calculate an odds ratio, the odds
ratio here will be 50 times a 150, divided
by 50 times 50, in other words that would
be 3, the odds ratio here, would be 3.
It appears therefore, that drinking is
strongly associated with lung cancer.
However, we know that there's this third
variable,
the smoking variable, lurking behind the
scenes.
So what happens when we try to account for
smoking?
Well a very simple way to account for
smoking would be to simply.
Look only, compare smokers only to smokers
and
compare non-smokers only to non-smokers.
And in fact, that's what I'm going to do
here.
I'm going to stratify my table on smoking,
divide it into smokers and
non-smokers, and look specifically within
each of those strata.
So, if we turn to the smokers.
What you'll notice with the smokers is
that there's a large number of
lung cancer cases among the smokers.
That would be expected because of course,
smoking is very strongly related to lung
cancer.
So 75% of the smokers had lung cancer,
were cases.
You can also see that a lot of smokers
drink.
So I, I've made the total here just 100 to
make it really easy to do percentages.
You can see that we have 45 plus 15 or 60
drinkers so 60% of my sample as drinkers.
So among the smokers your very likely to
have lung cancer your also very likely to
be a drinker, however, if you restrict to
just the smokers and
you look at the relationship between
drinking and cancer within the smokers.
In fact 60% of lung cancer cases are
drinkers and 60% of controls are drinkers,
so once we restrict to smokers even though
drinking is high and lung cancer is high,
you can actually see that there is no
relationship between drinking.
And being a case or control among the
smokers.
Then you turn to the non-smokers.
Among the non-smokers, you can see lung
cancer was much more rare.
Only 25 out of 200, 12.5% had lung cancer
in the non-smoking group.
And drinking was much more rare.
So only in this case 20% of the total
were, were drinkers.
Again though, if you look at the
relationship between drinking and
cancer just within the non-smokers, it
turns out 20% of the lung cancer cases
were drinkers and 20% of the controls were
drinkers so there's no relationship.
Now between drinking and cancer.
So stratifying on smoking allows you to
see that actually,
there's no relationship between drinking
and cancer once you've accounted for
smoking, and the way we've accounted for
it here is just to stratify on it.
But that's the kind of, what you're going
to kind of see numerically.
Now, I just want to throw in a real life
example of confounding here.
This is a very interesting story, that
goes back to, many decades actually.
And for a long time, women were prescribed
postmenopausal hormones for
many reasons and I was actually a graduate
student back in the late.
1990s, and I studied osteoporosis, and we
happen to know with pretty good
certainty that if you put postmenopausal
women on hormones, estrogen and
progestin, that it actually does indeed
prevent osteoporosis.
However, when I was a graduate student in
the 90s.
It was also widely believed that
postmenopausal hormone
therapy reduced a woman's risk of heart
disease and there was a lot of evidence,
a lot of lines of evidence, particularly
from observational studies to support that
protective effect, so this would.
The protective effect here that it looked
like that, that the therapy,
the hormones reduced the risk of heart
attacks.
However, again, most of that data was
coming from observational studies and
you can imagine a number of confounders
could be at play here.
So it turned out that the women who were
taking hormone replacement therapy
tended to be more well-educated to have a
higher socioeconomic status.
They tended to be healthier in a lot of
different ways.
They were less likely to smoke, because
smoking was a contraindication for
taking estrogen and progestin.
So there's a lot of reasons Why women on
this therapy might have
had lower heart disease,
that weren't necessarily a biological
connection between those two things.
But just to kind of show you how widely
accepted the dogma was that
estrogen therapy, or estrogen and
progestin therapy prevents heart disease.
This is an article going all the way back
to 1996,
when I was starting graduate school.
And if you read through this article, I've
just put a few quotes in here.
It was pretty much, you can see that,
though the language is written in as a way
that it was accepted fact that,
in particular, estrogen after menopause,
would reduce the risk of heart disease.
You can see more than 30 studies have
found that estrogen after menopause is
good for the heart.
So it was really widely accepted dogma.
And there was, again, a lot of evidence to
back this up.
So here's one of the studies that helped
establish that.
This is called the Nurses' Health study.
It's a cohort study that followed nurses,
over many decades.
It's done out of Harvard, some great data
from this, but it you
look carefully at this particular paper,
which was published many decades ago.
They were looking at major heart disease.
And if you look at estrogen alone or
estrogen with progesterone,
the two sort of forms of post menopausal
hormone therapy, and
you look at the relative risks for heart
disease, so the, this is just in the first
column is the age adjusted relative risks
so that you can see they're very
protective, .45 and .22, that's really far
from one in the protective direction.
And even if you do multivariate
adjustment, where you try to adjust for
confounders, they're still protective .6
and .39.
Now notice that as we went from age
adjustment to adjusting for all these
other confounders, The relative risks get
closer to one, the effect size gets
attenuated, they don't, these therapies
don't look quite as protective anymore.
That's a clue to you,
that there is definitely important
confounding going on here.
We were able to adjust for
some of it hence, the relative risks got
closer to one.
But even in this study where we were
adjusting for all these confounders
we're still cutting the risk of heart
disease about in half with those hormones.
So this was one, just one of the many
examples of observational studies that
even though they had tried to adjust for
confounding, still found that
these hormones were protective against
heart disease in postmenopausal women.
All right, well a long comment comes in
2002.
The results of the,
the early results of a, a study called the
Women's Health Initiative.
So this is where researchers actually went
out and
decided we've done a lot of observational
trials, what we really need to do is to
randomize women to take postmenopausal
hormones or a placebo pill so that we can
really see what happens getting, removing
a lot of the confounding from the picture.
So this was a very large randomized trial.
The trial was actually stopped early.
It was stopped in 2002 because when they
did an interim look at the data,
they found that hormones had more risks
than benefits.
So they found out hormones increased your
risk of breast cancer,
which was actually an expected outcome,
that was not surprising.
But what really surprised people, what was
unexpected, is that
they found that the hormones actually
increased the risk of heart disease,
not protected against it but increased it.
And you can see that illustrated here in
this graph in the left hand panel,
this is just showing the cumulative risk
of getting heart disease.
And the top graph,
which has a higher rate of heart disease
is the, is the group on hormones.
The placebo group is the lower graph.
And people were expecting this to come out
the opposite.
So the trial was actually stopped early.
Because even though we thought that the
hormones
were protected against the heart disease.
In fact they increased a woman's risk and
probably a lot of the observational
studies that were done and that had.
Setup this dogma that, that it's hormones
were protective,
a lot of them didn't get the right answer
because of confounding and
it just goes to show you how difficult it
really is, as much as we're
going to try to account for confounders,
its very difficult to fully account for
confounding and sometimes in the case like
this, that con, you know that
confounders were not fully adjusted for in
the observational study and therefore
the observational studies were getting the
opposite of the correct answer.
I just want to tell you about how we're
going to attempt to control for
confounders in medical studies.
So one way to [INAUDIBLE] control for
confounders is to control for
them in the design of the study.
So as I've alluded to here, randomization
So if you randomly assign people to
one treatment or another, or one group or
another.
That takes away a lot of the confounding
because now all these,
the clustering of risk factors that goes
away.
So that's probably the best way to deal
with confounding is just to randomize,
of course we can't always do a randomize
trial.
You can also do something called
restriction which would
be something like if you thought smoking
was an important confounder you
could decide to restrict your study to
only study non-smokers.
You could also do matching which we talked
about last week.
This is not a course of study design so we
are going to assume that for
the purposes of this course we're.
Stuck with the data that,
that have already been collected and we're
not talking about the design of the study.
But at the point where we have data and
say we didn't do a randomized trial,
how can we then go ahead and control for
confounders in the analysis phase of this
study?
And the main way that we're going to do
that, and the main.
You know, that I've sort of been talking
about in most of these examples.
The main way people adjust for confounding
is with multivariate regression.
We're going to get to that starting next
week.
But I just want to show you this week that
there is kind of a simple way to
look at confounders.
I.
It gets back to the lung cancer example I
gave earlier in this module.
We can try to stratify on the confounder
if it's a categorical confounder.
So this week we're going to talk about
methods that involve stratification.