[BLANK_AUDIO]
Welcome to week 2 of HRP 261.
Last week we talked about some basic
tests,
that you can use to analyze data from
contingency tables.
So that was a situation where we just
wanted to see whether or
not a categorical predictor and a
categorical outcome were associated,
not taking into account any things like
confounders or any other variables.
This week we're going to complicate the
picture just slightly by adding a third
variable to the picture.
So this week I'm going to be talking about
three concepts that are important for
you to understand before we move on to
regression analysis.
Some of you may already be familiar with
these concepts, but
they are confounding, interaction, and
mediation.
And for the first few modules this week,
I am just basically going to go over
conceptually, what those things look like.
Now I'm going to tell you a little bit
about,
what it called the Mantel-Haenszel tests.
These tests can be used to evaluate
confounding.
In a very simple situation, when we have a
single categorical confounder.
So again, we're sort of adding a third
variable to the picture we
talked about last week.
Last week we talked about trying to see
whether or
not a predictor in an outcome variable
were statistically linked.
We looked at a bunch of tests that you
could use to evaluate that.
This week again, we're going to add a
third variable to that picture,
either a Confounder, a Mediator or an
Effect modifier.
And I'll go over in turn with you what
each of those variables is.
I'm going to try to start each week with
at least one teaser.
This is just something I'm going to
preview something that we're
going to be talking about in the future
modules just to get you thinking.
So this was an interesting example that
was looking at gender bias or
potential of gender bias at Berkeley.
Now this was back in the 1970s and
this was dealing with graduate admissions
to graduate school at Berkeley.
Of course we probably were more worried
about overt gender bias back in the 1970s.
And somebody went ahead and
looked at the admissions data to graduate
school at Berkeley one year in the,
in the 70s and you can see the data
represented in a two-by-two table.
You can see at that point, back in the
70s,
more men apply to graduate school than
women.
1,835 women versus 2,681 men.
But if you look at who got into graduate
school and
who didn't, indeed the women were denied
at a higher rate.
So I can calculate the risk ratio in the
way that we talked about last week here.
And it turns out that the risk ratio is
1.25.
I would interpret that as that women were
25% more likely to be
denied admission to graduate school at
Berkeley than men.
So of course, people were up in arms about
this there was a lawsuit but
there's actually something else going on
here besides gender bias and
that relates to the material we're
going to talk about this week.
So, we'll get back to this in a future
module and
actually tease through the numbers, in a
little more detail.