Welcome to Week Five.
This week we're going to start our three
week discussion of model building.
I'm going to talk about model building
specifically in the context of
logistic regression, but most of the
principles that I talk about will also
apply to other type of regression, such as
linear regression and Cox regression.
This week I'm going to talk about how to
model your predictor, so
we are going to be talking about the right
hand side of the equation.
When you have different types of
variables, continuous versus categorical,
how are you going to actually put them
into your model?
There's some choices you have to make, so
for continuous variables you
need to choose what units you're going to
model the continuous variables in.
Sometimes you may choose to model them in
standard deviation units that's
something called standardization which
we're going to talk about.
For every continuous variables you're
going to plot it in a logit plot and
make sure that it's actually linear in the
logit like we talked about last week.
But what happens if some of those
variables are not linear,
how are you going to transform them before
putting them into the model?
Finally if you have kind of a large set of
predictors, especially if
they're highly correlated, you might want
to do some kind of variable reduction.
And we're going to talk about a specific
technique this week taught called
principal components analysis that does
that.
If you have categorical variables, you're
most likely going to be dummy coding them,
so I'll review dummy coding.
Sometimes if you have ordered categories,
you actually might treat those variables
as ordinal, which means that they're
going to appear a little bit differently
in the model, and I'll talk about how to
do deal with ordinal variables.
Just a little preview to this week,
we're going to spend quite a bit of time
on principle components analysis.
And one of the places where that turns out
to be pretty useful is when you're
analyzing dietary.
Dietary data.
So if you think about dietary data,
what people often do is to give especially
if you have a large sample of people,
you're going to give them some sort of
questionnaire.
They're going to check off things like how
often do I eat apples?
How often do I eat fish?
And you end up with a, a larger, or
more variables for all of these different
food types.
How are you going to analyze those data?
Well you're probably not going to want to
put each individual food type into
a regression model.
For one thing there's just going to be so
many variables.
You're going to increase you're type
chances of a type one error if
you just throw them all in the model.
And secondly, of course, it's really hard
to isolate the effect of
any one particular food, because foods
tend to cluster.
People who eat a lot of hamburgers, for
example, are probably also eating a lot of
French Fries, and a lot of,
soda, just because they're frequenting
fast food joints.
So what principle components analysis
allows you
to do with dietary data is to pick out
patterns of eating.
Food groups that, food types that cluster
together.
And so, you might be able to pick out that
fast food pattern type of
eating using principle components
analysis.
So you're going to reduce the bigger set
of dietary variables about
individual foods into a smaller Smaller
set of pattern.
And the particular study that I'm showing
on this screen is one we're going to
talk about this week and it actually did
that in this study.
They had a large number of women teachers
from California and
they applied principal component analysis
to their dietary data and
came out with five predominant food eating
patterns.
And you can see them listed here,
plant based, high protein high fat, high
carbohydrate, ethnic, and
the the salad and wine diet which I think
is a particularly interesting one,
and then they tried to link women's
scores, every woman will get
a score on each dietary pattern saying how
much She follows that pattern.
They linked then those scores to breast
cancer risk.
So that's a particular example of the use
of principal component analysis that we'll
return to later this week.