In this next module I'm going to talk
about strategies for
dealing with missing data.
So, first of all, this is a really
important problem.
In the context of regression,
it's important that you understand that if
you're putting a bunch of variables into
your regression model An observation that
is missing just one data point on any
one of those variables will not be
included in the logistic regression model.
That means you could start with a dataset
that has 400 observations in it.
And you think you're running your
regression on 400 people, but
in fact, because of a smattering of
missing data here and there,
that when you run that logistic regression
it actually might only include 200 people.
Because different people might be missing
values on different variables,
all of a sudden a little bit of missing
data here and
there over ten variables results in a
huge.
Huge number of your sample being cut from
the model.
So this can be a really big problem,
especially if you're not aware of it.
And just to review the likelihood term in
logistic regression and
kind of show you How come people are
knocked out of
the regression if they're missing just one
data point.
Just think about the likelihood term for
logistic regression.
So here's a model that say has just three
predictors in it.
But let's say this person and
remember every person in my data set gets
one term in the logistic regression model.
Let's say this person has a value for
predictor one and
has a value for predictor two, but they're
missing data for predictor three.
Well, when the computer sees their
likelihood term.
There's no there's nothing here for
predictor three therefore there's no
number there the computer can't use this
for the estimation problem.
And so they just effectively get thrown
out so this can be a major problem and
this is where you really need to think
about what do I do when I
have missing data.
So I'm just going to go some, through some
possible strategies for
dealing with missing data.
So first of all imagine that you've got
some variables in your dataset that aren't
necessarily that important you maybe
there's there potential confounders and
you've collected that data but its not
your primary predictor of interest,
it's not your primary outcome of interest.
But those variables are missing a huge
amount of data.
40, 50, 60% of the observations in your
data set don't have a value for
that variable.
The first thing you might consider doing
is just not including that variable in
your analysis.
Especially if you've measured the same
construct with other variables.
If there's other variables available to
get at it.
It's worth considering, is there enough
information here?
Is it really even worth it for me?
To use that variable.
If I use that variable, I'm going to have
to impute those values.
That adds a lot of noise so,
I might just consider not even using that
at all in my analysis.
Now consider the situation where you're
doing some kind of observational study,
and you have a particular hypothesis that
you're trying to test.
So, for example, I want to know, does
having a high level of
mercury in the body Does that increase the
risk of cardiovascular disease.
And I've got some data.
Not everybody has mercury measured and
not everybody has cardiovascular disease
measured.
I've got some missing data on both of
those variables.
Well, since that's completely what you
care about, evaluating that association,
in that situation you probably just want
to exclude observations that
are missing data on either the primary
predictor or the primary outcome.
They really are going to non-informative
for the hypothesis you care about.
And I mean, exclude them from the very
beginning of your analysis so
your table one of your paper should not
include those people.
You just say, we only analyze people who
had measurements on both of
those things because those variable are
just so important in that situation.
Another possibility, another situation is
where, maybe you've
got some variables where they're not
missing, you know, too much missing data.
There may be missing data on as much as
10, 15% of the data set but
they're still pretty valuable.
You're not missing so much.
But they're also not the primary predictor
of interest or
the primary outcome of interest.
They're variables that I care about, and I
maybe want to include in my model.
Maybe they're confounders.
But they're not the most important
variables in the data set.
However, if I want to put them in my
model, and I don't fill in
that missing data, again, lots of
observations are going to get Kicked out.
So I want to fill in something for
those missing values and that's where I'm
going to do some kind of imputation.
I'm going to fill in the missing values so
that, that variable becomes complete and I
don't have any missing data.
So that's another option and
I'm in a minute going to tell you about
some specific ways you can impute the,
the missing values.
I just want to mention, however another
scenario that tends to come up
more commonly within predictive models,
but you could imagine a scenario where,
where you have this in explanatory models
as well, but
sometimes, the missingness itself is
informative.
In other words, whether or not somebody
has a value.
On a particular variable, might tell you
something about that person.
therefore, you might want to actually make
missingness,
whether you are missing that value or not,
a predictor in your model.
And an example of that, is the NetFlix
pry.
So, probably most of you have heard of the
Netflix price.
Netflix offered a million dollars to the
team that could come up with
the best algorithm to predict a mo movie
viewers' rating on
a future a new movie based on the ratings
on all movies.
Well, you can imagine that many movie
viewers watched a lot of movies but
didn't necessarily rate every single
movie.
So some of their movies will have missing
values because they
didn't bother to break that.
It turns out that that's in formula
because people tend to rate a new
movie when they really like or when they
really hate it and if they find so
sure about that they may not bother to do
a review.
So actually that tells us something about
how they felt about that movie.
So that variable, whether or
not they rated the movie at all becomes a
predictor in the model.
Again, comes up more in the context of
predictive model.
So here are some simple imputation schemes
that you could use to
fill in missing data.
So one option is to use the mean of the
sample.
So imagine I've got data say on height.
And, you know, lots of people have this
variable, but
[UNKNOWN] come along down here, and a
couple of people are missing height.
But height's important enough that I
want to put it in my model, but
it's not my primary predictor of interest.
One strategy that's often good enough Is
just to say,
well, what's a good guess for height for
this person?
Well, I don't, I can just guess, that they
have the mean of the sample.
So let's say the mean of the, the height
of the sample was 65.
I'm just going to fill in a 65 for that
person.
And in a situation where you're just
missing, a handful of data points for
a variable.
And that variable's not one of the most
important variables, but
you want to include it in your model.
Just filling in with something is better
than not filling in,
because that's going to mean that this
observation gets included in your
regression analysis when it otherwise
would've been thrown out.
So filling in with the mean is often good
enough.
And it's not the best thing that you can
do, there are other potentially better
alternatives but it's very simple and easy
to do and it's a lot better than
not filling in with anything and just
having that observation kicked out.
So oftentimes if I've got variables where,
you know,
one or two people are missing the value
and I want to include it in my model and
it's not the most important variable I
might just fill in with mean.
Slightly better strategy, little bit more
work,
is to use linear regression to predict the
missing values.
So remember we've got a dataset that may
have other variables that
are related to height in it.
So, we might have weight on the person if,
you know, they're young.
children, age might be important for
height [UNKNOWN].
Other variables that could be used to
predict height, we can make a linear
regression model and get a better guess
at, what that persons value might be.
And I'm going to do this in the situation
where I'm missing, you know,
maybe 10%, a bigger number of people are
missing values on that variable.
And it's something pretty important to me
and
I want to actually make those guesses a
little more precise.
So just as an example here, again I have
this data set on 91 women runners that I
used as an example last week.
Mile time was a variable that I cared a
lot about because this told me
something about how fast of a runner they
were, so this is their best mile time.
But for whatever reason, ten out of 91
women,
were missing variable, the variable mile
time.
They hadn't reported a best mile time.
Maybe they'd never run a mile
competitively.
So for whatever reason, I'm missing a fair
amount.
And I care about this variable enough.
But I'm going to do a linear regression.
So, the, if I'd wanted to use the mean,
though, just to show you,
one thing I could have done was just to
take the mean time in here,
which was 6:16, among the 81 women who
actually had reported times.
And I could assign all ten women, the mean
the, value, of 6:16.
Again by filling in that, those data
points,
that means I'm not going to throw those
women out of the model.
So that really gains with something with
ten out of 91 is a fairly big
percentage missing this value, if I plug
in that 6:16s all of them, notice that
it's going to shrink the variance with
that variable just a little bit.
And also I happen to have in this dataset
other data that could be
informed about the mild times.
So why not in this case, dual linear
regression.
So I said about linear regression, I had
data about their 5K times, so
some of them were going to cross-country
runners They'd only run a 5K but
haven't run a track mile a some women had
every almost all the women had
reported how many miles they run per week
and their pace for speed workout.
so we had pretty good coverage on those
two variables not
everybody reported a 5K time.
We I fill a linear regression model.
And I use that to say well based on a
woman's how fast somebody runs,
how much they run.
How fast they run in a 5k time.
I can predict their mile time.
So I get a bunch of predicted mile times
for women who were missing that variable,
and I filled in the missing data with
their predicted mile time.
This is going to be a better guess obvious
because it's based on some information.
In this case just to note another thing
that there were I think
about three women who also didn't have a
5K time.
So I couldn't use this model to predict
their mile time because they were
missing the 5K time.
So what I did was then run another linear
regression where I just used the mileage
and their speed for their speed for
interval work to predict their mile time.
So this is a little, not as good of a
prediction but
since I didn't have the 5K times so this
is the best I could do.
So, I kind of did an iterative process
where I did more than one
linear regression depending on which data
points I had available for each women.
So you, this, using linear regression's
not too hard to do.
And it's a pretty good way to, to fill in
missing data.
I just want to point out another technique
that you can use to impute missing data.
This is commonly used because it is a
little bit more robust than
the simpler techniques that I just talked
about.
So if you've gotta a, a data set that
you're looking at.
Where the missing data are really
important and
this often comes up say when you're doing
a randomized trial and if you've,
a lot of people got lost to follow up and
you're not sure what their outcomes were.
That's pretty important because usually in
a randomized trial we like to
track exactly what happened to everybody
who was randomized.
So in that case you might to get the most
robust way of filling in
imputing those missing data so multiple
imputation does pretty well.
It's a little bit more work however
because it works likes this.
Basically you're saying I'm making a
guess.
This missing value I'm filling it in with
a guess.
So why not instead of filling it in with a
single guess which might be wrong?
Why not fill it in with a range of
possible guesses?
To do that, I'm actually going to have to
create multiple datasets,
hence the name multiple imputation.
I'm going to have to create more than one
dataset with different values for
those missing data, and then I'm going to
analyze them separately and
at the end of the day, I'm just going to
combine those results.
So I'm going to run separate logistic
regressions on all of those datasets and
then I'm going to average the beta that I
get from all those different logistic
regressions.
So again, it's more work but it's a good
choice if the missing data
really matter because this is a little bit
more robust than the simple techniques.
[BLANK_AUDIO]