[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module, we're going to dive
right into the Logistic regression model.
We've talked about when you have binary or
categorical outcomes, that, that is when
you're looking at proportions.
We've talked about some statistical tests.
When you don't want to adjust for anything
that you can use.
So this is like the risk difference,
relative risk, the Chi-square test,
the McNemar's chi-square test.
So we talked about those, but what about
when you want to
do a regression analysis when you have a
binary or categorical outcome.
In that case, you're going to be using
Logistic regression.
Which we're going to talk about in this
module.
I want to just give you a little overview
of logistic regression.
So, to remind you when we did linear
regression,
the model looked like the following.
We were predicting the value of some
continuous outcome variable, call it y.
As a function of x.
Here's a simple linear regression model,
we have the intercept alpha and
beta is our slope.
So that was the simple linear regression
model.
In the multivariate regression model, we
can add some additional betas and x's.
Additional predictors that makes it then a
plane or a higher dimension thing but
essentially we're fitting lines when you
are regression.
Logistic regression actually isn't that
different.
The right hand side of the equation is
identical in logistic regression, so
it's going to look something like this.
There's a linear combination of betas and,
and x's, risk factors.
It looks exactly the same, and
everything's going to be
set up exactly the same in terms of
defining the predictors of, the, of the.
The model, you can put binary predictors
then you can put continuous,
you can put categorical, you can do dummy
coding.
All of that is the same as with linear
regression.
What's different in logistic regression is
the left-hand side of the equation.
We are no longer modeling Yi, the outcome
variable, directly.
Rather, we're going to be modeling a
transformation of the outcome variable.
In logistic, the case of logistic
regression, we're going to be modeling.
The log odds of the outcome.
And I know that sounds terrible.
That's called a logit function.
But don't worry.
I, I'll explain why in a minute.
We're going to be modeling this logit
function.
The log odds of the outcome.
That's our outcome variable.
We're going to be modeling that as a line
though.
As an alpha plus beta x.
I intercept and the slope.
Because we made this transformation, the
beta is just slightly most
complicated to interpret than the beta
from linear regression.
So for linear regression, the beta was
just the slope.
Is, as x goes up by one unit, how much
does y go up.
So there was a direct interpretation.
It's just slightly more tricky to
interpret the betas from
logistic regression but actually, it's not
terrible because the betas from
logistic regression, if you exponentiate
them, what it gives you out.
Is the odds ratio.
And I refer to, in the second week of the
course, we talked a lot about odds ratios.
And I told you, hey logistic regression
spits out odds ratios.
And this is where it comes from.
The betas can be directly interpreted as
odds ratios just by exponentiating.
And the reason there's an exponential
involved is because our outcome variable
involves a natural log.
So this is just the overview of where
we're going.
This is just, keep in mind that the right
hand side of
the equation is the same as with linear
regression.
So we're still fitting a line, it's just
we're fitting the outcome variable there's
something, trickier going on.
Let me start here with a simple example
using that example dataset, dataset on my
Stanford students.
One of the questions I asked my Stanford
students is whether or
not they considered themselves to be book
smart or street smart.
This is a binary variable, book smart if
the variable is
equal to one that means that they consider
themselves book smart.
If the variable is equal to zero the way
I've coded it.
That means that they consider themselves
to be street smart.
So we can see that this is the book smart
group over here and
this is the street smart book, group over
here.
And I have, just as an aside, I have been
asking this question to lots of
Stanford students just for fun over the
years.
And it generally comes down about 80% of
my Stanford students consider
themselves to be book smart, and about 20%
consider themselves to be street smart.
And that was indeed, the case in this
little practice data set.
It's right around 80%.
I wondered if book smart students did
more,
spent more time on homework or more
studios than street smart students.
And so I wanted to look at the variable
homework in the number of
hours per week that they spent on
homework.
That's another question that I had asked
these students and
we can look at that here and I've done
this, I've looked at this graphicly here.
So I'm graphing.
My predictor variable is just the binary,
a yes no, book smart or
not, and my outcome variable here is
homework, in the number of hours per week.
Now surprisingly, there's students who
consider themselves book-smart as you
can see from this graphic here, actually
on average do slightly less homework
than the students who consider themselves
street-smart, for whatever reason.
So it went, kind of in the opposite
direction from what I might have expected.
This analysis, this graphic that I'm
showing you here actually coincides with
a linear regression.
So the way I've set up the problem now is,
I have got a binary predictor variable and
a continuous outcome variable homework.
And we could model this with a linear
regression,
using what we talked about last week.
When we have a binary predictor, it's a
very simple linear regression.
Right, that line is just, you connect to
the mean for
the street smart group with the mean for
the book smart group.
And when, if you connect two points with a
line that, that defines a line and
so we end up with a very simple line.
So we could answer this question.
Look at this question in this data set
with a linear regression, or
even a t-test, which of course is a
special case of a linear regression.
This is cross-sectional data, however, so
I've happened to pick, just for
the purposes of illustration in, for this
slide to put book smart as
the x variable as the predictor, and
homework as the outcome variable.
But because this is cross sectional data,
I could ask, I could flip that.
I could ask not, whether or not whether
you classify yourself as book smart
predicts the amount of homework you would
do, but I could ask it the other way.
Does the amount of homework you do, the
amount of time you spend on homework,
predict whether or not you consider
yourself book smart.
So I'm just going to flip the x and y
variables.
So here is the graphic when I flip the x
and y variable.
So now my x, my predictor variable, is
continuous, the number of hours spent on
homework per week and my outcome variable
is this binary, this yes, no.
Zero is street smart, one is book smart.
We've got a new graphic.
And we could try to fit a line to these
data, but
look what happens when I try to fit a line
to these data.
Notice that all of my my outcomes are
either all one or
all zero, so you just get these two
stripes.
And it doesn't, it doesn't seem optimal to
try to fit a line.
I, did fit a line to these data.
You can do it.
This is a linear regression line, so
I fit the linear, the best fit line to
these data.
But you can see that if you look at this
picture,
it doesn't really look like that line, it
fits the data very well, right?
I mean, when we were doing linear
regression last week,
we had these scatter plots and
we were trying to find a line that was
kind of very close to all those dots.
Well, this line does, you can fit it, but
it doesn't look very close to all of those
dots.
It doesn't look like a very good fit.
So, a linear regression model was not
optimal, here.
Well, what do we do?
Again, I told you we're still going to
want to fit lines here.
So how can we still fit a line but do
something other than linear regression.
How could we, what could we do.
So what we could do here, is to transform
the outcome variable.
Again, I still want to fit a line
ultimately but
I don't want a 0-1 variable.
As my outcome, because a 0-1 variable
doesn't fit well to a line.
It has only two possible values.
So what could I do?
How could I transform that binary, that
0-1 variable,
into something that better fits a line.
Well, here is one thing.
This is really just a starting point
because we're going to go further with
this but let's just start with, with some
simple thing that we can do.
So, recognize that instead of modelling it
as a yes no, a 0-1.
What if we could somehow model it as a
probability?
A probability, as you know, is a value
that ranges from 0-1 but
it can take on any value between 0-1.
So we would do a little bit better.
We would put in all these values between
0-1 back into play,
if somehow we could model this as, we
could make the outcome variable
the probability of being book-smart,
rather than yes, no, you are book-smart.
Just looking at the data here you can see
well, that's not immediate obvious,
immediately obvious, how you would do it.
In fact we are going to do something
called the logit which is a function of
the probability and in fact what the
computer is going to do, is do
a little algorithm involving some calculus
to calculate the probability or the logit.
But we can kind of approximate it just
actually looking at the data.
And I think this is the best way to
understand it.
So if I wanted to get a probability here
rather than a 0-1 variable.
Well imagine I did the following.
What if I just,
to get a probability I'm going to have to
look at more than one person.
I'm going to have to look at a group of
people.
So what if, I kind of arbitrarily looked
at, you know, a group of people.
Let's just pick say.
The, the ten people with the lowest amount
of homework time per week.
Notice that these little red dots here,
actually some of these dots represent more
than one person, because there were a lot
of people who had tied values.
They selected the same number of homework
and they also called themselves book-smart
for example so that, each of these dots
may represent more than one person.
So imagine that this,
this is what I've put in this box here
represents ten people.
I could look at it, say the ten people
with the lowest amount of homework time,
putting in the lowest amount of homework
time and
I could count up how many of them called
themselves book smart.
And how many of them called themselves
street smart.
And I could calculate a proportion, a
percentage, a probability.
So let's say.
I'm just making this up, but let's say
when I calculate that against since some
of these dots are overlapping I can't do
it exactly but, from the graphic.
But let's say I count up and
I find that among those doing the least
amount of homework.
Let's say that 90% of them, again, I'm
just making this up, let's say 90% of that
ten, nine out of ten, consider themselves
book smart rather than street smart.
Now I've got a probability rather than a
0-1.
And I could do this for the next group of
ten.
The next highest in homework.
Maybe in the next group, the probability
is again, I'm just making this up, is 85%.
And I can't tell because again these dots
are overlapping.
Maybe that comes out to be 85%.
But I could go along and I could group
people.
I have to group people in order to be able
to get a percentage or probability.
But I could come up with some
probabilities.
And of course the probabilities I come up
with are going to depend exactly on
how I group them.
But, just realize that the grouping is
just for the purposes of illustration.
When you actually do this with calculus,
you don't have to make any arbitrary
groupings.
Of course we won't go through the calculus
here.
But the computer does that for you.
So if I could get that probability now, I
can make a graphic.
Which is my predictor variable is the
number of hours of homework per week,
the continuous variable.
Now my outcome variable is a probability.
A number that ranges between 0-1.
I have fewer dots on this graphic.
I'm going to just, for now talk about the
graphic on the left side, this 10 groups.
I notice I have fewer dots on that
graphic.
None of these dots are overlapping any
more.
So I actually have a I had my previous
graphic represented 48 people.
This graphic only represents ten
observations.
I divided those 48 people up into roughly
even groups of
10 groups of you know somewhere between of
about four or
five per group and I got those percentages
and I plotted them here.
What you notice is,
this is much more amenable, this, this
scatter plot to fitting a line.
Right now we've got dots all around the
range and
you can imagine actually fitting a
meaningful line to those dots.
As I mentioned, this is just for
the purposes of graphing, just to show you
the concept.
And so it's arbitrary how I group people,
so of course the graphics is
going to look a little bit different
depending on how I group people.
So just to show you that I also divided
into five groups.
There's 48 people, so this is roughly
groups of, you know, eight, nine, or ten.
And I calculate the proportion who
considered themselves book smart.
That probability, in each of those five
groups and I plotted it here.
By the way, when I'm each of these groups,
of course, has a range of homework values.
I'm using the mean homework time for
each group that's what I'm putting in the
plot here.
So for example the lowest homework group
on this plot here,
they have a mean homework time of just,
you know it maybe 30 minutes to an hour.
And there, the proportion that consider
themselves book smart was right about 78%.
So I'm using the mean just for graphical
purposes but the picture
looks a little different depending on, how
you group it but you can get the idea.
Now we've put back all the numbers between
0-1 into play it
makes much more sense to feel a life.
But this is still limited okay, so this is
not, we're going to go further than that
with this because a probability is a
number that's bounded between 0-1.
So it's still a bounded quantity, you
can't go lower than zero,
you can't go higher than one.
The problem with that is imagine when we
fit a line.
When you fit a line, theoretically, that
line can go anywhere from negative,
the y value can go anywhere from negative
infinity to positive infinity.
So with this it's still not perfect.
So what we're going to do, is instead of
directly having the probability
be the outcome variable, we're going to
make a little transformation.
So probability is bounded from 0-1.
If I divide the probability, however, by
one minus the probability, that,
of course, is what we had learned earlier
is the odds.
So divide the probability by the
probability of something not happening to
the probability divided by one minus the
probability.
That's what we learned in week two of the
course, is in odds.
Why would I want to do that?
Well, a probability can't be bigger than
one but
an odds can go from anywhere, anywhere
from zero to positive infinity.
The odds has no right hand bound.
So now we've put in all the positive real
numbers back into play.
We're still missing the negatives.
How can we get the negatives back in?
So, here's where the natural log comes in.
So, if I then take the natural log of the
odds, it turns out, that when you take
a natural log, any value that was below
one now becomes a negative number.
So this, the natural log of the odds,
actually ranges from negative,
can theoretically range from negative
infinity to positive infinity.
So now we put all the numbers back into
play.
So now this is the most optimal
fore-fitting a line.
So the outcome variable for logistic
regression, as I'd mentioned earlier,
is actually going to be the natural log of
the odds of the outcome.
A little complicated, but, it's for
mathematical reasons that we,
we choose that.
And just to illustrate, I took those, the
same groupings, ten groups and
five groups where I had calculated the
percent, the probability of
being book smart in each of those groups
and I transformed that into a log on.
So that as I took the percentage, divided
one minus the percentage and
then took the natural log of that number.
This gives me some numbers like 0.5, 1.0,
1.5, 2.0.
The, the log odds has no inherent meaning
to me.
But that's okay,
because when we eventually will translate
it back into something meaningful.
But now this outcome variable is a number
that
can theoretically go anywhere from
negative infinity to positive infinity.
Makes a very fit, nicer fore-fitting a
line.
I'm graphing here the logit for each of
these groups against, again,
the mean homework time in each of those
groups.
And you could fit a line to that.
And that's what we're doing in logistic
regression.
That's the line that we're fitting.
So we're going to estimate an alpha and a
beta, an intercept and
a slope for that particular line.
As I mentioned, the groupings here are
completely arbitrary.
When you actually do this in a computer,
there's calculus going on and so
you're going to get the best alpha and the
best beta.
When I do this graphically, it's a little
bit of an approximation.
You can see that the line is slightly
different when I group it into ten groups
than when I group it into five groups,
these lines are slightly different.
But we can actually kind of look at these
graphics and just kind of
visually approximate the equation of that
light, so I'm going to do that now.
This is not as good as doing the calculus
in the computer, but
it is, it'll give us a little bit of an
approximation, and
I think is also good for illustrating
what's actually going on here.
So what is the equation of this line?
There's two lines here, and
we can kind of say the, the real line is
going to be somewhere around these two.
So first of all what's the intercept
value.
So if I just look at the graphic, my
intercept for this line over on the left
side is then, I guess about 1.6 you know,
I'm just approximating here.
And the intercept over for
the line on the right hand side of the
page is maybe about 1.8.
So let's just kind of call it that the,
the equation for this line.
Again, if we're kind of saying there's one
line here that we're trying to
approximate, maybe it's around 1.7.
I'm just making,
somewhere in that ballpark, maybe around
1.7 is the intercept.
How would I get the slopes of these lines,
just visually here,
how could I approximate the slopes of
these lines.
So what's the slope is rise over run, so I
can say well, how much have I gone up
in the y variable and how much have I gone
up in the x variable.
So, I can just kind of look at this as a
triangle here, and say,
well, what's the, how far did I go on the,
on the x-axis, I went from about 0 to 40.
So, the x change is about 40, here, for
this triangle.
On the y end of things, yeah, if you
kind of approximate it,
it's maybe going from about 0.3 maybe to
1.6.
I'm going to just call it 1.3.
So, sort of the, you, the, we go up 1.3,
in the log odds.
So the slope here is going to be rise over
run, so, 1.3 divided by 40,
or approximately 0.03.
So the slope here is about 0.03.
For this line we can use the same kind of
logic.
So, for the x we went over about 35 here.
That's about 0 to 35.
On the y end we've gone up a little bit
bigger,
maybe about 1.8 from one to about 1.8.
The slope then would be 1.8 divided by 35
which is about 0.05.
So, you know, the somewhere, I'm going to
approximate somewhere between 0.03 and
0.05, let's call it 0.04.
And, of course, this is negative.
I should emphasize here that this is a
downward slope.
We've gone down 1.3 or down 1.8 in y.
So both of these slopes are negative.
So on average, the slope's maybe somewhere
around negative 0.04.
This is just my graphical approximation,
but
that's what we're doing on logistic
regression.
That's the line we're fitting.
Now I'm actually going to put the data in
the computer, and
let the computer use the beautiful
calculus to estimate this perfectly.
To get the actual best intercept and best
beta slope that fits these data.
And I'll show you that our, our
approximation wasn't bad.
Here's what the compute comes out with
when it does what's called the maximum
likelihood estimation.
This involves calculus.
And it gives us some maximum likelihood
estimates.
I'm not going to go into the details of
maximum likelihood estimation.
That's for another course, but this is
just a way that, using some calculus,
that we're getting the best alpha and the
best beta here, the best fit line.
So, when I do this on the computer, the
intercept comes out to be just over two,
so just slightly different than what we
did, got in our approximation.
The slope came out to be right around
negative 0.04, negative 0.039.
So, and where did I get those in the
output?
Here's the estimate for the intercept.
That's the alpha estimate.
Here's the estimate for the beta.
That's the estimate for the slope.
Along with the alpha and the beta, we also
get a p value to tell us whether that
alpha or beta is statistically different
than zero.
A beta of zero would mean no association,
same as it did with linear regression.
So the intercept is clearly significantly
different than zero.
Again, that's not all that meaningful
here,
because we wouldn't expect the intercept
to be zero.
However, the, the p value for homework is
not statistically significant.
So as you might have guessed,
just looking at the picture, there isn't a
strong association here.
So it's not statistically different than
zero, probably meaning it doesn't look
like there's a lot of evidence that
homework and whether or
not you consider your book, yourself book
smart are related.
But here's the final model.
The log odds of your champion, the log
odds of being book smart, or
considering yourself book smart, is equal
to the intercept 2.12, minus the slope,
point 0.039.
And we would, of course, multiply that
beta times the amount of homework.
So this is a continuous predictor.
So we would be multiplying the amount of
homework for
a particular person times that slope.
What's this logistic regression equation
useful for?
So, just like when we talked about linear
regression,
there's many couple different pote,
potential functions here.
So one thing is we could use the logistic
regression equation model to try to
do some kind of prediction.
This is very useful in clinical
applications,
because often we want to classify people
as having a condition, or
not having a condition, that's a binary
outcome.
So, if we're doing that kind of
prediction,
we would likely be using logistic
regression.
So we can try to come up with a set of
predictors that predicts who's going to
have a disease or not have a disease.
So that's one of the functions of logistic
regression prediction.
A second function of logistic regression
which is probably used even more often,
is just to try to say, is a particular
predictor,
like homework, related to the outcome.
In this case, book smart or
street smart, are those variables related,
these are treatment related to an outcome.
And, that's very useful in an,
in and of itself, and of course, we can
say, is that predictor,
that treatment, related to the outcome
after adjusting for potential confounders.
So that's another very important use of
the logistic regression model.
I'm going to start by talking just briefly
about the first of these aims which is
the prediction end of things.
Again, here is the logistic regression
model.
We've modeled the outcome variable, is the
log odds of the outcome the,
we're modeling that as a line.
Let me take that model that we just fit
and
how would we actually apply it to make
some predictions?
So, if you're somebody who does no
homework per week.
Zero hours of homework per week.
You could plug in that [COUGH] value for
homework of zero into the model.
You get that you're predicted logit is
2.12.
As I've mentioned, most of us don't think
in logit, so in a minute,
we're going to do something with that
number to make it more interpretable but
if you did ten hours per week of homework,
you could plug in ten.
The predicted logit there was 1.73.
If you did 50 hours per week, the
predicted logit is 0.17.
So the more homework you do the more the
logit goes down.
Well I don't want to deal with a logit,
because the logit I,
I can't think in logit.
However, we can get this, notice the
[UNKNOWN], there's a probability in there.
What we want to get out is the predicted
probability of the outcome.
The predictive probability of considering
yourself book smart in this case.
I want to isolate this predicted
probability.
Well it's actually not that hard to do,
right.
We've got one equation one unknown.
We can isolate that probability.
So, how do we do it?
First thing that we're going to want to do
is,
we are going to want to exponentiate both
sides.
So for example the zero hours per week.
That person would be predicted to have a
logit of 2.12.
I can then exponentiate both sides of
those, of that equation.
So that would tell me that the odds for
somebody who does zero homework per
week is the exponential raised to 2.12.
That value is 8.33, if you actually
calculate out.
So e raised to 2.2 is 8.33.
That's the odds for a person who does the
odds of being book smart, for
a person who does zero hours per week of
homework.
Then we could exponentiate this 1.73,
that will give me the odds for somebody
who does ten hours per week, that's 5.64.
We could exponentiate the 0.17, that gives
me the odds for
somebody who does 50 hours per week, that
comes out to be 1.19.
So your odds of being book smart again
goes down as
you do more homework per week.
Sort of the opposite of what you might
expect.
But of course this is not statistically
significant.