[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to show you
how to apply principal components
analysis to real data.
So I'm going to use this example of the 91
women runners,
the data set that I've been referring to
this week.
This was a data set I was looking at on
potential predictors of bone density and
stress fractures in adolescent women
runners.
This is a group that's at risk of low bone
density and fractures.
So the research has measured a number of
variables.
They measured some variables on body size
and composition.
We saw those in an earlier module.
They also looked at running performance
and training, since these are all runners.
They also looked at menstrual function,
which is linked to bone density.
They also looked at things about diet and
disordered eating.
I'm just going to focus on a subset of
variables,
just to keep this exercise manageable.
So I'll look at these first three
categories.
And just a few of the variables from
within each of these categories.
I'll look at a total of 11 variables, and
I'm going to apply principal components
analysis to these 11 variables.
So here are the 11 variables that we're
going to be using for
this principal components analysis.
So first of all, the researches did a DEXA
measurement on all of these women.
The DEXA measurement measures their bone
density, but
it also gives you very precise
measurements of fat and lean mass.
So they had measured what's called the
Android fat ratio,
which is a marker of visceral fat like how
much belly fat you're carrying.
They also had fat mass, BMI, lean mass and
height.
The fat mass comes also out of the DEXA as
well as the lean mass.
Not surprisingly, all of these measures of
body size and
composition are all highly correlated.
They also have measures of running
performance and training.
Those would include the best mile time,
how many miles per
week women were running, and the pace at
which they did their interval work.
And of course, those again are all highly
correlated.
They also looked at menarche age,
menstrual periods in the past periods in
the past year, average menstrual periods
since menarche.
These are all obviously menstrual function
variables that also relates to
bone density.
So not only are the variables within each
of these categories highly correlated,
but, they're also correlated across
different categories.
So, it turns out that the women who had
higher fat mass and
weighed more, tended to actually be slower
and to run less.
And, so that was related, correlated to
running performance.
And, this is probably bidirectional.
So, if you're carrying more fat, that may
slow you down.
And plus, the women who are competitive
and who are running more miles per
week are probably also going to be leaner
because they're running a lot, so
that could go in both directions.
But those were correlated.
Also, your measures of body composition
and
size, especially, fat mass, again, was
related to menstrual function.
So in this population it turns out that
carrying more fat is
actually good in terms of having better
menstrual function.
So we're going to take these highly
correlated 11 variables and
we're going to put them in our principal
components analysis.
And the goal here is to try to come up
with a smaller subset of
variables that represent these larger
constructs such as body size and
composition or menstrual function.
And I'm now going to walk you through the
steps of
actually doing a principal components
analysis.
And I'll just walk you through each one of
these steps in turn, so
let's just turn to each one of these steps
now, okay.
So, the first step, before you even put
the data into the principal components
analysis, there's a few processing steps
that you have to do first.
Very importantly, you need to impute any
missing data.
So, if an observation is missing even one
data point, from just one variable,
that observation will not be included in
the principal components analysis.
What that means is, if just a few of your
observations are missing a few data
points on a couple of variables, that can
really add up.
One missing data point gets you kicked out
of the analysis.
There, we're for putting 11 variables into
the principal components analysis.
There's a lot of opportunities for
observations to get kicked out.
If you were putting more than 11
variables,
which is very typical, you can imagine
that a little bit of missing data here and
there can result in, say you start with a
sample size of 500,
that suddenly might turn out to go down to
a sample size of 200.
In other words, your analysis might only
run on 200 of your observations even if
you started with 500.
So you've got to be very careful and
make sure that you always fill in your
missing data in some way.
The other thing that you're going to need
to do is you need to
standardize your variables.
We already talked about that.
They all have to have a mean of zero and a
standard deviation of one.
One other thing I just want to point out
now,
is that principal components analysis
typically run numeric variables.
So, we saw in the last module that
principal components analysis is based on
the linear relationship.
That is, the linear correlation between
pairs of variables.
So technically, all the assumptions of
linear regression would apply here.
That would mean that you should have
continuous normally distributed variables.
Now in practice we actually don't always
worry about these assumptions.
It's important to meet these assumptions
if you're trying to calculate p values.
But that's not what we're usually doing
with principal components analysis.
We're usually doing something more
exploratory.
And for exploratory purposes it
really doesn't matter if you violate these
assumptions.
But generally we're going to be dealing
with numeric variables.
Even if they're not perfectly normally
distributed.
And these nu, numeric variables need to be
standardized.
So we're going to do that first, I've
already done that to this data set.
The next thing we're going to do is we're
going to actually apply the PCA
analysis and you can do this in most
standard statistical packages with
the right code or the right click of a
button.
Its usually fairly straightforward, I put
my 11 variables into a SASS and apply
my principal components analysis and I'll
show you the results in just a minute.
But the first decision that you actually
have to make after you apply this
analysis to your data is to decide how
many components do you want to retain?
So we started with 11 variables, and
the idea is we want to compress those
variables into a smaller number.
So at some point I have to decide what's
that smaller number?
When I run the principal components
analysis on 11 variables, I'm going to get
11 components back out, but I'm going to
want to weed some of these out.
So I have to decide, do I want to get down
to three variables, do I want to
get down to four, five, six, how many
components am I actually going to keep?
And there's a number of different criteria
that can be used to make this decision.
There's no hard and
fast rule, so here's all the different
kind of criteria that we're going to use.
I'll walk you through these in turn, but I
just want to point out that there's,
there's no hard and fast rule, and the
answer at the end of the day really is
going to depend on your particular data
set, and the goals of your analysis.
Okay.
Now let me go through each one of these
steps in turn.
So, first thing is, I applied my principal
components analysis to my data set.
So when I have, start with 11 variables,
I'm going to end up with 11 components.
So you see those 11 components are
pictured here.
So this is one of the outputs that you get
from your statistical package.
You get the Eigenvalues.
We talked about the Eigenvalues in the
last module.
Remember that Eigenvalues just re,
represent how much variance is explained
by that particular component.
And they, the components are going to be
from the highest to the lowest, so
the first component is going explain it in
the most of the variance and
they get diminishingly smaller after that.
Now, some people will use a very simple
criteria for deciding how
many components to retain in your analysis
by just looking at the eigenvalue.
So, they'll say, if the eigenvalue is
greater than one,
then we're going to keep that component
and
if the eigenvalue is less than one, we're
going to drop that component.
According to that criteria, here, we would
retain four components in our analysis.
This is the idea.
Each variable entered into the model
started with a variance of one.
So every original variable, by itself,
explained a variance of one.
Remember because we have standardized
variables, so
all of the variances are going to be equal
to one.
So we started with a variance sort of of
11.
Each one had one for a total of our
variance of 11 in our data set.
So a very simple criteria would just be to
say, okay,
well, any eigenvalue greater than one
would mean that that
component explains more of the variance
than any single original variable.
Since we're getting more information than
a single variable could give us,
it seems like it would be worth keeping
them.
On the other hand, if the eigenvalue is
less than one,
then that component explains less than the
variable contained in any single variable.
So, that would argue that you might want
to drop that variable because it
contains less information than sort of,
you started with.
Now, this eigenvalue greater than one
criteria has advantages and disadvantages.
So an advantage is that it is really easy
to, to apply.
A disadvantage is, it may not always be
the right choice for
your particular data set.
You're going to need to look at other
things to make this decision.
In the end of the day in this particular
example I did in
fact end up retaining four components.
There are several reasons beside just the
eigenvalue greater than one criteria.
So here's some other things that we can
look at.
We can also just look at the percent of
the total variance explained.
So you'll notice that again,
as I mentioned, each of these explains
some amount of variance.
Well obviously the,
the first component always explains the
greatest amount of variance.
So you can see that this output tells me
how much,
what proportion of the variance, did each
component explain.
The first principal component, in this
case, explained a variance of 3.5.
The total variance was 11, so
this principle component explained 31.95%
of the total variance.
The second principal component explained a
variance of 2.15 out of a total of 11.
So that one explained 19.59% of the total
variance.
You can look at the cumulative total.
So when, the first explains 31 or 32%.
Once we've got two components,
we've actually explained more than half of
the variance in our original 11 variables.
If we go to a third component, we've now
got up to explaining 64% of the variance.
If we go up to a fourth component, we've
now explained 76% of the variance.
So in just four variables now,
we have captured 76% of the variability of
the information in the original 11.
And that might be enough, we might say,
well hay that's pretty good.
With just four I can get 76% of the total
variance.
Some might argue that well, if I go up one
more I can get and
additional 8% up to 84%.
And so, some people might argue to go up
to five,
just to get that much higher with only one
additional component.
Again, in this case I ended up deciding to
go with four.
I'll tell you that I also ran on the
analysis with five,
so I can show you what the difference was
in the little a little bit later on.
So that's the eigenvalue greater than one
and just looking at the total variance.
Another common thing that people look at
is something called the Scree plot, okay.
So this scree pot, plot, what it's showing
you, is it basically take the information
that I was showing you, on, in table form,
and it just puts it into a plot.
So on the x axis, we have the components.
They're just numbered here from one to 11.
Those are just, so, the number component.
On the y axis we plot the eigenvalue,
which,
again, I was just showing you in the last
table.
So, for example, the first principal
component had an eigenvalue of 3.5.
And then you just connect the dots.
And the idea with this Scree Plot is
you're looking for
a place where, you know, that, you'll
always see where
this Scree Plot there'll be kind of a
steep drop at the beginning.
And then at some point it might level off.
And if you can find that point where the,
you,
goes from being a steep drop to leveling
off, that's what we call the elbow.
And a lot of people will say you'll just
retain components up until the elbow.
Now, this a is real data and so
real data doesn't always come out the way
we want it to.
And in this particular screen plot doesn't
have a really clear elbow, I mean you
could kind of say, well you know you could
drop down here and then maybe at three.
Maybe that's an elbow, because you start
to level off.
But then it starts dropping steeply again
between four and five.
So, you could say, well maybe, you know,
the elbow is here at six,
because this clearly starts leveling off
at about six.
So, if there's no clear break point in
this particular data set,
I would say, you know, we can say for
sure that by the time you get to six,
you're really leveling off.
So you're probably going to want to retain
fewer than six components.
Again, whether you choose four or five or
three, it's a little you're going to
have to use some other information to help
you make that decision.
Now, because, this is what I, I just
want to show you that our data set didn't
generate the most interesting scree plot,
so I made up a hypothetical scree plot,
just to show you what you're kind of
hoping your scree plot will look like.
So this is sort of a typical scree plot
that you're hoping to get because it
will make your life easier.
This one again has a total of 11
components on the x axis.
The eigenvalues are on the y axis.
And again these are made up data, so
that's why they look so pretty and, and
nice and smooth here.
So, what we're looking for in the screen
plot again, is this elbow.
So the elbow in this case occurs at
component four.
The elbow is the inflection point.
It's where you go from having a steep drop
off to have, to plateauing.
And you can see there's a clear elbow here
at four.
And what people will do is they'll say,
okay, you, you identify the elbow, and
you either decide to retain the number of
components that marks the elbow, so
you, you could retain four, or even more
typically,
more commonly, people will retain, retain
one less than the elbow.
So they might say, okay, the elbow's at
four, so
therefore I'm going to retain three
components.
So looking at a screen plot like this, you
were going to, you're going to decide to
retain either three or four, after three
or four there is clearly a diminishing
returns, you're not getting much from the
additional components.
Again, with real data, doesn't always look
so perfect.
But this is sort of an idealize scree
plot.
So we're going to look at all of those
factors,
the eigenvalues, the percent of the
variants explained and the scree plot and
we're going to make some kind of decision
about how many variable to retain.
In this case, I decided to retain four.
I'll also show you what happened when I
retained five,
just to show you the difference there.
Just to emphasize again, you're always
considering your own
dataset-specific goals, so there may be
cases
where you decide to retain a component
that doesn't explain much of the variance.
So, let's say that there's a particular
construct that doesn't
appear until component six.
But you really care about isolating that
construct and
looking at the effect of that construct.
In that case, even if that particular
component doesn't explain much of
the variance, you might decide to go out
to six components just because there's
something out at six that you really care
about.
So again, you really have to consider the
goals of your particular analysis when
making this decision.
Okay.
So, the next step that we're going to do
is we're going to apply something called a
Varimax rotation, okay?
Actually, the computer is going to do this
for us.
So once we've decided how many components
to retain, we're going to retain four in
this case, then we're going to ask the
computer to apply this Varimax rotation.
What is the point of this?
The point of the Varimax rotation is that
it forces each variable,
each of my original 11 variables, to load
strongly.
To align with only one particular
component and not with the other.
And, I'm going to show you exactly how
this works in a minute.
This is going to make our results more
interpretable because it
will be really clear, for example, that
fat mass loads on principle component one.
And thus that principle component one has
something to do with body fat.
So this rotation helps us purely in terms
of interpretation of the components, and
if you didn't need to interpret the
components for some reason.
If your analysis wasn't focused on that,
then you wouldn't necessarily need to
apply this.
But for most examples in epidemiology and
medicine, we actually want to understand
what those components actually mean.
So we're going to apply this Varimax
rotation.
The rotation is also orthogonal.
All that means is that it guarantees us
that at the end of the day,
our components will be uncorrelated with
one another.
They'll be independent.
And so that's also important, we want to
end up with independent components.
So let me show you just how this works.
So first of all,what I'm showing you here
is what we get before I apply the Varimax
rotation, just to show you here.
I also want to point out something about
the output here.
So if you're looking carefully, you'll
notice that I was talking about
components but all of a sudden, in the
output, we see factor pattern and
factor one, factor two, factor three, et
cetera.
So where did the word factor suddenly pop
up here, okay?
What's happening here is that there is
something called a factor analysis,
which is related to a principal components
analysis.
And a lot of computer programs,
you actually do your principal components
analysis from within the factor analysis.
And that's what I have done here in SASS,
I ran a principal components analysis but
it was run from within a factor analysis.
You actually have to do that if you want
to apply this Varimax rotation.
So the output says factors because this
was done as part of
using the algorithm for doing a factor
analysis.
This is still a principal components
analysis however, so I'm basically going
to end up using the words factor and
component interchangeably here.
You should just be aware that a factor
analysis is something different than
a principal components analysis.
But, again,
you can do a principal components analysis
from within a factor analysis.
If you do that,
obviously, the output from your computer
program is going to say factor.
But these are just components, these are
the components.
So wherever you see, say, see factor, you
can just say, component.
And what I'm showing you in this table,
what the,
the, this output shows you is what are
called the factor loadings.
So recall that all that the factors or the
components are these new variables.
All they are is a linear combination of
your original variables.
So they're, we're going to apply some
weights.
And multiply each one of my original
variables by the, by a weight, and
add those up to get a sort of a composite
variable.
That's called the component.
And, once I calculate those component
variables.
I can then take the, those new variables,
the factor one or
component one, and I can find a
correlation between each of
my original variables with my my new
variable, with my component.
And that's called the factor loading.
So all that you're seeing here in this
table is a correlation coefficient.
So I came out with a new variable.
Principle component one, that new
variable, when I run a correlation
coefficients, when I calculate correlation
coefficients with all my
original variables, I get the correlations
you see pictured in this table.
And remember, these principle components,
again, are just a linear combination of
the original variables.
But the factor loadings are very important
because you can look at
them to get a sense of what is it that the
components represent, so what is
principal component that new variable,
what one, what does that represent.
Well if you look at the the factor
loadings before applying this
Varimax rotation.
It's very hard to say what principle
component one means.
You can see that Android fat mass is
really highly correlated to
this new variable.
Lean mass, somewhat.
Fat mass is highly correlated to this new
variable.
So is BMI.
The others are a little bit lower but you
get down here also mile time and
miles run per week are highly correlated
to this principal component one.
So it's some compilation of body size,
body fat mass, performance.
It doesn't have a clear meaning to it.
We'd like, instead, for
each one of these original variables to
only appear in one of the components.
To make it a very clear, to make it very
clear.
What each of the components mean.
So, we apply the Varimax rotation, and
notice what happens.
This is wonderful, when we apply the
Varimax rotation, all of a sudden,
the meaning of these different principal
components falls out.
So, for example, the Android fat ratio,
where if you look at before the rotation,
it loaded heavily on factor one but
it also loaded somewhat on factor three
and somewhat on factor four.
If you look now after the rotation,
Android fat
ratio has a really high correlation with
principal component one and
it loads hardly at all on the rest of the
principal components.
So this is going to make interpretation
much, much easier.
If you look down the columns, each one of
these columns is one of these,
is the principal component.
So principal component one, for example,
has a high correlation, the factor
loadings are high for Android fat ratio,
which is a measure of visceral fat, or
belly fat, for fat mass and for BMI.
So we have correlations of 0.87, 0.79, and
0.91.
So those three variables load very
strongly on principle component one.
That's telling you that principle
component one has something to
do with body fatness.
If you keep going down the column you'll
notice that most of the other
variables have values very close to zero,
correlations very close to zero.
Mile time is a little bit correlated
still, but it's it's of,
still a fairly small correlation.
So we can now interpret what principal
component one actually means.
It's a measure of body fatness, how much
fat are you carrying on your body.
We go to principal component two, and we
look down the column, and
we look at these correlation coefficients.
So Android fat, fat mass, BMI, are no
longer strongly correlated,
they're not that strongly correlated with
principal component two.
However, the measures of running, training
and performance are.
So mile time is highly correlated with
principal component two.
A higher, faster mile time gives you a
higher correlation here.
A so this is saying that principal
component two is a measure of
how competitive you are, higher numbers
mean more competitive.
Mileage meaning your running more miles
per week that was highly correlated with
principal component two.
Interval pace also strongly loads on
principal component two and so
we can see that principal component two is
a measure of
running performance and competitiveness.
Now, here's something that's really
interesting.
Menarche age, which doesn't have anything
naturally to do with running performance.
This is the age at which a woman begins to
menstruate.
You would think that that variable would
load on the same principal component as
the other variables of menstrual function.
But, actually, in this data set,
menarche age loads most strongly on
principal component two.
Notice it does not load strongly on any of
the other components.
What this is telling you is that menarche
age, in this population,
is strongly related to a woman's running
performance and competitiveness.
And if you think about it carefully,
this kinds of make sense because these are
adolescent woman runners and
some of them have, may have started
running before they hit puberty.
And, that running has a big influence on
the age at which they begin menstruating.
So that's kind of an interesting insight
that comes out of the principal
components analysis.
Menarche age is much more strongly related
to your running competiveness,
competitiveness, than it is to other men,
measures of menstrual functions.
So that's an interesting insight.
Now looking at principal component three,
principal component three turns out to be
some kind of measures of body size.
So, if you look down Android fat ratio,
fat mass and
BMI do not load strongly on principal
component three.
But, lean mass and height load very
strongly on principal component three.
That's telling you that this is some
measure of kind of how tall, and
big boned, and how much muscle you have.
It's some measure of body size, and what's
really cool here is that normally measures
of body size and composition they're kind
of they're kind of hard to tease apart.
Normally all these measures, fat mass,
BMI, even lean mass, height,
all these things conflate both your body
size and your body fatness, right.
Because, if you're somebody who is, has a
higher fat mass,
that could be both because you're just
somebody who is bigger, and it could be
because if you're bigger you're obviously
going to ca, carry more fat mass.
But it also could be because you're
somebody who is carrying extra fat.
Higher fat mass could mean both of those
things.
But what we've done here is,
remember the principal components are
independent of one another.
They're uncorrelated.
So we have untangled body fatness,
that is how much body fat you're carrying,
from body size.
And Principal component three represents
now just a measure of just how big you
are, independent of how much fat you're
carrying.
Whereas principle component one represents
a measure of how much fat you're com,
carrying, independent sort of of how big
you are.
So we've untangled these two constructs,
which is really useful,
because now we can say, we can isolate the
effect of each one of those constructs.
And then finally, principal component four
is just a measure of menstrual regularity.
So this was the periods in the past year
and
the average periods per year since
menarche.
Those two variables look very strongly on
principal component four,
and actually none of the other variables
really have
any correlation with principal component
four.
So, this is really a measure of how
regular your menstrual periods are.
So, those are the meanings of the, the
four components.
And I'll just mention that I also reran
the analysis.
Asking to retain five components, just to
see what would happen.
And so what happened when I did that was
actually that menarche age, which had
loaded with running performance before,
became its own principal component.
So the fifth component became a measure
purely of menarche age.
And the rest of the components stayed
basically the same.
So if I wanted to isolate the effect of
menarche age and
separate it from running performance, I
would have to ask for a fifth component,
so if I cared about specifically about
that, the effect of that variable.
But it's interesting, and it gives me
insight when I ask for four components,
because it tells me that there's this
relationship between running and
menarche age in this population.
Now, these are the factor loadings,
which I was showing you on the previous
slide here.
I just want to tell you exactly how the
principal
components are actually calculated.
The factor loadings are the correlations
between each
principal component variable and the
original variables.
But, what are the actual weights that are
used to calculate those
principal components.
How did, how does the computer actually
calculate those?
So, what I'm showing you on this next
screen is the actual weights
that are used to calculate the principal
component.
So just how, how do we actually calculate
these, so here's a set of weights.
Notice that the pattern is the same here,
so these are the weights that would be
multiplied by the original variables and
summed up, and that would give us
principal component one.
So you would take a woman's Android fat
ratio, whatever number she has for
that, and would multiply it by 0.4.
You would then add that to her fat mass
times 0.28.
You would then add that to her BMI times
0.41.
You would then add that to her lean mass
times 0.09.
You would add that to her height times
negative 0.19, etc.
You would do this for all 11 variables,
you'd come out with some number,
that score is a, is a women's score on
principal component one.
Those scores will turn out to have a mean
of zero and a standard deviation of one so
they will be in standard deviation unit.
So a woman who comes out with a, say a,
you know, a standard deviation of
a score on principal component one of 1.6,
that would mean we had somebody who
was carrying a relatively high amount of
body fat for this population.
And again you can see that whatever
variables are heavily weighted in
the linear combination, those are going to
be the same ones that have
a high correlation with principal
component one.
So that's just how you actually calculate
the principal components,
of course you don't have to do this by
hand the computer will
automatically calculate new variables,
principle of components one, two,
three and four, for all of the
observations in your data set.
But this is just where it comes from.
All right, so now we've gone through all
the steps of the PCA.
We applied the Varimax rotation.
We interpreted the meanings of our
components.
Did that.
And then the final thing we can do is,
now we can take these new variables, now
we have four new variables that
contain scores in standard deviation units
for all the women in our data set.
We can take those new variables.
And we can do further statistics on them.
So what I actually did here was,
I ran a logistic regression to predict
stress fractures.
So we have a binary outcome.
They either had a stress fracture or they
didn't.
I put my new variables, my four principle
components, into a model.
Where the outcome is the logitive stress
fracture, and I've got my body fatness,
running performance, body size, and
menstrual function variables now.
Now, I'll just mention that because the
principal components are actually
independent, they're uncorrelated with one
another, it actually doesn't matter if I
throw them all together in a single
multi-variate analysis.
Or if I run them in separate univariate
regressions.
You really don't even need to do a
multivariate analysis anymore
because there's nothing to adjust for.
The predictors are already independent.
So that makes your model building quite
easy.
So, look, for example, if I were to run
the same model with stress fractures as
my outcome, but only body fatness in the
model and
nothing else, I would get the exact same
data coefficient.
And the exact same people are very,
very close, so that's makes life easy in
terms of model building.
But now let's just kind of look at the
results, now remember that I actually
showed you some results about stress
fractures in an earlier module.
And all of the measures,
we were looking at the measures of body
size and composition.
And it turned out that having a bigger
body size or carrying more fat, all of
those things were linked to protection
against a lower risk of stress fracture.
But now, we can separate out the body
fatness, that is,
how much fat you're carrying from your
body size,
we weren't able really to do that before,
those things were confounded.
When we do that, you'll notice that
principal component one, which is
body fatness, remember in the original
analysis, the earlier analysis I showed
you, the best protection against fractures
was due to having a higher fat mass.
But fat mass was related to menstrual
function, and so it
was probably the case that carrying more
fat improved your menstrual function and
that's why you're protected against
fractures.
Now we've teased out the effective body
fatness from the effective
menstrual function.
When we do that, the body fatness variable
is no longer statistically significant and
you can see that it's, you know that it's
still a little bit protective to
have more body fat but the estimate here
is not very big.
The beta coefficient is not very big.
If you look at principal component two,
which is this measure of running, how much
you run and how fast you run.
That actually is significantly related to
fracture.
The beta coefficient is pretty big, 0.9,
and so if you run more,
if you're more competitive, you have a
higher risk of fracture,
this beta coefficient is positive, higher
risk.
That makes sense, because the harder you
run, the more you run, and
the faster you run, the more like you are,
likely you are to fracture.
The third principal component, body size,
doesn't quite make statistical
significance.
The p value is 0.07.
But the, the beta coefficient is about the
same as it was for running performance.
It's negative, meaning that this is
protective.
And what this is telling you is that,
if you're just a bigger person, if you're
taller, if you're big boned and
maybe carry more muscle, all of that
protects you against fracture.
And that probably has to do with the fact
that if you're a bigger person, you
tend to have bigger bone density because,
you know, we call people big boned.
If you have more bone density,
more bone strength, that obviously would
protect you against fracture.
And then, finally, the principle competent
four.
This one was to have the strongest
relationship with fracture.
It is significant and it's negative 1.04.
So having better menstrual function
protects you
pretty strongly against fracture.
And that's actually a well known thing
that in this population of women runners,
having better menstrual function improves
your bone density and
protects against fracture.