In this next module I'm going to briefly
review the concept of
exact logistic regression.
I am actually going to spare you the math
details on this one so
we'll just go over what it means
conceptually.
We've already talked about exact tests
within this course.
When are exact tests used?
They're used in the situation where you
have sparse data.
Well it's the same thing here.
Logistic regression relies on maximum
likelihood estimation,
as we talked about in the previous
modules.
Maximum likelihood estimation is an
asymptotic technique.
All that means is, that it requires sort
of an, at least a moderate sample size.
Otherwise you're making some assumptions,
some approximations, and
those will fall down when you have very
small data sets, very sparse data.
So maybe you have a situation where some
of the groups in your sample,
have a very low outcome rate.
Sparse data you might then need to turn to
exact logistic regression.
And it's analogous to when you need to use
Fisher's exact test rather then
the Chi-squared test, it's analogous to
that situation.
I won't go through the details of how
exactly logistic
regression works mathematically, but
basically it's very similar to what we did
with the Fisher's exact test.
You're calculating all possible outcomes.
What you saw in all possible outcomes.
So you're looking at actually calculating
exact probabilities rather
than approximating.
And actually I'm going to go back to the
exact example that we
used with the Fisher's exact test.
So we had this example about Fisher's tea
tasting experiment.
And you can analyze these data, as we did,
with a Fisher's exact test.
There's a simple, binary predictor here.
So we don't really need to get
complicated.
But I'll just show you,
these, that it can also be analyzed in the
logistic regression framework.
There's no reason we couldn't put this
into a logistic regression.
Our outcome here.
Is whether or not the milk was poured
first.
The predictor here is what she guessed.
Does her, do her guesses actually predict
the,
the correctly which cups have milk poured
first?
So we can put this in the logistic
regression framework but because
there are sparse data we're going to need
to turn to this exact logistic regression.
So what is the logistic regression model
going to be here?
Well either the outcome here is that it's
either a milk poured first cup or its not.
This is the kind of the truth.
Is it a milk poured first cup or not?
That's the outcome.
It either is or it isn't.
We're going to be monitoring the log odds
of that as a function of alpha.
Plus and what's beta here?
Well beta, the predictor here, is whether,
is whether her guess is correct.
She guessed it was or she didn't.
Guessed milk first.
So she either guesses that the milk is
first or she doesn't.
Milk was poured first or she doesn't.
If she is a good, if she can really
distinguish them, then this
beta should be significant because her
guesses should predict whether or
not the, actually had milk poured first.
So it's a very simple logistic model.
We can throw this into the computer and
actually get some outputs.
So first of all I'm going to show you the
maximum likelihood estimation results.
So this is just running a regular logistic
regression.
It'll do it in this case, even those it
has sparse data,
it will estimate it for you.
The algorithm will solve.
You'll get some alphas and betas.
You'll get some p-values.
The one that we care most about is the
p-value for the guessing milk first.
That tells us the null hypothesis here is
that
she can't guess any better than chance.
And that tells us in this case she, we, as
we saw before.
We don't have enough evidence to reject
the null hypothesis.
We also get here an odds ratio estimate
because we've done logistic regression.
We can get out an odds ratio.
The odds ratio here comes out to be nine.
Of course that just comes from three times
three, divided by one times one.
That comes out to be nine.
We get these, confidence limits as well.
So just pay attention to those values.
That's the maximum likelihood estimation
results.
However, the problem is that again,
maximum likelihood estimation falls down
when you have very sparse data.
So now I'm going to show you the exact
logistic regression results instead.
So here's what I get when I run this in an
exact logistic regression which is
fairly easy to do in most computer
packages.
So now I get that the estimate for guess
milk is actually different
than we saw before and the p-value, the
two-sided p-value is also quite different.
And the odds ratio is different and the
confidence limit for
the odds ratio is different.
Notice that the confidence limit becomes
much wider here.
The p-value becomes bigger.
In fact, the maximum likelihood
estimation,
estimates were overly optimistic.
When we run the exact logistic regression,
we get different inferences, and so
it's important with sparse data to
remember to run those exact statistics,
otherwise you might be overly optimistic.
I just want to point out one thing that's
very interesting here.
Notice that the two sided p-value from
this exact logistic
regression comes out to be 0.4857.
You probably don't remember, but
if you go back to that module on the
Fisher's exact test.
The Fisher's p-value, the Fisher's exact
p-value came out
to be exactly the two sided one, came out
to be 0.4857.
It came out to be exactly the same.
Well, that's a good check.
Fisher's exact test is an exact method.
That means it should be calculating
exactly the probability.
Logistic, exact logistic regression, is
also an exact method,
that means we should be calculating
exactly the probability.
Well if we're calculating the exact
probability in both cases,
we're going to hope that that exact
probability comes out to be the same.
There's nothing fancy going on in this
model, we're not adjusting for
any confounders, so we ought to get
exactly the same p-value.
And indeed we do, which is kind of a good
check.
That this method works as it should.