In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about some tests that you
can use to check the logistic regression
model.
The example data that I'm going to use in
this module is sort of a classic data set,
it's referred to in a lot of statistics
textbooks, but
it was some data on 81 children who have
corrective spinal surgery.
Some of them went on to get kyphosis,
curvature of their spine, and
some did not.
So we have a binary outcome here, kyphosis
or not.
The predictor I'm going to focus on for
the purposes of this module is age.
Can we use age as, as a predictor of who's
likely to go on to get spine curvature.
And so I went ahead and I ran the logistic
regression model with kyphosis as
the outcome in age as the predictor.
And here is some of the results from the
computer.
So this is showing you the test of global
fit.
And remember what we talked about earlier,
these are a test which
are testing the null hypothesis that all
the data's in the model are equal to 0 and
we only have a single beta in this model
age, so this in this case we're
just testing whether or not beta age is
equal to 0 but you would
also be using these to test whether a
series of predictors were all equal to 0.
We're going to focus on the likelihood
ratio test, we talked about that earlier,
that's probably the most widely used test
for goodness-of-fit.
So this is non-significant in this
example, clearly non-significant, so
this is telling that we, us that we don't
have a well fed model.
Age doesn't really do anything.
If we had multiple predictors in the
models and
it was non-significant then we'd say that
there are multiple predictors aren't
really doing anything.
So we don't have a good fit in this case.
So that's a global test that you can use
to look at the model overall.
The Likelihood Ratio test which we already
talked about in detail earlier.
We can also look at the ROC curve.
And so the ROC curve here you can see that
it's not so great, right.
We if you're just guessing you're, you're
going to end up
on this diagonal line where pretty much at
the diagonal line,
the area under the curve here is 56%, so
this is a really bad ROC curve.
Remember, what we're looking for with ROC
curves is that we're ending up
something like this, with a high area
under the curve.
Somewhere around 80, 90, 100%.
So the ROC curve shows us that we have
really poor accuracy.
If we were trying to make predictions
based on age, we have poor, poor accuracy.
So that's another thing we can look at
just to see how well the model is
doing overall.
Now I'm going to tell you about how to use
residuals, in the context of lig-,
logistic regression, to diagnose,
underlying problems in the model.
You've probably all seen this in the
context of lin-, linear regression before.
So there's very obvious residuals that
come out of linear regression.
Residuals, of course, are just your
observed value minus your predicted value.
In the case of linear regression where we
have a continuous outcome variable,
this is very simple.
You say have a blood pressure of a hundred
and fifty, the model predicts that you're
going to have a blood pressure of a
hundred and forty.
In that case your residual would just be
ten.
So, observed minus predictive is a little
bit trickier though,
in the context of logistic regression.
So, what's your observe, you remember
what,
start with the predicted, your predicted,
the predicted value that you get out of
logistic regression is a predicted
probability.
It's your predicted probability of having
kyphosis or whatever the outcome is.
But what do you observe?
We don't observe a probability for an
individual, right?
And individual either has the outcome,
they either get kyphosis, or they don't.
So the observed value for logistic
regression is only one of two things.
It's either a one, or it's a zero.
So we end up for logistic regression, we
take,
if you had kyphosis you would be one minus
your predicted probability.
If you didn't have kyphosis you're
going to get zero minus your
predicted probability for the residuals.
So the residuals are just a little tricky
for logistic regression.
So again, just to repeat,
residuals are observed minus predicted for
logistic regression.
That's either going to be one minus your
predicted probability or
it's going to be zero minus your
predictive probability.
So it turns out that these aren't quite as
useful as they are for
linear regression, because the residuals
are a little bit funny.
But we'll see in a minute that they do
have,
they can tell you some things about the
model.
We generally, imagine if you actually
plugged in some numbers,
what if you had a predictive probability
of say, 80%,
and you actually did have kyphosis, you
would get a value of 20%.
Any residual you can calculate on logistic
regression is going to have to
come out to be a number between zero and
one which is bounded.
So, we don't really like dealing with
things that are bounded like that, but
you can take this residual and
you can translate into a Z-score that you
would just do
some kind of observe minus expected
divided by the standard deviation.
You can translate that into a Z-score, say
based on other people's residuals in
the data that you can transform that, with
a Z-score.
So generally, the types of residuals that
you're going to see in computer packages
there, you're going to see things like
Pearson's residuals and
deviance residuals.
All of those are essentially, you can
interpret them as if they were Z-scores.
OK.
So here is an example of a residual plot.
This is the deviance residuals that I just
mentioned.
Essentially you can interpret these as
Z-scores.
So, first of all,
the first thing you're going to notice on
residual plots for logistic regression.
I've, by the way, plotted the residuals
against the predictor age.
That's typically what we do with
residuals.
We plot the residuals against the
predictors in the model,
in this case, age.
And you can see that we get two stripes
here.
So, you might look at that and say, well
why are we getting these stripes.
Remember in linear regression, we were
looking.
We wanted to see things [SOUND] which were
completely random around zero.
So if the residual plot looks something
like this.
Here's my predictor.
My continuous predictor.
Here is my predicted value or sorry, my
residuals and
I get something that's a nice [NOISE]
kind of random scatter around zero.
That was, that was what we were looking.
Now we clearly see a pattern here.
We've got these two stripes.
Well why does that happen in logistic
regression?
OK.
In logistic regression,
you either are a one or you're a zero.
So everybody, in fact, who did get
kyphosis, they're going to be
positive because one minus a probability
is always going to be positive.
That's the group here.
Those are the ones who actually had
kyphosis.
Everybody who did not have kyphosis is
going to be in the negative range,
so that's why you end up with two stripes.
There's going to be all the people who are
controls are going to be in the negative
residuals and all the people who are cases
are going to have positive residual.
So, you end up seeing a lot of patterns
like stripes like that.
So, there's nothing wrong with stripes and
seeing patterns like that.
Now, I have done one thing to this
residual plot which I
have to tell you about.
I asked the computer to plot for me a
smooth curve.
That fits these dots.
So you imagine if I just did this plot and
I asked [NOISE] for the dots, and
I get something [LAUGH] that looks like
this, I am not going to know,
hey is that a nice, even?
You know, I, again, I'm looking for my
residual plot of having sort of
a straight line where there's no kind of
pattern.
And I can't really tell that just by
looking at two stripes of dots.
So what I did here was I asked the
computer, most computer packages can do
this for you very easily, to put a, a
curve, to fit a curve to these dots.
You want actually want a fit a curve and
not like a linear regression line, 'cause
the curve is going to tell you a lot more.
So I fit, put the best curves to these
dots.
And there's a number of different
algorithms that we have for curve-fitting.
This one is was calculated using a, a
spline, a smooth spline.
There's a lot of choices in most
statistical packages.
You see, will usually see their splines or
low-res curves.
Either one of those is good.
And you can get these kids of curves fit
to the dots here.
That curve is very revealing.
Again, the dot plot I can't really,
my eye is not just not finely tuned enough
to make much sense of that, but
if I add the curve here as I've done here,
here's what you notice.
So, there is a quadratic relationship
between the residuals and
age, that's what you can see much better
when you've actually plotted the curve on,
on top of this graph.
What does that imply?
Well remember from linear if we ended up
with residuals that look something like
this, that actually weren't you know,
weren't a random pattern, but
had a quadratic pattern, that meant that
probably one of
our predictors needs to be modeled as a
quadratic, as a square.
And it means the same thing here in
logistic regression.
We're seeing a quadratic pattern.
That means that age is probably modeled as
age squared rather than age.
That's what that is revealing.
And I'll just showing the Pearson
Residual, yet
another type of residual you can get.
It comes out with slightly different
values if you compare to the last
slide But you see again, the two stripes.
I've plotted the, the curve as well and
you see basically the same pattern.
So you're going to get similar things
whether you
choose the Pearson residuals or whether
you choose the deviance residuals.
I most commonly would choose the deviance
residuals.
Again, something indicating that we have a
quadratic.
Now there were, there's actually other
ways, to figure out that actually,
it is true in this data set that age
squared is predictive.
And there's other ways to figure that out.
So we could have done the logit plot.
We talked about doing a linear and a logit
plot earlier.
So I've actually done a logit plot here.
I've binned, the data set is pretty small,
so I made five bins and
I've just connected the dots here with a
smooth line.
And you can see, again, that the logit
plot also indicates that we do,
we're not linear in the logit, for sure.
It doesn't appear to be a line.
It really does appear to be a quadratic, a
curve.
And, so that.
We could have just, rather than looking at
the residuals,
we could have also just looked at the
logit plot to come up
with the same conclusion, and I'm going to
show you even something simpler.
So the logit plot and the residuals take
some work, but here's something that
takes you no work on the computer that you
also could have done.
You could have just done the very simplest
scatter plot you
can do which is to plot age your predictor
against kyphosis.
So my y-axis here just has kyphosis and
remember that's just a 0-1 variable.
Again, if I do the dot plot, if I don't
super impose a ca-,
curve I'm going to end up with something
that looks like this.
It's going to be hard for me visually to
see that that's a quadratic.
But when I ask the computer to, to fit a
curve to these data,I can
immediately see that, hey, there's a
quadratic relationship with age.
Again age is in months, which is why we
are getting up to the 200's here.
These are children.
So one could argue that, you know,
in this case, all you had to do was the
simple scatter plot, or
the logit plot, you didn't really need to
look at the residuals.
I just want to tell you what the advantage
of the residuals is.
And I'm going to show you that in a
minute.
When you want to do a simple scatter plot,
you can only look at one predictor at a
time.
When you want to do a logit plot, you can
only plot one predictor at a time.
When you look at the residuals,
the residuals come out of a multivariate
model.
So the residuals have accounted for the
fact that you have adjusted for
other things in the model.
If you put multiple predictors in the
model.
I'm going to show you in a minute that
makes a difference.
If I go on and add a new mo-, variable to
this model such as age squared,
I'm, it's going to be hard for me to
evaluate whether or
not age, once I've adjusted, accounted for
age square has a,
has a linear relationship with kyphosis, I
can't do that in a simple scatter plot.
So the residuals will reflect a
multivariate model and
things being adjusted for one another.
So that's where the residuals do better
than these just simpler plots at,
at capturing things.
So, this all suggest that we should add
age squared to the model.
So that's when I went ahead and did here
is,
I added an age squared term to the model.
And I just want to show you a couple of
things that came out of the computer.
Generally I left age in as a linear value
as well.
Generally, when you're adding interactions
or higher order terms, like squares,
to the model, you're also going to keep
the linear term in, the main effect.
So, we're going to have both age and age
squared in the model.
Now, notice, we go to our test of global
fit for
the model our goodness-of-fit test, the
likelihood ratio statistic.
Well now that comes out to be significant,
suggesting that we do have a good fitting
model now.
And you'll notice that age squared turns
out to have a, to be significant.
And now, age itself is also significant.
So the linear part of age is also
significant,
once we account for age-squared.
It's hard to interpret [LAUGH],
we're going to talk about interpreting age
the effect sizes of age-squared later.
But basically remember this is, if you
kind of think about this mathematically,
and you also saw it in the picture, this
is saying that if you are in
the middle ages, you're more likely to get
get kyphosis.
So the very youngest and
the very oldest children ha-, were less
likely to get, have kyphosis.
The children with ages in-between were
most likely to get kyphosis.
And if you sort of did out the curve
mathematically, you would
see that this positive linear term and
this negative square term reflects that.
So now we have two things that are
predictive in the model.
And doing the residual plots told us that
we needed, we wouldn't have
known that we needed age squared in the
model had we not done the plotting.
You could imagine that somebody just
re-entered this whole regression,
this whole data set, just dumped age in
the model and
said, oh, age is not significant.
I'm getting rid of it.
And dumped it out of the model.
And that was the end of the story.
If you failed to do plotting,
you are going to real-, run the risk of
missing important relationships like this.
So just throwing age in as a linear term
and not doing any of your
diagnostics could result in, in errors
being made as, as it would have here.
Luckily we did the residual plot.
We saw that there's, we actually had to
put age squared in.
Now again, you could have figured out
the same thing from doing either the very
simple scatter plot,
which is super easy to do in a computer or
from doing a logit plot.
Either of those would have also told you
that you need to put age-squared in
the model.
But the point I made earlier is that the
residuals are a little better because now
we can get residuals for a model that
includes both age-squared and age.
And in those simple plots, there's no way
to plot age-squared and
age at the same time.
But the residuals capture the effects of
both of those.
So now what I've done is, I've taken this
model and calculated, or
asked the computer to calculate for me the
residuals for
everybody based on a model that contains
both age and age-squared.
And then I've done the residual plots for
all the predictors in this model which,
again, is just age and age squared.
And here's the neat thing.
So now you can see that once I have both
of these predictors in the model, I,
I fit my curve to the,
to the dot plot again in which you notice
is that I have exactly what I want.
Which essentially a flat line.
That's telling me that there's no sys-,
systematic powder in the residuals, so we
don't have a problem in our model.
And the same with,
if I plot against age-squared, it's also a
flat line, which is exactly what we want.
So, the nice thing here is, now I have a
way of evaluating.
Once there are multiple things in the
model.
How is my model doing, in terms of
individual predictors?
Once, I've adjusted for other things.
So, age now, has a good relationship, now,
that you've adjusted for age-squared.
That's the idea.
And, the use of the residuals.