In this next module, I'm going to talk
more about the odds ratio.
So I'm going to tell you how you get a p
value and
a confidence interval from a simple two by
two table odds ratio.
And I think that's useful to know.
Because in fact understanding the shape of
the distribution of an odds ratio as
well as the standard error, will give you
some insight into the measure itself.
And I'm also going to tell you a little
bit more about this problem of
interpreting odds ratios correctly.
So, first of all you may be asking
yourself why do we ever even use odds
ratios when they're so confusing and
there's actually two reasons for.
So one reason is that when you do a case
control study you go out and
you sample people based on whether or not
they already have a disease.
So you may go out and sample 50% of your
sample may be cases and
50% of your sample may be controls.
When you sample on disease status you can
no longer validly estimate things like
the risk of the disease or the prevalence
of the disease.
Therefore, you cannot estimate risk ratios
or rate ratios.
It turns out that with a case-control
study,
the only valid measure of relative risk is
the odds ratio.
The odds ratio can therefore be applied in
the case control study, and
since it's the only relative risk that
works, we use it there.
A more important reason that odds ratios
come up so
much, however, is just simply the fact
that even when we're not
dealing with a case control study, a lot
of times when you have covert studies.
Or even randomized trials, as we saw in
the last modules, or
cross sectional studies, a lot of authors
will choose to use logistic regression
because it's the most commonly used
regression method for a binary outcome.
When you run a logistic regression it
gives you odds ratios, not risk ratios.
So you're just kind of stuck with odds
ratios and
you have to be very careful about what you
do with those and how you report those.
this class is largely about logistic
regressions.
Not surprisingly, we're going to see awful
lot of odds ratios in this class.
So I just want to quickly review,
how do you calculate an odds ratio from a
simple two by two table.
That's what we're going to be talking
about in this module.
So if you have a two by two table, you can
say well, you have, you either are exposed
or not, and you have the outcome or not,
any two binary variable will work there.
By convention, we sometimes call the cells
of the two by two table a, b, c and d.
And to calculate an odds ratio, it's very
simple.
So, if you're looking at some kind of
exposure and you want to know,
what's the odds of getting the outcome in
the exposed group?
You just look at cells a and b.
So the odds is going to be your chance of
getting it
divided by your chance of not getting it.
So that's a divided by b.
That's the odds of getting the outcome in
the exposed group.
The odds of getting the outcome in the
unexposed group therefore will be
c divided by d.
So it's an odds ratio, so we divide those
two odds.
Mathematically however it's even simpler
to calculate than this.
Because if you multiply by the reciprocal
here you realize that
to calculate the odds ratio, from a two by
two table, all you have to do,
is do a times d, divided by b times c, so
just use those cross products.
Very straight forward to calculate.
Now, I'll just note, that if you're doing
a case-control study, it's a little bit
different, but mathematically, it ends up
being exactly the same.
So in a case-control study, it's not valid
to say what your chances of, or
your odds of being a case versus a control
in the exposed group because remember,
we've sampled on case-control status.
However, it is valid to say if you're a
case, what are your odds of being exposed?
That's a divided by c.
So we can calculate the odds ratio, the
odds of exposure in
the case group versus the odds of exposure
in the control group.
But notice that mathematically that turns
out to be exactly the same thing: it's
still just a cross-product, a times d,
divided by b times c.
And it turns out that this odds ratio, the
odds of.
Being exposed in the case version of the
control group is mathematically equivalent
to the odds of getting the disease in the
exposed group versus the unexposed group.
Since those are mathematically equivalent,
that's why this is the only valid measure
of relative risk for a case-control study.
But again, its calculation is very simple.
Just a times d over b times c.
Now, what is the distribution of an odds
ratio?
That is, if you were to go out and repeat
your study over and over again
under multiple samples, what would the
distribution of the odds ratio look like?
This is what we always need to know,
fundamentally about a statistic.
What is its distribution?
What's the shape of the distribution,
what's its mean?
And what's the standard error?
To answer this question you could go look
up the formula for
this and I'll give you the formula in a
minute.
But I always think it's nice to illustrate
the distribution of
a statistic by doing a simulation.
I think simulations are fun and they kind
of, interesting things pop up.
So we're going to look at doing a
simulation for
the distribution of an odds ratio.
So how do I actually do this in the
computer,
I'll just give you a brief summary of how
I did this on the computer.
So what I'm essentially doing is I'm
saying imagine that I just got a large or,
you know, it can be infinite on a
computer, large population of cases and
a large population of controls.
And for the purposes of this simulation,
I'm going to start by assuming that the
null hypothesis is true.
So that my exposure, which in this case is
smoking, is unrelated to whether or
not you're a case or a control.
And I can set that by just saying imagine
that 20% of the case
population are smokers, and 20% of the
control population are smokers.
Now imagine that I do a virtual case
control study.
I tell my computer to randomly select 50
people from the cases and 50 people from
the controls and then to tell me how many
smokers popped up in each group.
Every person has a 20% chance of being a
smoker in both the case group and
the control group.
But, because of random chance,
it's not like I'm going to get exactly ten
smokers in the case group.
I might end up with 10 smokers that's the
most likely outcome but
I can also get 11, 12, 13, 14, nine,
eight, seven.
I'm going to get around 20% smokers in the
case group but
with a sample of only 50 which is pretty
small.
I could easily end up with say 15 smokers
in the case group.
And then my, and
then the, the risk of being a smoker in
the case group would actually be 30%.
So I'm not going to always get 20% in
those two groups.
And what I'm essentially doing in my
simulation.
Is I'm just telling my computer to pick
things randomly from
a binomial distribution.
With an n of 50 and a p of 0.2 and
that will get me the counts for cases and
smokers and controls in smokers.
So when I get those counts for
a single virtual case control study, I can
just drop them in a two by two table.
How many, you know, in one iteration, one
virtual.
Case control study here, maybe, you know,
here's case control, and
maybe what I end up with is smokers, not
smokers.
And maybe I end up in this case with 12
cases who happen to be smokers, and
therefore 38 who aren't, and maybe I end
up with.
Eight controls who are smokers and 42 who
aren't.
And that's just random chance.
Remember, there's really no relationship
between being a case and
smoking, in this case.
But when I calculate the odds ratio, I'll
get 12 times 42 divided by 8 times 38.
It's not going to be exactly one, it's
going to be a little bit greater than one.
So I'm going to calculate that observ,
observed odds ratio, I'm going to save it
and here is the key to the simulation.
I get my odds ratio from my one virtual
case control study and
then I do this over and over and over and
over again.
I keep sampling new samples and
I'm going to get slightly different odds
ratios every time.
I'm going to repeat this run arbitrarily
large number of times, say a 1,000 times.
Now since I did 1,000 times for this
particular simulation, I can do it 10,000,
I can do it 15,000.
I'm only limited really by, by computing
power.
And then I'm going to plot the
distribution of those 1,000 odds ratios.
So I got 1,000 odds ratios from 1,000
different virtual case control studies,
and I'm going to plot them in a histogram,
and
I can literally observe the distribution
of odds ratios.
So that's what I did to the computer and
here's the results.
Here's the simulated results from my a
thousand case-control studies.
Now notice, a couple of things to notice.
So first of all, if you look at this
distribution,
the mean of the distribution happens right
about one.
Well, you're expecting that because,
remember, we assumed that the x axis here
is the observed odds ratios, the the Y
axis here is the frequency.
This is just a histogram.
So again the odds ratios of 1 were most
common because we assumed here that the no
hypothesis was true.
There is no difference in smoking levels
between the case and the control group.
Therefore the odds ratio actually is one
and
when we do our sampling, when we, when we
are going to get.
Ratios around one, and you can see that
that impact happened.
But what's really interesting about this
distribution, is notice that it
did not come out as a bell curve, as a
Gaussian or normal distribution.
Remember that when we talked about.
Statistical distributions in the past,
like the distribution of a mean, or
the distribution of a proportion.
A lot of times those things just magically
happen to come out to be
a normal distribution, which was great.
It was easy to deal with.
The odds ratio does not come out to be a
normal distribution.
It comes out to be a right-skewed
distribution.
You can see that in the right tail here.
And why does this happen?
See, notice that you get a long right tail
here.
Why does this happen well, odds cannot be
negative you can't have a negative odds.
Therefore, an odds ratio can never be
negative so you have a left tail boundary
at zero you can't go lower then zero,
however odds ratios can get as big.
It theoretically can be as big as you
want.
There's no right hand bound here.
And so the odds ratio can go out and be
quite high.
And notice that in this case, the no
hypothesis is true, yet
a couple of times out of a thousand,
we saw odds ratios in the three, four,
five, six purely by chance.
Just we happened in a particular sample to
get many more smokers in
the case group than the control group.
Purely by chance.
So you can see an odds ratio of 6.8, even
when there's no
relationship between the exposure and the
disease in a small study like this.
Only happened one out of 1,000 times, but
it can happen.
So, we get this right skewed distribution.
It's hard to make inferences from a right
skewed distribution.
We don't want to deal with a messy
distribution like this.
We want to end up on a normal distribtuon
like everything else.
Well the good news is there's a simple
transformation that you can
make to make the distribution of the odds
ratio normally distributed.
And what's that transformation, you can
take a natural log.
So, why a natural log?
Natural log's obviously going to come up a
lot in this course, because of this.
The natural log, what that does, is all
the numbers,
remember odds ratios can occur between
zero and one.
You can have fractions for odds ratios.
All those numbers between zero and
one, suddenly, when you take a natural
log, those become negatives.
So we put all the negative numbers back
into play which now makes it
a much more symmetric distribution.
When you're dealing with a natural log of
the odds ratio the odds ratio is equal to
1, then the natural log of the, of one is
zero.
So the natural log of the odds ratio will
be zero.
Under the no hypothesis.
So notice that our graph here is centered
around zero.
It's a nice symmetric, normal curve.
What's the standard error here?
What's the standard error?
Well, we can kind of just eyeball it on
the graph and say well, gee,
it looks like maybe the standard error of
the natural log of the odds ratio is
somewhere around between five here.
Well there's actually a formula that
somebody's derived to tell you
what the standard error of, the natural
log of the odds ratio is.
And so, of course, we don't have to run a
simulation every time, so
we just like a nice formula for the
standard error, and
somebody's approximated that, has worked
it out.
And I think it's useful to actually look
at that standard error formula because it
gives you some insight into the odds
ratio.
So what is this formula?
So remember I told you in a two by two
table we can label the cells, a,
b, c and d.
So this a, b, c and d, that's just the
four cells from a two by two table.
And what's really interesting here is
notice that the standard error
is related to the reciprocal of those cell
sizes.
So what does that actually mean?
Well, just let's plug in some numbers.
What if we had a study where we ended up
with a very small cell a, you know,
had a 1 in it, and maybe cell b has ten,
and cell c is 100, and cell d has 1000.
What's that going to mean in terms of the
standard error?
If we plug into the standard error
formula, we notice is we get 1 over 1,
plus one over 10, plus 1 over 100, plus 1
over 1000.
Now, notice what that breaks down to
inside the square root.
Though cell a contributes a one to the
variability.
All the other cells contribute decimal
places.
So this just ends up being 1.111, right.
So everything else is just a decimal
place.
Cell a,
almost completely, the smallest cell,
almost completely drives the variability.
And that makes a lot of sense.
In terms of how much variability there is
in an odds ratio,
the smallest cell is really the limiting
factor.
Because imagine that I were, was to change
cell a by just 1%.
Subtract 1 or add 1, that's going to have
a huge impact on the odds ratio.
Whereas if I were to add or subtract 1
from cell b or cell c or
cell d it's not going to have much a an
impact on the odds ratio so,
the variability of an odds ratio really is
driven.
By the size of the smallest cell and that
insight is kind of burred in
the standard error there so I think that's
neat.
Alright, so just to summarize the natural
log of the odds
ratio luckily is normally distributed, the
mean value is whatever the true value of
the natural log of the odds ratio ratio is
under the null hypothesis, that's zero.
And the standard error is that formula
that I just gave you.
We're not going to have to calculate too
many of these by hand in this class, but
again I think just understanding the
distribution here gives you some insight.
So, inferences for the odds the ratio, if
I want to do a hypothesis test.
I want to test whether or not the odds
ratio is one,
which is equivalent to the natural log of
the odds ratio being 0,
so that would be my null hypothesis, if
there's no difference between the groups.
I would just do a z test, because we're on
a normal curve.
I compared the natural log of the odds
ratio that I observed with its standard,
with its standard error.
Simple to calculate.
The 95% confidence interval is similarly
going to be based on the standard error.
Notice, though, that we're going to be
calculating the 95% confidence interval
for the natural log of the odds ratio by
adding and subtracting 1.96.
Times the standard error.
That will give me a confidence interval
for the natural log of the odds ratio.
You don't want to report that in your
paper, though,
because odds ratios are hard enough to
understand.
Don't bother with natural logs of odds
ratios, nobody can understand that.
So what we're going to do, of course, at
the end of the day, is take the upper and
lower bounds and exponentiate them to get
back to an actual odds ratio measure.
And that's going to have an interesting
effect, that,
if you've ever noticed odds ratios and 95%
confidence intervals in the literature,
a lot of people would remark, well,
they're not symmetric.
If you look at the confidence interval,
this was the confidence interval from a
previous module for an odds ratio.
Notice that it's not symmetric.
The 0.243 does not fall right in the
middle.
We actually end up with kind of a high
upper bound, and
the point estimate is closer to the left
bound.
Well, this is an effect of exponentiating,
of dealing with logs.
So sometimes in the literature,
you'll see that the upper bound for an
odds ratio can be really high.
It might be something like 100.
I've seen ones that have 200, 300.
You know, ridiculously high.
Well, that's because when you
exponentiate,
you're putting back in that right hand
tail.
So the 95% confidence interval for
the natural log of the odds ratio is
symmetric, but for
the odds ratio itself, it's going to have
this, kind of, right skew.
So if you've ever wondered why that is,
that, that's the explanation.
So that's inferences for odds ratios.
Now moving on to just this question, how
to interpret odds ratios.
And then you have to again be very
cautious in your interpretation or
funny things can happen.
So, odds ratios give the increase or
decrease in the relative odds of the
outcome.
Of course, if you say that in your paper
people will look at you cross eyed.
There are certain situations where the
odds ratio can actually be interpreted as
a risk ratio and you'll okay, and this is
the case where you'll have rare outcome.
So if your outcome is rare, it turns out
that the odds ratio and
the risk ratio are pretty close to one
another.
In other words, if you say that, if you
interpret your odds ratio as
the increase or decrease in the risk of
the outcome, you won't be very far off.
The general rule of thumb is that as,
as the outcome incurs at less than 10% of,
say, your reference group,
that's rear enough where the, the odds
ratio and risk ratio are kind of similar.
They can be interpreted in, you know,
they can interpret the odds ratio as a
risk ratio.
However, when the outcome is more common
than this, the odds ratio can
distort the effect size quite a lot, and
you have to interpret things cautiously.
So, if you're doing a case control study,
generally case control studies are run on
rare outcomes so you're likely to have a
rare outcome and it's likely okay,
that you interpret that odds ratio as an
increase or decrease in risk.
However, when you're doing cohort study,
cross sectional study,
randomized trial, all of those usually
involve more common outcomes.
So if you apply logistic regression in one
of those cases and
you get all those odds ratios, be very
careful if your outcome is common and
make sure that you don't interpret those
odds ratios incorrectly.
And just to give you some more examples of
exactly how this works.
So imagine I have a situation where I have
a rare outcome.
Okay, so my outcome occurs in, you know,
3% of my exposed group and 1% of my
reference group.
So my risk ratio is three.
There's a three fold increase in risk in
the exposed group.
What would the corresponding odds ratio be
here?
So the odds ratio would be the risk.
The probability of something happening
divided by the probability of
it not happening.
So, 1 minus the risk.
So my odds, 3% divided by 97% is actually
still
pretty close to 3% because 97% is very
close to 1.
So you're essentially dividing by 1, it
doesn't change things much.
Similarly, in this denominator we would
divide 1% by 99%, but
that odds is essentially still 1% because
the 99% and the 97% are essentially 1.
We end up with a,
an odds ratio that's just slightly bigger
than the corresponding risk ratio.
If I were to say, hey, that's a threefold
increase in the risk in the exposed group,
I wouldn't be off, I wouldn't be far off,
that would be fine.
But compare that to the situation where we
have a common outcome.
So imagine that we have a situation where
my exposed group has
a 60% risk of having the outcome and my
reference group has a 20% risk.
The risk ratio's still three there.
But look what happen to the odds ration
now.
The odds ratio is calculated by doing the
odds of the exposed group.
That's 60% divided by 40% or three out of
two.
Very three to two.
Very different than 60%, and the odds for
the unexposed group is 20% divided by 80%.
When I calculate that out, it comes out to
be an odds ratio of six.
So it's quite distorted from the risk
ratio.
You would not want to look at this odds
ratio and
report it in your paper as a sixfold
increase in risk,
because clearly there's only a threefold
increase in risk.
So again, be careful with common outcomes.
And just to illustrate this a little
further, if you had HRP 259 in fall again,
you can breeze through this, because I,
I've made a lot of these points already in
that class, because it's so important.
But if you have a rare outcome, your odds
ratio is also always going to be
slightly bigger than your risk ratio if
you have a harmful.
Something that's harmful a harmful effect
a risk ratio above one that means your
odds ratio is going to be bigger if you
have a protective effect a risk ratio
below one that means your odds ratio is
going to be a little bit smaller.
But if it's a common outcome those
distortions can be much greater.
And there's actually a direct mathematical
relationship between the odds ratio and
risk ratio.
So remember, the odds ratio just involves
having the probabilities of
things not happening.
So we get these extra terms, mult, if we
multiply the risk ratio by
these extra probabilities of things not
happening.
That's the odds ratio.
So this is the direct mathematical
relationship between those two quantities.
If you're having rare outcome, clearly 1
minus something that
doesn't occur very often is going to be
close to one.
So, 1 minus 1% and
1 minus 2%, for example, that quantity
again is going to be very close to one.
This was what you might call the
distortion factor.
That distortion factor, if the outcome is
rare, is going to be close to one.
However, if the outcome is common, that
can,
distortion factor can be much different
than one.
That's the main point.
And people drawing, you know, graphs to
show exactly where this occurs.
This graph is sort of justifying that 10%
rule of thumb that I mentioned earlier.
So if you look at the graph here, you say
okay on the x axis, this is the risk or
prevalence of the outcome in the
unexposed, the reference group.
The y axis here shows you odds ratios for
different risk ratios.
So, if the risk ratio say is three,
if the real relationship is a three fold
increase in risk.
And you have a, a outcome that occurs in
10% of your reference group.
Notice that's going to distort the odds
ratio a little bit.
It's going to be closer to, you know, like
3.5, but not a huge amount.
And you can kind of see that within this
zone of 10% prevalence,
most of the alterations and restorations
are pretty close to one another.
However, if you go out to prevalence as
if, say, 30%, and you go out
to big odds ratios like 2.5, 3.0, you can
get odds ratios that are huge.
So for example, with a prevalence of 30%,
and a risk ratio of three,
your odds ratio might be something, you
know, like 15.
So huge.
A, a big distortion.
So you're going to be careful with common
outcomes and also the bigger.
The effect actually is the bigger this
distortion will be, too.
So, I'm just going to give you a few
examples of where you have to be
a little careful about these types of
things that pop up in the literature.
I just happened to be looking at something
the other day that somebody sent me
from an, this was in their abstract, and
I've changed things a little for anonymity
here.
But basically the abstract said the
outcome was twice as likely,
odds ratio is 2.2.
To occur in the experimental group
compared with the standard group.
What was funny here was that the authors
had actually put the percentage of
people that were affected in the
experimental and the standard group.
You can see it was 85%, about 85% versus
about 73%.
Well, clearly that's not a twice as likely
right?
I mean.
So 85% is not two times 73%.
So the odds ratio here was misinterpreted,
that twofold odds
ratio did not correspond to a doubling of
risk.
And the, you know, somebody who was
reviewing that paper picked that up, and
of course the reviewer didn't like that.
Another example, this was in a paper in
Neurology a few years back.
They were looking at patients with
dementia and they wanted to say whether or
not mortality, the mortality rate was
increased among
patient with dementia compared to
similarly aged patients without dementia.
And indeed they saw that 82% of
the patients with dementia died during the
study period versus 22% without dementia.
Well, that's clearly about a four-fold
increase in the risk of
death during the study period.
However, because the authors wanted to
adjust with things.
They ran a logistic regression.
The logistic regressions spit out an odds
ration of 16,
so you can see that that's really, you
know, high.
Clearly you do not want to interpret this
as a 16 fold increase in
the risk of death during the study period.
The risk ratio itself was only about four
as we saw on the previous slide.
Now fortunately the authors didn't really
dwell on this odds ratio.
Who they didn't interpret it incorrectly
but even reporting an odds ratio like that
sometimes can just be misleading because
readers might misinterpret that if
you don't frame that or put it in context
for your reader.
One more last example, this was from a
randomized trial looking at
a new diet drug and here's the table that
came out of that paper.
I'm just going to highlight a few things
here so, notice that even thought this was
a randomized trial a perspective study we
still are getting odds ratios here
because the authors wanted to adjust for
something.
So, the outcome that they were looking at
in this a top part of the table was the.
The chances of losing at least five
kilograms, so
you lost at least five kilograms or not, a
binary outcome.
So the calculated odds ratio, adjusting
for
a few things notice the odds ratios are
huge, right?
So, the odds ratio for low-dose versus
placebo, they were
trying different doses of this particular
drug, low-dose versus pla, placebo.
The odds ratio was four.
For the medium dose, it was 21, and for
the high dose it was nearly 32.
Clearly, there's not a 32 fold increase in
your chances of losing this much weight.
That's clearly a distorted effect size.
In, in, in fact, in this table you can
actually see the percentage of
people who lost that much weight in each
of the different groups.
So if you just look at the raw
percentages, well.
The placebo group had 29% of people losing
at least five kilograms.
Now it was much higher in the high dose
group, it was 91%.
But notice that a three fold increase in
risk,
a risk ratio of three, not a 32 fold
increase in risk.
So, in this case, yeah, I might even argue
that the odds ratio here, just,
I'm not even sure I would want to report
them in my paper.
Because they're so distorting.
And they actually don't have any effect
size value.
That is, when I look at this 31.
I can't look at a 31 and
make any conclusion about the magnitude of
the effect.
So I'd be a little careful about even
reporting odds
ratios when they're this distorted,
because a reader could be mislead.
[BLANK_AUDIO].