In this next module I'm going to review
probability distributions.
If you're totally comfortable with the
concepts of probability density function
and cumulative distribution function, then
you can skip this module.
However, if you need a little refresher
then,
you should watch this module [SOUND].
So, first of all, what's a probability
function?
A probability function is just a
mathematical function that happens to
integrate to one.
So, here's one example.
This is an exponential function.
And without me even kind of proving it
mathematically to you,
you can kind of believe that indeed the
area under the curve of
an exponential function [SOUND] might
indeed be equal to one.
You can see it's kind of coming down
towards the x-axis which limits its value.
Another probability function is the
uniform distribution which
just ranges from zero to one and has
probability of one everywhere.
That's another example of a probability
function.
You don't have to be able integrate
anything to see that the area under that
curve is one.
Just for fun.
To show you, since we're going to be
talking somewhat about
the exponential distribution in this
class.
The ex, the formula for an exponential
distribution is the following,
where [SOUND] h is just a constant number.
And if you use different values for
h, that's going to change the exact shape
of the exponential.
Some exponentials are more steep than
others and
some are more shallow than others.
And that just depends on what you plug in
there for h [SOUND].
Regardless of what you plug in for h,
however that curve will
integrate to one and I'll show you that
just in a second here.
I just want to note that I am using t
rather than x as my x axis variable here.
And the reason I'm doing that is because
why we're talking about
probability distributions.
I that we're gong to be trying to say, do
my times two event,
happened t follow a known probability
distribution.
It could be the case that in my study, the
times to death, or the times to pregnancy,
or the times to depression, or whatever my
outcomes is, it could be that those
times actually follow something like an
exponential distribution.
Function.
If you can pin that down then that's
obviously you
can fit those data to a pretty nice,
smooth mathematical model.
So I'm just going to be using t rather
than x to start with here since
eventually we're just going to be talking
about probability distributions for
the, survival times.
So this is an exponential function I've
written out here.
You do not have to do any intervals in
this Course, but just totally for
fun, I'm going to integrate this curve
from zero to infinity.
It starts at zero, there's no negatives
here on an exponential.
From 0 to infinity, if I integrate this
curve,
I can show you indeed that the area under
the curve is one.
If you totally hate integrals and
you don't want to see this, feel free to
forward the video.
But just for fun, here's my function.
[SOUND] And it's an easy function to
integrate actually because the exponential
the derivative of the exponential is just
the exponential.
It's a little more complicated because we
have to do chain rule since we
have our key.
Our variable has been multiplied by a
negative h.
So a negative will come down.
They each will cancel.
And we're left with that the interval here
is negative e raised to negative ht.
We then evaluated it at zero and in,
infinity and so
if I plug in infinity while negative e
raised to negative infinity anything
raised to negative infinity is going to
zero [SOUND].
And then I do minus.
This negative e raised to negative ht.
I'm going to plug in zero now.
And, well, of course, e raised to zero
just goes to one,
so I've got a minus minus one.
That's going to here, have an area under
the curve of one.
I won't integrate the, uniform
distribution is pretty obvious that
the area under that curve is one since
it's just a box with sides one [SOUND].
We can talk about the probability density
function.
That's just the formula, for
example, I just gave you f of t is equal
[SOUND] to h e raised to negative h t.
That's that function there.
That's just the original Function and what
it [SOUND] gives me is it gives me
the probability of say death occurring at
any particular time point.
So before you know anything about anybody
in this study before this study starts.
If you think that times are going to
follow a particular distribution like
an exponential, you might say: Well what's
the probability that
somebody's going to die at exactly 2.2
years into the study.
Or what's the probability that somebody's
[SOUND] going to die at exactly 3.2 years.
And this turns out to be not particularly
useful because, in fact, since we're
dealing with continuous numbers here,
there is no such thing as exactly 2.2.
Right?
It could be 2.2013.
We have to go way out to the decimal
places.
So what we really need to talk about with
continuous probability function is
ranges of values.
But the density function just defines this
curve then what we end up
talking about in, in reality here is the
cumulative distribution function because
what we want to know is about eerie is
under this curve.
What is the chance that somebody dies
between your two and
your three for example.
So the probability density function
defines that curve, but
then what we're really want is to get the
cumulative distribution function which
tells us about ranges of values.
So for example [SOUND], I could say what's
the chance that somebody dies with.
In the first 2.2 years of the study.
That's something I can actually calculate
a probably for that makes sense.
The convention for
cumulative distribution functions is that
we always do areas to the left.
So we're always doing what's the
probability that
a person dies before a particular time T.
Before two point two for example we are
always doing areas to the left [SOUND].
And you don't need be able to do any
integrals here again but just for fun I'll
show you we can get a general equation
Equation that will give us the area under
the curve for any time T, whether it be
2.2 or 3.2, or whatever it might be.
So of course all we'd do to get that is we
can do an integral here.
So we will be integrating now from zero to
T.
The integral is the same as before
[SOUND].
So if I take this interval it's just
negative e raised to negative ht.
But now I'm evaluating it from t, to, from
zero to t.
So any time T that I want to plug in to
get the cumulative probabilities I
can plug in T here, so negative e raised
to negative hT [SOUND] is the first part,
and then we're going to do minus, a minus
e raised to negative h times zero.
Well, that's of course going to go to one.
So we rearrange this, this is a negative
negative one, minus minus one, so
that becomes positive one minus e raised
to negative hT [SOUND].
So this is a general formula for
the CDF [SOUND], the cumulative
distribution function, of the exponential.
That's a particular example.
Again [SOUND], don't worry about doing the
interval, intervals.
And that's a cumulative distribution
function for an exponential.
We're going to see this equation require a
little bit later.
Now, when we're doing survival analysis,
we're often actually more interested
not in the probability of a particular
event occurring by a particular time.
We're usually interested in, what's the
chance that you survive past that time?
So we're usually more interested in the
right hand area rather than
the left hand area.
Area.
Well that's very easy to get if we have
the left hand area,
we just do one minus the CDF to get the
right hand area.
So in other words, in survival analyses we
often talk about what's
the probability [SOUND] of surviving past
say, time 2.2, what's this area.
Well that's easy to get, it's just
going to be one minus the CDF [SOUND].
In that so we call this the survival
probability, so
the probability [SOUND] of surviving past
a particular time T, that's one minus CDF,
which in this case is one minus one minus
e raised to the negative hT.
So that is going to be
the ones will cancel we end up with
positive e raised to negative hT.
And you would just pug in a value for
t to say what's the probability of
surviving past a particular time t?
Again, don't worry about deriving that
formula,
that's a formula that will reoccur in an
upcoming module.
Just briefly, I want to just throw in one
additional concept here,
because this is something we're going to
talk about a lot in.
In the next module, but this is directly
related to the probability density and
cumulative density functions.
Something called a hazard function, and
all a hazard function is, is it says.
Imagine that you know that a person has
survived up
until exactly the time 2.2 years into the
study [SOUND].
If you know they've survived up that far,
so it's conditioned on them
surviving that long, what's the
probability that they're going to die or
have the event in the exact next instant,
it's an instantaneous incidents rate.
That's what we mean by the hazard
function.
It's the probably of dying right dead.
Conditioned on the fact that you've
survived up until this point.
And so the hazard [SOUND] function is
equal to the density function.
The PDF [SOUND], divided by the survival
function,
because you're conditioning on surviving
up to that time point, so you have to
divide by that, what's the chances that
you will die in the absolute next instant?
So again, I just want you to understand
this conceptually, but
that's a concept that we're now gong to go
into in the next module.
[BLANK_AUDIO]