[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module,
I'm going to talk about how to
standardize, your continuous variables.
That is, to translate them into standard
deviation units, or
Z scores, prior to putting them, in your
regression model.
So, when you're doing a regression model,
you get a beta coefficient and
those beta coefficients are slopes.
So, of course, slopes are going to depend,
on the units that you choose for x and y.
For example, if you were to put weight, in
the model as.
Pounds, you're going to get a different
beta coefficient, a different slope, than,
if you put, weight in the model as
kilograms.
Now, mathematically, there's really no
difference here,
you're going to get exactly, the same P
values for those 2 beta coefficients.
So, it really, doesn't matter which units
you choose however,
in terms of the message,
that you report to your reader, the betas
are going to look differently.
One is going to look bigger than the
other, and
that might make a different impression on
your reader, so
you have to be a little bit careful, about
unit choice.
For logistic regressions specifically,
the magnitude of the odds ratio is
going to depend, on the units.
So, let's say we have a data set where we
have age measured in years, and
I throw that into my logistic regression
model.
I come out, with a beta for age of .1.
And let's say that's indeed, a
statistically significant effect.
I might, then report the odds ratio for,
a, one year increase.
That's what my computer program's,
probably automatically going to calculate
for me.
I exponentiation the beta of .1, I get an
odds ratio of 1.11.
Again, that's statistically significant.
But, that odds ratio looks kind of small,
right?
It doesn't ,look very impressive.
That 1.11 and 11 percent increase in your
odds of the outcome here,
well that's small,
because, a one year jump in age is also a
small jump in the predictor variable.
It's a small unit, however, I might choose
to instead,
talk about a report ratio for a ten year
increase in age.
So, how would I calculate that?
It's very easy, to do, I'm just going to
take my beta coefficient and
multiply it by ten before exponentiating.
Well, then you see, it come out with an
odds ratio of 2.7.
Well that looks much more impressive.
Now that, P value, for this last ratio is
exactly the same, nothing has really,
changed here.
Except that, the message that you convey
to your readers is a little bit different.
Because, of 2.71 jump is going to grab the
attention of your reader.
A little bit more than a 1.11 odds ratio.
So, the trace of units is a little bit
arbitrary and to get around this issue.
What, sometimes, we'll do and which,
often, is a good idea to do.
Is to standardize, their variables, before
putting them into the regression model and
typically ,that means, translating our
variable into Z-scores.
So, what are Z-scores?
Z-scores are just standard deviation
units.
You can calculate them, very easily.
All you do, is you take an observations,
value, you subtract the mean and
divide by the standard deviation.
That will give you standard deviation
units, rather than the original.
Units, so instead of kilograms per meters
squared, you'll have Z scores, or
standard deviations of BMI.
This is nice, because, then all the
variables are sort of comparable to
one another, because, they're all talking
about, they're all in standard deviation.
How do we actually accomplish this against
very simple, I'm assuming,
all of you have had to calculate Z scores
before.
But, you take, to calculate Z score,
you take a particular observation, you
subtract from the mean of your sample, and
you divide by the standard deviation of
your sample for that particular, variable.
This is best to illustrate this with an
actual example.
I'm, going to ,be talking, a lot this week
about a particular data set,
that I worked on, for some sports
medicine, physicians.
And one of the variables, that was in that
data set was fat mass.
And so we were interested in bone density
and
these were women and, male, young runners.
And sometimes, they will have bone density
issues.
So, these athletes were measured with dual
x-ray absorbtomotry, which gives you
your bone density, but it also gives you a
very precise measurement of fat mass.
So ,that's one of the variables we have in
the data set.
The mean, for this group, for
the women, for fat mass, was 31.4 pounds
worth of fat mass.
That's actually, very lean, because, this
is a very young and athletic group.
The standard deviation for the variable is
11.4 pounds, so
,just kind of randomly picking, a
particular observation from the data set,
one of the women had a Fat mass of 11.6
pounds, which is actually fairly low.
So, what would her z score be?
It's simple to calculate.
We know it's going to be negative.
We know it's going to be, a fair bit
negative, because,
she's quite low compared to the mean.
To calculate her precise z score, we take
her value 11.6 11.6,
subtract from, from that, the mean of the
sample which was 31.4,
divide by the standard deviation which was
11.4.
Her Z score is negative 1.74 meaning that
she's one and
three quarters of a standard deviation
below average.
On fat mass, now you're not going to have
to do too much of this,
by, hand because most computer packages,
statistical packages,
come, with an algorithm to do standard
devi, standardization for
you, so it's not like have to tell the
computer this is subtractive mean,
and you don't have to find the mean
standardization to do this.
The computer, will just do this
automatically.
Most, computer programs, it's the click of
a button or teeny piece of code.
So, for example, I said, I told the
computer to translate, fatmass,
my variable fatmass into, to standardize
it into z scores.
And it does, It did it automatically, I
didn't have to do any work.
I rounded the values, here, but, for
example, a fatmass of 26 turns,
out to be a z score of -.5.
This person's about ,a half standard
deviation below average.
And ,I get this for all of the
observations, in my data set.
Again, really simple you shouldn't, have
to do much work to get this.
This new variable, the z-scores of course,
will have a mean of 0 and
a standard deviation of 1.
And that's also nice, that's a nice
property.
All of your variables then, that you
standardize will have means of 0 and
standard deviations of 1.
Now ,why might you want to bother to go
through, this little extra step?
There's a couple of reasons, so one thing,
is standard deviation units,
are more, comparable than the original
units, units, so
it makes it a little bit easier to compare
effects across different predictors that
have different inherent units.
You can talk about the standard deviation
that your standard deviation of
caloric intake, your standard deviation of
bone density,
your standard deviation of BMI, and it
makes it a little bit easier,
to look at different data coefficients and
get some sense of how they compare.
You want to be careful, though, because,
some people think,
well ,if I've translated, everything into
standard deviation units,
then the beta with the highest number, is
therefore the most important variable.
And that may not quite be true.
Because, a standard deviation of age,
might mean something a little different,
than a standard deviation of BMI for
example.
So, it's more comparable, although not
completely comparable, compared with the,
original unit.
If you've got variables with arbitrary
units,
standard deviations, are really nice.
So, for example ,we might give people, a
depression questionnaire and
they get some score, on that
questionnaire.
You just put the score, into your
regression model.
You're going to get the betas, for, a one
unit increase in depression score.
But, what does that mean intuitively?
Nobody's really going to understand, what
it means to go up,
one point on that particular arbitrary
scale.
If you translate, it into standard
deviation units,
however, it has a lot more meaning,
because now, you can say what does it
mean to be a standard deviation, above
average in this population.
So, it's easier to interpret.
And then finally, it makes the intercept
more interpretable, as well.
So, the intercept of course, is the value,
in this case for the lougan, when all
the predictors, in your model that you've
included in your model are equal to zero.
If you've put into you model age and
weight and
things like this, what does it mean, to,
if you've set all of those to zero?
There is no person that exists.
That has an age of zero and a weight of
zero.
Right, so that intercept has no kind of
natural interpretation,
if you've got continuous predictors of the
model.
However, if you standardized ,all your
continuous predictors, the, a mean of
zero, a value of zero now means, you're at
the mean, for that variable in the sample.
So, now the intercept has some nice
natural interpretation.
It's the expected value for someone with
the mean, value of all the predictors.
So ,a little easier, to make sense of the
intercept.
[SOUND] I'm now going to show you, a
particular example.
And, this, example, again, comes from the
data,
that I was looking at, on bone mineral
density, in, young.
These are adolescent, runners, and
we have some data on girls, as well as,
boys, adolescents.
So, just I'm showing you, a subset of the
data.
This is from linear regression, just to
start with.
Just to show you that this also works, you
can, do this with a linear regression.
The outcome here, is the spine, bone
density, and whole body density.
Two places, we are interested, in the bone
density.
And, this, these bone density measurements
,are also in Z score, so
the outcome here is Z scores.
[LAUGH] The predictors are all Z scores.
Makes it fairly easy, to, interpret those
beta coefficients.
Then we have a number of different, body
measures: weight, height, BMI, lean mass
and fat mass, and android fat ratio, which
is a mark of visceral fat, all of those
come out of your decks, your dual X-ray,
other [UNKNOWN] bone density measurement.
Now, and, how do you interpret the beta
coefficients, that you see here?
So, I'm just going to, show you, one how
to interpret it.
So, this 0.24 here, this is the beta
coefficient, for a model,
in which spine Z score, is the outcome and
I had, these are all unit variant.
From univariate linear regression, so
it had a single predictor, weight, in
standard deviation units.
So, the way you interpret this 0.24 is
that for
every one standard deviation increase in
weight, spine, Z score goes up 0.24.
You get a,
about a quarter of a standard deviation
increase ,in your spine, bone density.
So, that has a nice easy, interpretation
and, it makes it easier to compare,
across different predictors, as well as
across different bone density sites,
as well as across different genders.
And again, you can't, assume that the
comparison is absolute, here, but
it gives you a sense of which of these
body measures is
more strongly related to bone density, at
which site, and in which gender.
And, you can see that, so for example, the
point for one,
is the highest beta coefficient and women
here had point four one so
for weight as the predictor in whole body,
bone density ,as the outcome.
So, that gives you a sense that weight,
is really important, in terms of your
whole body bone density.
If you look at spine.
For the spine, it looks like, you're,
actually your visceral fat, having more
visceral fat, was actually fairly good for
the spine, for both, men and women.
You get a higher coefficient there, out of
all those, predictors.
It's also interesting just to note,
that there are differences, between men
and women.
Also the P values, tend to be very, easy
to predict, because,
you can see that as long as, for women,
where N is 90 1 as long as you were 2 or
below, the P value was definitely, a was
point at the10 level you had to get above
.2 to hit that .05 level and then when you
got above .25 you hit the.
0.005 level.
So, there's kind of a natural progression
here,
again, it's a little bit more comparable.
You can kind of compare across and
they naturally, become significant at a
certain level, depending on the end.
So, all of that makes this just a little
easier, to, interpret.
And, just to show you an example, from
logistic regression as well,.
So, I threw those same body measurements,
into a model,
where my outcome now is stress fractures,
and if you have lower bone density, then,
you're more likely to fracture.
So, all of those body measures which were
tied with
higher bone density are tied with a lower
risk or lower odds of stress fractures.
Interestingly, the one that has the
strongest odd ratio is fat mass.
This is just looking at women now, not in
the men.
But, in women, having a higher fat mass, a
one standard deviation increase in
fat mass, was associated with about 64%,
decrease in the odds of stress fracture.
Notice, that, that's the biggest odd ratio
or
the most protective and the reason that,
is, probably is that in this.
Population of women runners, they tend to
get, menstrual irregularities,
Amenorrhoea, and that's linked to low bone
density.
Low bone density is linked to fracture.
So ,having more fat, actually incre,
increases your chances of having a normal
period, which increases your bone density,
which, you know, makes you protected
against fractures.
But these standard deviation units, again,
make these odds ratios very easy to
interpret.
I just want to point out, one thing, just
a clarification.
When we're talking about z scores,
everybody thinks about the standard normal
curve, so you automatically,
start thinking about normality, that your
variables must be normally distributed,
but z standardization, is not the same
thing,
as making a variable normally distributed,
so, if you just ,subtract the mean and
divide by the standard deviation, of a
variable, if that variable started out as
a non-normal variable, as a skewed
variable, it will remain non-normal.
It doesn't magically, become normal, just,
because you done a z-standardization.
Of course, if the original value was
normally distributed,
then the z-score will also be normally
distributed, but
that's not a guarantee, so don't assume
,just because you've standardized ,that
your variable is then normally
distributed, because it may not be.
[BLANK_AUDIO]