[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about the difference between modeling for
explanatory aims versus modeling for
predictive aims.
So first of all, explanatory models, the
endgame is
to identify causal relationships, to
really understand what is happening.
Why is something happening?
So for example,
if I want to know does alcohol increase
the risk of breast cancer?
In an explanatory model and
context, I want to know does the alcohol
itself Have some
direct biological effect that therefore
increases your risk of breast cancer.
Or I might want to know does a particular
drug actually cause weight loss?
Is it an effective for that outcome?
Or I might what to know does psychological
stress itself, as opposed to the many
possible things that might go along with
Stress such as poor eating habits and
poor sleep and lack of exercise.
But does the stress itself somehow
increase your mortality risk?
So all of these are trying to get at
specific causes of disease.
Of course, in order to tease out whether
or
not something is causal, especially if
we're talking about observational studies,
we're going to need to deal a lot with
confounding, and
we've talked a lot, so far in this course,
about how to evaluate confounding.
We're going to continue that discussion
today, because explanatory modeling
really has a lot to do with adjusting,
taking into account, confounders.
Predictive modeling has a very different
aim, the goal of a predictive model
is to be able to predict who is likely to
have a particular outcome or
to even try to calculate their,
their probability of having that outcome
As accurately as possible.
So notice that in the predictive model.
We care about accuracy.
We don't necessarily care about actually
working out causal relationships.
We don't necessarily care why something is
a good predictor.
All we care about is that something is a
good marker, of whether or
not you are likely to go on and have an
outcome or whether or
not you have a particular underlying
condition in the context of diagnosis.
So some examples would be things like,
what clinical factors,
when somebody comes into an emergency
room, and they have ankle pain,
are there particular, particular clinical
factors that you can identify and say,
hey, this person has a high probability of
having an actual fracture.
And therefore, we should send them for an
x-ray.
Or this person has a low probability of
having a fracture and
therefore we don't have to bother to send
them for an x-ray.
Note I said I don't care about anything
causal in that picture.
I just want to know if I can have,
find markers of who's likely to have a
fracture.
Or you might want to know if you can
identify breast cancer
patients who are most likely to benefit
from a particular chemotherapy.
For example, there's some gene expression
tests out there that can help tell us.
Who is likely actually to benefit from
chemotherapy.
Now, a lot of those gene expression tasks,
they are measuring the expression of
a whole bunch of genes, and we don't
necessarily know how those
genes play into either breast cancer or
chemotherapy response.
But what we care about here is just that
they are accurate predictors of who is
likely to respond.
Another example was the probability of the
sub-fertile couple.
Some of the couples having trouble getting
pregnant, will become pregnant
spontaneously without any assisted
reproductive technology within a year.
That might be really useful to be able to
tell couples that.
So can we identify a set of predictors
about the couples that we therefore we
can go on and so well you're probability
of getting pregnant without help is
you know 40%, 50%, 10%.
That can be very useful, and again we
don't necessarily care why those are good
predictors, we just care that they are
good predictors, that they are accurate.
Because the goals are very different here,
the way that we mill, we build and
evaluate a predictive model is going to
look a lit,
lot different from how we build and
evaluate a, an explanatory model.
Again, we're going to talk about
predictive modeling,
specifically, next week.
[BLANK_AUDIO]