Okay, so just one more example, actually
from the medical literature of some
authors who applied principle components
analysis, a really nice interesting study.
This was a, a dietary study, and they were
looking for
dietary patterns that predicted breast
cancer risk.
And this is a great cohort of data,
there's a big cohort of,
information collected on women, California
teachers studied,
I think it was mostly women, a cohort of
118,000 women.
They measured, food frequency, they sent
them food frequency questionnaires,
measured to a bunch of dietary variables.
How many apples do you eat per day?
How many fish do you eat per day?
And things like that.
Well, that becomes an unwieldy data set.
We have to use it some how and extract the
useful information, so
they apply principal components analysis
to identify dietary patterns.
That is, again people who tend to eat a
lot of, you know, apples probably also eat
a lot of broccoli and probably also eat a
lot of peaches, because people you know,
just, you know, some people eat a lot of
fruits and vegetables.
People who eat a lot of cookies probably
also eat a lot of bread and
and things like that.
So they're going to extract these dietary
patterns and then try to relate them to
perspectively to breast cancer risks with
a cohort study.
We're just going to now show you actually
directly from the methods section.
Sorry, It's actually maybe a little fuzzy,
'because I took it from a screenshot, but
I really like their, they [UNKNOWN] nice
to say,
I also teach writing and they had a nice
succicnt clear description of
how they prefer the principal components
analysis in their method section and
it also covers a lot of the things that we
just talked about.
So first of all, each variable was
standardized to a mean of zero and
a variance of one.
I told you, you need to do that before
applying principal components analysis.
Then a coefficient was assigned to each
variable depending on the weight
it contributed to the principal component.
So that's just the,
what we just talked about going through a
principal component analysis.
How are principle component variables
actually calculated?
Factor scores for each subject for each
dietary pattern were calculated by
multiplying the participant's consumption
of each food or beverage by the weight,
the factor loading given to that food or
beverage for that dietary pattern and
summing those values for all foods and
beverages.
So that's just telling you, you take
those, those weights again,
you multiply by the individual variables,
add them up.
And you get for each woman,
you're going to get a score for each
dietary pattern.
An orthogonal varimax rotation procedure
was used to
obtain uncorrelated components.
So again, we applied that so it was easier
to to figure out what
those variables mean and it guarantees
that they're uncorrelated components.
The number of factors retained was based
on eigenvalues of less, greater than or
equal to one.
So that's the eigenvalue of criteria I
talked about.
As well as examination of scree plots,
which I also talked about,
and factor interpretability, so again you
know it's study dependent [UNKNOWN], so
it's also a nice little description of all
the things that we just talked about.
So when they did all this and came out
with their principle components they
ended up with five principle components,
five dietary patterns that they found.
I guess that all of these, you know, the
eigenvalues were greater than one and
they decided to, these are the only ones
they decided to retain,
'because they are the predominate ones in
this data set.
So they found a plant based diet, so this
is women eat a lot of fruits and
vegetables, that's a one dietary pattern
they, they saw.
They found a high protein, high fat
dietary pattern.
So these are people eating a lot of meats,
eggs, fried foods, high fat condiments,
probably eating a lot of fast foods.
A high carbo diet, a hard carbohydrate
diet pattern, which is
high inconvenience foods like you know
pre-processed cookies, pasta and bread.
Ethnic diet which has a lot of beans, soy,
dark green leafy vegetables,
rice might represent other di,
diets in another cultures and then finally
I love this, the salad and
wine diet which was high in lettuce and
salad dress, low-fat salad dressing.
Fish and wine, coffee and tea and I think
I, I identified, I'd probably get
a high score on that particular dietary
pattern, so but unfortunately that's
the one that got linked to breast cancer
probably because of the wine.
But anyway you,
you see these kind of interesting patterns
that emerged and it's actually hard to
put on a whole screen all of the
information that they put in their paper,
there's a rather big table where they show
the factor loadings from a princi-,
principal components analysis for all the
different food and vegetables that,
that foods and beverages that were on
their food frequency questionnaire.
These are pretty short food frequency
questionnaires,
that we are able to show this all in one
table.
So here is all the, you know, kind of
fruits and vegetables.
Well, those all loaded highly together in
this plant-based diet.
And they show up to the point where, you
get to a factor loading of 0.35 and above.
And then they just didn't bother, that
there are some,
there's little factor loadings here,
which they're not zero, but they didn't
bother to show them after that point.
Because these are the primary ones that
loaded on this component.
So all of the fruits and vegetables, not
surprisingly.
And then we can keep going, I won't go
through this whole table, but
the high protein, high fat diet had a lot
of butter, beef, sausage, pork,
hamburgers, cheeseburgers, fried chicken.
You know, the, the, what they call the,
the high carbohydrate had a lot of pizza,
tortillas, spaghetti, bagels, things like
that.
The, the what they call the ethic diet
beans, tofu, vegetable soups, rice,
meat substitutes and so on.
And then finally you get the salad and
wine diet.
So the green salad, fish, wine, salad
dressing or even a lot of salads,
coffee and tea, tomatoes that was all the,
the wine and salad diet.
So you can see, these, these are the
variables, the,
the foods that clustered in each one of
these dietary patterns.
And then they took these dietary patterns,
so every woman gets a score for
each dietary pattern.
So you maybe high in more than one dietary
pattern, or
you may have one that predominates.
They took these scores and they divided
them into quantiles.
So one, two, three, four,
five [UNKNOWN] the quintile of scores on
each of these dietary patterns.
And then they try to relate that to breast
cancer risk.
This was actually using Cox Regression
because it was a perspective study.
So they're calculating hazard ratios, so
not logistic regression, but same idea.
And we end up with hazard ratios or
relative risks at the end of the day.
There's something here called a p trend,
which we're going to talk about in a few
modules from now.
But you can see that, but unfortunately
the salad and
wine diet was linked to a higher risk of a
particular type of breast cancer,
estrogen positive, progesterone positive
breast cancer.
There probably has a lot to do with the
fact that we know that
alcohol actually increases your risk of
breast cancer and if you're on a salad and
wine diet, you're probably having a, a
reasonable amount of alcohol.