In this next module,
I'm going to walk you through the specific
steps of bootstrap validation.
So just recall that by bootstrap
resampling, what we mean is that we're
going to be taking repeated samples from
our original sample, but we are going to
be using replacements, we're going to be
sampling with replacement.
Such that some of our observations will
appear more than once
in a given bootstrap sample, and some
won't appear at all.
In any given bootstrap sample, about two
thirds of the observations will show up,
and about a third will be left out.
This allows us to create a whole bunch of
different samples from
our original sample.
And we can do all sorts of things with
these bootstrap examples.
Including bootstrap validation.
So the steps of bootstrap validation are
the following.
Number our observations from 1 to n, so
that we can have an easier time
selecting them out for this specific
Bootstrap samples.
Then we're going to randomly draw a sample
of size n from those
original observations, but we're randomly
sampling with replacement.
Which means again, that a given
observation can appear multiple times or
not at all in, in so, one of those
samples.
We're then going to fit our model on this
bootstrap sample.
Remember, that means we're going to repeat
any variable selection steps that were
used to fit the original model.
We're going to test our model on the
original sample, so
the test data in this case is going to be
the entire original sample.
So notice that there is some contamination
when we do it this way.
In other words, we're fitting the model on
the bootstrap sample, but
some of those same observations exist in
the original sample.
That's not considered ideal, so there are
various variations of
bootstrap validation that people have come
up with in the literature.
I'll just point out two, the .632 and the
.632 plus.
The 632 just comes from the fact that in
any given bootstrap sample,
about 63.2% of the observations will
appear.
Those are alternate ways of doing
bootstrap validation, and
there are more than just those.
I'm going to just show you the original
bootstrap validation.
It's in, it's kind the simplest but you
should be aware that if
you're going to use this, there are other
alternatives that you might choose.
So we're going to test our model on the
original sample, that's our test data set.
We're going to record some measure of
model performance.
Let's say we record the area under the ROC
curve, for
example if we're doing a logistic
regression.
So we save that area under the ROC curve
and
then we repeat this an arbitrarily large
number of times.
Maybe 100, maybe 200 times.
Every time we make a model on a new
bootstrap sample,
remember we are going to repeat variable
selection.
We're now going to come out with say 200
measures of model performance.
Say, 200 areas under the ROC curve.
We can just average them to come up with a
average model,
me, average measure of model performance.
And that's going to be not as biased as
the one that we got
when we calculated that measure of model
performance on all of the original data.
This best illustrated with an example.
So here's an example where they were
building a prediction model for
pulmonary embolism.
Some people are, may have suspected
Who's actually likely to actually have it,
and really need the full clinical workup.
The sample had, was 398 people with
suspected pulmonary embolism.
43%, or about 170, actually had pulmonary
embolism.
They had 27 candidate predictors that they
were interested in, and they threw all of
those into a stepwise regression that came
out with a final model.
They wanted to then validate the model.
The, the final model originally had an
area under the curve,
as this was logistic regression because we
have a binary outcome,
it had an area under the curve of 78%.
Now I'm actually just going to walk you
through how they described how, their
process of doing bootstrap validation in
their statistical method section.
It's good for you to get practice in
reading these kinds of method sections.
So they say we applied bootstrapping
techniques to quantify the amount of
overoptimism of the final model and
to adjust the model's predictive accuracy
for overoptimism.
You could probably say this much more
concisely,
they're using the bootstrap technique, the
bootstrap validation to come up with a,
an estimate of predictive accuracy that's
been corrected for
overoptimism, for overfitting.
200 random bootstrap samples of size 398
from 398 subjects were
drawn with replacement from the original
sample.
All they're saying there is we did 200
bootstrap samples.
From each bootstrap sample a final
prediction model was fitted using the same
criteria for predictor selection as in the
previous section.
So they're saying that in every bootstrap
sample, they repeated their
predictor selection, their stepwise
regression which they need to do.
And then the predictive accuracy of each
bootstrap model was estimated in
the bootstrap and in the original sample,
to quantify the difference.
So, they estimated this was a logistic
regression.
So, they estimated an area under the ROC
curve in the bootstrap sample.
That's going to be overfit.
And then they estimated it in the test
data which,
in this case, they're using the original
sample as the test data.
That ROC curve, area under the curve is
going to be lower.
They looked at the difference between
those to get a gauge of how big is
the overoptimism.
They calculate 200 of these differences
and
then just took the mean of them to get a
single estimate of overoptimism.
So they're just saying that there,
they, such average is considered a stable
estimate of the overoptimism.
So that's just how they,
they just averaged them together to get
one measure of overoptimism, and that
tells you how much optimism there was in
that apparent performance in the original
area under the curve of the model that was
obtained from the original sample.
So, when they did this, they original area
under the ROC curve was 78%.
They, they calculated this measure of
optimism in all of
the bootstrap samples and averaged it, and
came out to be 6%.
So, the area under the curve was
overestimated here by 6%.
So the bootstrap-adjusted area under the
curve here would be 72%.
You could also just calculate the area
under the curve in
each one of the bootstrap samples in the
test data and
then average those together and that would
give you 72%.
You could subtract these to get the 6%.
You could do that either way, it will give
you the same answer.
But this is a way again, of saying, how
much was my model overfit?