Alright so
now we're going to turn to a little bit of
an even trickier problem to solve.
We're going to look at the odds ratio for
worry.
So worry has a, a couple of things going
for it that make it a little tricky.
Worry is continuous and we not only have
worry times family history in the model,
that interaction, we also have this worry
squared which essentially is
worry interacting with itself.
So that means that the effect of worry
depends on the level of worry.
To make this a little bit more tractable,
we are going to start with the situation
where we are with the women who don't have
a family history.
That means family history is going to
equal 0.
That will make our lives a little bit
easier to start with.
So what's the odds ratio when fam history
is equal to 0?
What's the odds ratio for a one unit
increase in worry?
So if you go from a worry of four to a
worry of five,
how does that change your odds of getting
a mammography?
The way to represent that generally, to
make this problem doable,
is to say we're comparing a woman who has
a worry of worry plus 1.
Versus a woman who has a value for worry
of W.
That's how we're going to represent it in
the model to make this easier to solve.
So, I want to compare a woman who has a
higher level of
worry to a woman who has a lower level of
worry keeping family history at zero.
So what's the odds, so again,
in the numerator of the odds ratio we have
to put the odds, which we calculate from
the logistic regression model for a woman
with a worry plus 1 value.
So she gets e alpha, now, luckily family
history's 0 here.
So that's term is going to go to 0.
We are just going to hold age fixed at any
value.
I'll just call that A, it's going to
cancel.
Then we get negative 0.04 times worry plus
1,
W plus 1, that's going to be the woman
with higher worry going in the numerator.
We also get the squared the term, so
negative 0.03 W plus 1 squared.
And then finally, minus 0.02 oh sorry e
raised to 0.02.
And this woman has a family history of 0
so
her interaction term goes to 0 so that
term is always going to go away.
What about the denominator?
Well in the denominator were going to have
a lot of the same things this is 0 this
is this same as the numerator for age.
She's just going to have e raised negative
0.04 W, and
she's going to have e raised to negative
0.03 W squared.
Everything else will go away.
So we're, a lot of things are going to
cancel.
These cancel, these cancel, these cancel,
these cancel.
We're left with this here.
Okay so just to to give myself a little
more space to write things here,
I've copied over what we had left from the
formula from the previous slide.
And this is what we have left.
I also expanded the W plus one squared is
the same as W squared plus 2 W plus one.
Now some things are going to cancel.
So notice that we have an E raised to
negative 0.04 times W plus one.
Well if we expand that,
that becomes E raised to negative 0.04
minus 0.04 you are raising it to 0.04 w.
The 0.04 w cancels with the denominator so
are left with just e raised to negative
0.04.
And then we've got the negative 0.03 will
be distributed here.
And the negative 0.03 w squared will also
cancel with the denominator, so
we are left with e raised to negative 0.03
times 2 w is negative 0.06 W.
And then we get an negative 0.03,
so that's what we are left with for the
odds ratio.
We can go one step further here, and just
add things up.
So e raised to negative 0.04 times e
raised to negative 0.03 just becomes
e raised to negative 0.07, and then we've
got a minus 0.06 w.
So we can see that this odds ratio is
indeed a function of worry.
So the effect of worry of you having
higher worry depends on worry itself, and
that's our final formula for that odds
ratio.
We can plug in some values.
So, for example, you're going to reach a
peak.
You're going to have an odds ratio of 1.0.
When if you put, if you just put in here,
you'll see if you put in 0.06 times
negative 7 6th so worry is equal to
negative 7 6th or
negative 1.166 that's the break even
point.
That when this sum is going to be equal to
1.0.
So all that tells you is that if you're at
a worry of level of negative 1.16,
and you increase your worry by one unit.
It's not going to change your odds.
So we, if you think about the curve,
we have a peak at a level of worry of
about negative 1.16.
Our, our curve on mammography so it should
peak about there.
We can plug in different levels of worry
just to,
to kind of see what you're getting.
So if I plug into this formula e raised to
negative 0.07 minus
0.06 if you're at a worry level of
negative 5, that's like, very low worry,
that is going to equal e raised to 0.23
because those
negatives will become a positive, that's
an odds ratio of about 1.26.
And we saw that if you're over here in low
worry, you were,
as you were going up in worry, your odds
ratio is going up.
That's what it means to be on a curve.
But if we're on the other side of worry,
if we're at a positive level of worry,
a positive point, a positive 5 so
a high level of worry, this is going to be
negative 0.07 minus 0.30.
So that equals e raised to negative to
negative 0.37.
So that means that you're at an odds ratio
there of 0.69.
So if you're on the other side here this
is a worry over here,
you're going down the curve.
So as you increase in worry,
you're chances of getting annual
mammography actually go down.
So that's really representing the fact
that worry is on a curve.
And again, you can kind of see that in the
picture, that we're really on a curve.
As you're at the low levels of worry, and
again, this is for
the average-risk women, your odds ratios
are increased, are high.
We reach a peak at about negative one, and
then it starts to decrease and
your odds ratios go down as you're at
higher levels of worry.
So for the average women, at either end of
worry,
she's less likely to get mammography.
Alright so that's for the women who have a
family history of 0.
So just's for fun let's do the same thing
to see what
changes among women who have a positive
family history.
So one more little calculation here.
So now family history is equal to 1, so
now we have to account for that in our
odds ratio.
So this is for the odds ratio for a 1 unit
increase in worry.
So worry plus 1 versus worry.
And same logic except now we gotta worry
about the family history.
So the numerator is somebody how has a
family history, and so she gets that 0.14.
Again we are going to hold age fixed, so
that doesn't matter.
And now for her worry.
So, let's put her again.
We're going to leave worry as a general
term here.
So, negative 0.04 times worry plus 1.
E raise the negative 0.03, worry plus 1
squared.
All the same as before, but now we have to
worry about the interactions term
because she has a family history, and she
has worry of some amount.
So she is going to get this e raised to
negative 0.02 times w plus 1.
Her, actually, her worry is w plus 1, so
this will become w plus 1 again.
What about in the denominator?
See how a lot of things are the same as
before but
now we've got somebody with a positive
family history.
She gets a one there.
Same with the age.
She gets a value of W for worry and a
value of W squared for worry squared,
and she has a value of W for worry.
So that's going to be negative 0.02 just
times w.
Well, a lot of things are going to cancel.
So the, the alphas still cancer, cancel.
Notice that the main effect for family
history is the same.
They both have family histories.
So that main effect cancels, although the
interaction will remain.
The age of course cancels as we've seen
before.
This component right in here well
thankfully [LAUGH] That looks like
exactly the same formula we just solved.
So the only thing that's changing in this
picture now is this last term.
So remember that we just showed that all
of this
simplifies down to E minus 0.4 minus 0.6
W.
But now we've got this additional term.
So what does this turn out to be?
E raised to negative 0.02, we can
distribute the negative 0.02.
Well, the negative 0.02 w will cancel, so
we're just left with an additional
negative 0.02.
So we can say that now oops and this
should have been a value of 0.07.
Sorry, from before, so that became
negative 0.07 minus 0.06 w from before.
And so she now gets negative 0.09 minus
0.06 W.
So, that's our general formula for a woman
who has a positive family history.
It's different.
Notice that all we changed here is that
she has the interaction term
whereas somebody who does not have a
family history does not get
that additional interaction term.
So we just differ here by e raised to
negative 0.02.
All that this is going to have the effect
of
is that it's going to slightly change the
curve, as we saw in the picture.
So her break point for
the peak of her curve will occur not at
negative 7 out of 6.
But it will occur out of, at negative 9
6th.
So for the peak will be slightly, if you
look at the peak, the peak for
the women for the average risk was at
about negative 1.
The peak for the women with the higher
risk is going to be at about negative 1.5.
So that's, you're going to see a different
peak.
And that we already saw the picture, which
I will show you again in a second here.
And, you can calculate then at various
levels of worry
what the odds ratio will be.
You're going to see the same general
pattern that is the, you are going to be
increasing your chances of mammography,
your odds are going to be positive in
the negative values of worry and then,
then after you get, after you get
past this peak, as worry increases, the
odds ratios are going to go down.
So same general pattern, slightly
different peak, slightly different curve.
And you can see that in fact the women who
were high-risk, that's the solid line,
indeed their peak occurred lower than the
women who were average-risk.
That's represented in this general
formula.
So this now we've gone through and
seen how to calculate odds ratios in the
presence of interaction.
We've done some really tough ones in this
problem.
Hopefully the ones where we just have two
binary predictors interacting now will
seem really simple to you.