[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to give you
an overview of
prediction modeling by walking you through
a real example.
So this example is from the British
Medical Journal.
The goal here was to identify predictors
of delirium in the intensive care unit.
So some people in the intensive care unit
will become delirious, and
it's important to be able to predict who's
most at risk of that.
They actually developed a prediction model
here.
They had 1,600 patients from an intensive
care unit in one hospital.
That's the data that was used to fit the
model.
They fit a logistic regression model,
because the outcome is binary, delirium or
no delirium Now the reason that I picked
this particular example to show you is
because they did a really great job on
what's called validation.
Whenever we do a prediction model, it's
always going to be overly optimistic,
it's going to be well fit to the data,
that we use to fit the model, and
so, any measures of accuracy, of how good
the fit is,
are going to be orally optimistic if we
just look at the patients.
That were used to fit the model.
There are things that we can do to adjust
for that overoptimism.
So one of them is called internal
validation.
I'm going to talk about this yeah, in
great detail in a future module, but
just to to, get across the basic idea,
there are ways to get a better gauge of
the, of how accurate are model is.
Using only the data that we started with
it's something called
internal validation and again we'll get to
that a little bit later, a little bit
easier to understand we can just take the
model we fit on these 1600 patients and
we can take that model and apply it to new
patients.
That's what predictive modeling is
supposed to be about is Supposed to be
about predicting things for new people.
So, in this case, the author's temporarily
validated, meaning that they took
549 new patients from the same hospital,
and they applied the model to them.
So, what do I mean by applying the model?
They take the logistic regression they,
model they get at the end of the day.
They use the values from the new patients
to plug into that
logistic regression model and get out a
predicted probability of delirium for
each one of those new patients.
And then they can say how well did our
model predict who was
actually going to get delirium or not.
They not only did that but they then
externally validated the model meaning
that they applied the model to patients
from other hospitals.
So this is getting at whether how
generalizable the model is.
They took 894 patients from four other
hospitals and
they applied the model there and saw how
accurate it was for
those totally new patients from different
hospitals.
I'm now just going to kind of walk you
through the actual statistical methods
section from the statement.
This is going to show you how they did,
how they went about their model building
process.
And I think it's actually important that
you be able to read these sections.
I'll kind of walk you through it and talk
you through.
So first of all they say, we used
univariate logistic regression.
Okay so, this is what I call a univariate
screen,
you can take our outcome here is delirium.
And what you can do is just simply run a
univariate logistic regression
that contains only one predictor at a
time.
So you take each of your candidate
predictors,
you put it in a model, one at at time,
with delirium as the outcome.
And you see whether or not this predictor
has a significant Relationship with
the outcome, if they're, if we haven't
adjusted for anything.
And so they assess the association between
each potential predictor, and, and
delirium, using this univariate
regression, and then which one
of these variables are we going to move on
to the multivariate regression.
Well in this case they said we're going to
exclude anything, any of
these predictors that have a p value above
.15 in the univariate analysis, so
if you run this regression.
And P is greater than .145 and we're not
going to bother with this predictor any
more, we're just going to drop it now
because it's not related to the [UNKNOWN].
They also excluded variables that had a
prevalence below 10% so
if there was a particular predictor that
was a binary predictor and
only 10% of the population or less had
that, had the positive value on that one.
Since so few people had it they thought
that it's not going to be a good predictor
because it's just so rare.
So they screened those out as well.
Then whatever predictors were left, after
this initial screen,
they're going to move forward to a
multivariate logistic regression.
So they just put them all into a
The outcome is delirium, and
whatever predictors made it through that
screen are now in the model.
And then they're going to prune the model,
using backward elimination.
Any variables that have a P value over
0.10,
are going to be taken out of the model,
any P variables that
have a P less that 0.10 are going to be
retained in the model.
Now backward elimination could be done
manually,
meaning that somebody goes through and
looks at the p values, and
takes out the variables that are higher
than that, or it can also be done au,
automatically, with an automatic algorithm
in the computer.
And then they're just saying they did this
to Come,
come up with independent risk factors for
delirium.
None of that is very specific, so we don't
need to pay attention to it.
We then estimated,
how good is our model at discriminating
who will get delirium and who will not.
And what did they use as a measure of
predictive ability?
They used the area under the ROC curve.
We've Seen that in logistic regression.
The area under the ROC curve tell us,
tells us how well our model does at
classifying people and that's what we
want to know here.
So, that's going to be our measure of
model performance.
Now, the problem is that whenever you
build a model,that area under ROC
curve is always going to be overly
optimistic for
the sample that you used to build the
model.
You're always fitting to noise in your
particular sample, so
it's going to look a little better than it
really is.
So what they did to try and adjust for
that is they used something
called the bootstrapping, which we talked
about in earlier module.
We used the bootstrapping to adjust for
overiftting, that is, To try to assess
like how optimistic is our model?
How overly optimistic is our model?
And they, to do this they do 200 random
bootstrap samples.
So, this is just sampling with replacement
from that original sample of 1613 patients
and when they did this [UNKNOWN] sampling,
what they were able to do Was to shrink
the area under the,
our c curve so they were to kind of
correct for that overoptimism.
And they also did something called
shrinkage of
the regression coefficients because again,
when you [COUGH] a [COUGH] model like this
You're going to be overly optimistic, that
means your data coefficients are going to
be a little bit bias, a little bit too
high, you can do something like multiply
them all by .9 to shrink them
all a little bit to correct for that bias,
and that's what they did here.
So just to summarize again.
The steps that they took, and, everybody
going to be a little different, but
this is what they took and one potential
approaches,
that they did a univariate screen,
univariate logistic regressions.
If the p value is greater than .15 or the
predictor was fairly rare in the sample,
they screened it out, they didn't move it
forward.
Everybody el, all the rest of the
predictors they moved forward into
a mulitvariate logistic regression.
They pruned that regression with backward
elimination and
they removed anything with a p value
greater than .10 from the model.
Everything else was retained.
That then becomes their model, their final
model.
If they look at the area under the ROC
curve from that model,
Which is just calculated based on the
people in their own sample, it's
going to be a little bit over-optimistic
and there's a way to adjust for that.
And one of those is something called
bootstrapping validation and
that's what they did here.
Basically they're able to adjust for that
optimism to shrink the area under
the curve a little bit and shrink the beta
co-efficient a little bit.
I'm not going to go into all the details
here because we'll be talking about this
In an upcoming module, but here's the
final model they came up with.
After the the shrinkage of the, the
selection process in
shrinking the beta coefficients a little
bit for, to correct for over optimism.
Now here's the final model.
Now, it's a little complicated but
you can imagine that this could be
programmed into a little app on an iPhone.
And you could pretty easily plug a
patient's values into this model and
it's a logistic regression model.
So what are you going to get out when you
plug out, in their values?
You're going to get out a predictive
probability.
This will give you their predicted
probability for delirium.
[NOISE]
And again, you probably don't want to
calculate this by hand, but
there could be a little app or something
that you plug in.
So, if you knew a person's age Their score
on this particular test,
something about coma, infection, etcetera.
You would plug in a new person's actual
values for each of these variables,
multiplied by their beta coefficient,
that's their weight in this score,
this model And you'd come up with some
kind of final score.
And of course for predictive probabilities
we're doing something, you know?
E raise to this over one plus E raised to
that.
Here you can see that it, they have it,
they, they're calculating the risk of
delirium as one over this, so they made it
a little easier by trans,
translating this into so that you only
have to do one over one plus E.
In any case you can plug into this.
You can get a predicted probability.
You can take a new patient.
It doesn't have to be a patient that was
used to fit the model.
You can take a new patient whatever their
values are for
these variables you plug in.
You get out their predicted probability of
delirium.
Hopefully that predicted probability lines
up pretty well with who
actually got delirium.
And how well does this model do?
Well, we can calculate an area under the
ROC curve to get at that.
So when they just calculate the area under
the ROC curve that just comes out of some,
you plug this into your statistical
package, you plug your 1600 people in,
you fit the model you ask for the ROC
curve.
What you're going to get out is the ROC
curve based on
the predicted probabilities the original
people in your data set.
So you're fitting the model With those
people then you're applying the model to
those people and then you're getting an
ROC curve.
When they did that it came out that they
had an ROC curve area under
the ROC curve of 87%.
That's pretty good.
But again it might be overly optimistic.
So what they did was they adjusted that
ROC curve estimate by
doing bootstrapping and again we'll go
into the details of that later.
You can see that when they did that the
ROC curve value only went down 1%,
so now it's, it's 86%.
So that's telling you that there wasn't,
there wasn't too much optimism here.
The, the original estimate was pretty
good.
This is a pretty robust model.
It only fell a little bit when we made
this adjustment.
They then did Temporal and External
validation.
So actually taking new patients.
And this is really what you want to do is
to take your model and say that it
could be applied to new patients and still
Have similarly good predictive ability.
So they took new patients from the same
hospital.
They plugged that values into that little
formula I showed you to get out of
predictive probability.
And then use those predictive
probabilities to draw an [UNKNOWN] curve.
the area under that curve was actually
really good.
It was eighty nine percent.
So it didn't go down at all.
When we talked about patients from the
same hospital.
When the model was then applied to new
patients from other hospitals who
might be a little bit different in their
characteristics, right.
This is what we call external validation.
Then they calculated those predicted
probabilities from, for
those patients they made their ROC curve.
The area under that ROC curve went down a
little bit as you would expect for
an entirely new patient population.
But it was still very high.
It was 84%, so it didn't go down a lot.
So this is showing me that the model is
fairly robust.
Now interesting, the authors noted in
their paper that they
also went to the nurses and physicians and
just asked them to predict on their own,
without any formula, who do you think is
going to get delirium?
And, how did the nurses and physicians do
with that prediction?
Well, their area under the curve wasn't
50%,
but it was Pretty close to 50 %, and the
confidence interval does even cross 50%.
So they're probably doing a little bit
better than chance, but
not much better than chance.
So, this is saying, just using sort of
clinical judgment to guess who's going to
get delirium or not doesn't do very well,
whereas plugging into this
predictive model Can get you a much, much
better prediction.
And they have a nice graphic here, so I
thought it was just worth sharing.
So what they did is here is the ROC curve
for everybody.
So if you take the predicted probabilities
based on the model for
everybody from the original From the new
patients from the same hospital, and
from the patients from the new hospitals,
and you put all of those together into
an RO seeker, that's a lot of predicted
probabilities represented here.
You can see that the area under the curve,
since they were all high,
is going to be high and, what they then do
is just to say okay,
we can define some particular risk groups.
So we'll say that people who have a
predicted probability of
greater than 60% based on the model.
That becomes the very high risk group.
Now it turns out that, that, that getting
above that threshold is hard, and so
the sensitivity for that if you made it
above the very high risk group,
the sensitivity here is only 30% but the
specificity is great.
So if you find somebody who has a, pretty
good probability in this model,
greater than 60%, you're pretty sure that
they are very likely to get delirious.
You're not going to catch everybody, who's
going to become delirious, but
you're going to, you're not going to have
very many false positives, so
that's a great group to focus on.
They defined a high risk group,
which was predicted probabilities between
40 and 60%.
That had better sensitivity without too
much drop off in specificity.
So they might use both of these you know
to kind of screen for
patients who are likely to get this
condition.
If they then went down to moderate risk,
20 to 40%,
this sensitivity becomes better and as
you'd expect, the specificity drops off.
There's always that trade off.
They may define low risk as anybody who
got a probability between 0 and
20% that has low sensitivity as you'd
expect in low specificity.
So probably that group you, we're,
going to just say we're,
we're not expecting them to get (no
period) delirium.
Although some of them will still will.
So that's kind of a nice way to just, to
make this clinically applicable because
people can look at, could stratify people
on their risks based on this model.