In this next module I am going to talk
about variable selection for
the easiest case when there's a single
primary predictor of interest.
So if there's just one main hypothesis
that you are trying to test.
That's going to make your variable
selection quite a bit easier than some of
the cases we're going to see in a little
bit.
This is going to come up in the situation
we've got a randomized trial.
So in a randomized trial,
you've randomized people to different
inter, interventions.
The regression model,
the final regression model that you report
at the end of the day is going to have to
have intervention, the intervention, as
your main predictor variable.
That might be the whole model.
Your predictor variables, your
intervention, then your outcome variables,
your outcome, and you might be done.
Sometimes with randomized
trials there might be a couple additional
variables in the model.
But they're usually pretty simple.
That's all the benefits of randomization.
For observational studies, if you're
testing one main hypothesis,
I'm going to show you an example in a
minute where,
they were looking at whether or not
mercury levels in the body were linked to
an increased risk of cardiovascular
disease.
That there's a clear hypothesis that the
study was set out to test,
then you know at the end of the day that
you're going to have a regression model
that contains that predictor of interest,
as the main predictor in the model.
And there might be other variables
included
in the model on the basis of things like
confounding.
Now, variable selection, a lot of the
principles about variable selection in
this case, we've already talked about in
this course.
So how do I evaluate confounding and, and
in interaction, we've already talked about
that.
A lot of what we're going to be doing here
is just evaluating
confounding and interaction.
For a randomized trial again is really
simple.
All of your regression models are going to
have to center,
center on the intervention of interest.
You might not have anything else in the
model.
It might literally be, here's my outcome,
and I've got you know, maybe an intercept,
and my beta for intervention, if it's a
yes-no intervention, only two groups.
That might be it.
Now, you'll see that in actual published
randomized trials,
in the literature there's often something
else in the model.
So for example for multi-site trials it's
very common to adjust for
the clinical site as a set of dummy
variables, so
maybe there's site one, and site two,
maybe there's three sites in that,
in a trial, so you add two additional
variables for clinical site.
Some smaller trials may also adjust for
chance inbalances in the groups.
Randomization is supposed to mean that the
confounders are balanced, but perhaps
there's a chance imbalance that arises in
a small trial, you might say then
I'm going to adjust for that indifference,
that base line difference in,
say, maybe the groups are slightly
different in age or whatever it might be.
So you'll see that in real situations,
a lot of times there's something more in
the model.
But it shouldn't be a lot and
it should be pretty easy to say what
you're going to put in that model.
also, you can be using the regression
model to test interaction, so
you might have an interaction with the
treatment.
So your intervention time,
say gender if you think there's going to
be an interaction with with gender.
But hopefully those interactions have been
pre-specified, so
that you're not just going through and
taking all the variables you've collected,
and trying to interact them with the
intervention.
Obviously that's going to highly increase
your type one error.
But pretty straight forward for randomized
trials, in terms of variable selection.
For observational studies it's not too
much harder.
Again, you're going to have a regression
model.
Here's your outcome.
On the right hand side of the equation,
your intercept and a beta for your primary
predictor of interest in whatever form you
happen to model that predictor in.
Of course, if it's an observational study,
you're going to need to tease out
confounding so
your model's going to contain a lot of
other things which are the confounders.
You may also be testing for some
interactions, as well.
Everything again is centered around the
primary predictor so
that's going to stay in the model whether
or not it's significant, obviously,
because non-significance is an answer to
the question.
So for example, if mercury does not
increase your risk of
cardiovascular disease, that's important
to know, and you're going to keep that
beta in the model, you're going to report
that it was non-significant.
And general principles, here, of model
building, we're going to aim for
a parsimonious model, that is,
we're not necessarily going to stuff every
possible confounder in the model.
We're going to be a little bit choosy.
And especially that's the case if the
sample size is low because we
don't want to overfit our models.
So the general rule of thumb is you only
want to have you need to have about
ten observations in your data set for
every predictor, for
every variable in your model for every
parameter you're estimating, so
you want to just kind of keep that in mind
and not overstuff your models.
Just to give you an example of an
observational study with
a clear single main hypothesis, a clear
predictor of interest.
So this is a study on mercury levels and
cardiovascular disease.
It was a nested case control study, so
they were able to get cases, those with
cardiovascular disease and
controls from two larger cohorts, one on
woman and one on men.
About 4,000 women and 2,000 men.
So a pretty big study.
The main predictor of interest was mercury
levels.
So what they did was they measured mercury
in the toenails of these men and women.
And there's a number of potential
confounders here because it
is an observational study.
The biggest confounder here is fish
consumption, and
that's because probably the biggest
determinant of whether or
not you're going to have a high mercury
level is how much fish you eat.
That's our main source of mercury is fish.
Of course, fish also has really good oils
in it for you.
And people who eat a lot of fish tend to
have lower cardiovascular risk.
So that's going to be a really important
confounder to consider and
then there's many other confounders that
you can think of.
Many things were measured in this study.
So how did they actually do the process of
model building?
I'm just going to kind of walk you three
it, through it, to show you their process.
I'm actually going to use the exact
language from the paper because I
want to expose you to how people write
things, these things up in papers.
And it may sound a little complicated, but
actually, you have enough knowledge to
follow all of this.
I'll try to decode it a little bit.
So, first of all, how was mercury modeled?
We talked, last week, about, how do I
model my predictor?
So there's choices.
You could model mercury here as a
continuous predictor,
because it was measured as something
continuous.
They evaluate it as as quintiles.
And I'm not sure the reason for that
desicion.
[COUGH], but it might be that it's easier
to interpret.
If you have quintiles of mercury
concentrations, it might be
a little bit easier for somebody to look
at than say, high versus low, for example.
I'm not sure about what that, why that was
decided, but.
It says mercury concentrations were
evaluated in quintiles as
indicator variables.
Now that may sound foreign to you, but
this is just code for dummy coding.
So indicator variables are one zero
variables.
So what they're saying there is that they
dummy coded the quintiles,
as we talked about last week.
Just a little detail here,
they used sex-specific cutoff points among
the controls.
All that means is that in the
determination of what quintile you're in.
The cut offs for those quintiles were
determined only based on the control and
they were determined separately for men
and women, that's all that's saying.
They did test for trend because they were
doing an ordinal variable quintiles.
They did those test for trends that we
talked about last week.
So the tests for trend involve assigning
participants the median value in their
quintile of exposure and evaluating this
as a continuous variable.
Okay so this is just slightly different
than the test for
trend that I told you about last week.
So again, the test for trend says I'm
going to put my ordinal variable into
the model as a continuous predictor as a
number.
And I told you last week that that's
commonly done by, say I've got a five
level ordinal variable, I just stick in
the numbers one through five.
That's almost what they did.
But they did something just a little bit
different here, which was, instead of
putting one, two, three, four, five, they
actually took the, the median value of
the mercury levels for each quintile, and
they stuck that into the regression model.
And I'll just show you that, maybe, I'm
making up numbers, I don't know what
the units are, here, but I'm making up
some numbers to illustrate a point.
But maybe, the quintiles look something
like this.
So there's actually not an even jump from
one quintile to the next so
by actually putting the median value in
each of these quintiles
is going to show a slightly different
relationship with the outcome.
And again, though, you, you're going to
have a beta, a single beta coefficient.
This is just treating this as a number and
you're going to get a p-value associated
with that beta coefficient.
That's the p for trend.
[NOISE]
Okay, so here's the model, though, that
they did.
They divided mercury into quintiles.
They dummy coded it.
That's just showing the dummy coding.
That's the basic model.
The outcome is CVD.
In a way, we're kind of done now.
We need, however, to add things to this
model to account for confounding and
potentially for interaction.
So this is the main model but everything
else now is going to be
put in the model because it's a confounder
or an interaction term.
So what else are we going to put in the
model?
This is where the variable selection comes
in,
I gotta decide what other variables are
going to go in here.
I know for sure this is going in, but then
I have to decide on the rest.
So again, I'm going to show you the
language from the paper about how they
chose their confounders, and
different people will do this in slightly
different ways.
We'd talked about the way of choosing
confounders of the 10% rule,
which is I'm going to put the confounder
in the model.
I'm going to see whether or
not it changes the beta for my predictor
of interest by more than 10%.
Now that's not totally easy to do here
because we actually have
four betas in the model but
you can kind of do the same thing by
scanning across the different betas and
seeing if a, a number of them changed a, a
significant you know, more than 10%.
So we've talked about choosing confounders
in that way.
You'll see that there's other factors that
go into choice of confounders.
It's a little bit of an art.
So as potentional confounding was assessed
with the use of multivariate models,
all it means is that they ran a logistic
regression.
They put in that model some very important
confounders, definitely went in the model.
So like, other major risk factors for
cardiovascular disease, something like
diabetes, is going to go in the model.
The fish consumption, I already mentioned,
is very important as well,
those omega fatty acids,
additional dietary factors that we know
are associated with mercury.
So there were some things that they were
saying, I'm,
we're definitely going to try these as
confounders, because they're,
we have good reason to believe that they
might be.
And then the multivariable modeling, that
just means what variables we decided to
keep in the model at the end of the day,
was guided by the principle of parsimony,
so again, you're not wanting to stuff the
model with everything you have.
You have to be choosy.
And also guided by clinical relevance, so
this just means that when you're
model building, a little bit of clinical
judgment does come in to say, you know,
this is something I really think is
going to be an important confounder.
I might put it in the model even if
there's no real evidence
that it's a confounder just because
somebody's going to wonder about it if I
don't put it in.
So just for face validity I might be
putting it in.
They also looked at the strength of the
association between the potential
confounder and mercury or cardiovascular
disease, so
if there was a potential confounder that
had a really strong association with
the either the exposure the outcome they
might have included that in the model.
And then here's the percent change rule.
The percent change of the risk estimate
when the confounder was included so
that's the one that we primarily talked
about.
But notice that there's a lot of
additional factors guiding this whole
choice here.
It's a little bit of an art.
I'll show you which confounders they came
up with at the end of the day as
going in the model.
I just want to point out missing data here
for covariates.
Which accounted for
less than 1% of all data, were imputed by
the means of multiple imputation.
So we just talked about multiple
imputation that was used here.
So here are the results.
They had quintiles of toe, of toenail
mercury is there, is here.
And fish was such an important potential
confounder that they
actually stratified on total fish.
On specific kinds of fish because it was
just so, so
much of a potentially important confounder
here.
So, here is the adjusted models.
What you'll notice is the P-values for
trend are all null.
There's a couple cases where the P-value
is getting up here,
where the P- value is getting a little
close to significance.
And actually, though,
as you go up in mercury your risk of
cardiovascular disease is going down.
That potentially could be due to residual
confounding with fish consumption.
But you can see that in general doesn't
look like mercury is
a particularly good predictor of
cardiovascular risk.
I'll just note if you read the fine print
you can see what final confounder has
made it into the model.
BMI, smoking, age, sex, race, physical
activity, alchohol,
lot of confounders made it into the final
model.
This is a fairly big data set so they can
afford to put in a fairly large number of
confounders there, they're detailed there.
But again, because fish consumption was so
important that one got special treatment
and actually they stratified on it.
They also say, did some test for
interaction.
They actually stay in their statistical
methods, test for interaction involved
multiplying the variable by the effect
modifier of interest and using the Wald
test to calculate the P-value associated
with the multiplicative interaction term.
All that means is, my translation here for
you, they, they took the variable, the,
the thing that they thought was an
interaction term, so
like, they're going to test for an action
by sex or
gender here they multiplied that by their
predictor of interest, mercury.
They put that term into the model.
It's exactly how we've tested for
interaction before, so even though this
may sound a bit cryptic to you, you
actually know everything that's in here.
The Wald test to calculate the P-value,
that's just the P-value associated with
This beta.
It's nothing fancy.
We've talked about all of this before.
So that's how they tested for interaction
in the normal way.
Now they didn't actually specify what
interactions they tested, but the one
that was most important was they actually
had data from two separate cohorts,
a female cohort so the most important
potential interaction term was sex.
So they tested for interaction by male,
female.
When they did a stratified analysts, men
separated from women, they noticed that
it looked like there was a lower incidence
of cardiovascular disease with
higher mercury for women, in other words
the more mercury you had, the lower your
cardiovascular disease risk, they saw that
in women, they didn't see that in men.
However, we've talked about this before
that is very careful,
just because the trend looks different
that doesn't necessarily guarantee you
that you're going to have a significant
interaction.
So is that difference between men and
women, is it statistically significant?
In this case it turned out not to be.
So when they did those interaction tests
for sex with mercury, there,
it didn't quite reach statistical
significance.
So they didn't have enough evidence that
there's really a different
relationship between mercury in men and
cardiovascular disease in men and women.
All right, so that's the, one example of
how to build a model.
But basically, we're going to be following
some process like that when
there's one primary predictor.
I just want to bring up the issue here of
P-value shopping, because
it comes up in all contexts in variable
selection when you're building models.
There's just a lot of opportunities,
especially in observational studies,
where not everything has been
pre-specified for multiple testing errors.
So, this is not what you should do, and
this is what you should not do on this
slide.
I'm cautioning you against this kind of
p-value shopping.
So, there's a lot of ways to make sure
that you find the smallest
p-value possible.
Every time you're hunting, you're on the
hunt and shopping for
smaller P-values, you're increasing your
chances of a type one error.
So, for example, you could try all these
different forms of the predictor,
not based on like looking at graphics.
But just keep dumping different ways of
modeling the predictor into your into your
model and see which one gives you the
lowest p-value.
You could say well, if I use this
combination of confounders, and
I run this model, and then I try this
other combination of confounders,
which one gives me the lowest P-value for,
for the primary predictor of interest.
Or sometimes people will say like, oh,
this guy's the little high value.
Maybe I'll just throw him out.
And if I throw these three observations
out,
I can get my P-value down to be under
0.05, and so on.
This P-value shopping obviously is a
really bad idea.
However, I get a lot of emails [LAUGH],
that are somewhat along these lines.
So that's why I just want to make sure
that I'm cautioning you against this.
I get emails that say, Dr. Sonati ] if I,
you know, how can I get my P-value to be
under point, my p-value is 0.052.
How can I get it to be under 0.05?
As if that's the goal, right,
of doing statistics is to get your p-value
under 0.05 or.
Dr. Sonati if you know I, I think this
data point might be an outlier and
if I include the outlier my p-value is
0.06.
But if I don't include the outlier my
p-value is 0.04.
So is it okay therefore to throw out the
outlier.
They're looking for my permission to, you
know p-value shop, basically.
So obviously you gotta be really careful
that you're not
basing your variable selection decisions
simply on what gives you the best p-value.