In this next module,
I'm going to talk about one of the
assumptions of linear regression that
you really should test if you've got
continuous predictors in your module.
I think it's often an ignored assumption.
So when you're reading papers you should
look to see whether or not it was tested.
And if you're doing your own data analysis
it would be important to run this test.
This assumption is something called linear
in the logit.
And it's, it's as simple as just when we
do a linear regression,
remember what do you want to do of course?
When you do a linear regression, you
want to do the plot.
And you want to see if it actually looks
like a line.
This one looks like a line, here's a
scatter plot that doesn't look like
a line, it actually looks like a
quadratic.
So for linear regression, it's really easy
because we can just plot x against y.
We can see immediately if it looks like
the, the scatter plot roughly fits a line.
For logistic regression we're still
fitting lines but
it's harder to draw this graphic, because
the outcome, remember,
is this logit function, and there's no way
to directly see the logit function.
The best you can do, as I did some logit
plots in the first module for this week.
And how I did that, in order to be able to
do that,
I had to group people according to their
level of the predictor.
So I can group people who did the lowest
number amount of homework and, you know,
like the ten lowest, ten people with the
lowest homework time, and
then the next ten, and then the next ten.
So I have to somehow group you people in
order that I
can calculate the proportion who've had
the binary outcome.
From that proportion I can then calculate
the logit.
If you do that, then you can make some
plots.
But of course the plot's going to depend
slightly on how you bin people,
how you group people.
So I'm going to show you in a minute some
examples of testing this,
a linear in the logit assumption and
you'll see that I,
we'll usually run several different graphs
with several different bin sizes so
that I can get a sense of the data
without, you know, being too arbitrary.
And we're looking for that.
What we're testing is that,
if you have a continuous predictor in
logistic regression,
what we're doing is we're fitting a line
that says that continuous predictor acts.
Has a linear relationship, roughly, with
the logit of the outcome.
So you actually want to make that plot as
best you can and
see if the relationship is really linear.
Or if, maybe it's not.
If it's something else, if the
relationship looks, you know,
quadratic, that means you're going to have
to model a quadratic variable for x.
You're going to put in an x squared into
the model or you might have to
transform that continuous variable into a
categorical variable.
It may not be simply fine to just put that
continuous predictor
directly into the model.
Notice, if you have a binary or
a categorical predictor, you do not have
to worry about this assumption.
Because, if you have a binary variable, a
binary predictor,
you're only doing a zero, one.
You've got only two dots therefore, and
anytime you connect two dots it's
automatically a line.
If you've a categorical predictor, you're
going to be dummy coding it, so
you're going to have a series of zero,
ones, those are all going to make lines.
So this is only a worry when you have a
continuous predictor in
logistic regression.
I'm going to show you some real examples
with real data.
Various examples where I have had to draw
linear in the logit plots.
This example was from a data set where the
outcome is heart disease,
the predictor that we're looking at here
called tobacco,
this is the number of cigarettes smoked
per day.
And I grouped the data set up into four
bins as well as ten bins,
just to give us a, a sense of the
relationship between the number of
cigarettes per day and the logit of heart
disease.
And again, I have to group people, what
I'm graphing here is the,
I'm graphing their mean cigarettes per
day.
The mean cigarettes per day for
the group against the logit for that
group, the observed logit for that group.
What you can see here is that for this
particular variable,
the number of cigarettes per day, it does
not look linear in the logit.
The relationship between cigarettes per
day and
are, the logit of having heart disease
appears curvealinear.
There tends to be a curved relationship.
In both of these graphics you can see it
that there's sort of
a curved relationship here.
Why is that?
Well think about the variable cigarettes
per day.
You have a bunch of people who smoke zero
cigarettes per day, and
then you've got people increasing on their
cigarettes per day.
What you're seeing in this graphic here,
is when you dump from being a non smoker,
to smoking you know, some little amount
per day,
there's a huge jump in your odds and risk
of getting heart disease,
its a major seed jump, jump But then there
are sort of diminishing returns.
Once you're already a smoker, whether you
smoke a couple of cigarettes per day,
or more, it, you're risk does go up, but
it doesn't go up as steeply.
And then it, when you go from being kind
of a moderate smoker to being a heavy
smoker, your risk also goes up, but it
goes up even less steeply.
So the relationship is really curved,
rather than linear.
How might you account for this?
Probably the best way is to think about
cigarette smoking as
a categorical variable.
You might want to model this as non
smokers versus light to
moderate smokers versus heavy smokers.
And that might be the best way to actually
model this.
This is the.
This might be a case where it
makes sense to treat tobacco smoking,
cigarettes per day, as a categorical
variable, rather than continuous, so
that's an example that violated the linear
in the logit assumption.
Here's an example where we're actually
meeting the linear in the logit assumption
pretty well, this was some data that I had
on women athletes.
And the outcome variable here is low bone
mineral density.
So, low skeletal strength.
It turns out that women athletes sometimes
don't menstruate normally.
And, if you don't have normal menses, that
actually can reduce your,
your skeletal strength, your, your bone
mineral, bone mineral density.
So that, this was a dataset looking at
that.
Again, I did too many earlier in the logit
part, so
I'm getting a sense depending on how I bin
things,
how many people per group that I'm getting
the right relationships.
So I grouped into about 12 bins as well as
five bins.
And you can see that there's, of course,
more local noise when you have 12 bins,
but the pattern looks pretty similar in
both cases.
I would say that this is pretty close to
fitting the line.
It's not a perfect line but
it looks like it actually is reasonably
linear in the logit.
In both cases, you can imagine kind of
drawing a line,
again with lots of points there's going to
be some local variability.
But essentially that's well fit by a line.
So, in this case our predictor variable
here is the number of menses,
the number of menstrual periods per year.
So where, you know, normal is sort of
around 12.
A lot of women athletes are having many
less than that.
And it turns out there's a linear
relationship here.
As the number of menstrual periods goes
up, from zero all the way up to a normal
of 12, the chances, the odds of getting
low, of having low bone density go down.
And it appears to be well modeled as
linear, so
I could put the number of natural cycles
per year in as the predictor variable and
get an odds ratio for every one unit
increase in menstrual,
in menses, how does that decrease my odds
of getting low bone marrow density.
This one seems reasonably modeled as a
linear variable.