[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about negative binomial regression,
which is just an extension of Poisson
Regression.
So negative binomial regression is also
used in a situation where you
have Count data.
It's a lot like poisson regression,
except you're going to estimate one
additional parameter.
But that additional parameter can be
pretty important.
So the parameter that you're estimating is
something called the dispersion parameter.
And here's why you might need that.
So when you did a poisson regression, you
were assuming.
That the data actually had
a Poisson probability distribution that it
actually followed that.
Remember with the Poisson probability
distribution, the mean and
the variance are equivalent.
It turns out that with a lot of real life
count data, that is not true,
the mean and the variance are not
equivalent,
in fact the variance, Can be quite a bit
bigger than the mean.
If that's the case, then our data are what
we call over-dispersed.
And Poisson probability isn't quite the
right fit.
We have to correct for this dispersion,
for
the fact that the variance is actually
bigger than the mean.
We can do that by estimating an additional
parameter.
Called the dispersion parameter.
Now, what's the consequences of pretending
we're on
a Poisson distribution when in fact the
mean is smaller than the variance?
Well, what would happen in that case, we
run a Poisson regression,
we're assuming that the variance is
smaller than it actually is,
and therefore all of our estimates of
standard error are going to be too small.
And therefor, our p values are going to be
too small, and
we're going to have an overly optimistic
model.
So if you don't estimate this dispersion
parameter when it's needed,
your model might be overly optimistic.
My general recommendation actually is
you're going to see in
a minute that it's fairly straight forward
to run the negative binomial regression.
You can always run the negative binomial
regression for count data.
It will tell you, essentially, weather or
not you need this dispersion term.
If you don't need the dispersion term,
you can default back to the Poisson
regression.
If you do need it, then you can stick with
the negative binomial.
So then my general approach would actually
be, with count data,
to start with the negative binomial
regression, and then default to
Poisson only if the dispersion clu-,
parameter's close to zero.
Just as, a, just a quick note here, I
want to mention that,
we are, negative binomial, that's the
another probability distribution.
So, I am not going to go into a lot of
details about it but the negative
binomial probability distribution works
again, the probability distribution.
Therefore, we can use it to do regression
and just to like you know.
A sense of what it is, is a situation like
this.
So imagine you got a coin, and
you say I'm going to flip this coin until
I get 50 heads.
So I'm going to stop when I get 50 heads.
You can ask the question then, well how
long, how many flips of
the coin are you going to have to do
before you stop, before you hit 50 heads?
And of course.
On a given try, it might take you 80 flips
of a coin.
It might take you a 100.
It might take you a 120.
So, we can talk about the probability of
each of those possible outcomes.
So, whether it takes you 90 coin flips
before you get 50 heads or
whether it takes you a 110.
We can actually calculate all of this
probabilities.
Those probabilities follows what's
called a negative Binomial probability
distribution.
Turns out that the negative binomials
related to both the binomial and
to the Poisson and and that's as much
detailed as I'll, I'll go into there.
But let me actually just give you a real
example.
So, go back to the data that I had on the
number of swimming world records that
are set in a given year.
We fit all that data with a Poisson
regression.
But actually that probably wasn't optimal,
because if you look carefully at
that outcome variable here, it is in fact
over-dispersed.
The variance of the number of world
records in a given year is
actually bigger than the mean.
So that indicates that we should probably
try a negative binomial regression here,
and that's indeed what I did.
So let me just remind you what the Poisson
regression model we ended up with
was the following.
So this came out of Poisson regression, we
had Ended with a model of year,
year squared, number of new technologies,
and
the interaction between year and number of
new technologies.
Something that's hidden here is that we
set the dispersion parameter to zero.
So we're saying we're not allowing for any
dispersion.
The only difference you're going to see
with the negative binomial is
that we'll actually estimate this, we
won't set it to zero.
What you're going to pay attention to in
the output here,
is just kind of scan the Poisson
regression model that we've got,
look at the beta coefficients, And then
also look at the standard errors.
What's going to happen when we do a
negative binomial is
that the beta coefficients aren't going to
change much at all.
because this doesn't really effect the
beta coefficients at all it
simply effects the variants or the
standard error.
However, look carefully at the standard
errors they are about .01,
.004, .1086, .0036 Those standard errors
are going to get a lot bigger,
when we account for dispersion.
So now let me show you the negative
binomial regression for the same data.
Same model, same data.
So notice now first focus on this
dispersion parameter.
We've estimated this additional parameter,
that's called the dispersion parameter.
Came out with a value of positive ,1654
and we also get a standard error for
this dispersion parameter.
Notice if I divide the point estimate by
its standard error here,
I'm going to get assuming this is normally
distributed, I'm going to get a Z score.
You know, of above three, it's going to be
highly statistically significant.
That's telling me that the dispersion is
different than zero.
There is dispersion.
That means I need to account for it.
If I had fit the negative binomial
regression and
the dispersion value had come out close to
zero And
you know wasn't statistically significant,
then I would say Poisson regression model
is good enough, it doesn't look like it
have a lot of dispersion.
So you can actually fit the negative
binomial, check the dispersion parameter,
if its close to zero, go with Poisson, if
its away from zero as is it here,
then go with the negative binomial.
Notice, that you actually look at the
betas, they don't change much,
they're almost identical to what we got
from From plus on.
So this does not effect the point
estimates.
However, look over here at the standard
errors.
We had about .01 before that's more than
doubled, we had .04 that's now .008.
A lot of that, they're almost all either
nearly doubled or, or doubled.
So the standard errors are quite a bit
bigger that's going to
make a huge impact on the p-values.
So you'll notice that all of the p-values
are smaller than they were.
This new technology, linear term, is no
longer significant.
And the year squared term is kind of only
borderline.
All of them were significant before.
This is important because it can really
effect the p-values.
Just for fun, I also took this data,
because sometimes you get data and you're
not quite sure which model to put them in.
So you have to go through this thought
process.
I also took these count data and because
if you plot them in a histogram,
you realize that they're, you know,
there's a, there's a fair range here.
Perhaps, we can make these a little bit
normally distributed if we apply a log.
And so, you could try to kind of force
these data in a linear regression and
I did that just to show you what happens.
So I took the log count data because
that's more normally distributed than
the count data.
Although, still not perfectly normally
distributed.
And I ran it with a regular old linear
regression, same model.
And here's the outcome that I get.
So notice, first of all,
that the beta coefficients are almost
identical to what we saw before.
So no matter which of these models you
choose,
your basically getting the same beta
coefficients.
So that's good.
What changes is the standard error.
So the standard errors here are now
actually a little bit higher than with,
the optimal model, which is negative
binomial regression.
The standard error is a little higher, so
the p values are even Even bigger.
And we're going to miss some things that
actually are statistically significant
in the negative binomial regression.
So, the linear regression turns out to be
overly conservative for these data.
So, if you had forced this into a linear
regression,
you might have missed something.
So, with count data, it's probably best to
just start with the negative binomial.
And then if you want to get simpler from
there, you know if you don't need
the dispersion parameter, or you could try
a linear regression if it looks like you,
really the counts are really filling in
all the wide range that aren't
normally distributed, but often with
counts, they're not normally distributed.
So with counts, think of negative binomial
or plasan.
And then finally, I just want to mention
that as with the plasan regression.
You can take the data co-efficients from a
negative binomial regression and
they have a direct interpretation as
relative risks.
So, if you just exponentiate the data
co-efficients from
negative binomial regression.
That's going to give you the incidence
rate ratio, same as with Poisson.
So, everything is identical.
I want to give you an example here or
a model is a little complicated because I
have got all Interaction in
a higher order terms, but let me walk you
through one calculation.
So, for example, our beta for
the number of new technologies, that was
negative .27.
Our beta for the interaction between
technologies is And
year turned out to be positive 0.015,
and remember that I've modeled years here
as the number of years since 1969.
So how would I get the incidence rate
ratio for new technology Well, of course,
because of an interaction term that means
that this rate ratio depends on the year
that we're talking about, technology has a
different effect depending on the year.
The easiest one to calculate it for is if
I just look at 1969.
So if I look at 1969 the interaction term
will go to 0 because I've modeled
this as year since 1969 so that will have
a value, year will have a value of 0.
This interaction term will go away.
So at, in 1969, the ri, the risk ratio,
the rate ratio for new
technologies was e raised to the negative
0.27 which is a risk ratio of 0.76.
So introducing a new technology in 1969
had little effect, if anything, it,
there were less world records when that
happened.
However, scroll ahead 40 years later to
2009.
[UNKNOWN].
What are we going to get in our model.
So our risk ratio's going to be negative
.27 but
now we get the interaction term so I'm
doing this very one, one new technology so
technology will be one, I'm going to
multiply it by 40, 40 years since 1969.
The beta co-efficient here was .015.
.015 time 40 is .60.
This is going to, if I add .60 minus .27 I
get e raised to .33 so
the odd, the relative risk here is 1.39.
So if you're talking about 2009 than every
new technology
increases your weight of world records or
your risk of world records by 39%.
So new technologies are having a really
big impact in the later Four years.
That's what the interaction term tells us.
But again with negative binomial, there's
a nice, easy, you can get out these,
these rate ratios better than odds ratios
as, as we know.