In this next module I'm going to introduce
you to propensity scores.
So propensity scores are another data
compression technique, but
it's a data compression technique
specifically for confounders.
So we're going to be taking a whole big
set of confounders and trying
to compress it into a single number, a
probability called the propensity score.
The primary use case for propensity scores
are observational treatment studies.
So this is where there are multiple
possible treatment options for
a particular condition, but
they've never been compared head to head
in a randomized trial.
And perhaps that's just really a difficult
randomized trial to do and
they may never be compared in a randomized
trial.
So the best thing that we can do is to try
to
do some kind of observational study
comparing those two treatments.
The problem here is that there's going to
be a huge amount of confounding,
because doctors often have very specific
reasons about why they're
going to choose one treatment over another
for a particular patient.
And those reasons might also be related to
the outcomes.
So we have what's called confounding by
indication.
And propensity scores are trying to
address this type of confounding.
I'm going to be using two examples to
illustrate propensity scores, so
I'll just introduce them now.
So the first example is a retrospective
cohort study that was
comparing two treatments for aortic valve
replacements.
So there's something call the Ross
procedure, which is an autograph,
meaning that person's own tissue was used
for
the value replacement, versus a mechanical
value, with some anticoagulation therapy.
They wanted to know whether or
not one of these procedures is optimal in
terms of long-term survival,
that is not immediately after the surgery
but long-term.
Now, previous studies have actually
suggested that the Ross procedure might
have an advantage.
However, the patients that were getting
the Ross procedure were
quite different than the patients who were
getting the mechanical valve.
For whatever reasons, physicians tended to
recommend the Ross procedure for
people who were younger and who were in
better physical condition.
So that it's really hard to tease out.
Is it because the Ross Procedure actually
improved mortality or
is it just because those are the patients
that would have done well anyway?
So the propensity scores are going to try
to address that.
So you can see from table one of this
paper just how different these two groups
were, people who got the mechanical valve
verses people who got the Ross procedure.
So this was from, again, a retrospective
cohort study, so
they went back into medical records.
They found people who had had mechanical
valve, people who have had the Ross
procedure, and they were able to get data
on outcomes on death in this case.
But you can see that the mechanical valve
patients were
quite a bit older than the Ross patients,
almost a decade older, highly significant.
The mechanical value patients,
76% had calcification, strong
calcification in their arteries,
which is a lot versus only 36%, about half
as many in the Ross procedure.
36% of the mechanical valve patients had
had
a coronary bypass at the same time versus
only 4% of the Ross procedure patients.
So obviously, those getting the Ross
procedure are going to
have better outcomes in terms of
mortality, because they're younger,
because they're healthier.
Is there any additional advantage for the
Ross procedure?
Second example is looking at whether or
not patients with stroke who are in
a nursing home, whether or not they
benefit from rehabilitation.
And this was another retrospective cohort
study.
They were comparing patients who got
rehabilitation or, or who didn't.
The outcomes were community discharge,
that is getting out of the nursing home,
and just their functional status for these
stroke patients.
Now it turns out other studies have shown
that patients who receive rehabilitation,
indeed, do have better outcomes.
But you have to consider who gets
rehabilitation.
They tend, it tends for whatever reason
that people who
are less disabled actually are the ones
who are getting more rehabilitation.
They tend to be better insured for
probably obvious reasons.
They also tend to have more social
support.
So they're just healthier, better insured
to begin with.
How do we know it's the rehabilitation
that's improving their outcomes as
opposed to just the type of patient that's
selected for rehabilitation?
Propensity scores are going to help us
answer that question.
Now we could try to just adjust for
confounding by indication in
all the ways that I have told you about
how we can adjust for confounding.
So we adjust for
confounding by stratification, matching,
or statistical adjustment.
So you can imagine him saying, well, maybe
I can just adjust for
all these differences between the groups
with is some kind of, for
example, some kind of regression analysis.
There's obvious issues with all of these
in, in this particular case.
So there's many confounders here and
we're, stratification usually works
well if you're going to stratify on one
confounder, but
it's really going to be impossible to
stratify in a whole pile of confounders.
So we really can't use stratification
here.
Matching, we're going to run into the same
problem,
which variables are you going to match on?
If you try to match on to many it's going
to be really hard to find good matches, so
we cant really do that here.
We're essentially left with statistical
adjustment.
And statistical adjustment could work in
this case, we could just adjust for
all these differences between the groups.
But there's some potential problems.
It may turn out that some people in the
study, or
entire groups, are simply incomparable.
They're just too different to compare.
We can try to adjust for
the differences, but we, there's just no
way to actually adjust out for them.
We've talked about some of the limits of
statistical adjustment already.
There going to be a high chance of
residual confounding because of this.
And we just may run into this situation
where there be,
may be so many things that we want to
adjust for
that we may not have a big enough sample
size to handle that in our model.
So for the example of the Ross procedure
study, they wanted to adjust for
24 confounders.
There were actually only 36 deaths in that
study.
And when you're building models which have
a binary outcome,
you either have the event or you didn't,
you actually want to make sure that you
have enough events for every parameter
that you try to estimate in your model.
So if you have only 36 events, the general
recommendation would be that you
should only have three or four parameters
in your model and not 24.
So that's going to be a high chance of
overfitting if we try to put so
many confounders in the model when our
sample size is too small.
So there's all these limitations to
adjusting for confounding in this way.
With propensity scores, we can do well on
all of these.
So our propensity score is a single
number.
It's the probability that you would get
one treatment or the other.
So for the Ross study example it's
going to be the probability that
you would have been a person who would get
the Ross treatment.
And we can take those propensities towards
that single number and
we can stratify on them.
We can say, group people into quintiles of
propensity scores and then we
only compare people in the lowest quintile
to other people in the lowest quintile.
So now we can do stratification.
It's also now easy to match.
We can just match on that single number.
For every Ross patient with a propensity
score of 0.7, we're going to try to
find a mechanical valve patient who also
has a propensity score of 0.7.
So it makes matching really easy.
We can also now more easily statistically
adjust,
because we can only have to put a single
number into our regression model, so
we don't worry about issues with sample
size.
Alright, here's the idea with propensity
scores.
Think about a randomized trial.
The great thing about a randomized trial
is that all participants have the same
probability of receiving each of the
interventions in the trial.
That's not the case in observational
studies.
In observational studies some patients are
more likely to get the Ross procedure and
some people are much less likely to.
What we try to do with the propensity
scores is actually explicitly
estimate the probabilities, these
probabilities.
What is the probability that a particular
person has of getting the Ross procedure?
Propensity scores estimate these
probabilities.
And how do we do it?
Well, logistic regression,
because you can estimate predicted
probabilities with logistic regression.
We fit a logistic regression model with
all of a person's covariates,
all of the things that might be related to
whether or
not they get a certain treatment.
We put that into the logistic regression
model, out we get a predicted probability.
That's their probability of getting a
certain treatment.
Now everyone in our study,
of course, they've already gotten one
treatment or the other.
But this is theoretical, this is saying
that if this type of person went to
a physician, went to kind of any
physician, what's, what's the likelihood
that they would have come out with Ross
procedure versus a mechanical valve?
The propensity score,
again, is the probability of receiving a
given treatment given one's covariates.
We're estimating that with a logistic
regression model.
So what's the probability that this
patient would have got the Ross procedure,
given that they're young, they didn't have
coronary artery bypass, et cetera,
et cetera?
And, for example, when we do this logistic
regression the predictive probability for
a young patient who's in good physical
condition might end up to being 70%.
So that patient, whether or not they
actually did get the Ross procedure, they
theoretically have a 70% chance of getting
it, based on all these characteristics.
Now an older patient in poor physical
condition,
they might have had only a 30%
probability.
The idea here is that we’re going to to
try to find` people who have
equal probabilities and compare only those
people to one another, apples to apples.
Propensity scores are estimated using
logistic regression, so
we're literally going to fit a logistic
regression model.
We can model the probability of getting
the Ross procedure, for example.
And of course, if we don't get the Ross
procedure, you get the mechanical valve,
so this is just the binary outcome.
We can choose either one, but
let's say we choose to model the
probability of the Ross procedure.
If you don't get the Ross Procedure, then
you get the other one.
And you're just going to fit the the
logistic regression model with that as
the outcome and all of your potential
covariates, all the things that
might predict which procedure you get, as
your predictors in the model.
You get, out of logistic regression,
we've already talked about how to
calculate predicted probabilities.
We then apply a particular person's
covariates.
We put them in the model.
We get out a predicted probability for
that person.
The computer will do that for you.
You get a propensity score or a
probability for each person.
Now notice that we've taken a huge number
of covariates and
we've compressed them into one number, one
probability.
Now theoretically, we think,
the patients who have similar propensity
scores are somehow comparable.
So if it turns out that we end up with a
patient who has a 70% propensity score,
but they actually received the Ross
procedure, and then we have another
patient who also, based on all their
characteristics, had a 70 percent chance
of getting the Ross procedure, but they,
in fact, received a mechanical valve,
now we have a situation where these two
people are comparable.
They were both equally likely,
based on their characteristics, to get
this procedure.
One got the Ross procedure and one didn't.
It's as if we had randomized them at that
point.
In theory then, any difference in the
outcome would be attributed to
the treatment rather than to patient
selection.
Now just a quick note that all we are
requiring here is
that their propensity scores be equal, it
doesn't matter how they got there.
So somebody could have a high propensity
score because they were young; another
person could have a high propensity score
because they were healthy.
But as long as they're both equal, we
think that they have an equal chance and
that it's something like they were
randomly assigned at that point.
They each had a 70% chance.
We flipped the coin with a 70% chance of a
heads and
one got the procedure and one didn't.
So what the idea here is that we're then
going to match people,
one of the options is to match people, on
their propensity score.
So we take somebody who actually got the
ross procedure and
had a propensity of 0.7.
We match them to somebody who actually got
the mechanical valve procedure but
also had a propensity score of 0.7.
If we look at the match score, for
example, or
we could stratify and, and match people
within strata.
If we then look at the two treatment
groups after this matching or
stratification, what we'll see is that
they
will hopefully be balanced with respect to
all the covariates that we measured and
included in the logistic regression model.
Now, this is a little bit different than
what happens with randomization.
This is not as good as randomization.
This is like a poor man's randomization.
Randomization is much better because
randomization tells,
when you randomize that's going to yield
treatment groups that are balanced,
both with respect to measured confounder
and with unmeasured confounders.
That's because it's a random assignment,
so even if you don't know
about the confounders, theoretically those
are going to be balanced too.
Propensity scores,
on the other hand, don't balance anything
that you didn't measure.
So they don't eliminate unmeasured or
residual confounding in the same way that
randomization does.
So we'd always prefer randomization, if it
was possible.