So now to illustrate Poisson regression,
I'm going to refer to a particular set of
example data, this was data that was
compiled by a student at Colorado College.
The outcome here is the number of world
records broken in swimming in
any given year.
And this means like anytime a world record
is broken in any event, men or women.
So you can see that the there are a fair
number of records can be broken in any
year.
The predictors that we're going to look at
are the calendar year.
Is there any trends over time and also in
a given year if a lot of technologies,
new technologies are introduced like
better swimsuits or better goggles.
Does that predict that more world records
will be broken, so
we're going to look at those two outcomes.
Now first of all let's examine the outcome
variable here, the outcome variable again,
is the number of world's records broken
per year.
This is a count variable, because you
can't break 1.5 records or
one and three quarters records.
You can only, you, you know, it's a cal
variable.
You can only break from zero up to some
number of records.
So when I plot the histogram of my outcome
variable here.
.
First of all,
what you'll notice is that on some years a
lot of world records get broken.
So here's my frequency distribution, my
histogram.
My predictor, my variable here on X axis
is world records so in
a lot of years you're going to have five,
15, even 25, 35 world records broken.
There's a lot of events in swimming and
again we have.
Multiple genders and things.
So there's a lot of opportunities for
world records to be broken.
The average here was 17.95.
So in an average year, on average, about
18 records fall each year.
These are world records.
Now, clearly, if you look at this
histogram,
this is not a normally distributed
variable.
[UNKNOWN] We actually wouldn't expect to
be normally distributed, because we have
a bound at zero and it's not continuous,
we can only take on discrete count values.
So if you were to get this data set, you
know, couple of things are going to go
through your mind, in terms of what model
am I going to apply to this data set.
It's not as obvious that it's a discrete
outcome.
Because, you know, it can take on a fair
range of values here.
And the first thing you might think of
when you look at these data is to say,
well, yeah its truly discreet but I'm
going to kind of look at this and
say it has a good range of values, I'm
going to pretend its continuous and
I'm going to do some kind of linear
regression.
That might be something that you reach
for,
that's not unreasonable actually with this
data set.
Now, clearly however, on my end here by
the way, is I have 41 years that I,
we're look, looked at.
So it's a small sample and this is clearly
not normally distributed so
I'm not going to want to.
Apply linear regression to this outcome
with such a small sample.
We're going to have problems with
inference there.
But remember, one of the things that you
can do is take an outcome variable like
this and transform it in some way to try
to make it look more normally distributed.
So in this case, we could take the counts,
and we could log transform them.
Simply just take the natural log of the
counts rather than the original counts.
When you do that,
you'll notice that it's starting to look
more normally distributed.
It's still actually not a perfect, normal
distribution, but
it's kind of getting to the range where
it's close to normal.
So potentially, you could take these log
counts and
you could model them in a linear
regression.
That wouldn't be terrible here.
The sample size is still really small so,
it's, you know,
we are off of our normality a little bit.
It's going to make some difference.
It's also a little tricky to interpret log
accounts at the end of the day, so
there are some drawbacks to doing a linear
regression here however and
that might not be optimal for this data
set.
So, keep in the back of your mind, though,
that, that's sometimes what happens.
You should also keep in the back of your
mind that there are,
this count, this particular outcome
variable I've chosen because i's kind of,
it, it could almost be modeled in, with a
linear regression because it
has a reasonable range of values and
they're not totally all clustered at zero.
A lot of times with count variables,
what you see is something that looks more
like this though.
You've got a lot of people clustered at
the low numbers: zero, one,
two, and then you've got a long right
tail.
And that variable's clearly not normally
distributed if it looks like that.
And it's hard, even with a transformation,
to get that to look normally distributed.
So when you have count data that looks
like that or you know again, in this
case because we have a small sample size,
it's not quite normally distributed.
When you have count data, consider Poisson
regression,
because Poisson regression is actually
setup for count data.
So we're actually going to apply Poisson
regression to these data.
Now, what I'm going to do first,
is I'm just going to run a Poisson
regression model with no predictors in
the model because it's very simple to say
what's going on.
If you can do the model with nothing else
in it, with just the intercept,
it gives you a sense of the model, and
then we can add predictors later.
So, first of all, when we're doing a
Poisson regression,
the likelihood function is going to be
based on Poisson probabilities.
I'll show you that in a, in a little bit.
But what you need to know is that where
you're actually your
outcome variable is not going to be the
counts directly.
It's going to be the log counts.
And when you plug into a computer and
ask for Poisson regression it will know to
do that.
You don't have to ask for what's called.
The log link function.
But, that's pretty easy to do.
But, essentially what you're modeling is
the log counts.
That means that when we test you know a
continuous predictor, like year,
against log counts that ought to be linear
in the log counts.
So, we'll have to do a test of linearity
in the log count.
I'll show you that in a minute, but our
output here is actually the log count, and
now I'm going to say what,
what we'd expect when I fit this model
with just the intercept.
So I told you that the average number of
world records broken per year in
the time period studied, which was in data
set, was 1969 to 2009.
The mean records broken in any given year
was about 18.
We're looking not at the original counts
but
we're going to be looking at the log
counts here.
So if I take the natural log of 17.95
The mean of the log count is, turns out to
be about 2.89.
So what that means is that the alpha, when
I fit the model with nothing else,
my alpha value is going to come out to be
2.89, about 2.89.
Because if there's nothing else in the
model, the best guess for,
since we're just modeling log counts.
The intercept.
The intercept is just the mean for
the log counts.
That's it.
So here's what happened when I actually
put these in into the computer and
asked it to run a Poisson regression for
me.
So I get.
It's an intercept only model.
So and I get my intercept is about 2.9,
because that is the mean of the log
counts.
So that's what I'm going to get out of my
model.
So that's the intercept only model.
Nothing surprising.
The intercept represents the mean log
counts and
indeed we got out the mean log counts, so
nothing fancy there.
Alright, now I'm going to think about
putting a predictor into my model.
So the first predictor I'm going to look
at is the calendar year.
Okay?
And let me just do a plot here.
because we alway want to plot our data to
see what's going on.
So here I've plotted the calender year and
the data were collected between 1969 and
2009.
So here's the calendar year, and
I'm plotting my outcome of the number of
world records broken against the year.
So you can see like in 1969, there was
something like 15 world records broken.
In 1970, there was 18 world records
broken.
In 2009, it went up pretty high.
It's somewhere closer, you know, to the
mid 40s.
I added a smoothing line to this plot to
kind of help us see the pattern in
the dots, so what you'll notice right away
is this is not a linear relationship.
The year and
the number of world records broken does
not have a linear relationship.
It has more of a quadratic relationship.
So something's happening where.
You know, back in the 1970s, there were a
lot of world records being broken, and
then there was a drop-off in that and it
kind of plateaued to a,
to a bottom here in the 1990s.
But then, probably due to new technology
in the 2000s,
it starts to rapidly rise again.
So we end up with a quadratic function.
Now, this graph isn't quite right, doesn't
quite match our model because, remember,
I told you that the outcome for a Poisson
regression is actually the long count.
So technically we should model.
We should graph the year, of the calendar
year against the Log Counts.
The pattern we see is actually pretty
similar.
It's still definitely a quadratic.
So what does that tell us?
That tells us that when we go to fit our
Poisson regression model,
we're not going to want to simply throw in
our continuous predictor of
Year as a linear variable.
We need to put it in as a quadratic, as a
squared term.
So I'm going to start by writing the
following Poisson regression model.
Again, the outcome is the log count, it's
going to have an intercept, and
then I'm going to have a beta for year and
a beta for year squared.
And whenever we're putting a squared term
in
we also want to include the, the linear
term.
Term.
So I'm going to run that model first in my
in my computer, but
I want to now tell you what the likelihood
function behind this
model is actually going to look like just
to give you again,
a deeper understanding of what's actually
going on behind the scenes here.
So let me now kind of write out the
likelihood function that
we're going to be using.
We're assuming we're on a Poisson
distribution, and
therefore our likelihood function is going
to contain Poisson probabilities.
So what is it actually going to look like?
Here is our likelihood function.
Remember, the likelihood function is just
the probability of our data as
a function of our unknowns.
The unknowns that we want to estimate.
In this case, are a beta for year, a beta
for year squared, and an intercept, so
we have three unknowns we're trying to
estimate.
All right, so let me just take a
particular year.
Every year, every observation, the
observations are years here,
is going to get one term in the likelihood
function.
So let me take the year 1969, for example.
In 1969, there were 15 world records
broken.
Okay?
So, what are we going to put in the
likelihood term?
That's what we saw.
That's what our data saved at.
And that year, there were fif, fifteen
world records broken.
So, our likelihood function is going to
look like the following.
It's going to be a pruson probability.
So, what's the probability?
That we got exactly 15 world records
broken in that year.
Okay, so, first of all, I showed you that
the Poisson probability function is
going to look like the following.
That is the probability of breaking
exactly 15 records in that year.
Now, it's a function of some unknowns.
Okay?
So, it's a function of this mean count.
Well, what's the mean count going to be?
The mean count, we can break this down a
little bit.
There's several pieces to the mean count.
The mean count, remember we're modeling
the, the Poisson regression
model as the log count, is equal to alpha
plus beta year plus beta year squared.
Well, the, expected value or
the mean that's going to go in here, is
going to depend on the year.
So, this is the log count, when, once we
solve for the betas, for
year in your [INAUDIBLE] for the alpha
there, we would get the log count.
We would then plug in the year 1969, and
we would get the log count.
We don't want the log count, because what
this mean is actually in counts and
not in log counts, so we're actually
going to exponentiate.
So what's actually going to go in for
the mean here is right from the Poisson
regression model.
In this case, it's going to be E raised to
alpha plus beta year times 1969.
Plus beta year squared, times 1969
squared.
This will actually be 1969 squared.
And then the same thing will be plugged in
here for the mu.
Now when I was actually fitting this
model,
I realized it would be simpler to not put
in the actual year.
But to put in the year since 1969.
So since we're talking about 1969, I'll
just plug in a zero for those.
We would then plug in the same thing over
here for the mean.
So it's going to be E raised to alpha, and
then since these go to zero,
if I'm doing the year since 1969, it would
be just E raised to alpha.
That raised to the 15th, E raised to
negative this, this whole term for, for
the mean here.
Expected value here this comes out of the
regression model, divided by
15th factorial, luckily you're never
going to have to do this yourself by hand.
But just to illustrate what's going on, so
did, nine,
if I were look at the year 1970, there
were 18 world records broken in 1970.
So when I put the term in the likelihood.
For 1970, it's going to look very similar
except I had
18 world records actually broken so I'm
putting in the probability of having 18.
The mean now again is a function of these
alphas and
the betas of the actual year for this one,
I'm going to give it a value of one.
Because it's one year past 1969.
So it will look like that.
That's my mean that's going to be raised
to the eighteenth.
And then e raised to negative of the mean,
which again is just this e alpha plus
beta plus beta because of, 1970 is only
one year past 1969.
Now that looks awful because you have all
these e's floating around, but just keep
in mind that this component right here is
what comes out of the regression model.
It's a term that looks similar to
something that comes out of the logistic
regression model, that is the mean that
gets plugged into likelihood function.
It's a function of the alphas and betas,
and the individual, you know years, that
have the number 1970, 1969, and any other
predictors we want to put in the model.
We can then do this for every year, every,
all of our 41 observations.
And then we can use that to solve for
Alpha and Beta, you will never have to do
this by hand, but I just want you to have
a sense of what's going in the likelihood
function; it's Poisson Probabilities.
Okay so now I let my computer do all of
the math there for
me, and I actually ran my Poisson
regression model and
here's what I [UNKNOWN] out when I have
year and year squared in the model.
Just to note again, I did the years since
1969.
So 1969 will get a value of zero, 1970
gets the value of one,
1971 gets a value of two, it's just
slightly easier so that we don't blow up,
you know, 1969 squared is going to be a
huge number.
So this keeps it things, the numbers
manageable.
So what do I get here?
So first of all, I get a term for year,
and the, and the term for year squared.
The estimate for year is negative, the
estimate for year squared is positive.
That's going to define the quadratic
function.
Notice that both of those are highly
significant.
Saying that there is indeed a quadratic
relationship with year in the log counts.
The intercept here represents the log
counts in the year,
1969 since I've set years as the year
since 1969.
So year is zero when we're at 1967.
Now I can take this model and I can plot
the expected values for each year.
I can put that in a plot so this is what I
got.
So this is what I, the model that I just
fit.
I am showing you the predictive log counts
and the Y axis and the year on the X axis.
This is what my model predicts that we are
following a quadratic function.
Remember what the picture of the data
looked like earlier,
that seems like a pretty reasonable fit
given the scatterplot that we saw earlier.
But that's actually the model that we fit.
We fit it a quadratic co,
connecting year with the log counts of the
world records broken.
Now, I just want to pause for a minute and
again I mentioned that with this data set,
it wouldn't be terribly unreasonable to,
if you didn't think of doing it as count.
To think of it as a continuous outcome.
And transform that outcome with a log, and
then run some kind of linear regression.
I'll just show you that you get kind of
similar results.
This is not optimal.
The linear regression model is not optimal
with these data.
But, you get pretty similar results.
So, what I, what I did here is I just took
my counts, like my 18, 15, 16.
Took a log of those, and then ran a linear
regression.
It's still the same idea.
I have still a quadratic relationship.
The beta coefficients look pretty similar
to what I got from the,
Poisson regression, although not
identical.
And the P values are still highly
significant although, you know,
you can see that it's, it's somewhat
different, but it's in the same ballpark.
So not terribly unreasonable to run a
linear regression here.
However that the linear regression is
really not optimal.
And actually in a future module I'm
going to tell you that
the Poisson regression here is not optimal
either.
And that in fact what you should do with
these data is
a negative binomial regression, but that's
getting ahead of ourselves.
But just to show you that you kind of get
similar results here if you did this
as a linear regression.
Just for fun I want to what, put one more
predictor into the model, this is
a really cool question about swimming
world records; I think it's kind of fun.
So 1 of the other data point] that this
person have collected was the number of
new technologies introduced in each year.
So in some years there might, I think, in
the, I don't,
exactly know how those are Counted, but
we'll assume that she did a good
job in that, you know this represents a
number of new types of swimsuits, or
new types of goggles or whatever you know,
swimmers, technology swimmers use.
And we're going to, I've plotted the
number of new technologies introduced per
year, you can see it's pretty low, one,
two, three, four,
five is the range, against the long counts
again of the world records.
Because that's truly what we're modeling.
In the Poisson Regression is the log
count.
You can see that we're again looking for
kind of a straight line.
You can see that it's not unreasonable
prob,
unreasonable probably to model this as a
straight line.
There does look to be some increase in the
number of log world records,
as you go up in the number of technologies
introduced.
So I'm going to put this in as a linear
term in the model.
So I went ahead and did this new model.
I will have years and years squares and
then, squared, and then I added the number
of new technologies as another predictor
to my model.
I ran a Poisson regression,
which again means that in the likelihoods
I'm dealing with Poisson probabilities.
And here's what I get out when I run that
model.
So, what you'll notice is that year and
year squared are still statistically
significant.
I now have a new term for New Tech, the
number of new technologies introduced.
The data here .15, it's high significant.
It's positive which tells us as more
technologies are introduced,
we do seem to have an increase in the
number of world records.
Now there's a.
Interpretation.
This beta coefficient can be interpreted
as a kind of relative risk, and
I want to show that to you now.
It was hard to do with years, because we
had that year squared term in, but
now we just have a linear term here, so
I can show you a direct interpretation as
a relative risk, and
the relative risk type that we get out of
a Poisson regression.
Is actually technically an incident rate
ratio because with Poisson regression,
we're talking about the rate at which
events occur.
So this turns out to have an
interpretation as
the incidence rate ratio.
So if I take this beta coefficient, the
0.149 that I got for
the number of new technologies out.
15, 1549, and I
exponentiate that, that gives me the
incident rates ratio.
And in that, this case that turns out to
be an incident rate ratio of 1.16 676.
So just exponentiating those beta
coefficients gives me
an incidence rate ratio.
At the reason is let me just kind of walk
you through the logic here.
So we're trying to get some kind of rate
ratio.
The expected number of counts, we get that
from the model by exponentiating.
So, the expected number of calves for a
given year and
I'm just going to plug in, I'm just
going to represent this as beta year,
the year plus beta year squared, year
squared.
And then, I'm going to actually put in the
value that we found for
the beta for technology.
And, I want to say well what's the
increase in the expected
number of world records if I have one
additional technology.
So imagine I have technology plus 1 here.
And now I want to control for year.
So remember, this is,
what I've now put in the numerator is the
expected number of world records for
a given year and a given number of
technologies, based on my fitted model.
In the denominator, I want to compare that
to the same year, controlling for
year, but in the same year, having one
technology less.
So I would represent that, I'm not even
actually filling in values for the betas
for year or year, because we're going to
cancel those out, as we've done before.
But I want to compare technology plus 1 to
just technology.
In other words, one more technology to one
less technology.
So this could be the difference of going
from zero technologies to one more
introduced, or one technology to two
introduced, etc.
You can tell a lot of things are going to
cancel.
Intercepts cancel.
All the stuff about years cancels out, so
all we're left with here is, e raised to
0.149.
The technology and technology will cancel
out and
we're left with 1.1549 in the numerator.
Greater.
So we can interpret this as for every one
unit increase in technology,
this is the increase in the rate of world
records per year.
So we call that an incidence rate ratio
and again that turns out to be 1.1676.
We could also use the standard error to
calculate confidence intervals.
The confidence interval here turns out to
be 1.085 to 1.256, so for every new
technology introduced in a year, we have a
16% increase in the rate of world records.
So it has, the Poisson regression has a
nice, easy interpretation.
These are not odds ratios, these are
actually rate ratios, so that's great,
because we don't have to worry about the
confusion.
With odds ratios being misleading.
We're actually getting out rate ratios
here.
Now one more thing just for fun.
As I was playing around with these data,
I also tried an interaction between the
new technol, the number of
new technologies and the year to see if
there was an interaction there.
And in fact, there did turn out to be a
highly significant interaction there.
The interaction term has a positive beta
coefficient.
I won't make you work out the rate ratios
based on interaction terms like I
did with odds ratios, although you could
do it.
But you can just look at the sign here.
It's positive, so what that's telling you
is that
new technologies introduced in later years
had a bigger effect.
Then new technologies introduced in
earlier years.
So back in the 1970s and 80s, the new
technologies weren't having as much of
an effect on the number of world records.
recently, all those new technologies with
the great new swimsuits and
things have had a bigger impact on world
records.
So there's actually a year times new
technology interaction here as well
which is kind of cool.
Now, I'm going to do a little bit more
with this data set in an upcoming module
and show you that actually we probably do
better with this data set
applying a slightly different version of
[UNKNOWN] regression something called.
A negative binomial regression.
And I'll tell you about that in an
upcoming module.
[BLANK_AUDIO]