Now I'm going to return to my two
hypothetical eye trial examples.
These are nice, some nice,
simple data that I can use to illustrate
how GE modeling works.
So remember, the first trial, every
patient,
there were 50 patients with bilateral eye
disease.
Every patient received both the drug in
one eye and the placebo in the other eye.
The outcome was a binary outcome of
improvement, yes or no.
In the second hypothetical trial, it was
basically the same except,
every person got the drug in both eyes, or
the placebo in both eyes.
So they only got one or the other.
Now, if we're talking about the first
example, the within person example where
we're having different things happening
within a person.
I can, we first need to look at what is
the correlation between you know,
within eyes in a person.
So, what is the left and right eye in a
person are they correlated?
And in fact, in these made up data.
Of course, they're made up, so I made sure
they were.
They were in fact correlated.
So there was a correlation of about 0.36
for within eye, you know, within a person.
A person who improves in one eye is more
likely to improve in the other eye.
That's what that means.
Now the as I said, for
GEE models, you have to start by choosing
a correlation structure.
So it's really easy here because the
correlation matrix there's only one
correlation coefficient.
I made a really simple example right.
So there's only one correlation
coefficient.
So we can just choose the exchangeable
correlation which is actually going to
be the same as the unstructured here
because there's only a single correlation.
There's only one choice here, which is
exchangeable and
that's the same as structured.
So I, I'll get, for a lot of cases, we're
just talking about cluster data.
Even if there is more than one correlation
coefficient,
oftentimes we're still just picking the
exchangeable.
That is sort of the most commonly used.
You might choose unstructured if you, you
know,
if there aren't too many correlation
coefficients to estimate.
Now interestingly, it turns out that in
this example, we could also,
I'm going to show you, we could also
choose the independent structure.
That way, as you know, we could pretend we
had that the correlation between the eyes
was actually zero.
And you might say, well how, how can that
be.
Because we, the whole point of GEE is to
correct for non-independence.
But it turns out that GEE modeling relies
on something called,
you can calculate something called robust
standard errors.
And those standard errors, when you
calculate those they're fairly.
Robust against the misspecification of
correlation.
In fact, if you put independents in here
but choose the robust standard errors,
you're still going to get clues to the
right answer.
So of course, you, in this case, want to
choose the exchangeable.
But if you got it wrong and choose the
independence, which is really wrong,
you still do well as long as you report
the robust standard error.
I'll, I'll talk more about that in a bit.
So first of all, I just applied regular,
all this logistic regression to these
data, ignoring the correlation.
This is the incorrect analysis.
So when I do that, what you'll notice is
that I get a P-value of 0.07 that's
too high, because the correct analysis
here is, is comparing within subjects.
And so ignoring the correlation makes are
P value too high.
Our odds ratio is about two.
We have an intercept because this is
ordinary logistic regression.
Recall that then also fit these data with
conditional logistic regression which is
a perfectly valid to set these data if you
just want to do with or
within person to person comparison.
The odds ratio is a little higher here.
But the P value went down because we, when
we analyze these data,
correctly accounting for correlation, the
P value becomes smaller.
Conditional Logistic Regression is a
possible choice here.
For this situation, I probably prefer to
use
the GEE model rather than Conditional
Logistic regression, but
you'll see that we get very similar
answers.
Again the correlation structure here is
just exchangeable because there's only one
correlation to estimate.
So I asked the computer to do a GEE model,
I specified
an exchangeable correlation matrix, and
here is the results that I get.
Now when we do the GEE model we are back
to getting the intercepts.
So we now do get in a unlikely with a
conditional logistic regression Where we
didn't get an intercept, with a GEE model
we will get an intercept.
We're not doing any kind of conditioned
likihood where things are cancelling.
The P value here comes out to be 0.0248.
I'll just remind you that when we analyze
the same data with McNamera's test the P
value was 0.029.
So, this is very close.
Its a little bit closer to the McNamera's
test than the conditional logistic
regression is.
Notice that the odds ratio here the 2.078
output in Sass, for
the odds ratio is a little funny, because
you have to ask specifically for this, but
this is just the odds ratio.
Notice that the odd, the odds ratio 2.078
and beta coefficient 0.7357.
If you go back to the incorrect analysis,
with regular logistic regression,
the beta, and of course the odds ration
then are identical.
So you're getting the exact same magnitude
of the effect is
only the standard errors that really gets
effected by doing GEE modeling.
So the point estimates don't change it's
just the standard errors.
So that's it, that's our GEE model.
Again, got the same beta coefficient as
with the ordinary logistic regression, so
if I didn't care about P-values and
standard errors.
I, you know, that would have been fine.
But usually I care about reporting
confidence intervals and
P-values, so I need to do the correct GEE
model.
I then ask the computer here to give me
the working correlation matrix.
So you can actually ask a computer to just
say,
well what did you come up with for that
correlation matrix at the end of the day?
So remember that when we look at the
actual correlations in this simple case.
The correlation within I's was something
like 0.3, it was close to 0.36,
it was 0.35 something.
Let me go back here and get that actual
number.
0.358 essentially.
So, that's what we actually, that's the
actual correlation.
Of course, we're doing some kind of
quasi-likelihood method here, and
it's estimating things, and it's coming
out to be pretty close.
It's right around where we'd expect, about
0.36.
So that's the working correlation matrix
we came up with.
It corrected our standard, and
therefore our P-values by the fact that we
have correlation here.
These standard errors that I reported back
here are what we call
robust standard errors in SASS.
This is the default.
You get out what are called the robust
errors.
They're also called the empirical standard
So that's the same thing as robust
standard errors,
I've been talking about robust standard
errors.
But you'll see it also as empirical
standard errors.
Those are the defaults, those are the ones
that you generally want to report.
Now, I want to just show you that there's
another type of standard error that you
can ask for.
That you have to actually ask for in SASS,
specifically, but
it's something called the model-based
standard error.
And I'll just show you that as long as we
specify,
I've specified an exchangeable correlation
matrix here, as long as we specify
the correlation structure correctly we get
about the same P value, but still 0.02.
So the model-based standard errors will be
fine if you
get the correlation structure right.
Notice beta doesn't not effected again
only the P value is.
So, I'll talk a little bit more about the
difference between these two
standard errors and
when you might want to use the model based
errors and just in just a minute here.
But I just want to point out that as long
as you're
getting the correlation structure right
they actually come out pretty,
fairly similar but I just want to show
you.
I then ran the GEE model but I specified I
wanted independent correlation structure.
Okay, that's the totally wrong correlation
structure.
Because clearly the eyes are correlated
within a person here.
But I got the robust standard errors
again, that's the default in SASS,
so here is when I ask for the independent
correlation structure.
I get basically the same P-value as when I
asked for the exchangeable.
As long as I'm using the empirical or
robust standard error, so nothing changes.
However, if I specify independent
correlation structure, but ask for
the model-based standard errors,
I'm basically going back to a regular old
logistical regression.
This is the same P-value I got out of an
ordinary logistic regression.
So, if I get the correlation structure
wrong and ask for
the model-bases standard errors, I could
be very off.
I'm essentially gone back to not
correcting for the correlation here.
but, the robust standard errors do well
even if I get the correlation structure
totally off.
So, ju, that's just something to keep in
mind.
again, there's two types of standard
errors, what we call robust or
empirical and model-based.
And in general, you're going to report the
robust standard errors.
That's generally what you report.
It's the default in SASS.
You have to specifically ask for the other
type, type of standard error.
The robust errors are great because they
are robust against the incorrect choice of
correlation structure, as we've seen.
Whereas the model-based standard errors
are very sensitive to that.
There are a few cases, however, where the
model-based standard errors are preferred.
So I'll just point those out.
If you have a situation where you have a
low number of clusters.
So you know,
this could be, like, a randomized cluster
trial where you have, you know,
you randomized five schools to one thing
and five schools to another thing.
So you'll only have ten total clusters.
There's situations where you might have a,
kind of a low number of clusters.
Then the model-based standard errors are
actually preferred.
Of course you're going to try to get the
right correlation structure, so
that in a way it doesn't matter.
So this latter situation with low number
of clusters,
you wouldn't find that usually for
something like repeated measures where
you're measuring a whole bunch of people
over time.
Usually with repeated-measures, you have
kind of a large number of subjects and
a few number of time points so they're
not, you know,
you don't have a low number of clusters.
But sometimes, we had you know,
again, something like a randomized cluster
trial, this situation could come up.
So that I'll just point out that those
model-based standard errors are there for
that kind of situation.
Now let's move to this hypothetical eye
trial two.
This is a situation where the patients
were
treated in both eyes with the same
treatment, either the drug or the placebo.
When I look at the correlation between
eyes in the same person from this
trial it's much higher.
And the reason being is that you got the
same treatment in both eyes.
So when you don't get the same treatment
in both eyes,
of course, if the treatment does anything
the correlation is going to be lower.
When we treat both eyes with the same
treatment, we're getting somewhat more
similar outcomes and so we get a little
bit of a higher correlations.
The correlation here is 0.6, which is just
quite a bit high.
Of course, these are made up data so
I just made the correlations come out high
like this.
So, that's the correlation matrix, the
observed correlation matrix for
the hypothetical trial two.
I then took those,
those data, ran them in the incorrect
ordinary logistic regression.
Remember, here we're doing between cluster
comparisons, right,
because we're comparing a person who got
treatments in both eyes, or, or
the, the eyes from the same person.
To and an, another person's eyes; who
didn't get treatment.
So we're comparing across people.
And so when we do the incorrect analysis,
we fail to account for
correlations, our P values are too small.
As we've already seen with this example,
our P value here comes out to be
significantly lower,
essentially over counting eyes The beta is
0.8, and the odds ratio is about 2.28.
So that's the incorrect analysis.
When I then run the GEE model, I'm
specifying I
want an exchangeable correlation matrix,
and I run my GEE model on the same data.
Notice I get the same data coefficient,
same odds ratio, so
that doesn't change, but my P-value goes
up.
This is no longer statistically
significant anymore.
Because now we've we've corrected for
that.
We've gotten rid of that double counting
of eyes, essentially.
So here's the, the correct P value.
I asked the computer to give me the
working correlation matrix.
Remember that the observed correlation was
about 0.66.
When it goes through this whole estimation
method,
it estimates the correlation matrix and
gets correlations of about .59 so that's
very close.
It's, it's doing you know, what we'd
expect here.
Now I also asked to get the model based
standard error just to show you,
If I correctly specify exchangeable
correlation matrix.
Which is the right structure here, you
know,
I get the same beta, I get about the same
P-value with this
model-based standard error as I get with
the robust standard errors.
However, when I incorrectly specify the
correlation structure,
I say it's independent when clearly these
are not independent.
The robust standard errors still do
perfectly.
So notice that the P-value's still 0.11.
That, that's the correct P value here.
So the robust standard errors are
empirical standard errors.
I get the right answer even if I specify
the totally wrong correlation structure.
However, the model based standard errors
take me back to just
a regular logistic regression now, and so
I get the wrong P value.
So again, there's only certain situations
where you might want to
think about the model based errors, but in
general you're going to chose the robust.
And I just want to add one last example
here just to show you again the,
the effect, the impact that this can have
upon standard errors and P values.
So hypothetical eye trial three, is the
same as hypothetical eye trial two.
But I rejiggered the data to make it so
that there's perfect correlation between
eyes.
So in a, in a single person who got
treatment Both eyes improve or
both eyes don't improve.
And the same with the person who got
placebo.
So I made it you know, a mock dataset
where the correlation is perfect.
So here's the observed correlation matrix.
There's perfect correlation between the
eyes.
I just want to show you that the bigger
the correlation the more impact it's going
to have if you fail to account for it.
So, when I did ordinary logistic
regression,
I'm still getting this overly optimistic P
value of about 0.04.
When I then run the correct GEE model now,
when I have this much correlation.
Same outcomes, same number of eyes
improved, in each group.
But more correlation between eyes than the
P-value,
the correct P-value was even smaller.
Because I'm totally double counting,
right.
If everybody always improves, both of
their eyes always improve, or
both of their eyes always don't improve,
then I'm completely double counting when I
count two eyes from the same person.
There's no longer any additional
information from the second eye.
So there's even more of an impact on my
p-values from over counting here.
The true P-value is even, is even worse
here.
So just to kind of bring home the idea
that it's very important to
account for correlation.
The bigger the correlations, of course,
the more impact they're going to have on
your standard errors and your P-values.
>> [BLANK_AUDIO]