[BLANK_AUDIO]
Welcome to HRP 262.
This is the third and
final course in the three quarter
biostatistics sequence that I teach.
This quarter should be a lot of fun,
we're going to be dealing with
longitudinal data,
which is when you have data measured over
time.
So just to give you a brief overview of
the topics that we'll be
covering in HRP 262.
The first part of the course, we're
going to talk about survival analysis,
this is when you have time-to-event
outcomes.
We'll go over Kaplan Meier methods, which
may be a review for some of you.
I'll talk briefly about parametric
survival models, and
then we'll spend quite a bit of time on
Cox Regression,
which is the most commonly used regression
method for survival data.
The second part of the course is going to
focus on repeated measures data.
This is when you measure people at
multiple time points.
You had, maybe have measured their
predictors multiple times, and
you may have measured their outcomes
multiple times.
I will cover, I will, I will, I will do a
brief of linear regression and ANOVA just
to make sure we're all on the same page,
before we jump into repeated measures.
With repeated measures data, it's going to
be extremely important to visualize, and
graph everything to get a sense of what's
going on in the data.
The repeated measures part, the time part,
does add some complexity.
And graphing is going to be even more
important for
sorting through some of that complexity.
So we'll talk about ways to graph a data
in different data structures.
The test that we are going to cover for
analyzing repeated measures data if we are
just wanting to compare groups and
not adjust for anything, we can use
repeated measures ANOVA.
And if we want to some kind of regression,
the two regression techniques I'll be
talking about, are generalized estimating
equations and mixed model.
Just to kind of show you where all of
these topics fit in our kind of
big chart of statistical tests.
So this chart is showing you for different
outcome variables whether or
not you have independent or correlated
observations.
All of that helps you to decide which
statistical test to choose.
A lot of these tests we covered in the
biostatistic sequence thus far.
So what we're going to hit this term,
again we
are going to hit time-to-event outcomes
which we haven't talked much about so far.
So that's why I want to include
Kaplan-Meier statistics,
a little bit of parametric regression, and
a lot on Cox regression.
When we turn to the section on repeated
measures data.
If we have continuous outcomes, we are
going to dealing with
repeated measure ANOVA, mixed models and
GE modelling.
We'll also talk a little bit of a, the
situation where we have binary or
categorical data or even count data where
we might use GE modelling.
Just a little preview to what we
are going to be talking about starting
this week.
Survival analysis.
So this curve here shows a very early
example of survival analysis.
It's way back from 1669, so somebody, a
mathematician, drew a curve of longevity.
And it's a really interesting curve to
look at because you'll see very
quickly that if we were in 1669,
a lot of us wouldn't still be alive, at
this point in our lives.
So you can see that the X axis here is
ages and what were looking
at here at the Y axis, is survival, so
this is the percent surviving.
And this is generally how we're going to
draw survival curves.
So by about age six, there was only about
64 out of 100 people still surviving,
that means about a third of people in 1869
would die before the age of six.
It's not so good when you look along here
at that age 16.
There's only about 40%, 40 out 100 people
surviving.
You go to age 20, it's only about a third
of us left.
Age 26, there's only about a quarter of
people left.
By age 36, five-sixths of the people had
died, and
only one sixth of the people were going to
live past the age of 36 back then.
So unfortunately, that means most of us,
if we were living in 1669,
wouldn't still be around.
And then you can see that there's you know
a tail end here, a couple of people live
our to 76 or 86, but longevity curves have
obviously changed a great
deal in just a couple of hundred years
which I find really fascinating.
And that's a tribute to modern medicine
that now most people are going to
survive much much longer than this.
But this is an example of our survival
curve.
And that's what we're going to dealing
with this week, is just how to draw and
interpret and understand survival curves.
[BLANK_AUDIO]