In this next module, I'm going to show you
how to evaluate confounding in
the framework of regression analysis.
I'm also going to tell you a little bit
about residual confounding.
So first of all,
it's important to understand that when we
evaluate confounding within regression
models, we need to focus on the effect
sizes, the betas, and not on the p-values.
You almost want to exclusively focus on
those effect sizes.
When we talk about interaction, for
interaction we're actually going to focus
on p-values.
But for confounding, the effect sizes are
what matter.
And here's the rule of thumb.
It's a rule of thumb, so it's not you
know, it's not set in stone.
But a general good rule of thumb is that
you would identify a variable as
a confounder if it changed the beta, the
effect size relating the predictor and
the outcome, the coefficient, by more than
10%.
So if you have a model, where there's, you
do the,
there's a beta for the predictor in the
model.
And then you add the confounder to the
And the beta for the predictor changes by
more than 10% when you add the confounder,
that would be considered, that then this
would be considered a confounder.
If adding the confounder doesn't really
affect the beta for
the predictor, then this third variable
would not be considered a confounder.
Now just know that this rule of thumb
doesn't really work very well if
you're talking about betas close to 0.
So if the beta between the predictor and
the outcome is already close to
0 it's very easy to change by 10% if
you're already close to 0.
So if you're at 0.01, 10% of 0.01 is very
small.
So this really works for
talking about things that have a beta
that's not the null value.
When you get to betas close to 0,
you're going to have to use your judgment
a little bit.
It's not, the 10% rule is not going to
really work there.
The example that I'm going to use to start
with here is this example of
gender bias in admissions at Berkeley.
So this example was from some data, this
was
collected in the early 1970s at Berkeley
and this was looking at whether or
not there was bias against females in
graduate school admissions.
And somebody, just looking at the crude
data overall,
concluded that there was indeed a bias
against women.
And here are just the data, presented in a
two by two table.
Fewer women were applying than men but
women were also getting denied admissions
at a higher rate.
If you calculate the risk ratio, women
were 25% more likely to
be denied admissions to Berkeley Graduate
School than men.
And that was indeed statistically
significant.
However, that's the crude data, but
there is an important confounder lurking
in the background here.
So let's start by just running the model
where we put
gender into the logistic regression model
as the only predictor.
So here is the model with only age in the
model.
So if we just say, does gender predict
whether or not you're going to
be rejected from Berkeley Graduate School,
indeed you can see that indeed,
there's a very strong relationship between
your gender and being rejected.
And the p-value is very strong here.
We have a very positive association gender
here.
1 is equal to female, I should clarify.
So a positive relationship means that
women are more likely to be rejected.
The outcome here is being rejected.
The risk ratio as we saw in the last slide
was 1.25.
We're doing logistic regression.
So we get out an odds ratio, not a risk
ratio.
So the odds ratio comes out to be 1.84.
Of course,
that's the increase in your odds of your
being rejected, not your risk.
But anyway, with nothing else in the
model,
age looks very predictive, but there's a
confounder here.
So the confounder here is that, especially
back in the 1970's, women and
men applied to very different departments.
So women, it turned out, were applying To
departments that were very hard
to get into in high numbers, whereas men
tended to apply to departments that for
whatever reason were easier to get into.
If you looked within a particular
department, the admissions rates for
men and women are actually very similar.
It's just that there's a confounder here,
women are applying to things,
to departments that happen to be harder to
get into.
Men are finding easier ones to get into.
So what we're going to do is,
we're going to adjust for program in our
logistic regression model.
Program or department.
And the, the programs are labeled as A, B,
C, D, E, and F.
There were six programs in the data set,
six programs were represented, essentially
departments.
This is a categorical variable, so there's
program A, B, C, D, E, and F.
How do we represent categorical predictors
in regression?
We're going to have to dummy code them, so
that's what's represented here.
There are, there is six categories, six
programs.
Then we're going to get five betas in the
model.
Why five betas?
Because the reference group is going to be
absorbed into the intercept.
So the reference group here turned out to
be program F.
That just happens to be because the
default in my the computer program I
was using, SAS, the default is to use the
alphabetically last
value as the reference group.
Of course I could change that,
but it's kind of arbitrary which one I
pick to be the reference group here.
So come, this is going to tell me that
indeed there
is a strong effect for program.
These p-values represent the comparison
between these individual programs with
program f, but certainly at least compared
to program f,
these other programs all have a very
strong difference from program f.
There seems to be an important effect here
of program.
But here's what we want to focus on in the
cost of adjusting for confounding.
So notice what happened to the estimate
from, for gender.
The estimate for gender, the beta for
gender was about .60,
maybe .61 before we adjusted for program.
After we adjust for program,
that beta coefficient actually becomes
slightly negative, it goes down to 0.099.
That is clearly more than a 10% change.
So program would absolutely be a
confounder in this context, and
it, clearly we need to keep program in the
model, because when we adjust for program,
it completely changes the relationship
between gender and
admissions to graduate school at Berkeley.
So the, again our general rule of thumb
for confounding is,
if we change the beta by more than 10%,
this, this clearly does that, then we're
going to consider it a confounder.
So program is a confounder in this
context.
Now, I'm going to go one step further
here.
It also happens to be that program is not
only a confounder, but
it's also a effect modifier.
So it happens to be in this data set that,
program, you can have variables that are
both confounders and effect modifiers.
In fact, program is also an effect
modifier, and
I just want to show you that here.
We're going to talk about interactions
very soon.
So I want to just kind of set up that
idea.
How would I test for an interaction
between gender and program?
Well, you can see the model is getting
rather complex, but
all we have to do to test for interaction
is to multiply gender times program.
That's how we test for interaction.
That's called an interacting variable.
Now, because there are five programs,
well,
there's six programs and five programs
represented as betas in the model.
What we end up with is that, when we add
an interaction term here,
because we are interacting with a
categorical variable,
we actually end up with five betas for
interaction.
So now we've got five betas for the main
effect for program, and
five betas for interaction.
So what you can see here is that, in fact,
some of the interaction terms,
specifically term, the, the interaction
between gender and
program A, that one came out to be
statistically significant.
So it turns out that, in this case,
that program A actually is more likely to
admit women than they are to admit men.
So the other programs were all pretty
even, but
program A in particular had a higher admit
rate for, for women.
So we have some interaction going on here.
So I just want to point out that you can
also have a,
something that's both a confounder and an
interaction, an interacting variable.
And I want to show you how you might want
to use the likelihood ratio test here
when talking in particular about the
interaction between gender and program.
You might just want to report this p-value
and
say, hey, program A is different from the
rest.
But sometimes we also like to just report
an overall p-value for
the interaction between gender and
program and not get into the fine level of
detail of individual categories.
So sometimes with a categorical variable,
we want to just report what's called a p
for interaction, which is just to say,
overall,
is there any interaction between gender
and the categorical variable of program.
And this is where we can use a likelihood
ratio test,
which we've talked about already.
This is a good use of the likelihood ratio
test.
If you wanted overall p for interaction,
what you can do is compare a model that
contains the interactions between gender
and
program to a model that doesn't have those
interactions.
And, that you can compare with the
likelihood ratio test,
because it's actually a group of betas,
that you have to compare it once.
So I ran the model with the interaction
term, that's the model I just showed you,
my negative 2 log likelihood here turned
out to be 4856.
When I then take the interaction term out
and I run the model
without the interaction, my likelihood, my
negative 2 log likelihood goes up.
Remember, this is the reduced model.
And this is the full model.
The reduced model will have a smaller
likelihood, but
therefore a bigger negative 2 log
likelihood, and
the full model will have a smaller value
for negative 2 log likelihood.
Remember that if we wanted to say whether
or not adding that interaction term,
which comprises five variables, whether or
not that
adds anything significantly to the model,
we can do that by using a chi square.
This is a chi square with five degrees of
freedom,
because we have five interaction terms in
the model.
It's a six level categorical variable, we
end up with five terms in the model.
So we have a chi square with five degrees
of freedom, the negative 2
log likelihood for the reduced model is
this, for the full model is this.
We just subtract those,
we get that we have a chi square with five
degrees of freedom with a value of 20.
We can then look to see whether or not
that comes out to be significant.
Indeed, I'll show you in a minute where
got this from.
But the p-value here comes out to be
significant.
So the expected value here is 5, and
the p value does indeed come out to be
significant.
So that's telling us that the p value for
interaction overall,
adding the interacting term to our model
improves our model.
So, in case you don't want to get into the
fine level of details of which particular
interacting terms came out significant
when you have a categorical variable,
this is a way to just report an overall p
for
interaction for that entire categorical
variable.
Just as a quick reminder, to get the, the
p-values that go with a chi square test,
you can plug in to one of these online
calculators.
I did that here.
The computer told me that my p-value here
is 0.0013.
I did have to do this legwork on my own.
I actually had to run the model in my
computer program, get out the negative 2
log likelihood for one model, and then run
the model with or the interaction term,
get the negative 2 log likelihoods head
out for that, and then I had to
subtract those negative 2 log likelihoods
myself, and go and get the p-value myself.
So sometimes you actually have to do that
legwork by hand, it's not automatically
built into your computer package to do the
comparison of a reduced and full model.
The automatic one that the computer
package will give you is
the intercept-only model compared with a
full model.
This is comparing something slightly
different, so
again, I had to do that legwork on my own.
'Kay, just want to give you a second
example of confounding here just to
throw out another example, so this was
from a study, well,
that was looking at whether or not
maternal smoking was going to
change your risk of having a baby with
Down's Syndrome.
This was the American Journal of
Epidemiology a number of years ago, but
I really like this example, because it's
going to also illustrate the concept of
residual confounding, which we'll get to
in a minute.
But the crude odds ratio here, so when you
just look at,
the outcome here is Down Syndrome, the
baby has Down Syndrome or not.
The predictor here is whether or not the
mother smoked during pregnancy.
And you just look at the crude odds ratio,
It indeed comes out to be significant.
This confidence interval does not
correspond.
It's actually significant in the
protective direction.
So it looks like, if you don't adjust for
any confounders,
that maternal smoking reduces your risk of
getting Down Syndrome.
Now, it's very hard to come up with the
biological story here that that
could somehow be causal.
We know that in general, smoking tends to
cause DNA damage.
DNA damage would relate to Down syndrome.
Perhaps you could come up with a causal
story here,
but it's more likely that this is due to
confounding, and indeed it was.
So that's the crude odds ratio.
But then, think about potential
confounders here.
The big confounder here, the most
important one, turns out to be age.
And that's I like this paper, because they
did a lot of nice graphics, and
that's well pictured here.
So here it's showing you, on the left hand
figure, this is showing you
the relationship between maternal age and
the rates of Down syndrome.
So as you all probably know, as maternal
age goes up, especially as you
get to 40 and above, there's a really big
increase in the risk of Down syndrome.
So you can see that there's a strong
relationship clearly between age
and Down syndrome.
You turn over to age and smoking though,
the predictor here,
age is also related to the predictor, and
it's a pretty strong relationship, so
younger women smoke much more, are much
more likely to smoke than older women.
So as you get older you're also more,
you're like, more likely to have
a baby with Down syndrome, but you're also
less likely to smoke.
Hence, we end up with a spurious
association between maternal smoking and
Down syndrome.
So, what the authors did here was then to
adjust for various things.
So here they're adjusting for various
things.
I'm just going to focus for
the moment on the most adjusted model,
that's the one at the end.
So when they adjusted for everything they
needed to adjust for, the most
important one being age, the crude odds,
the odds ratio now is exactly 1.0.
So there is no association between
maternal smoking and
Down syndrome once you've accounted for
the confounders here.
And you can see that we started with an
odds ratio of 0.8.
We have changed clearly by more than 10%.
We now are at an odds ratio of 1.0.
And again, I pay attention only to the
effect size and
not to the statistical significance here.
I usually like to apply that 10% rule to
the betas rather then the odds ratio.
So if you wanted to, you could covert the
ln of 0.8 here.
And then, of course, ln of 1 would be 0,
and you could compare whatever this
value turns out to be to 0] rather then
comparing the odds ratios.
But clearly we have a major change in the
effect size here.
So that's how we evaluate confounding in
the context of regression.