In this next module I'm going to tell you
about the mathematical connection between
the Mantel-Haenszel tests.
Which we learned about this week.
And McNemar's test which we talked about
last week.
These two different methods are going to
come at the same problem from two
completely different approaches, and yet
converge on exactly the same mathematical
answer.
Which I think is just really cool and
will also give you some insight into both
methods.
I'm going to start with an example that we
talked about last week,
when we talked about McNemar's test.
So, this was a particular example where we
had paired data.
For each case, a control was matched to
the case, based on age and gender.
So, we have case control pairs, and we
needed to account for
that correlation in those case control
pairs.
The question here was whether or not,
having a heart attack.
The cases here had all had a heart attack.
Whether or not that was related to having
a history of diabetes.
So remember that we had to present this as
paired data.
So what we did was we presented it as 144
pairs rather than 288 individuals.
And then we apply what's called McNemar's
test that was just a chi-square test with
one degree of freedom.
And it had a simple form which was just to
do b minus c squared over b plus c.
And when we applied that here,
it turned out to be 37 minus 16 squared
divided by 53, and that turned
out to be highly statistically significant
of chi-square value of about 8.3.
So that was how we adjusted for
the correlation he took into account the
correlation using McNemar's test.
Now, I want to approach this particular
problem from
a completely different, perspective.
So what if, instead of counting for the
pairing that way.
What if we, instead, envisioned each pair
as its own age gender stratum.
So remember, we've matched here on age and
gender.
So in a way,
you could view each pair as just having
its own unique age-gender combination.
And you could think of it almost as a
confounder,
which pair you're in could be thought of
as a confounder in this problem.
It's a really interesting way to think of
it,
because of course, if we're going to
stratify on pair.
We're going to end up with some very small
two by two tables.
But that's okay.
I'm going to show you that we can still do
this kind of stratification and
calculate mantle hansel statistics.
So let me just explain exactly what I
mean, here.
So, what we're going to do for example, is
take the cell As.
These were the situations, cell A was the
situation where we had pairs where,
both, the case and the control had a
history of diabetes.
What if you represented that as its own
two by two table,
it's own stratum, in this analysis?
Again, kind of thinking of which pair
you're in as being the confounder here,
stratifying on which pair you're in.
It makes a very funny two by two table,
because we only have,
our total here is only two people, because
it's a pair.
But we can do this.
And so just bear with me.
It's going to all make sense in a bit.
So in this case, how do we represent.
We're now going back to representing the
people as individuals.
So the two represents two individuals
rather than two pairs now.
So both the case and the control had a
history of diabetes.
So, both of them are going to get a one
for diabetes, and both of
them are going to get, and there's nobody
here who had, who didn't have diabetes.
So, we get zeroes in the other two cells.
Very simple two by two table, but we can
draw that out.
All of the cell A's, all of the pairs
where both the case and
the control had diabetes, are going to
have the exact same two by two table.
It's going to look like that.
And then, we can go ahead and do this
logic.
Across all the different types of pairs.
We only have four unique types of pairs
here.
So, we have, again, nine pairs where both
the case and the control had diabetes.
That can be represented in the top, the
two-by-two table you see in the top here.
What about the situation where we have
discordant pairs where it's the case
that has diabetes and the control that
doesn't?
That can be represented in the second type
of two by two table.
Right, there's again only two people in
each stratum and in this case,
the case has diabetes so we have one case
with diabetes and we have one control who
does not have diabetes and none of the
other types of people in this case.
We have 37 dischord appears in the case
that's diabetic.
So that's what those strata are going to
look like.
We get the opposite situation of
discordance,
where it's the control that has diabetes
in the case that does not.
Again, two total in that strata.
There's 16 of those strata that look like
that.
And then finally we have the situation, we
have 82 pairs where both the case and
the control do not have diabetes and
those would be represented in this two by
two table.
So we can write this out as a huge
stratified analysis with 144 different
strata, of course you don't really want to
have write this all by, out by hand, but
since a lot of the, strata look the same,
we can kind of just move them like this.
Alright, now, how are we going to apply
Mandel-Handel statistics, to these,
to this stratified analysis?
Well we're going to
apply it with the exact same formulas that
we learned this week.
So let's apply the Mantel-Haenszel methods
to those, all those different strata.
We want to know the relationship between
diabetes and heartattack, controlling for
age and gender.
The matching variable, so essentially we
are adjusting for hair here.
So we're going to apply the
Mantel-Haenszel methods to
the stratified data.
So, how does that look like?
What I'm going to start with here is I'm
going to
start by calculating the Mantel-Haenszel
summary odds ratio just because it is
slightly simpler to calculate.
So just recall, from an earlier module,
the Mantel-Haenszel Summary Odds Ratio
was just a weighted average of the odds
ratios across all the different strata.
So in this case, we're going to have 100
and k is going to be equal to 144.
You have 144 strata.
We're going to sum up a times d.
Divided by the total in each stratum,
which is going to be two in every case
here.
We're going to do that, for the numerator
and we're going to do
something similar for the denominator
except it's going to be the b times c.
So, again the total with two in each
stratum.
So, we can just do that here so let's
actually go ahead and apply this.
So, what about in the first situation?
We've got the case [INAUDIBLE] control,
both have diabetes.
So what, what's a times b in this
situation?
Well, it's going to be 1 times 0, so a
times b, ant the total here is 2.
For every, each one of those strata where
we've got concordance on diabetes.
You're going to have it a times d, is
equal to 0, and
divided by 2 is still equal to 0.
B times c, 1 times 0, is also going to be,
0, so we're going to get 0's.
So, essentially, those dis, those
concorded pairs are not going to
contribute anything to the Mantel-Haenszel
odds ratio.
We know that the concord impair should not
contribute because they're
not informative.
Alright what about this situation where we
have a discord up here with
a diabetic case, what would that look
like?
Well again where going to do a times d and
now we get 1 times 1 divided by the total
here which is 2.
So now we actually get a number a times d
divided by two here is going to be a half.
B times c because we got two zeros now is
going to be zero.
For the discord up here where it is the
control that has diabetes.
A times d is now going to be zero, but
b times c is going to be one over two, so
we get another half here.
So those discordant strata are going to
contribute to
the Mantel-Haenszel odds ratio.
Finally, though, those situations where we
have the pair both don't have diabetes,
those are both going to give us zeroes
again.
So again, the concordant pairs are not
going to contribute to
the Mantel-Haenszel odds ratio.
Now let's just calculate that
Mantel-Haenszel odds ratio.
Again, we have many, many strata here, but
they all look the same.
So we can just multiply by how frequently
each of these different strata occurs.
There was 37 discordant pairs where the
case was diabetic, and
16 where the control was diabetic.
So now we're just going to plug into the
Mantel-Haenszel odds ratio formula.
Again, we get a half everywhere where
we've got that, discordant but
cases diabetic, there were 37 of those, we
get a half in the denominator from these
pairs where we had discordance, but it was
the control who was diabetic, so
we get 37 times a half divided by 16 times
a half.
The halves cancel.
We just end up with 37 divided by 16 or b
over c.
That's the Mantel-Haenszel odds ratio.
So it works out to be exactly the same as
the McNemar odds
ratio as we saw from last week.
Now just slightly more tricky is to
actually apply the Mantel Haenszel
chi-squared statistic that you learned
about this week.
So what does that look like?
So here's the formula, first of all, that
I gave you earlier this week.
We're going to be comparing observed minus
expected for that A cell, and
then we've got this variance.
It was a little complicated to calculate
the variance.
I'll show you how to apply it here.
The expected value is like we calculate
for and MH chi-square.
So this is the formula for the Mantle
Hansel chi-square.
What are we actually testing in this
situation?
So the null hypothesis here would be that
diabetes and heart attack
are independent after we adjust for, or
control for, which pier you're in.
So we can apply that statistic here, and
again, because a lot of the strata look
the same, it's not going to be as bad as
you might anticipated.
I'm going to show you that what we come
out with is exactly equal to
the McNemar's chi-squared.
All right.
So what do the concordant pairs contribute
to the Mantel-Haenszel statistic?
Let's look at that.
So here's an example of concordant pair,
where both the case and
the control have diabetes.
If I go to calculate out the expected
value here,
the expected value is one, because the row
total is two, the column total is one.
Two times one, divided by two, there's two
total in the stratum.
Two divided by two gives you one.
We're expecting one case to have diabetes.
And indeed we observed one case having
diabetes.
So observed minus expected here equals
zero.
So again you can see that we are going to
get some zeros.
The concorded pairs are not going to
contribute to
the Mantel-Haenszel statistic.
The same with the variance.
Remember the variance is row one times
column one.
Times row 2 times column 2.
Since row 2 is equal to 0, were
multiplying in the 0,
that is going to come out to 0 as well, so
its not going to contribute.
Same way if you look at the concordant
pairs were both the case and
the control are free of diabetes we are
going to get all 0's for those numbers.
So when we add those into the
Mantel-Haenszel statistic,
they're going to contribute zero.
As they should, because they don't give us
any information about
the relationship between diabetes and
heart attack.
How about the discordant pair?
So where we have discordants we can either
have the case having diabetes so
that case is shown here.
When the case has diabetes and the control
does not, then when we do the expected
value, it's going to be row one times
column one so one times one divided by
the total in the stratum, which is two so
one times one divided by two is a half.
And, we're expecting to see about a half
of a case having diabetes.
In fact, we saw one case with diabetes, so
one minus the expected value of a half,
gives us a value of positive one half
here, for
that difference between the observed and
the expected.
The variance is going to turn out to be
one over four, 'cause every row and
every column here has a total of one.
And then, the total is two, so we're
going to do, put in the denominator,
two squared, times two minus one, which
is, to which is 2 times 2, or 4.
So we end up with that the variance,
every stratum, contributes one fourth to
the variance.
That's what's going to go in
the denominator of the Mantel-Haenszel
statistic.
If we look at the situation where we have
discordance in the other wave,
the control has diabetes and the case does
not.
The expected value, again, is going to be
a half.
But the observed minus the expected, now,
since we're focusing on cell A,
is going to B zero minus a half, or
negative one half.
So we're going to end up with a negative
in this case.
The variance is going to be exactly the
same as before, one quarter.
So now we can take all of those values,
and
plug into the Mantel–Haenszel statistic.
So again, here is the Mantel–Haenszel
statistic.
I'm now going to just kind of go through
how to calculate all this.
So, we've got a chi square with one degree
of freedom.
That is equal to, so what do we do?
Let's start with the numerator.
What do we do in the numerator?
We're going to add up the summations, that
means we're adding.
There's 144 strata.
We're going to add up all the observed,
minus expecteds, from each of the 144
strata.
We're going to do that.
First.
Well, what was the observed minus expected
for the concord in strata?
Those were all 0s.
We're going to get a whole bunch of 0s,
they won't contribute in, to anything.
Then, we're going to get, there were 37
discordant pairs, discordant strata,
where the observed minus the expected was
equal to positive one half.
There were 16 where the observe minus the
expected was equal to negative one half.
So that sum will be the total sum that
goes in the numerator.
And then after all of that we're going to
square it.
That's the, the squared part happens last.
That's the numerator of the
Mantel-Haenszel statistic here.
In the denominator we're again going to be
summary,
summing up over 144 pairs, 144 strata.
The variances.
But remember that the variances from those
concordant strata were again, all zero.
So they contribute zero.
Everywhere that there was a discordant
strata,
they, each of those strata contributed one
fourth.
So both, the discordant cells in both
directions.
So 37 plus 16.
A total of 53 contributed a fourth.
Now, what you'll notice is if you multiply
this out,
we can simplify this is a little bit.
It turns out to be,
you can say that we have in the numerator
1 half times 37 minus 16.
I just pulled out the half there.
With that is squared.
And that's going to be divided by a total
of 53 time a quarter.
But notice that if I pull the square over
here and
I square the half, and take that out.
Half squared is just a fourth, so those
two are going to cancel.
What do I end up with?
I end up with 37 minus 16 squared, divided
by 53.
Well guess what?
That is also the Macnemare statistic.
So we got, when we apply the
Mantel-Haenszel formula here,
we ended up with a, with the Macnemare's
chi square as well.
It's the exact same mathematical formula,
b minus c square, divided by b plus c.
So these turn out to be identical.
I've shown this here with specific
numbers, and now,
let's also show it more generally, using b
plus c rather than specific numbers.
For those of you who want a neat slide
where this is all written out,
I'm putting that, I'm placing that here
just in case you want to see it
written out more neatly than my
handwritting.
But now going to generalizing.
Let's generalize this whole thing.
So, now if we look at the Cochran
Mantel-Haenszel statistic and
we think about the general case.
Anywhere we have the situation of paired
data where we have discorded and
concorded pairs.
Notice what's going to happen when we plug
into the Mantel-Haenszel statistic.
Which again is a chi squared with one
degree of freedom.
We are going to be in the numerator we are
going to be adding zero for
all the concorded cells.
And then we are going to be adding
one-half, positive one-half for
all the B cells.
Remember the B situation is where it's the
case that has the diabetes
and the, control that doesn't or the case
that has the exposure and
the control that doesn't, if we're
generalizing.
For all the C cells, it's going to be
negative one half, and
then we're going to be squaring that.
In the denominator, the variances are only
occur where we have discordant cells and
that's going to be the b plus c and we're
going to,
each one of those contributes one fourth
to the variance.
So we can write this down generally.
We can show that is always the case that
the Mantel-Haenszel statistic when
applied to this particular situation will
simplify, again, these halves.
Halve squared will come out and it'll
cancel the one fourth
will simplify to B minus C square, divided
by B plus C.
Which is exactly the same as the
Mcnamara's statistics.
So mathematically, these things turn out
to be equivalent,
which is just pretty cool.
And again, I'm writing that out.
Is putting that in a neat slide for
any of you who need a little bit neater
handwriting there.