In this next module I'm going to give a
brief introduction to
the different types of study designs that
are used in medical research.
This is not a course on study design.
However, I am going to be throwing around
terms like cross-sectional study,
cohort study, randomized trial.
So it's important that you're familiar
with those terms.
It's always important to interpret the
data in the context of
the study design from which it was
collected.
So studies can be broken down into two
major types,
observational and experimental.
Observational studies are studies where
the investigator just
observes the participants.
They don't intervene in anyway.
Experimental studies the investigator
actually intervenes in some way.
The classic experimental study is the
randomized controlled trial, and
that's considered the gold standard of
study design.
And for reasons that we're going to talk
about.
But it's not always possible to do an
experimental study, or
to do a randomized trial, so much of the
medical literature that you're
going to encounter are observational
studies.
So, I'm going to just review the
different,
types of observational studies in this
module.
I'll point out to you that all of these
different study designs provide different
levels of evidence for the hypothesis
they're testing.
And they generally, the level of evidence
increases as you go down this list.
So when you're talking about descriptive
or cross-sectional studies or case-control
studies, those, as we're going to talk
about, have some potential biases.
And those are going to have a lesser level
of evidence,
than a cohort study which is next on the
list.
And a cohort study generally will have
less Of a level of evidence,
than a well done randomized controlled
trial.
So there's increasing level of evidence as
we go down this list.
The reason that observational studies
have, provide a,
a lower level of evidence for hypothesis,
the reason it's harder to
draw conclusions from them has to do with
a concept called confounding.
And we're going to spend a lot of time
talking about confounding in this course.
So I'm just going to introduce the idea of
confounding now.
So, confounding is this idea that risk
factors don't happen in isolation.
People who smoke also tend to drink and
also tend to do other risky things for
their health.
So if you're just observing participants
in a study, it's very hard to tease out
a single risk factor from among the many
risk factors that tend to go together.
So a classic of example of confounding
would be the following, if you went out in
the population and studied alcohol and
lung cancer, if you looked at drinkers and
tried to see whether or not drinking was
related to lung cancer, in fact,
you would find that people who are heavy
drinkers tend to get more lung cancer.
Those things are correlated.
That might lead you to think that alcohol
is somehow causing lung cancer.
Alcohol does, is involved in some cancers.
So that wouldn't be an unreasonable thing
to, to conclude.
However, it turns out that alcohol doesn't
biologically cause lung cancer.
What's going on here is that heavy
drinkers also tend to be heavy smokers.
And of course, we know that smoking is a
major, major cause of lung cancer.
So in this case, the apparent association
between alcohol and
lung cancer is really just due to
confounding by smoking.
I'm just going to show you this table here
because it's a really great illustration,
of how risk factors cluster in
observational studies.
So this is a study that we're going to
return to in another couple of weeks, and
we'll talk about in some, in some more
detail,
but I'm just showing you table one for the
men from this study.
And this study was looking at whether or
not, how much red meat you eat is
correlated to mortality?
And what the researchers did,
was they just asked people to report how
much red meat they're eating.
And they divided people up into quintiles
of red meat intake.
So Q one is the lowest quintile.
Q five is the highest quintile.
So if you just look at this table.
Obviously, red meat intake increases as
you go across the quintiles.
That's expected because the groups were
defined by red meat intake.
But if you kind of scroll down the table.
The ages and races aren't very different
between the groups.
But if you get down to the modifiable risk
factors for health, things like BMI.
Let's take a careful look at BMI.
So we look at BMI.
In the first quintile of red meat intake,
the lowest red meat eaters.
BMI is 25.9.
That increases as you go across the
quintiles.
26.7, 27.1, 27.6, 28.3.
So
as you become a higher red meat eater,
your BMI tends to go up.
It's not necessarily because of the red
meat eating, it's just there's something
about people who eat a lot of red meat
that tends to also make them heavier.
It's not just BMI though, let's look at
smoking.
So look at current smoking.
Current smoking also increases so
perfectly as you go up across the
quintiles of red meat intake.
So the lowest quintile has very few
current smokers.
The highest quintile has the highest
number of smokers.
So, red meat eaters also tend to be
smokers.
If you look at education, education,
higher education goes down as you go
across the quintiles.
If you look at exercise,
exercise also goes down as you look across
the quintiles.
Calories go up as you look across the
quintiles.
So basically, red meat eaters are doing
everything else wrong too.
They also tend to smoke, to be heavy,
they're not as well educated,
they don't exercise as much, etc.
So how do you isolate the effect of red
meat eating on health or mortality?
How do you isolate that one factor from
among all of
these factors that tend to cluster?
It turns out to be a really hard thing to
do.
That's the problem of confounding.
Now we do try to either avoid or control
for confounding in different ways.
So of course, one way to to deal with
confounding is just in the design phase of
the study is to do something like do a
randomized trial.
If you randomly assign people to different
interventions, then you're
ensuring that those interventions aren't
related to any other risk factors.
If you could do a study where you randomly
assigned people to eat a lot of
red meat or not Then people with different
characteristics would be equally likely to
get into the red meat eating group or, or
the low red meat eating group.
So you can isolate a factor by randomizing
on it.
They also do a few things in the design
phase of the study like matching, so
you might have a case control study, and
we'll talk about case control studies in a
minute here.
Where you have a, a case somebody, say,
who has breast cancer,
a 50-year-old smoking woman who has breast
cancer, you might go out and
find a control for that case who's also a
50-year-old woman who smokes.
So, you're trying to control for
confounding by finding people who
are similar on the, at least the most
important confounders.
Those are things you can do in the design
phase of the study.
This course isn't really about study
design.
So we are going to be talking about the
things that you can do when you
already have the data in hand.
So at the analysis phase of the study, is
there something you can to
statistically to try to tease out
confounding?
And there is.
The way we generally try to tease out
confounding is with
something called multi-variate regression.
So we use a statistical technique to try
to
isolate the effect of red meat eating,
eating.
From BMI, smoking and all of these other
risk factors that cluster.
So there are statistical ways to get at
this.
We call this statistically adjusting for
confounders.
Now, statistical adjustment is certainly
not a panacea,
people give it too much credit as we are
going to talk about in some future weeks.
So there are limitations to it.
Its not, never going to be as good as
doing a randomized trial.
But it, it is a powerful technique and
we are going to to try to use that to get
at isolating various risk factors.
So the first type of observational study
that I want to briefly mention here
is what is called a cross-sectional study.
If you look at the medical literature,
there are a lot of cross-sectional studies
in, in the literature.
That's because they're easy to do.
A cross-sectional study just looks at a,
a section of the population at a single
time point, might measure a disease,
an exposure, and try to see whether or not
those things are correlated.
But it's measuring everything at a single
time point.
It's easy to do because it's often done
with a questionnaire or a survey.
It's usually inexpensive, but it has a lot
of limitations.
So, first of all, since you're measuring
everything at the same time point,
you don't even know what came first.
You can't say for
sure that the disease didn't come before
the exposure rather than vice versa.
So it's hard to tease out temporality.
Of course, cross-sectional studies also
face confounding.
So there's a limited amount of information
you can get from cross-sectional studies,
yet they're easy to do so you're going to
see a lot of them.
An example of a cross-sectional study from
the literature is a study that was done on
a large cohort of elderly men and women in
Rotterdam.
And what they did was they took this
sample and they looked,
they wanted to know what's the prevalence
of artery blockage and
what's the prevalence of depressive
symptoms.
So they imaged their arteries.
They took a picture to try to figure out
how much blockage was there and
at the same time they also gave them a
questionnaire and
asked about their depressive symptoms.
So they're looking at everything at one
time point and
they just wondered if those two things
correlated.
Now if it turns out that those two things
do correlate, that artery blockage and
depression tend to go together in this
sample.
The researchers would not be able to
conclude that the artery blockage
caused the depression.
Right, it could easily that the
temporality could easily go in the other
direction, that is the depression could
have preceded the artery blockage.
We wouldn't know which way it went.
So, that's a major limitation of
cross-sectional studies.
Another type of observational study design
is called the case-control study.
This is a study design that's especially
used when you have a rare disease or
an outbreak situation.
So you're actually going to go out and
find people who have already developed the
disease of interest.
So this works really well.
Imagine if you were trying to just do a
cross-sectional study of something that
was a very rare outcome, or rare disease.
You wouldn't be able to find enough people
if you just randomly sampled in
the population.
So in a case control study, you go out and
actually actively seek people who already
have the disease of interest.
Then you form a case group.
And then you try to find a set of
controls,
people who don't have the disease, and you
try to figure out
what's different in the risk factors
between the cases and the controls.
So you're ask, asking retrospectively
about their risk factors and exposures.
So again, it's great for rare diseases
because a lot of times there
may not be any other study design that you
can realistically do for a rare disease.
It's also the only study design that
really works in outbreak situations.
So imagine we've got an outbreak of
salmonella food poisoning, and
you need to find quickly the, the source
of that.
The way that you're going to do that is
you're going to go ask the cases,
the people who came down with the illness,
what they have eaten recently.
And you're going to ask some controls,
people who live in the same area but
didn't get sick, what they've eaten
recently.
And that's how you'll ferret out the
source in that.
Of course, case-control studies have some
major limitations.
So it's actually very tricky to get an
appropriate control group.
Sometimes in choosing the control group,
you accidentally somehow,
systematically choose the control group
differently than the case group,
in some way that has nothing to do, with
the, the disease.
So that you, could cause a spurious
association between a,
an exposure and a disease.
There's also something called recall bias
that
you worry about with case-control studies.
You're asking people about their exposures
and
risk factors after they've already
developed a disease.
That may affect how they remember things.
So cases may remember things differently
than controls.
Of course, case control studies face
confounding, also we don't really know for
sure whether or
not the risk factor preceded the disease
or the disease preceded the risk factor.
Because again, you're measuring things
after the disease has already occurred.
But case-control studies have actually
been very important in history.
And I can point to some examples and
for example, in, the early days of the
AIDS epidemic in the early 1980s,
the early studies that were done, because
that was an outbreak situation,
were all case-control studies, and those
case-control studies were able to quickly
figure out that AIDS was transmitted by
sexual contact or blood products.
And that was before we even knew that this
was a virus.
One of the earliest case control studies
in the literature on AIDS was published in
the New England Journal of Medicine in
1982.
And they went out and found cases,
people who had, AIDS, and they found some
group of controls to compare them with.
And they found that the cases were much
more likely to have used a particular type
of drug, than the controls.
Now it turns out that that drug actually
wasn't a causative agent in AIDS, so
this is actually an example of
confounding.
But people who use this drug also tended
to be doing the other high
risk behaviors that were associated with
coming down with AIDS.
The next type of study design has some
major advantages over cross sectional and
case control studies.
It's still an observational design, but
it's called a prospective cohort study.
And what you do, is you measure people,
you measure their risk factors and
exposures.
Before they develop diseases or outcomes.
So you're measuring them when you know
that they haven't yet
got the disease of interest, then you're
following them over time.
So this allows you to know for sure that
the exposures or
the risk factors actually preceded the
outcomes or the diseases.
it also allows you, because you're
following people over time,
you can calculate some important measures
of disease frequency like what's the risk
of coming down with a given disease or
what's the rate of of that disease.
How frequently is that disease occurring
in the population?
Another advantage of cohort studies is
sometimes you'll design a cohort study to
look at one outcome, like maybe you want
to look at heart disease.
But then later on you've spent all this
time and collected all this data.
You might piggyback on a, a second
outcome, like, oh,
well, since we've, we've got all this
information on these people,
let's also look at the outcome of heart,
of breast cancer or something like that.
So, a lot of these major cohort studies
have actually ended up piggybacking on
multiple outcomes.
The drawback of prospective cohort studies
is that it's still observational, so
you're still going to deal with
confounding.
And they take a really long time.
If you're waiting for people to come down
with diseases, these things can go on for
decades, so they can be very expansive.
Also, if you're following people for a
long time you may lose a lot of
the participants and that can create some,
some trickiness in interpreting the data.
But a famous example of a cohort study is
the Framingham Heart Study.
This was started in 1948, researchers
enrolled about 5,000 residents of
Framingham Massachusetts in a certain age
bracket and they measured their health and
lifestyle factors.
So, things like their blood pressure,
their weight, how much they exercise.
They followed them for
decades after that to see who actually
came down with heart disease.
And it was from this study that we were
able to
learn things like high blood pressure
causes heart disease.
Being too heavy is bad for your heart.
Exercising is good for your heart.
All of those kind of things that we take
for
granted about heart disease now we, we
learned from this study.
And it, actually that study continues
today they're now going on to
track the kids and grandkids from that
original cohort.
Sometimes we do a little bit different
version of a cohort study called
a retrospective cohort study.
It's conceptually very similar to a
prospective cohort study.
So the exposures are still measured before
the outcomes.
However with a retrospective cohort study,
what you're doing is going out and
looking for databases, in which you
already have data on everything.
So, the data on the exposures in the data
on the outcomes has
already been collected, for some other
purpose.
So, that saves you time, because, you're
not, you're no longer waiting for
the outcomes to occur.
The outcomes have already occured, but
you're going back and
mining some data sources.
That has collected data on the exposure
and
has also collected data on the outcomes.
So, it's clearly going to be cheaper and
faster than prospective studies.
We still have the advantage that we're
going to know because of the timing of
when those databases were set up that the
exposure data were
definitely collected before the outcome
data.
We know that to be the case.
The major limitation here In addition to
the other other limitations of
a prospective cohort study is that because
the data were not collected expressly for
your study, you, you may not the,
the variables that you are interested in
may not exist in the stored data.
Or the data quality may be low.
So there's issues with data quality that
come up because you are just mining some
existing databases or stored data.
But an example of a retrospective cohort
study was a 2012 study in
the British Medical Journal.
And they were asking the question could
they relate
different types of athletics to mortality.
So they searched a sports reference
database.
And that database keeps track of lots of
famous athletes including all
the Olympians.
They were able to identify from that
database a cohort of about just under
10,000 athletes who had participated in
the Olympics between 1896 and 1936.
Somebody had put information about all
these athletes in this database.
They used a cutoff.
They wanted to look at only athletes who
were born before 1910 because they
wanted to look at mortality.
So they wanted only athletes who had had
time to die.
And the database also contained the dates
of deaths of most of these athletes.
So they were able to ferret out of this
database,
to compare the mortality rates of athletes
from different types of sports.
So they used all of this data that was
already stored, the outcomes that
has already occurred, but clearly they
knew that the participation in
the Olympics Had preceded the outcomes of,
of, the outcome of death.
A final little twist on the case-control
study that I want to mention,
because you'll see these occasionally,
is something called a nested case-control
study.
So a nested case-control study is a case
control study that
is nested within a prospective cohort
study.
So, you're already doing a prospective
cohort study,
but you've collected something, usually
some kind of biomarker like blood or DNA.
And you want to do some kind of expensive
assay on that blood or DNA.
So maybe you want to do a whole genome
sequence, or something.
Something that's costly enough that you
don't want to do it on every participant
in the cohort, because it would be
prohibitively expensive.
So, what you can do instead is,
do a little case control study from within
that cohort.
So, you, if you, there is a particular
disease you're interested in,
you wait, until enough people in that
cohort develop that disease.
That becomes the case group.
And then, you measure,
you run the expensive assay on everybody
in the case group, and these are samples
that you stored at the beginning of the
study when you had formed the cohort, so
you know that these blood samples were
collected before people got the disease.
But then, rather than measuring everybody
else in the cohort,
running everybody else's blood through
this assay,
you will set select just a small subsample
of the cohort controls.
People who did not get the disease, often
they'll,
they'll take, for every case they'll find
one control from the rest of the cohort.
And you'll measure the blood, the, the DNA
of that person, so
that it's an efficient study design.
You don't have to go through and measure
everybody in the cohort when you have so
many more controls in the cohort than you
have cases.
Let me just give you an example of a
nested case control study.
So, there was a study in Zimbabwe that
enrolled 177 pregnant women.
They were all HIV positive at enrollment.
And the study followed the women until six
weeks after the birth of the infant.
They identify 29 cases,
these were mothers who had transmitted HIV
to their infants by six weeks postpartum.
So, these 29 women, they're going to, run
the assay of interest, on all 29, and
what they were, wanted to look at was they
had measured blood during pregnancy, and
they wanted to see whether or not the HIV
RNA levels from
pregnancy affected whether or not the
mother transmitted HIV to her infant.
So they measured that RNA load test, they
ran that assay on each of the cases.
But then they only ran that assay on 29
controls, not the rest of the cohort,
the rest of the 148 people in the cohort,
but only on 29 of them.
So for each case, they found a similar
control, somebody who
was similar on things like age, but had
not transmitted HIV to her infant, and
they measured the HIV RNA load from the
blood samples of those 29 women.
So they only had to run 58 assays rather
than a 177.
So that's it for observational studies,
moving on to experimental studies,
of course, the gold standard is the
randomized clinical trial.
And the advantage of the randomized trial
is again that you are randomly assigning
people to interventions, which minimizes
confounding.
You are isolating a particular treatment
or drug or intervention.
From all of those other risk factors that
tend to cluster when you let
people decide for themselves.
There's other things you
can do in randomized clinical trials that
help to minimize biases.
So for example, often randomized trials
will be blinded, so
people don't know which intervention
they're on.
Sometimes the investigators will be
blinded, so
even the investigators in their analysis
in the data can't be biased.
Randomized trials are often
placebo-controlled, so
you can subtract out the placebo effect.
So, there's a lot of important information
you can get out of randomized trials.
And, again, it is considered the gold
standard in terms of level of evidence.
The major limitation is that randomized
trials tend to be very expensive.
You can't really run them for very long,
so
you can only look at short-term outcomes.
And it's not always possible even to do a
randomized trial.
It's not always ethical to randomize
people.
So for example, you couldn't really
ethically randomize people to smoke, or
to eat heavy amounts of red meat, or to
drink heavy amounts of alcohol.
Finally, randomized trials usually have
pretty strict eligibility criteria and
that leads to the results of the
randomized trial not always being
very generalizable.
That means the that the results might
apply to a very specific subset of
patients, but not to all the patients that
you would care about.
An example of a randomized trial,
is this example that I mentioned in the
teaser and it's an example that
I'm going to keep using to illustrate the
concepts this week.
So this was a double-blind, randomized,
controlled trial.
It was published in the New England
Journal of Medicine in 2000.
And the researchers were comparing what's
called a COX-2 inhibitor,
a COX-2 inhibitor named Rofecoxib.
I'm now going to tell you what the actual
brand name of that drug is.
The drug is actually Vioxx.
And if I say that.
The drug is Vioxx.
Some of you will remember, that will
trigger a memory,
that that was in the media, Vioxx was in
the media very heavily in the mid-2000s.
But they were studying Vioxx as a new,
pain treatment for
rheumatoid arthritis, and they were
comparing it with an older pain treatment,
a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory called
naproxen.
And what they were interested in is that
naproxen and
other non-steroidal anti-inflammatories
tend to cause stomach problems.
People get ulcers and stomach bleeding.
They believed that the cox 2 inhibitors,
this new class of pain drugs would be
beneficial because they would reduce the
incidence of things like ulcers and
stomach bleeding So their primary outcome
was to look at these GI events.
They randomly assigned about 8,000
patients with arthritis to receive either
Vioxx or naproxen twice daily.
It was a double blind study so the
patients didn't know what drug they were
on, the investigators didn't know And
again, the primary endpoint
was confirmed upper gastrointestinal
events, such as ulcers and bleeding.
So I'm going to be showing you a lot of
the data from this study in
the next couple of modules.