[BLANK_AUDIO]
>> In this next module I'm going to tell
you about bootstrap re-sampling, and
I decided to put this module first because
I'm going to be
using the term bootstrap sample in a lot
of the other modules for this week.
So I thought it would be important for you
to understand this term before I
even got to the discussion of prediction
modeling.
So first of all, the bootstrap was
invented by our very own Bradley Efron in
1979, and just to kind of motivate the
bootstrap for
you, let me take a step back here and do a
little review.
So, the bootstrap is something that's used
for repeated sampling.
And the idea of repeated sampling has come
up before in,
when we've talked about simulation.
So, let me just review here the concept of
the distribution of a statistic.
So, when we talk about the distribution of
a statistic,
there are three things we want to know.
We want to know what's the shape of that
distribution, what's the mean, and
what's the standard error.
And if you think about the way we do
studies.
If I say, well I went out and
I collected my sample of 100 people, and I
calculated a mean, then you would say,
well what do you mean by the distribution
of that statistic?
That statistic only has one number.
But remember that in statistics, what we
do is we think about theoretically if I
could repeat that same experiment over and
over and over and
over again, what would the distribution of
those means be?
In other words, if I could go out to my
original population and
take a new sample of 100 and calculate the
mean in that sample, and
then I could do that again and again and
again and
again, I could actually literally see what
the distribution of the means was.
And, of course, that information is
important because I need it in order to
be able to calculate P values and
confidence intervals.
So imagine that I could do somehow a
repeated sampling like this and I could,
since we've been talking about beta
coefficients from logistic regression,
I could calculate a beta coefficient from
logistic regression again, again and
again in multiple samples of the same
size.
Then I could actually look and
see what's the distribution, of that beta
coefficient.
You can see I'm putting it here in a
histogram, and we would say,
well it looks normally distributed, the
mean is the true beta, and
the standard error is some value.
Now I showed you in, in the fall that
there's two ways to
figure out the distribution of a
statistic.
There was simulation which I like to show
for
teaching, because it's very hands on and
it's very intuitive.
I can, in the computer, virtually do
repeated sampling.
And in a way the boot strap is going to
look a lot like that.
Of course more practically statisticians
spend their time figuring out formulas so
that we don't have to do a simulation
every time.
So for example, I told you that for an
odds ratio or actually for
the natural log of the odds ratio, it
follows a z distribution, and the standard
error there is the square root of 1 over a
plus 1 over b plus 1 over c plus 1 over d.
So that formula is there for you.
You can just apply it and you don't have
to run a simulation every time to
figure out the distribution of an odds
ratio anew every time.
And in most cases we're just going to use
formulas, and we don't have to
go through this whole process, but that's
the process behind the scenes.
and, there may be situations when where
you want to deal with a statistic or
make up a statistic that's new and
complicated and,
you know, nobody's ever used before and
there is no formula available for you.
In that case, that's where the bootstrap
sampling can come in.
You can calculate a bootstrap standard
error, and
you can look at the shape of the
distribution in bootstrap samples.
So that's one of the uses of the
bootstrap.
Also if, perhaps your using a well known
statistics that already has a formula, but
you're not meeting some of the assumptions
that went into calculating that formula,
the bootstrap could come up there as well.
And again, the bootstrap is a means of
doing repeated sampling.
But the key is that you're sampling, not
from the original population, but
you're sampling from your, own dataset,
from your one sample.
And this, if you start to think about it,
sounds impossible.
So I want to somehow take repeated samples
of the same size,
of size n, from my dataset of size n and
that,
of course, if you, says, that sounds
impossible, you can only take one sample.
because they're the same size.
So how can you do this?
Well the, the trick is the key to all of
this is sampling with replacement.
So what is sampling with replacement?
That means that when you're creating your
new datasets,
your repeated samples, some observations
can appear more than once, and
some observations will not appear at all.
Sampling with the replacement is something
like rolling a die,
the one you can roll a one twice in a row.
That's okay.
So you can get the same observation to
appear in your news sample twice and
some of the observations won't appear at
all.
And that's the key to this.
This is what will allow you to take
multiple samples from an an initial
sample, all of size n.
And this is just bell, best illustrated
with a picture.
So let me just illustrate that now.
So what we're doing, is we are taking some
original samples.
Say I had a very simple dataset.
It only has six observations.
because A B C D E and F in my original
dataset.
I want to take repeated samples of size N
from this original sample and
we're going to call those the bootstrap
samples.
So, here's how it works here's a new
dataset.
I want to fill a new dataset with six
observations from my original observation.
Observations.
And what I'm going to do in order to that,
is for every kind of slot in this
new dataset, I'm going to reach my hand
into this bag of letters,
this bag of observations, A, B, C, D, E,
and F, and with equal probability.
Every letter has an equal probability.
Or every observation has an equal
probability of being chosen here.
So I reach my hand into, to that bag and
maybe for the first slot here I pick out
B.
Okay.
Now, then I put B back into the bag, so
that it's again, with replacement.
So B can be selected again.
So, now I reach my hand into that bag of
six letters, and
I pull out another letter.
Every letter has a one in six chance of
being pulled out, and
let's say I happened to pull out B again,
that could happen.
Now I put B back in, I pull out another
letter,
in this case let's say I pull out C, and
then let's say for
the next one I pull out an E, and then
let's say I pull out an F, and another F.
So notice what happened.
B got pulled out twice, F got pulled out
twice, and A and
D were not included at all in this sample.
So it's a new sample.
It's different than my original, but it
still has an n of 6 and
it has all the same observations except
it's missing a few of them.
We can do this again.
So, that's one bootstrap sample.
Then we can repeat it.
So now, I've got to, again I want to make
a dataset with size of 6.
I'm going to, for the first observation in
this new dataset, I reach into my bag,
I pull out one letter.
Every letter has a one sixth chance of
being pulled out.
Let's say I get an E.
I put the E back in.
Now I'm going to pull out another letter.
Let's say then I pull out the C, put the C
back in, maybe C comes out again, and
then I, maybe I get an A, and then I get a
D, and then maybe I get another A.
So, now again, a slightly different
sample,
we have slightly different constitution of
observation.
Then I can do this again.
You get the idea by now so maybe this next
bootstrap sample will have D, E, F, C, F,
and F.
Maybe F will appear three times in that
sample.
That could happen as well.
So now I'm going to come out with a large
number of different,
I can come with a whole bunch of bootstrap
samples and with each of these samples.
Now of course this is a very small sample
so I can't calculate too many statistics
here, but imagine doing this for a bigger
sample, and in each one of these samples,
I could run a logistic regression on the
new sample, and come out with a beta,
from say, bootstrap sample one for my
logistic regression.
And then I run it again on the, the next
sample and
I get a beta from bootstrap sample two.
And I do it again and
I come out with a different beta, beta
from bootstrap sample three.
They're all going to be slightly
different.
Now, I can actually see what is the
distribution of beta,
because I've got beta calculated from all
these different samples of size N.
I can actually look at the distribution.
So that turns out to be very, very useful.
Now it would be useful to just talk about
for
a minute, how often does any particular
observation appear in, in a given sample?
How likely is it, say, for
example, that A happens to come up, in say
bootstrap sample one?
We can actually calculate this out, it's a
good review of probability.
So, say this is bootstrap sample one.
What's the probability that A is chosen
for bootstrap sample one?
That it appears at all, in bootstrap
sample one?
Well remember,
there is a 1 6th chance that each one of
these slots in the dataset.
There is a 1 6th chance that we're
going to pick A.
Okay?
So, how do we calculate the probability
that A appears somewhere in
a given bootstrap sample?
We need to calculate the probability of
that A appears at least once.
So this is at, on at least one problem.
So you know if we're doing it at least on
problem we're going to be
using a one minus the probability that A
never appears in this sample.
Well, what's the probability that A never
appears?
Every slot has a 1 6th chance of picking A
so
the chance of not picking A is going to be
5 6th.
So for A not to appear in this dataset we
have to not pick it with 5 6th chance for
the first slot.
5 6th chance for the second, 5 6th again,
again, again, again.
5 6th raised to the sixth,
that's the chance that we're not going to
pick A in this dataset.
Well, 5 6th raised to to the sixth is a
probability of 33.6%.
So one minus that probability is going to
be a probability of 66.4%.
So we had in this case a 66.4% of A,
appearing in that dataset.
Now it turns out that we can actually
solve this more generally, and so
the probability more generally of, a,
particular value, a particular observation
appearing in a dataset is 1 minus n minus
1 over n divided by n.
I'm just filling in, where n here is 6.
So then I'm just generalizing this
formula.
Well it turns out that if n gets bigger,
this will approach the value of 63.2%.
So, about 63.2% of the observations will
appear in any given dataset.
That means about 37% of the observations
are left out of any given dataset.
So that's kind of useful to know about 2
3rds of the observations end up in
a boot strap sample and about 1 3rd will
be left out.
Now, the bootstrap is a very general
method.
It has all sorts of uses.
So far I have been eluding to the fact
that it can be used to
calculate the distribution of a statistic.
So you might want to do that you get
standard errors, P values, and
confidence intervals when you have a new
statistic or
a complicated where we don't have a
formula.
Or you might want to do that where its a
well-known statistic but
we've violated some assumptions, so
maybe you have a really small sample or
you violated normality.
You don't have a normal distribution and
so you're not sure if
those formulas are really good so you
could actually bootstrap it and
there would be nothing wrong with just
basing it on the bootstrap distribution.
We're also going to use it in certain
cases for
prediction modeling, which we'll talk
about later this week.
But just to show you how the bootstrap
would be used specifically to calculate
standard errors for say a new statistic,
or
just a statistic where you may have
violated some of the assumptions.
So first thing you're going to do is
you're number your
observations 1 through n, and then you're
going to sample with replacement.
So you're going to draw a random sample of
size n.
So observation 1 might appear twice, and
observation 2 might not appear at all.
You're going to make a bootstrap sample.
Then you're going to calculate your
statistic, say the mean or
the beta coefficient or whatever statistic
you're interested in on that sample.
They you're going to do this a large
number of times.
So you're going to do this say a 1,000
times a 100 times 200 times
a large number of times, so that you can
figure out,
what is actually the distribution of this
statistic.
Then you take say those 1,000 beta
coefficients and you can say plot them in
a histogram and just look that what's the
shape of the distribution.
You can calculate the standard deviation
of those betas,
as you would calculate the standard
deviations of any number.
You've got a thousand, beta coefficients,
you calculate their standard deviation.
That's the standard error.
And then you can use that for calculating
p values.
You can also calculate confidence
intervals, so
you can just literally look and
say okay, where do I have, where do 95% of
my beta coefficients lie,
that's my 95% confidence interval,
whatever's in the tail is left out.
So, you can get empirical standard errors
and empirical confidence intervals, and
this one of the main uses of the
bootstrap, but again it has very a lot of
uses, and it will also see some uses in
prediction modeling.
[BLANK_AUDIO]