In this next module,
I am going to tell you about how we
evaluate predictive models.
And this is always going to involve some
kind of validation.
So first of all, it's just what're some
different measures of predictive accuracy?
So we saw with logistic regression that
we're typically using the area under
the ROC curve.
But there are other, plenty of other
measures of predictive accuracy.
So, if you just think about an individual
observation for example.
So what we want to know, is how well does
the model predict?
So, take a person's value from the
predicted, predicted from the model, and
compare it to their actual observed value.
That's called a residual.
So a residual is a measure of predictive
accuracy.
For a linear regression, the typical
measure we use for
predictive accuracy is just to look at the
residuals.
And the residuals are of course, our
observed minus expected.
You want to know, kind of, what's the
average residual?
But if you calculated the average
residual,
it actually comes out to be zero, right?
Because some of the residuals are going to
be positive and
some are going to be negative.
So the average will come out to be zero.
So what we instead use is to look at the
standard deviation of the residuals.
That's will give you the average distance
from the mean, and the mean here is zero.
So that will give you a sense of the
average magnitude of the residuals.
That's also sometimes called the, the root
mean square error.
But it's, all it is is the standard
deviation of the residuals.
Again for logistic regression, we've seen
already,
we can use the area under the ROC curve.
Now as I've already alluded to,
the problem with these measures is that
they're going to be overly optimistic.
So, when you just run your model in a
computer, you get out these measures.
The computer automatically calculates them
for you.
That's going to based on how well the
model predicts values for
the data in your data set.
Well that data was used to fit the model
and so
we are going to have some over fitting
going on.
And so, what is overfitting now?
Basically the idea is if you fit a model
to a particular data set,
you're going to end up fitting some of the
quirks of that data set, some noise.
That means that you can get really small
residuals.
So you fit to, you're almost like, fitting
to, for a particular people.
You can get really good predictive ability
in that particular sample.
But if you've really overfit, you fit to a
lot of noise.
Then when you apply to a new sample,
it will actually have very poor predictive
ability.
And this is kind of best illustrated with
a picture.
So, here is some data.
Okay, so I've got a, a scatter plot of
some data that I have.
These are made up data, but to illustrate
a point.
But I've got some data on my scatter plot.
And let's say I wanted to fit a linear
regression to these models.
So this, if I fit a linear regression to
these data points,
it's going to be a little bit what we call
underfit, actually.
So the residuals are higher than they
actually have to be.
We could do a little bit better in fitting
this model.
because if you look at the pattern here,
What you'll notice is that it's actually
is a quadratic and not a linear model.
So if we fit a linear model, notice that
the residuals, which again,
is just the distance from any one of these
points to the line.
The residuals are kind of big,
especially at the ends And in the middle,
they're big in the negative direction.
So we have some, some distance from, from
the line.
The, the predicted values are the values
on the line.
And of course the first observed values
are just these dots.
However, if we fit a better model,
we can get a glistening model by fitting a
quadratic.
Which is what I've done in the second
panel here.
What you'll notice is that the residuals,
if you kind of got the average residual,
again that, this root mean squared error.
The root mean squared error here is
going to be,
it is here, is going to be high.
because we're really kind of off.
The root mean squared error here, that is
the average distance from the line,
the average residual, is going to be
decent.
[SOUND].
going to be pretty good here.
And we still have some distance from the
line, but we area a lot closer.
So, this is a good fitting model.
However, compare that to this model.
So, this is an overfit model.
So, what I did here was I fit a really
complicated model to these data.
I'm almost kind of fitting the line to
individual points.
Imagine how complicated this model would
be if I actually had to
write out the model, like all the betas.
What are the betas here?
Well, there's going to be parameters or
betas for every little turn you see here,
for where this turns.
For every different slope.
These will all be, all these little
different lines in here.
This is going to be a hugely complicated
model.
It's going to have tons of parameters on
it, in it.
And this is when we run into overfitting.
When you fit a very complicated model,
lots of parameters.
Many more, this is going to have as many
parameters probably as there are points in
this data set.
Meaning again, we're kind of literally
fitting to individual points.
However, if you look at this model and
you compare it to the dots in this scatter
plot.
What you'll notice is my, my residuals are
really, really small, now right?
So, all my little dots are only, we are
really close to the line.
Sometimes they're right on the line.
So, my root mean squared error here.
[SOUND].
The average size of the residuals is
going to be very small.
It's going to look great.
We're going to, if, I just kind of threw
these data into my computer.
Fit this complicated model.
It's going to spit out to me the root
means squared error.
It's going to look really small.
My p values are going to be great.
I'm going to feel like I've got this
really, really great model.
It's going to look great in terms of
predicitiveability.
My residuals predicted minus observed, are
all really, really tiny.
Okay, so something's wrong here though,
right?
What we're literally doing is fitting to
noise.
And that means that it happens to be that
this dot here happens to be up at 30, and
so this point went up.
On, the you know we fit a whole parameter
to this guy, making this curve go up for
this one person.
But what am, what, I'm, when I look at the
larger population.
This relationship isn't going to exist.
This is just due to the quirk of one
person.
So what I did then to show this, was I
actually took a new sample,
a brand new sample from the same
underlying population.
And that's what I'm going to show you on
this slide.
I took a brand new sample.
Those dots are shown in blue.
So all the red dots were my original
sample.
The blue dots are now a new sample, but
the same underlying population.
And then I compared the model fit from the
very complicated model.
And the, the good fitting model, the good
model.
So notice what happens now.
When apply this really, really complicated
model to my new data set,
well all these little quirks that I fit in
the original data set like I had,
I must have had one dot way down here.
There's this little peak here, but
I don't see the, the similar peak in this
particular data set.
Now I've got really big residuals.
Notice how far my new data set is from
this model.
This model is really bad at predicting in
my new data set.
So the, our measure of predictive accuracy
our root mean squared error here,
is going to be huge.
So all of a sudden it went from looking
really great,
when we tested on our original data.
But when we tested it on new data, it's a
really bad model.
That tells us it was over fit.
On the other hand our, re, our root mean
squared error the,
kind of again the average distance from
the line here, is similar to before.
Maybe a little bit higher, but it's still
pretty close to what we saw before.
So, it's still very, very decent.
It didn't change much.
So, this is what we're going to be doing
to kind of look for
over-fitting, is actually trying to apply
a model that would fit on one set of data.
To a new set of data.
And seeing how does our measure of
predicted accuracy hold up.
Does it crumble or it it pretty robust,
does it stay pretty similar?
So how do we know if the model is overfit?
We have to validate.
Which means we have to apply the model to
new data.
Or, to somehow be clever and
get to apply it to our original data set
in a way I'll explain in a minute.
But we're going to have to do some kind of
validation.
So the easiest kind of validation is
external validation.
And I showed you some examples with the
delirium data set.
We just get a completely new sample of
data.
We apply the model.
And then we see how well the model did in
terms of prediction on the new data.
That's the ideal case.
However it also costs a lot of money to
get new data, right?
So it's often not possible to do external
val, validation at least not right away.
Even though that's the ideal.
What ends of happening a lot more
commonly, just for practical reasons.
Is that we do instead internal validation.
And this is going to use some kind of
clever scheme,
that we end up using part of our original
data set to fit the model.
And part of the data set to test the
model.
And we never test the model on data that
the model were fit.
So I'm going to show you a couple of
different of ways that we can do that
in just a minute.
But first of all, just external validation
is easy.
So it's exactly kind of what I showed
before.
What we do is we call the data sets
training data and test data.
So the training data are the data that are
used to fit the model.
The test data are the data that are used
to test the model.
And we don't want those two data sets to
overlap.
We want them to be totally different.
And what you can see is that you know,
with this very complicated model that I
fit to my training data here.
It looked great on the training data, but
then when I tested it, it looked terrible.
So predictiveability just went away.
So that tells you that we had an over fit
model.
however, when I do external validation on
this model,
which is that I said this kind of simple
one, that's a quadratic.
Which probably has, you know, two
parameters in it.
It worked well on the training data, but
it also worked well on the test data.
So that validates that this was a good
model and it wasn't over fit.
Now there's a number of ways to do
internal validation.
Which is to get to use the data you
started with and not have to go out and
collect new data.
So I'm going to taken a three.
Split-sample, cross-validation and
bootstrap validation.
And there's separate modules that we're
going to get to soon about both
cross-validation and bootstrap validation.
So, I'll setup the idea here, and
then we'll go into more detail in a future
module.
Now, split sample is actually pretty easy
too.
Because with a split sample, all you're
doing is saying,
I have got a big set of data.
They usually got, have a pretty large set
of data.
I've got some, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to split it into two.
I'm going to put some data aside and save
it.
So that I can test my model on it.
And I'm going to count, use some of the
model for the training data.
So I might say use 70% of my data for
training the model.
And I hold out 30% of the data.
And when the models fit on the, the 70%,
then I use it.
I test it on that 30% that was held out.
Of course, this requires that you have a
big enough data set.
Where you can afford to essentially you
know,
not use 30% of your sample or 50% of your
sample.
How, whatever percentage you choose for
fitting the model.
You have to have a big data set.
So, it's easy to do, but requires a lot of
data.
A lot of times, we don't have data to
spare.
And so we can use some kind of clever
techniques.
That don't require, that allow us to use
every data point for the model fitting.
And we can do something called
cross-validation.
So there's a couple of different versions
of cross-validation,
I'll just tell you about two.
So leave-one-out cross-validation, does
the following.
You fit your model holding out just one
observation.
So let's say have a data set with 100
people in it.
You're going to fit your model on 99
people.
You're going to hold out one of those
So you might fit a logistic regression on
99.
You get the betas from that logistic
regression.
You apply that model to the values for
that particular person that you held out.
You calculate their predicative
probability.
And then you see how well you did.
How, you know, we hope that if the person
actually had the disease,
your predictive probability is close to
one.
Where it, and we hope that if the person
didn't have the disease,
that their predicted probability is close
to zero.
But then we repeat this.
We do this again, and again, and again.
Holding out a different observation each
time.
So that every observation is held out
once.
And in this way,
you have only tested the model on data
that were not used to fit the model.
And you might think, well,
how much of a difference can it make if I
just hold one person?
Is the model really going to be any
different?
But in fact, it can make I think enough
difference.
And you can aggregate those differences
all over, all the people in your data set.
You'e then going to be summarizing your
predictive performance across.
So, you will if, if you have a data set of
100 people, you will get a 100 residuals.
So 100 observed minus predictives,
each one of those residuals was based on a
model that the person was not used to fit.
You, then take those 100 residuals and you
aggregate those somehow.
Or you aggregate the predicted
probabilities into
an ROC curve, for example.
So you're going to summarize across those
different models.
10-co, fold cross-validation is very
similar And again, I'm
going to go into more detail about this
particular method in the upcoming module.
But the idea is rather than holding out 1%
at a time, hold out 1 10th of your data.
Fit the model on the other 90% of your
data.
Test that model on the 10% you held out.
And then do that again, and again, and
again.
Do that ten times.
And then, you're going to summarize the
predictive performance across those
ten different models.
Again getting something like an average
area under the curve.
But you're getting to use all of your mod,
all of your observations get used at some
point for model fitting.
But they never add, the models never
tested on the same data that it was used,
that was used to fit it.
And you know, there's some fine details
about these,
again I'm going to go to, into in a future
module.
We can also use the bootstrap to do
validation.
So ins, you could take bootstrap samples
of your data.
So, samples with replacement from your
original data set.
You can then fit the model on the
bootstrap samples.
Test the model on, and
people do this in slightly different,
there's many versions of this actually.
But you can test the model on the original
sample.
Or you can test the, the model on the
observations that were left out of
a particular bootstrap sample we call the,
those the out of bag observations.
Again somehow we're then going to be
summarizing that predictive performance
across those different models.
And remember about a third of the
observations are going to be left out of
any given boot strap sample.
So those could be used for testing the
model.
[BLANK_AUDIO]