This presentation is about respiratory
viruses at the end of which you should
be able to define the different syndromes
caused by respiratory viruses you should
be able to name the main viral pathogens
causing respiratory infections.
I'll explain the pathogenesis of
respiratory viral infections and finally
explain the techniques used for diagnosing
specific types of viral infection.
To underscore the importance of viral
infections as a cause of death world wide,
I've pulled these data from 2004.
From the World Health Organization and it
was published in 2008,
that indicate the cause of deaths around
the world from infectious diseases.
And 17% of these of death,
deaths are attributable to acute
respiratory infections.
The types of infections that respiratory
viruses cause,
caused include the common cold which we
all have had.
Many times in our lives, pharyngitis,
infection of the back of the throat,
associated typically with a sore throat.
Laryngitis, infection of the voice box,
associated with a,
a hoarse voice or a loss of voice.
Laryngotracheobronchitis, occupying those
anatomical areas.
Typically causing croup in young children.
Bronchitis, infection of the larger,.
Airways,.
And, Bronchiolitis, infection of the very
small, terminal airways.
If the infection in the lower respiratory
tract spills from the bronchials or
the bronchi into the lung parenchyma,
there is bronchopneumonia.
And finally, there's a very in artful term
called the flu, which is meant to
refer to an influenza like illness, but it
is actually a bit of slang.
But you know what it's like to have the
flu.
This schematic indicates the different
types of respiratory viral infection,
according to the anatomical location.
And again, they're divided between upper
respiratory tract infections,
which are what they sound like in the
upper part of the respiratory tract,
including ear infections, rhinitis or the
common cold with the runny nose,.
And pharyngitis or laryngitis, or
infections in
the lower respiratory tract with the terms
that I've already introduced.
The types of viral pathogens,
that we encounter during life are listed
on this slide.
They include rhinoviruses, coronaviruses,
adenoviruses,
parainfluenza viruses, respiratory
syncytial virus or
RSV, metapneumovirus, parvovirus and
influenza virus.
So many viruses like to cause illness in
the respiratory tract.
And with regards to tropism, where the
infection tends to hang out, for
rhinovirus, most of the infections, as you
can see by the height of this.
Curve.
Cause infection in the upper respirators
tract in the nose, the common cold.
Different viruses that are listed on the
left cause infection in
different parts of the body, shown across
the top.
And you can see in general, where the
viruses tend to hang out,
in the respiratory tract.
There is a lot of overlap between the
different types of
respiratory syndromes caused by the
viruses, that this gives some general.
General picture of, the types of
infection.
Some generalities about respiratory
viruses.
So most of the respiratory viruses that
were listed are RNA viruses.
There is an exception, and that's the
adenovirus, which is a DNA virus.
Most of the respiratory viruses have
multiple serotypes,
multiple types that can infect you, each
year of your life, if you wish.
So, rhinoviruses, for example, there's
about a hundred.
Si if you add one rhino virus infection
per year and
you lived to experience all of them you
would be old.
RSV is an exception to that though in that
there's only a single type.
In North America most respiratory viruses
circulate during the fall and
winter months when people are in doors
sharing their pathogens with each other.
Most of the viruses spread by droplet
aerosolization.
And most of them spread in places like
schools, in homes, or
in other crowded environments.
I've already mentioned there's substantial
overlap between the different types of
viral syndromes.
With regards to the pathogenesis of viral
infections,
in general they enter in droplets through
the mucosa of the nose or the eyes.
They can not become in the mouth,
interestingly.
Once they cross the mucosa, they bind to
surface proteins and
then they enter the cells after they have
bound.
In the cells, they release their genome,
they synthesize new viral proteins and
progeny genomes, they assemble and they
get released to infect other cells.
After they've gone through this sequence
of cellular infection.
They then spread from cell to cell, down
the respiratory tract.
And in en route down the tract, they
caused substantial cellular necrosis and
an associated inflammatory reaction which
gives rise to
the symptoms you may experience.
They also stimulate host immunologic
responses and
mediator release, so cytokines for
example, and the release of those
mediators may cause additional symptoms.
When the cellular necrosis and debris that
is impairing the transmission of
gas exchange in the terminal airways you
can get hypoxia,
when the lower respiratory tract is
infected, because the viruses may impair,
host immune response that caused immune
dysfunction.
You may get a secondary bacterial
infection referred to
as a super infection.
Diagnosing viral infections is usually
just based upon clinical examination.
We usually don't care what specific virus
is causing us to have a runny nose.
Or a sore throat.
However, there are some circumstances
where we do care.
So, for investigating an epidemic of
severe disease,
we want to know what's causing that severe
disease.
If we're trying to decide that the patient
is sick enough that they
might benefit from antiviral therapy, we
need to
know they're infected with the virus that
is susceptible to antiviral therapy.
If we're looking to control infections
transmitted in the hospital then we
may end up wanting to cohort patients who
have the same type of viral infection
rather than mixing and matching different
patients with different infections.
If we make a viral diagnosis we may be
able to avoid antibiotics.
Therapy because we have a diagnosis, and
it's not a bacteria.
And if you're doing research studies and
trying to figure out the epidemiology of
an infection, you may want to make a
specific diagnosis.
The final slide shows the different types
of diagnostic tests available,
when approaching the cause of a viral
infection.
And the types of tests are shown along the
left.
One can do it by Cytology.
Meaning looking at the cellular.
Spot of the host and that can give you a
hint as to what the infection is,
you look at the specimen under microscopic
the nice part is it is widely available,
but it is not definitive,
you can't tell what the specific virus is,
based upon cytology, you can get a.
Clue.
On the other hand, if you take a sample
from the patients respiratory track and
you send it to the viral laboratory and
the viral laboratory puts the specimen
onto a variety of
different tissue cultures and looks for so
called cytopathic genic effect.
You can make a diagnosis of a specific
viral infection.
The advantages are, the, you can look for
multiple viruses at the same time.
The disadvantages that it's slow and
rather expensive.
The next two detection of viral nucleic
acids.
By something like PCR or detection of
viral proteins through immulogic
fluorescence technique for example are
both rapid and they're very sensitive and
specific but they're both quite expensive
and then finally one can
diagnose a viral infection based upon the
host antibody response, that is Serology.
You measure it when the patient first
comes in and
a couple weeks later, to determine what
the specific infection is.
The problem is it takes a long time.
You have to get specimens a couple of
weeks apart.
And therefore you may not make the
diagnosis in
time to impact any sort of intervention.