This presentation is an introduction to
virology.
At the end of this presentation,
you should be able to explain the ways, by
which viruses are transmitted.
You should be able to define the common
terms that are used to
describe viral infections, including
tropism and virulence.
You should be able to list the major host
immune factors that
are important to both the occurrence of
viral infections, and to their severity.
And finally, in general,
to describe strategies that can reduce the
spread of viral infections.
With regards to transmissions, viruses are
readily transmitted between hosts.
They are referred to, historically, as
communicable diseases.
This transmission can be direct, that is
host to host, or
it can go through an inanimate object,
also referred to as a fomite.
With regards to mechanisms of spread,
viruses can spread by direct
contact between bodily fluids, exemplified
by oral herpes or genital herpes.
Viruses can spread across the placenta,
from a pregnant mother to her unborn fetus
and cause congenital infection,
such as congenital rubella, Viruses can be
directly inoculated, into the body.
For example, through injection by illicit
drug use and resulting in hepatitis.
They also can be directly inoculated
through trauma, the trauma of a bite, for
example, from a rabid bat or rabid dog.
They can be transmitted with the help of a
arthropod vector, for
example, a mosquito causing and spreading
West Nile virus.
Or, they can be spread with the help of a
different kind of vector,
a rodent vector, as is exemplified by
Lassa fever.
Some key terms to know with regards to
viruses are highlighted in red.
A primary infection is one occurring for
the first time in a susceptible host.
If the infection is associated with
symptoms,
the symptoms tend to be more severe than
an inf,
a secondary infection or reinfection,
which I'll talk about in a moment.
A latent infection refers to an infection
in which the virus has
entered the body and has become latent if,
it, it becomes dormant.
It is integrated in the body, but it's not
causing any problem.
Nonetheless, it can be reactivated from
latency, and that is called reactivation.
Herpes viruses exemplify this.
Viruses may also, you can get a
reinfection, rather than a reactivation.
A reinfection means exposure to a new and
unique virus, maybe of the same family,
but it's a reinfection, it's not the
reactivation of an old infection.
A subclinical infection is what it sounds
like,
an infection occurring in the absence of
symptoms.
An acute infection is one that occurs in a
short period of time, for example,
a common cold.
Whereas, a chronic infection is one that
has a long
relationship with the host, such as
certain forms of hepatitis.
Viruses, you can get two viral infections
at the same time,
that's called a coinfection.
Or, a viral infection can set the host up
for a bacterial infection,
in which case the bacteria would be
causing a superinfection,
an infection on top of a previous
infection.
Viral tropism and virulence are also
important terms.
Tropism refers to the avidity of the virus
for
particular type of host cell or tissue.
Much of tropism is defined by host cell
receptors,
different types of receptors and there are
other factors that drive tropism.
Some viruses favor particular organs.
Obviously respiratory viruses like to go
to the respiratory tract, and
hepatitis viruses like to go to the liver.
Virulence is different from tropism.
Virulence reflects the inherent ability of
specific viruses to cause disease.
A low virulent virus would cause very
little disease,
a highly virulent virus would cause a lot
of disease.
Viruses that are localized in one organ
often are of low virulence, but
if they spread throughout the body,
they disseminate, those might be of higher
virulence.
So localized versus dissemination helps to
think about virulence as a viral
characteristic.
The host immunity against viruses is
widespread and
includes both the innate immune system and
the adaptive immune system.
The immune system not only determines
whether we get infected or
not, but also the clinical expression of
the infection including the outcome.
The skin and mucosal surfaces are the
first defense against
many infectious pathogens, including
viruses.
The ciliary function of the respiratory
tract is the protective mechanism to
prevent viruses from going from the upper
to the lower respiratory tract.
Antibodies are an important source of
immune protection against viruses,
both secretory antibody, such as occur in
the nasal mucosa, and the gastrointestinal
tract, and systemic antibody responses of
IgM and IgG classes, for example.
Natural killer cells are an important part
of the innate immune system,
trying to protect us against viral
infections, and T-cells and
cytokine function and responses are
important components of the immune system,
as for many viral infections.
The key to preventing viral infections,
there really are three.
One is vaccination, another is
hand-washing, and
the third is transmission-based
precautions,
meaning wearing some combination of masks,
gloves, and gowns.
Vaccination is available for all of the
viruses listed, and
these are routine parts of vaccinating
populations in North America.
Whenever one encounters a patient or even
a family member who is infected,
it's very important to wash your hands
often and
completely, because this helps to prevent
infections.
And the transmission-based precautions
vary a bit.
If the virus is airborne by small
particle, the examples given,
or by droplet particle or by direct
contact, some combination of mask,
gloves, and gowns will be recommended to
prevent the transmission of virus or
the spread of virus between individuals.