This presentation is an introduction to
virology.
At the end of the presentation you should
be able to name the structural components
of viruses, describe the different types
of viral genomes and how these replicate.
Recall the basis for classifying viral
families and explain viral life cycle.
So with regards to some of the
nomenclature,
the keywords are highlighted in red.
first, it's important to recognize that
viruses require living cells for
their survival and for their replication.
They cannot exis, exist on their own.
They're not free living creatures but
rather they're obligate intracellular
pathogens.
A viral infectious particle is referred to
as a virion and
this virion is the viral genome encased a
capsid protein coat.
The capsid's vary in shape and some of the
shapes are outlined on this slide and
these capsids are composed of structural
proteins called capsomeres.
The capsomeres are specified by the viral
genome and they are antigenically unique.
Many viruses are surrounded by a
lipoprotein membrane envelope and
that envelope may have glycoproteins
embedded within it.
These viral glycoproteins facilitate the
attachment of the virus to a host cell and
the release of the virus from that host
cell.
An example of a viral structure is
illustrated with this dna virus,
this DNA Herpes virus.
Where you can see at the core of the
virus, the viral genome.
That genome is surrounded by the Capsids,
and in turn,
the Capsids, which make up the Capsomere,
are surrounded by an outer protein
membrane and, embedded within this
membrane are the Herpes glycol proteins.
Viral genomes are either DNA or they're
RNA and most
viruses have one copy of either the DNA or
RNA and they're referred to as haploid.
Retroviruses are an exception to this,
they're diploid.
They have two identical copies of RNA.
The genomic structure varies from virus to
virus.
They may be double-stranded.
You can see the abbreviation, single
stranded, or
any partially double stranded and RNA
viruses may be either positive, or
negative sense, and I'll explain that in a
moment.
Genome structures may be either segmented
or non-segmented and
this is important in the ability of
viruses, some viruses to evolve.
The genomes also may vary from being
linear, to circular, to partial circular.
And finally, many viruses carry their own
enzymes to facilitate their replication or
to perform other functions.
There are about 20 major viral families
they're referred to as viridae,
that have been associated with human
disease.
And these viral families are classified
according to a number of characteristics.
I've already alluded to one of the
characteristics, whether they're
DNA viruses or RNA viruses, and also as to
their strandedness,
double stranded, single stranded or they
may be partially double stranded.
Their so called sense of their nucleic
acid.
Whether they are negative sense, positive
sense, or they're ambivalent,
they have ambisense.
I'll come back to this.
The capsid shape as mentioned earlier,
may also vary and the viruses may have an
envelope or they may lack an envelope.
The genomes may be segmented or
non-segmented, and the physical appearance
of the virus, if you happen to own an
electron microscope, will vary.
Also the size of the virion itself, or
the size of the viral genome varies, and
finally, the nature of gene expression.
So these are all different characteristics
that allows one to
assign viruses into different families.
We're going to start by talking about the
DNA viruses, and this is not a table,
this is not a table to be memorized, but
rather outlines the key
families of DNA viruses and you can see
that there are seven.
And they vary according to whether they
are double stranded or single stranded.
They vary according to their genome shape.
They vary according to where they
replicate in host cells and
their type of capsids and some examples of
the viruses in these different
families are shown on the far right and
some of these you will be familiar with.
Hepatitis B virus, a major cause of liver
infection,
liver cancer and liver cirrhosis in the
word.
Herpes simplex virus, the cause of cold
sores.
Small pox virus which has been eradicated
but
nonetheless is feared as a weapon of mass
destruction.
Human papilloma viruses for which we now
have a vaccine.
And then viruses that cause infections
primarily in an immunocompromised hosts.
This picture is to try to display the DNA
viruses in a simpler fashion
that is they may, depending upon their
envelope, nonenveloped vs enveloped.
Depending upon their strandedness, single,
double, or double stranded circular.
And that applies to both the enveloped and
the nonenveloped and some examples at the
bottom.
Again, this is not, to be memorized, but
rather just to appreciate the general
family structure of the DNA viruses.
With regards to the RNA viruses the
genomes may be
either positive-sense or negative-sense.
A positive-sense RNA virus means that the
the virus,
the positive-sense segment acts as
messenger RNA and
can be directly translated after it's
entered host cells.
If an RNA genome is negative-sense they
actually have to carry an enzyme,
an RNA dependent RNA polymerase that turns
the negative-sense RNA
into positive-sense RNA before it can be
translated.
Many RNA viruses have a segmented genome
and this is very important because it
means that the virus can mix and match by
its genome shifting.
Because it's segmented it can break apart
an recombine with something else.
This will be especially important with
influenza viruses.
Most RNA viruses replicate in the
cytoplasm, although there are exceptions,
shown parenthetically and most RN, are,
RNA viruses are sti, single stranded.
That there's an exception to that as well.
The accompanying table illustrates the
fourteen viral
families bodily speaking with some
specific examples of the family members.
According to the name of the family.
And this picture like the one for DNA
viruses, is meant to simplify the class of
occasion of RNA viruses between those that
are nonenveloped and
those that are enveloped, based upon their
strandedness and
also based upon whether their positive
sense or negative sense.
Again, not to be memorized but rather to
be appreciated.
With regards to viral pathogenesis, a
virus' cycle and
in, in a very similar way.
They enter the body and they attach to a
host cell.
They then enter the host cell.
They're uncoated if they have a coat.
They replicate, and then they rely upon
host cells,
and sometimes their own enzymes, in order
to create progeny, and
then can be released so that they can go
on and infect.
Other cells.
Schematically this is represented on this
picture.
With, at the top, showing the virus
binding to the host cell.
When it comes into the host cell, it, the
virion is released,
the genome is released and there us
ultimately replication and
translation of the virus so that progeny
genome can be made, and
the virus ultimately can be repackaged and
released as progeny to infect other cells.