[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi, my name is Sharon Chen.
I'm a pediatric infectious disease
physician, and
I take care of many children with
respiratory viral infections.
In this video I want to share with you the
important concepts about
all respiratory viruses.
I will also introduce you to the anatomic
framework that we will use in this
video and in other subsequent videos that
dive deeper in each respiratory virus.
This video is an overview about all
respiratory viruses with a focus on
the clinical syndromes.
The learning objectives are to define the
different syndromes caused by
respiratory viruses and to name the main
viral pathogens.
Here is the pathogen list for our course,
and in this video and the entire module,
I will be discussing these viruses that
cause respiratory infections.
Respiratory viral infections are something
that I know you have all
experienced personally, and that you will
see a lot of as a physician.
You will usually not know which virus is
causing your patient's symptoms.
But in this video we will teach you about
the clinical syndromes and the hallmark
viruses that cause these syndromes, so
that you can make an educated guess.
We want you to learn what the typical
clinical presentation is of each one of
these respiratory viruses so
that you can make a better decision about
when not to give antibiotics.
Or when your patient may get clinically
worse and need to be in the hospital.
Now the pie chart here shows you some of
the names of the common respiratory
viruses, and as you can see rhinovirus and
influenza virus are quite prevalent.
Now it may be daunting to learn all these
respiratory viruses, so
that ones that I just named and their
biology and what symptoms they cause.
But we've created a way to simplify this
all for you.
The beauty about clinical syndromes of
respiratory viruses is that they can
actually be organized anatomically.
So in the next series of images, well,
I'll show you the clinical syndromes and
their associated hallmark or
typical virus mapped anatomically to the
upper and lower respiratory tract.
This can help you later when you review
this material.
We will discuss each one of these clinical
syndromes and
their associated virus in depth, in later
videos.
Now, think back to the last time you had a
cold.
What was the most annoying symptom that
you had?
Many of you might have said a stuffy nose,
or congestion, dripping mucus.
And this clinical syndrome is what we call
Rhinitis.
And so this is specifically infectious
Rhinitis, not allergic Rhinitis.
It involves inflammation of the nasal
cavity only.
And the typical viruses that cause
Rhinitis are Rhinovirus and Corona Virus.
Further down the upper respiratory tract
is a nasal pharynx or
pharynx involved chords.
When this area is infected,
we get clinical syndromes of sore throat
and hoarseness.
And we term these Pharyngitis and
Laryngitis.
The viruses that typically infect these
locations are different than those
that infect the nasal cavity.
Adenovirus and Parainfluenza virus are the
most prominent viruses.
We've decided to
define the lower respiratory tract as
below the vocal cords.
And in general, lower respiratory tract
infections can be more severe.
Because the infection can cause gas
exchange leading to hypoxia.
The smaller airways or bronchioles are
also easier to fill up with a lot of
mucus and this causes breathing problems.
Sometimes these patients will actually
have to be hospitalized.
And that's in contrast to the majority of
patients who
have upper respiratory tract infections.
One clinical syndrome that's classic in
young children is Croup.
And this is also known as
Laryngotracheo-bronchitis.
The word Croup comes from the sound of the
cough, which is hoarse and barking.
And young children are more affected,
because the size of their airway is
smaller.
Croup involves swelling swelling of the
area right below the vocal cords.
We'll discuss a lot more about Croup in
later videos.
The typical virus that causes Croup is
Parainfluenza.
Lower down the lower respiratory tract are
the large bronchi that branch off
the trachea at the level of the Carina.
Infection bronchi causes Bronchitis.
An inflammation of the mucus membranes of
the bronchi leads to a lot of
secretions and then that needs to be
cleared by coughing.
Patients with Bronchitis have a lot of
coughing.
And this cough can actually last for many
weeks.
Any of the common respiratory viruses can
cause Bronchitis.
And we've listed them on this slide.
The bronchi branch off into smaller
airways called bronchioles.
An infection of bronchioles is called
Bronchiolitis,
which is clinically more severe in infants
and young children.
The size of the bronchioles in infants and
young children are smaller compared to
adults, and thus it's easier to block up
with all the mucus and cellular debris.
Most of the respiratory viruses can also
cause this clinical syndrome.
But RSV, which is short for
Respiratory Syncytial Virus, is the
typical virus for Bronchiolitis.
At the end of the bronchial trees are the
alveoli, and
this is where gas exchange occurs.
When these areas are involved,
when infection of the alveolar epithelium,
we call this Pneumonia.
Inflammation around the alveoli decreases
gas exchange and this can lead to hypoxia.
And really increases the severity of this
particular infection.
All of the respiratory viruses can cause
Pneumonia.
Influenza is the typical virus that causes
viral Pneumonia.
The anatomic framework we hope will allow
you to organize and
remember these respiratory viruses.
The location of the infection determines
the clinical symptoms, and
certain viruses have a predilection for
infecting certain locations.
However, it is important to remember that
there's a lot of overlap.
Many of these viruses can cause many of
these clinical syndromes.
What we listed on this slide are the most
typical respiratory viruses for
each clinical syndrome.
Sometimes respiratory viral infections can
be
complicated by secondary bacterial
infections.
The same anatomic locations that I showed
you for the respiratory virus
infections can also manifest clinical
syndromes due to bacteria infection.
For example, a viral Rhinitis can be
complicated by a bacterial infection of
the sinus causing Sinusitis.
Now some of these clinical syndromes that
I've listed on this slide can be
bacterial infections without a preceding
viral infection.
For example, strep throat is a Faringitis
caused by Streptacacus Piogenese.
And Bordatella Pertussis can cause
Bronchitis.
Different from respiratory viral
infections, bacteria infections of
the upper and lower respiratory tract need
to be treated with antibiotics.
These bacterial infections that I've
listed on the slide will be discussed in
depth in other modules.
The last clinical syndrome that is listed
on this particular image is Pneumonia.
This is a very important clinical syndrome
to pay attention to because some of
these patients can actually have really
severe infection.
So when we take care of patients with
Pneumonia we want to distinguish whether
that Pneumonia is caused by a virus or a
bacteria, and this is not so easy.
The clinical symptoms are pretty similar
but if you happen to get a chest x-ray,
the typical chest x-rays can look quite
different.
So in general, viral Pneumonias tend to be
diffused, affecting both lungs.
And so the chest x-ray I'm showing you
here is of a 12-month-old infant,
who is presenting with rapid breathing and
cough.
And what you can see in this chest x-ray
is this haziness in both sides of
the lungs.
And this suggests a very diffuse process.
Bacterial Pneumonias can have many
patterns on chest x-rays, but
in general they tend to be more focal.
So this chest x-ray on the right is of a
six-year-old little girl.
She has fever, cough, chest pain when
she's breathing.
And what you can see is a demarcated area
of whiteness in the left lung.
This represents alveoli filled with
inflammatory infiltrate within that
particular lung segment.
Now, keep in mind that this is a broad
generalization.
There are bacteria, such as mycoplasma,
that can also cause a generalized abnor,
abnormal pattern of both lungs.
[BLANK_AUDIO]