Hi my name is Sharon Chen and
this video is about the lower viral
respiratory tract infections.
The learning objectives are to recognize
the clinical characteristics of
Bronchitis and Bronchiolitis.
To describe how the clinical
characteristics of Bronchiolitis.
Relate to the pathogenesis of RSV
infection.
To discuss potential complications,
management and
prevention strategies for RSV induced
Bronchiolitis, and
to compare the clinical manifestations of
RSV to that of human metapneumovirus.
Here is the pathogen list for our course,
and in this video and the entire module,
I will be discussing these viruses that
cause respiratory infections.
We're going to use the same anatomic
framework and
focus on Bronchitis and Bronchiolitis.
Influenza can cause both, but influenza is
such an important respiratory virus
that we will be discussing in, this in
depth in a separate module.
We already talked about
Laryngotracheo-bronchitis in
the upper viral respiratory tract
infection video.
So now we're going to continue down the
airway to discuss
Bronchitis and Bronchiolitis.
The clinical symptoms of Bronchitis really
center on cough.
It's a productive cough and can last for
several weeks.
The cough is due to attempts of clearing
the secretions caused by inflammation of
the mucus membrane of the bronchi.
Sometimes the secretions in speed-um can
appear virulent, but
this does not mean that the patient has a
bacterial infection.
The perelence is from sluffing cells mixed
with mucus.
In this case because it is not a bacterial
infection,
you do not need to give the patient
antibiotics.
In fact Bronchitis is one of the leading
diagnoses of inappropriate antibiotic use.
Bronchitis is predominantly a viral
infection, and
most of the respiratory viruses that we've
been discussing can cause it.
Only a few bacteria can cause bronchitis.
Inflammation of the Bronchi can cause
Bronco spasms so
wheezing can be heard in these patients.
However fever and systemic symptoms are
unusual.
And, if you see these in your patient,
another diagnosis should be thought about
including influenza and pneumonia.
Now, we're going to discuss Bronchiolitis.
This is the inflammation of
the Bronchioles that are narrower than
bronchi.
Any of the viruses that we have discussed
can cause Bronchilitis but
the hallmark virus is RSV.
Bronchiolitis mostly affects infants and
young children, and has a 4 to 6 day
incubation period which is when the virus
colonizes the infant asymptotically.
The upper respiratory infection symptoms
and fever manifest once the innate immune
system recognized the virus and initiates
production and secretions of citocons.
A third of the infants and young children
with RSV infection will progress to lower
respiratory tract disease.
And the patient will have fast breathing
or tachypnea,
coughing, and respiratory distress with
retractions and wheezing.
Here is a video of a baby with RSV
Bronchiolitis.
[SOUND] What you should have noticed that
this baby is really struggling to breathe.
He's breathing fast and in respiratory
distress.
And you can see the pulling in of the soft
tissue between his ribs and
above his clavicles.
This is called retractions and
is caused by the baby using his accessory
muscles to breathe.
So how did the baby get these symptoms?
The pathogenesis should be familiar to you
now.
It's very similar to what we discussed in
detail in
the upper respiratory tract video.
RSV infects respiratory epithelial cells
starting in the nasal mucosa, and
then progressing down the respiratory
tract.
Innate immune sensors detect PAMP's and
produce interferon other cytokines and
chemo-kines, which then recruit the
inflammatory cells.
Vascular flow, permeability and mucus
production increase.
The epithelial cells undergo apoptosis and
slough off into the airway.
All of this cellular debris, and the
outpouring of mucus in
inflammatory cells leads to plugging up of
the small airway.
This can trap air and lead to poor gas
exchange.
With worsening respiratory distress,
you should worry about potential clinical
complications.
Respiratory failure occurs when the
patient needs
to be entibated and mentilated.
It does not commonly occur.
But young infants are most susceptible.
Apnea is also more common in newborns and
premature infants.
And Apnea is when babies spontaneously
stop breathing.
This is a scary complication for both
parents and doctors.
Especially because it occurs in very, very
young babies.
Now there are certain patient populations
such as newborns and the elderly.
Who are at risk of more severe disease,
other because they
have pre-existing lung problems or, a
relatively deficient immune system.
You should keep these patients populations
in mind,
because it may effect your decisions about
how you manage and treat your patient.
Here are several things you should think
about when you manage and
treat a patient with Bronchiolitis.
So first you want to figure out how much
respiratory
distress your patient is showing?
What is her oxygenation?
Does she have retractions?
Is she eating and drinking normally?
Or is she having such a hard time
breathing that she can't eat or drink?
In addition you want to know if the
patient is actually getting worse or
getting better.
Next, you want to know if your patient is
in a high risk group
of having severe disease.
I already mentioned these patient
populations in the pervious slide.
If you find that your patients having a
really difficult time breathing and, or is
in one of these high risk groups, you may
want to admit her for closer monitoring.
Now treatment of Bronchiolitis is
predominately supportive.
You should supplement oxygen and monitor
for Apnea.
In some situations you may need to
intubate and
mechanically support the infant's
breathing.
Nasal gastric feeding or intravenous
fluids is important to think about.
Remember this baby might be quite
dehydrated because she hasn't
been able to take her bottle.
Because Bronchiolitis symptoms can be
analogous to asthma.
Some drugs that are used in asthma to
overcome airway obstruction have been
tried for Bronchiolitis.
These include bronchial dilators,
epinephrine, corticosteroids.
However, the results have been
disappointing.
Although many respiratory viruses can
cause Bronchiolitis,
RSV is the prototypical virus.
Because it causes mostly Bronchiolitis, or
RSV is the most important viral pathogen
during the first year of life.
Unlike many of the other respiratory
viruses, RSV has only one syrotype.
So it's a bit surprising that reinfections
are common with RSV.
Now RSV is in the paramyxoviridae family,
just like parainfluenza virus, and
metapneumovirus.
Both of which can also cause
bronchiolitis.
Paramyxoviridae family are all RNA
envelope viruses.
RSV has 2 important proteins.
You can see them sticking out of the
capsid in the cartoon drawing.
Both of these proteins are important in
eliciting neutralizing antibodies.
The cheap protein is for attaching the
virus to the host cell receptor
although the actual receptor is not known.
The f protein is important for
fusing the viral envelope to the membrane
of the respiratory epithelial cell.
In cell culture the f protein fuses cells
together forming a syncitian.
This is where RSV got its name,
respiratory syncytial virus.
Syncytial formation is a cell culture
phenomenon.
How is it with one serotype can RSV cause
re-infections?
Well RSV has multiple mechanisms of
evading the immune system.
The development of neutralizing antibody
is made at a low frequency.
And this may be because the G-protein has
heavily glycosylated, and
interferes with antibody production.
It can also be made in a secreted form,
acting as a decoy for neutralizing
antibodies.
RSV can also infect T cells by infecting
dendritic cells,
which then decreases their ability to
present antigen to T cells.
Cited toxic T cells are recognized RSV in
the lung.
Don't secrete key cytokines like IL2 and
interferon gamma.
These are important for killing the
infected cell.
These examples of evading and modulating
the host immune response may
explain why natural immunity is not
complete and not sustained.
The important point to remember here.
IS that protective immunity against RSV is
incomplete and short lived.
The examples I have given you are only to
illustrate this point.
One other important point.
The host immune response may not be robust
but it's also not zero.
RSV reinfections tend to not be as sever,
suggesting that the immune response was
protective enough against severe disease.
But not infection.
Viral disease is from actions of the virus
and from the host.
The clinical pattern that we observe on
the host side is that most
children older than 2 years of age don't
get severe RSV disease.
Why is that?
We already said that infants and
young children have small airways which
increases their risk of severity.
An added disadvantage is that infants are
born with an immature immune system.
And this is in addition to the mechanisms
that RSV uses to evade and
modulate the immune response.
I just discussed how an immature immune
system can lead to disease.
An over exuberant immune response can also
cause disease.
Wheezing is a clinical symptom common to
RSV Bronchoilitis and asthma.
There is a group of children who continue
to have recurrent wheezing.
Even without getting RSV infection.
Some of these children will eventually be
diagnosed with asthma.
Now it's unclear whether RSV Brochiolitis
causing asthma or,
is indicative of a child prone to asthma.
There is no RSV vaccine available.
Physicians do have other means of
providing some protection to infants.
This is in the form of passive immunity
and
the monoclonal Antibody is called
Palivizumab.
This is an antibody against the F-Protein.
It is given as an intravenous infusion,
and
given to high risk groups of infants and
young children less than 2 years of age.
The most recently discovered virus in
Paramyxoviridae family is
Human Metapneumovirus.
It was discovered in patients who had
Bronchiolitis very similar to
RSV bronchiolitis.
But RSV could not be isolated.
Human metapneumovirus essentially mimics
RSV.
Both are in the same virus family and
those are enveloped RNA viruses.
Human metapneumovirus only has one
serotype.
You should recognize the cartoon image of
the virus,
because it's very similar to RSV.
Human metapneumovirus also has a f and g
protein.
The epidemiology and clinical disease for
human metapneumovirus and RSV are the
same.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This slide is, all of the,
lower respiratory tract.
Virus infections for you to review later.