[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi, my name is Sharon Chen and
this video is the second part of the
Introduction to Respiratory Viruses.
Giving you an overview of all respiratory
viruses with a focus on the virus.
The learning objectives are to recognize
the epidemiology and
main route of transmission of the
respiratory viruses.
To recognize appropriate use of diagnostic
tests for viral respiratory syndromes and
to explain the techniques used for
diagnosing specific viral infections.
Here's the pathogen list for our course
and in this video and the entire module,
I will be discussing these viruses that
cause respiratory infections.
Now, let's talk about the virus and
how the clinical syndromes relate to the
life cycle of the virus.
What viruses want to do is spread to other
hosts.
Essentially, exit.
The strategy that respiratory viruses have
evolved is to replicate quickly,
reaching high numbers of viruses causing
acute infection.
They cause symptoms in people to then exit
from that person.
For example, you can see this man sneezing
and he's spreading high titers of
viral particles to another person through
droplets and
aerosolization of the secretions.
All respiratory viruses transmit in this
same way.
And another similarity between the
respiratory viruses is in
RNA genome with one exception, which is
Adenovirus.
This allows them to mutate and avoid
immune surveillance.
Because of the ability to mutate many of
these viruses have multiple serotypes with
RSV being an exception.
Despite these similarities, they cause
different clinical syndromes.
The virus evolved to find its preferred
means of causing infection and disease.
This image looks at the clinical syndromes
relative to the virus.
It's essentially the same information that
I discussed already, but
I want to repeat an important point.
Each of these respiratory viruses can
cause multiple clinical syndromes.
For example, RSV and human metapneumovirus
mostly cause Bronchiolitis,
you can see the hump on the graph.
But sometimes it can cause a common cold.
Another difference between respiratory
viruses is that they cause illness in
different seasons.
Adenovirus is constant and doesn't have
seasonality.
Parainfluenza peaks in the late fall, but
RSV mostly occurs in the winter.
The seasonality suggests that there are
virus specific and
immunologic specific reasons for these
differences.
You can see from this image that several
of them peak in the winter.
All us us realize that we get more
respiratory infections in the winter and
this may be due to a more crowded
environment allowing the virus to
transmit easily from person to person.
I told you before that most, for
the most part you will not know which
virus is causing your patient's symptoms.
Usually, respiratory virus infections are
diagnosed clinically.
Which is why we wanted to teach you the
clinical syndromes.
However, there are certain times when
identifying a virus is important.
And you'll have to decide when to do these
tests on your patient.
Here are some reasons for ordering tests
on an individual patient.
For example, you may choose to give
antiviral therapy for
a patient with influenza.
Or if the patient is hospitalized or
has severe disease, you'll luckily want to
know why the patient's so sick.
For immune compromised patients,
you may want to give experimental
antiviral therapy.
In some patients, you could actually avoid
empiric antibiotic therapy.
The other reason is to place all patients
who have respiratory virus infections in
the same area of the hospital.
This is a, this is called cohorting.
It decreases the chance of spreading the
virus to other patients in the hospital.
A third main reason for
identifying a virus is to investigate an
epidemic of a respiratory virus.
This is important in case the virus found
is a new emerging virus.
Now studies are done on respiratory
viruses, which is the only way I
can tell you about the clinical syndromes
and seasonalities of these viruses.
Identifying viruses is crucial in these
epidemiology studies.
The image on the right shows you how we
obtain samples to identify a virus.
It is called a nasopharyngeal swab and it
needs to be put all the way to the back of
the nasal pharynx in order to get the
correct sample.
I hope you can see how far you need to
insert the swab.
If you ever had one of these, you know
it's a bit uncomfortable.
But it's very important to do the
collection correctly.
Otherwise, you will not be able to
identify the virus.
Once you collect the sample, you'll have
to decide what tests to do.
And this table shows you the different
methods available.
You will hear about all these different
tests when you start clinics.
Different hospitals use different methods.
For example, until very recently, our
hospital used the first method that
detects viral proteins by antibody testing
for the viral antigen.
These tests are very fast and
we had an entire panel that tested most of
the respiratory viruses.
The disadvantage is that these tests may
be negative if the sample doesn't
have a lot of viral antigen.
This may be because of sample bias or
because it just wasn't collected well.
So now our hospital is using the second
method,
which detects viral genetic material with
molecular methods.
We now test for more viruses including
rhinovirus.
Vallecular methods are much more
sensitive.
One of the new patterns we are finding are
patients who
have multiple viruses at the same time.
Not all hospitals have this type of test,
because it's quite expensive.
In the past, viral culture was gold
standard.
You can directly isolate the virus, but
this is a slow test and
sometimes you don't even get the answer
until after the patient is better.
The last method is serology.
This test looks for the antibody response
to the virus, so
it's different compared to the other tests
that I just talked to you about.
It doesn't detect a presence of the virus.
This test can be used after an infection
has cleared.