[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi my name is Sharon Chen.
In this video we are going to discuss more
about the viruses that
cause Upper Respiratory Tract Infections
and
relate their clinical symptoms to their
pathogenesis.
The Learning Objectives are to describe a
general model for the pathogenesis of
viral respiratory tract infections that
explain the symptoms and
clinical manifestations.
To relate the epidemiology and clinical
manifestations to the pathogenesis of
viral respiratory tract infections caused
by Rhinovirus, Coronavirus, Adenovirus and
Parainfluenza virus.
Here is the pathogen list for our course.
In this video and the entire module,
I will be discussing these viruses that
cause Respiratory Infections.
I'm going to use the same anatomic
framework that I've shown you before for
this discussion, but what I want to do
first is to talk about a general scheme of
how these viruses cause disease in the
upper respiratory tract.
I will use our framework to show you how
the virus fulfills its life cycle,
interacts within the immune system to
cause clinical disease.
This is a diagram of an airway, so the
lumen is at the top.
The epithelial layers next and their job
is to clear the airway of debris.
It is lined by ciliated epithelial cells
and
also contains mucus secreting cells called
goblet cells.
The mucus that goblet cells produce is
constantly being moved out of
the airway by the cilia.
You can see that in the video.
Underneath the epithelium is connective
tissue containing blood vessels and
smooth muscle.
Now, as we mentioned before most
respiratory viruses will be transmitted by
droplets and enter via the nose or mouth.
In this person, you can see the virus
enters the nose and
then reaches the epithelial surface.
If the virus is lucky enough to not be
cleared by the cilia.
It may find a specific receptor on the
epithelial cell.
These receptors determine whether or
not the virus can enter that cell and
thus, the location of infection.
This is the concept of Tropism.
Once it enters, the virus rapidly
replicates in the cytosol because RNA
viruses are ready to make protein.
One of the first thing it does is to
enslave that cell to be a virus factory.
So, for example, Rhinovirus closes the
nuclear pores and
shuts down host cells' transcription, so
that epithelial cell will use all of its
machinery to make virus.
Now as the infection progresses, viruses
will spread to neighbouring,
unaffected cells, effecting more of the
epithelial lining.
Infected cells begin to sense the foreign
invaders,
by detecting pathogen associated molecular
patterns, or PAMPs.
This represents the beginning of innate
immune defense.
The infected epithelial cells send signals
to try and stop the infection.
The signals include secretion of
Interferon, other cytokines, and
chemokines, to recruit immune cells into
the local area, which then extravisate.
These cytokines and chemokines also
stimulate mucus production and release.
All of this results in increases in
vascular permeability,
which cause swelling of the walls of the
airway,
it increases inflammatory cell
infiltration into the interstitial tissue,
and it fills up the airway lumen with
mucus and cellular debris.
What the patient notices is a lot of
swelling, mucus and debris.
In order to exit,
viruses need to be released back into the
lumen of the airway.
Non-enveloped viruses, or naked capsids,
exit cells by lysing the cell.
Virions then enter into the environment
within mucus secretions and droplets.
Now you can see in these two images, that
the airway of the infected person has
a lot more swelling and mucus, compared to
the non infected person.
I would like you to try and
remember this process of how respiratory
viruses cause disease.
Because now, I'm going to show how this
pathogenesis explains the clinical
syndromes of each virus, using our
anatomic framework.
What we just talked about, in this series
of slides on pathogenesis is depicted very
well in this Rhinoscopic picture.
It's a nasal cavity of a person with a
respiratory virus infection.
And I think, you can
easily see that this person's nasal
turbinates are really swollen.
And there's some clear secretions oozing
out.
The swelling in this nasal cavity could
also extend into the nasopharynx and
the eustachian tube that connects to the
middle ear.
This can result in ear pain and a viral
Otitis media.
The two viruses that cause the common cold
or
rhinitis, are Rhinovirus and Coronavirus.
These viruses colonize a person
asymptomatically for two to three days.
This is called, the incubation period.
When the innate immune system, recognizes
that we are infected with
either Rhinovirus or Coronavirus, we get
mild symptoms of a common cold.
But fever and systemic symptoms are not
common.
Although they usually cause mild disease,
there are certain situations where they
can cause Lower Respiratory Tract
problems,
especially in people with pre-existing
lung problems.
People who smoke, or el, elderly patients
might have more problems.
Immunocompromised patients are at
increased risk of more severe disease,
including pneumonia.
I take care of a number of children, who
are immunocompromised at our hospital.
So I can tell you first-hand that
respiratory viral infections in
these children can progress to the point
that they need hospitalization in
an Intensive Care Unit because they're so
sick.
I very actively educate our providers and
parents to not ignore a cold in these
particular children.
Here's an image of the Baltimore
classification scheme.
And both Rhinovirus and Chronovirus are
RNA viruses and fall here in group four.
RNA viruses are ready to make protein and
thus can quickly replicate in the cytosol
to make new vir, virions.
This is why they cause such an acute
infection.
Although, these two viruses have many
similarities,
they're actually different viruses.
There are hundreds of serotypes for
Rhinovirus but only six serogroups for
Coronavirus.
Rhinovirus is a naked capsid,
which allows them to be more resistant to
desiccation and to detergents.
The capsid however, can be destroyed in
the low pH of their stomach.
And this is very different from the other
viruses that Rhinoviruses are related to
in this family Picornaviridae.
Polio virus, Enterovirus, Coxackievirus,
and Hepatits A virus all survive stomach
acid and replicate in the gastrointestinal
tract.
Now, the name of this family may help you
remember this virus.
Think of it, as PICO RNA, a very small
RNA.
In contrast to the naked capsid
Rhinovirus,
Cronavirus has an envelope, which means it
is
relatively more susceptible to desiccation
of detergents in the environment.
The name Coronavirus comes from the
spike-like of proteins that
create a crown appearance.
And you can see this crown appearance in
the image on the slide.
Corona means crown.
In the family of Coronaviridae there are
two new emerging viruses.
Severe Acute respiratory Syndrome or
SARS Coronavirus, and Middle East
respiratory Syndrome, or MERS Coronavirus.
Prior to SARS,
Coronavirus infections in humans were
thought to just be common colds.
But in 2003, a respiratory infection
outbreak started in China,
and quickly spread to the rest of the
world via travelers.
It was eventually figured out to be SARS
and
this particular Coronavirus caused
significant mortality.
The case fatality rate was about 10%
overall.
Goes up to 50% in the elderly.
I still remember this outbreak vividly.
This was an exciting and
frightening time for me and other
infectious disease doctors.
At the time many of us suspected that the
outbreak was the start of
the influenza pandemic that we'd all been
waiting for.
But no one knew what it was and how bad it
was going to be.
I distinctly remember the fear and dread
of just not knowing.
And the fact that doctors had been
infected by their patients and
some had died made things even worse.
During this outbreak, I had to take care
of one little boy who had just come
back from China with this family.
He had a fever and a mild cough.
He ended up not having SARS infection but
of course they didn't know that at the
time.
I must confess I had a bit of fear going
into see my patient.
You can imagine that I paid very close
attention to how I put on and
took off my protective gear.
Now, this outbreak was a good lesson to me
and
should be a good lesson to you that
emerging viral infections will occur.
We need to all be vigilant.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
A current outbreak of a new emerging viral
infection is MERS Coronavirus,
first reported in 2012.
It's case fatality rate is even higher
than SARS at 40% but
it hasn't spread as fast.
Interestingly, both are zoonosis.
SARS was eventually found to have it's
natural reservoir in bats.
For MERS, there is some recent evidence
that camels can transmit the virus to
humans but the actual natural reservoir is
still not known.
The next clinical syndrome to discuss is
Pharyngitis and Laryngitis.
These are predominantly caused by
Adenovirus, and Parainfluenza virus.
Adenovirus typic,
typically causes a prominent fever in
addition to the pharyngitis.
The tonsils and the adenoids are right
behind the pharyngeal tissue that you
can see in this picture.
In fact, the name of the virus comes from
adenoids, adeno.
The tonsil and
adenoids are also the location where the
Adenovirus can persist for a long time.
I told you before, I take care of many of
these immunocompromised patients.
And they can reactivate their Adenovirus.
More often than not, it causes really
severe disease in these patients and
I typically give them treatment early and
quickly.
Adenovirus can also cause conjunctivitis.
And you can see this in the picture of
this eye.
The conjunctiva are completely injected
and red.
Now, both the pharyngitis and
conjunctivitis are caused by similar
process of pathogenesis that I described
to you at the beginning of the video.
As I already mentioned, Adenovirus can be
especially deadly in
immunocompromised hosts, unlike other
respiratory viruses Adenovirus can go
beyond the epithilialium, and actually
cause a systemic infection.
This can be with viremia, hepatitis, and
other in organ disease.
This may be why immunecompromised hosts
get so sick.
Adenovirus is characterized by more than
50 serotypes.
Only, although, only a portion of these
cause respiratory symptoms.
Unlike the other respiratory viruses,
Adenovirus can cause Gastrointestinal
disease.
The other difference is that Adenovirus is
the only DNA respiratory virus.
Now, like other naked capsid viruses,
they are relatively hardy against
desiccation detergents.
Adenovirus can also travel and transit
through the gastrointestinal tract, and
transmits by the fecal-oral route.
The cartoon that you see of Adenovirus
shows the capsid in blue.
The red spikes are called fiber proteins
and the globular end attaches the virus to
the host cell receptor in the tight
junctions that join cells.
In the Adenoviridae family, there are no
other viruses that infect humans but
there are many viruses in this family that
can infect other animals and
are species specific.
The other virus that can cause Pharyngitis
is Parainfluenza virus.
Parainfluenza virus is also the typical
virus that causes Croup.
And although, I've listed this in the
lower respiratory track,
I'm going to discuss Parainfluenza virus
and Croup here.
Croup is quite distinctive and it's
because of its cough.
It is a barking cough associated with
inspiratory stridor.
Here's what it sounds like.
[SOUND] Fever and
hoarseness are also quite common.
The cough improves if you take the child
outside in the cold air.
Croup is quite common in the fall in,
in contrast to many of the respiratory
viruses that peak in the winter.
There are four types of Parainfluenza, and
type one is most often impli, implicated
with Croup.
Parainfluenza virus buds out of the cell
only at the apical surface,
where it then infects neighboring cells.
This is likely why we rarely see viremia.
Because it buds out of the cell,
Parainfluenza doesn't cause cell death
like Rhinovirus, but
it does increase the replication rate of
epithelial cells so more cells are shed.
It increases the number of mucus cells,
increasing mucus production and
it also decreases cilary motility.
All this together increases cellular
debris, mucous, and
swelling all along the wall of the
trachea.
The subglottic area of the trachea is
already narrow in children, so
even a small amount of swelling and
mucous will more easily cause Stenosis in
this area and cause the classic symptoms.
Here's a picture of what the su,
Subglottic Stenosis looks, like on
radiograph.
You can see the narrowing of that region.
This radiographic sign is called the
Steeple sign.
For the most part though, Croup is a
clinical diagnosis not a Radiographic one.
Parainfluenza virus is an RNA virus like
most of the respiratory viruses.
However, it's enveloped which is different
from some of the other RNA viruses.
It has four serotypes and their clinical
manifestations can vary.
Reinfections are common.
And this could be a result of the virus
budding from the apical surface of
the cell not allowing a chance for the
immune cells to appropriately respond.
I should point out, that Parainfluenza
virus is not related to influenza virus.
Parainfluenza virus is actually in the
family Paramyxoviridae.
And you can see that in this family there
are two other respiratory viruses.
RSV, Respiratory Syncytial Virus and
Metapneumovirus.
We will be discussing these two viruses in
depth in the video on
lower respiratory tract infections.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This next slide is for you as a resource.
So that you can review this material
later.
[BLANK_AUDIO]