Welcome students, this is a video K-M part
one How to draw Kaplan-Meier Curves,
K-M stands for Kaplan-Meier.
Of course, you're very unlikely to need to
draw Kaplan-Meier curves yourself, and
certainly software programs do this for
you given the data, but you need to know.
How the data are actually converted into a
Kaplan-Meier curve intige,
in order to truly understand what a
Kaplan-Meier curve does so
we're going to take you through it I hope
your not too nervous the math won't be
too hard because we're only going to do a
very small clinical trial.
So, here's our clinical trial.
The clinical trial is a study in which we
are interested in survival after
surgery for pancreatic cancer and what
kind of survival are we talking about?
We're talking about overall survival.
We're, we're not going to ask why the
patient died.
We're only going to ask is the patient
alive or dead.
And we're going to measure it in time and
it just so
happens that our measurement in time will
be over the course of months,
because pancreatic cancer is a pretty
dismal tumor and lots of people die.
So here we go.
Now, what we're going to do is we're
going to start enrolling patients,
with the first surgery that I perform as a
surgeon.
But I dont operate on ten patients, all in
the same day.
The patients will get operated on in a
spaced out way and I may not be willing
to wait until every last patient has died
before I write my paper up because
I may have some interesting results that I
want to share before that point.
And in the case of some clinical trials
which,
in which you are going to measure survival
in say five years you don't and
you're accumulating the patients over a
five year interval,
you don't want to wait ten years before
you publish it.
Because if you started the trial on year 1
and you enrolled the patients for
the next five years,
you're going to have to wait at least 10
years before you can analyze it.
So Kaplan-Meier has a way of getting
around that and also it, as you'll see
it's a way of dealing with incomplete
information in a very clever manner.
So here's our clinical trial.
We've got ten patients and the first
interval that we're interested in looking
at is the interval from 0 to 1 month.
And the reason were going to look at the
interval from zero to one
month is two patients happened to die at
the end of that interval.
So during that interval from zero to
one month no patients were censored, we'll
talk about censoring later.
And we did talk about it in class, but at
the end of the interval,
there were 10 patients left and there were
two deaths, okay?
So, at the very beginning of course,
Kaplan-Meier curve shows 100% survival.
At the end, two patients die so the curve
is going to come down a certain amount.
And one patient, one patient died,
from surgical complications, from surgery.
[NOISE] one died from complications of the
pancreatic cancer.
It does kill very quickly, okay.
And as a result, the curve will drop down.
Now, how much will the curve drop down?
Well at, at this point that we're talking
about,
there are 10 patients at risk, and 2 died.
So 2 out of 10 patients, died.
And the percent surviving, is 8 out of 10.
So, the percent surviving is 80%.
All right, good.
So, we've got 80% and now we follow that
out.
The next interval will be from one month
to four months.
Now, it turns out in that interval nobody
died.
The reason we pick one month to format
this because there was one death,
at the end of that interval.
But, several other things happened.
Now, at this point
at the two month mark, one patient showed
up to clinic.
At the two month part, but never came to
clinic again and
we don't know what happened to them, we
made phone calls and so on.
So that patient is lost to follow-up, lost
to follow-up, alright.
We can't say whether or
not that patient lived or died after two
months, our information is incomplete.
However, we do know that, that patient did
not die up to the two month mark and
that's valuable information.
So, we don't want to throw that patient
out.
[COUGH] In addition, we'll have another
patient here, okay.
Who entered the study three months ago.
Enrolled three months ago.
Okay, we're writing the paper now.
But we did the surgery, three months
before.
So that patient we know, survived after
three months.
But we're not really, willing to wait
linger, before something happens.
All we know is that patient still, at the
three month mark, was still alive.
We don't know anything after that and
you'll notice that at the beginning of the
study we had eight patients left, okay.
And four were censored one lost a follow
up, one that enrolled three months ago.
Another one that enrolled three and
a half months ago and say another patient
lost a follow up, okay.
Some censoring events.
Now of course less the follow up and so
on they tend to get lost to follow up as
you get further and
further out because say this one, this one
wasn't really lost to fall up.
This one may have, I mentioned very
quickly that this one
enrolled three and a half months ago.
This one moved to
England, okay?
This patient moved, she had pancreatic
cancer and
wanted to move to be closer to her family.
She had, she had children who had moved to
England and she wanted to move there too.
But because we saw her at this point but
never saw her again and really, she, she,
she was in, no longer in any communication
and we don't know what happened to her.
She's also censored.
Now at this point, at the end of this
interval from one to four months.
There are four p, patients at risk, one
dies.
So, the survival at that point is three
out of four patients were still alive for
75% survival at that interval.
So from this point down, we have to have
75% of 80%, or 60%.
So at that point, we have 60% survival.
And this patient right there,
one, died from pancreatic cancer.
All right and then we move out.
Now we have three patients left, okay?
We're going to have another patient who's
censored at this point.
One patient censored.
That patient entered the study six months
ago.
Enrolled six months ago.
Okay, only followed for
six months and then we go out to eight
months and something else happened.
Okay, so at the end here at the end of six
months we have two patients left,
because we started out with three.
We, we have one, who was censored.
We ended up with two, two patients left
and then one patient dies.
And then the number of patients at risk is
two, one died, so that's
an overall survival for that interval,
survi, survival of that interval of 50%.
So we go from 60% down to 30%, okay?
And that patient,
that patient died in a car accident.
[NOISE] And you'll say,
wait a minute that's not very fair.
It looks like, it looks like it's
impacting survival after surgery.
But remember, we're only,
we've specified that we're going to look
at overall survival.
So, we have to, we have to just measure
whether patients are alive or
dead, and that's overall survival.
All we know, and all we know is that it
looks like a big effect because,
at that point, there were only two
patients at risk and
one died, happened to die in a car
accident, which is an unlikely event.
But there are many possible unlikely
events and if we
had a bigger study this wouldn't have much
of an impact, but we have a small study.
So at the end of that interval, we have
one patient left.
There's no censoring that goes on.
There's one patient at the end.
No deaths at the end and so, the last
patient's there and we're done.
So the overall survival that we have from
this
study is shown as a Kaplan-Meier curve,
okay.
Thank you very much.