Welcome students.
This is the video K-M Part 1: How to draw
Kaplan-Meier curves.
K-M stands for Kaplan-Meier.
Of course, you're very unlikely to need to
draw Kaplan-Meier curves yourself, and
certainly the software programs do this
for you given the data, but
you need to know how the data are actually
converted into a Kaplan-Meier curve and
to, in order to truly understand what a
Kaplan-Meier curve does.
So we're going to take you through it.
I hope you're not too nervous,
the math won't be too hard because we're
only going to do a small clinical trial.
So here's our clinical trial, the clinic
trial is a study in
which we're interested in the survival
after surgery for pancreatic cancer.
And what kind of survival are we talking
about?
We're talking about overall survival.
We're, we're not going to ask why the
patient died.
We're only going to ask is the patient
alive or dead?
And we're going to measure it in time.
And it just so
happens that our measurement in time will
be over the course of months,
because pancreatic cancer is a pretty
dismal tumor and lots of people die.
So here we go.
Now, [COUGH] what we're going to do is
we're going to
start enrolling patients with the first
surgery I perform as a surgeon but
I don't operate on ten patients all on the
same day.
The patients will get operated on in a
spaced out way.
And I may not be willing to wait until
every last
patient has died before I write my paper
up because I may have
some interesting results that I want to
share before that point.
And in the case of some clinical trials
which,
in which you were going to measure
survival in say five years, you don't, and
you're accumulating the patients over a
five year interval.
You don't want to wait ten years before
you publish it.
Because if you started the trial on year
one and you enrolled the patients for
the next five years,
you're going to have to wait at least ten
years before you can analyze it.
So Kaplan–Meier is a way of getting around
that.
And also it, you'll, as you'll see,
it's a way of dealing with incomplete
information in a very clever manner.
So here's our clinical trial.
We've got 10 patients, and the first
interval that we're interested in looking
at is interval from zero to one month.
And the reason we're going to look at the
interval from zero to one
month is two patients happen to die at the
end of that interval.
So during that interval from zero to one
month, no patients were censored,
we'll talk about censoring later, and we
did talk about it in class.
But at the enter to the interval there
were ten patients left and
there were two deaths.
Okay?
So, at the very beginning of course,
Kaplan-Meier curve shows 100% survival.
At the end, two patients died.
So the curve is going to come down a
certain amount.
And one patient, one patient died
from surgical complications, from surgery.
And one died, from complications of the
pancreatic cancer.
It does kill very quickly.
Okay.
And as a result, the curve will drop down.
Now, how much will the curve drop down?
Well, at, at this point that we're talking
about,
there are ten patients at risk and two
died.
So, two out of ten patients died.
And the percent surviving is eight out of
ten.
So, the percent surviving is 80%.
All right, good.
So, we've got 80% and now we follow that
out.
The next interval will be from one month
to four months.
Now, it turns out in that interval nobody
died.
The reason we pick one to four month is
because there was one death
at the end of that interval.
But several other things happened.
Now at this point,
at the two month mark, one patient showed
up to clinic at the two-month part,
but never came to clinic again.
And we don't know what happened to them.
We made phone calls and so on.
So that patient is lost to follow-up, lost
to follow up, all right?
We can't say whether or not that patient
lived or died after two months.
Our information's incomplete.
However, we do know that that patient did
not die up two month mark, and
that's valuable information.
So we don't want to throw that patient
out.
[COUGH] In addition, we'll have another
patient here.
Okay?
Who entered the study three months ago.
Enrolled three months ago.
Okay, we're writing the paper now.
But we did the surgery three months
before.
So that patient we know survived after
three months, but
we're not willing, willing to wait longer
before something happens.
All we know is that patient still at the
three month mark, was still alive.
We don't know anything after that.
And you'll notice that at the beginning of
the study we had eight patients left,
okay, and four were censored.
One lost a follow up, one that enrolled
three months ago, and
another one that enrolled three and a half
months ago.
And say, another patient lost to
follow-up.
Okay?
Some censoring events.
Now, of course, lost a follow-up and so
on they tend to get lost to follow-up as
you get further and
further out, because say, this one, this
one wasn't really lost to follow-up.
This one may have I mentioned very
quickly, that this one enrolled-
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Three and a half months ago.
This one moved to England.
Okay?
This patient knew she had pancreatic
cancer and
wanted to move to be closer to her family.
She had, she had children who had moved to
England, and she wanted to move there too.
But because we saw her at this point, but
never saw her again, and
really she, she was no longer in any
communication.
We don't know what happened to her, she's
also censored.
Now at this point at the end of this
interval from one
to four months there are four patients at
risk.
One dies.
So, the survival at that point is three
out of four patients were still alive for
75% survival at that interval.
So from this point down we have to have
75% of 80%, or 60%.
So, at that point we have 60% survival.
And this patient right there,
one, died from pancreatic cancer.
All right.
And then we move out.
Now we have three patients left, okay?
We're going to have another patient who's
censored at this point.
One patient censored.
That patient entered the study six months
ago.
Enrolled six months ago.
Okay?
Only followed for
six months, and then we go out to eight
months and something else happened.
Okay, so, at the end here, at the end of
six months we have two patients left,
because we started out with three.
We, we have one who is censored.
We ended up with two, two patients left.
And then, one patient dies.
And then the number of patient at risk is
two, one died.
So, that's an overall survival for that
interval, a sur-,
survival of that interval, of 50%.
So, we go from 60% down to 30%, okay?
And that patient,
that patient died in a car accident.
[SOUND]
And, you'll say, wait a minute, that's not
very fair.
It looks like, it looks like is impacting
survival after surgery.
But remember, we're only,
we've specified that we're going to look
at overall survival.
So, we have to, we have to just measure
whether patients are alive or dead.
And, and that's overall survival.
All we know, and, and all we know, it's
like it looks like a big effect,
because at that point there are only two
patients at risk, and
one died, happened to died in a car
accident, which is a very unlikely event.
But there are many possible unlikely
events.
And if we had a bigger study this wouldn't
have much of an impact, but
we have a small study.
So, at the end of that interval we have
one patient left.
There's no censoring that goes on.
There's one patient at the end.
No deaths at the end and so the last
patient's there.
And we're done.
So, the overall survival that we have from
this
study is shown as a Kaplan-Meier curve.
Kay.
Thank you very much.