Good morning, students.
This is Kaplan-Meier part two, how to Read
Kaplan-Meier Curves.
For this video we are going to look at two
sets of data from,
from the actual clinical literature.
So, here we go.
This is the result of a clinical trial
comparing two chemotherapy regimens after
surgery for colon cancer.
And the two regimens are given here by the
gold and blue lines.
One, is the control arm 5FU plus
Leucavorin, and
the other is the experimental arm,
which is 5FU plus Leucavorin plus the
experimental drug, Oxaliplatin.
[COUGH]
And what is being measured here, is
disease free survival.
In other words, the patient has had
surgery and there is no evidence of
disease following surgery, but of course,
there's a a risk for recurrence.
And so the patient may have a recurrence.
So the question is,
what is the proportion of patients who are
disease-free after surgery?
And the time axis shows data up to four
years following surgery.
Now, the first thing we notice is that,
the curves are very smooth and
in fact, it's a pretty large clinical
trial.
The number of patients enrolled in the
study are shown here.
1,200 and 1,207 patients in both arms, in
each of the arms.
You see a difference between the blue and
the gold curves, and
you want to know whether that's
statistically significant,
that's given here by the p-value of
0.0034.
So, what you need to know, is what is the
p-value, well the p-value is this.
The p-value equals the probability
[SOUND] that, this result would
occur under the null hypothesis.
Null hypothesis, what is that?
The null hypothesis is, the hypothesis
that nothing is going on.
So, the p-value is 0.34%.
That there's a 0.34% likelihood that what
you see here would have occurred
with Oxaliplatin, actually having added
nothing to the 5FU and Leucavorin.
So the p-value is pretty low,
so it looks like this is highly
statistically significant.
The usual cut off for clinical trials is
that
something is significant if it has a
p-value of less than 0.05.
0.05 would be considered border line of
0.04.
So, being significantly less than that,
suggests that this is a, a,
a good clinical trial.
Now, what is the size of the benefit,
that's conferred by Oxaliplatin?
That's given by the hazard ratio.
So the hazard ratio.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Is a ratio of hazard rates
[SOUND] for the two groups.
[SOUND]
Okay?
What is the hazard here?
That hazard here is, the hazard that the
disease would recur.
And the way hazard ratio is defined, is
the convention is, the numerator
is the experimental group, and the cont,
denominator is the control group.
And the hazard ratio uses all the data
here calculated by a very clever formula
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Calculated by Cox Proportional Hazards.
[COUGH] And what Cox Proportional Hazards
does, is it makes use for
the fact that there is incomplete
information in this trial.
So, another way of looking at hazard is,
in addition to the Cox Proportional
Hazards,
you might want to explain to your patient,
say oh, what,
what are the chances that this treatment,
Oxaliplatin, which is not benign at all.
There are significant side effects with
Oxaliplatin.
Most notably pain and tingling in the
fingers and
toes which actually can become permanent
in some cases.
So, what, what is the likelihood that
you'll actually get benefit from
the Oxaliplatin, in terms of preventing
recurrence of the disease, and
you could say to the patient, well, let,
let's look at the two year mark.
And at the two year mark,
the chance that you would remain
disease-free with just 5FU and Leucavorin,
disease-free here, would be 75%.
However what would be the chance that you
would be,
remain disease free had you added the
Oxaliplatin and
that roughly here is about 80%.
So, by adding Oxaliplatin,
you increase your chances of being disease
free from 75 to 80%.
So, there's a 5% benefit here.
That means, that if you
take the Oxaliplatin there's a 5%
improvement in your disease free survival.
But there's a 95% chance that you wouldn't
have benefited at all.
In fact you, even without the Oxaliplatin,
there's a 75% chance you would remain
disease free.
And, even if you took the Oxaliplatin,
there's a 20% chance the disease would
come back anyway.
So that's another way of looking at it.
Now, moving on, let's look at a second
curve.
This is a randomized clinical trial
comparing Crizotnib against
standard chemotherapy in patients with
metastatic lung cancer.
And what, they're looking at here is
progression free survival,
and they're measuring it over a period of
months,
because the metastatic lung cancer has a
pretty dismal prognosis.
And what you can see from this clinical
trial immediately,
is that it's a much smaller clinical
trial, far fewer patients are at risk, but
the p-value is quite good 0.001.
And not only that, the hazard ratio is
0.49, again a very good number.
What you can see is at the end,
because this is a very small clinical
trial, the curves are coming together.
But we should ignore that part of the
curve,
because actually the number of patients at
risk is very small.
Now, what is progression free survival.
Progression free survival is, will measure
the survival of the patient.
The patients still alive without
progression of disease.
So, censor, censoring here would occur for
the various reasons that we discussed in
part one.
Lost a follow-up, moved away late entry
into the study or
left the study due to toxicity.
Now, the events.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The events are progression of tumor.
So that, the each event causes the curve
to drop, progression of tumor.
Okay?
That's progression free survival, but
also death and, and death from any cause,
death from cancer.
Death from toxicity of chemotherapy or
even death in a car crash.
Now [COUGH]
this is progression free survival.
Okay?
So there's another thing that we talked
about in part one overall survival.
[SOUND]
And overall survival simply uses as
events, death.
It doesn't care about progression of
tumor.
It just measures death, with other
reasons.
Obviously a whole list of reasons for
censoring, which we had gone over.
Now, there's yet another way of measuring
things, and
that's called time to progression.
Time to progression is almost, the same as
progression free survival,
but not quite, and the reason it's not
quite the same as in time to progression.
One of the reasons for censoring in
addition to all
the other reasons is that deaths are
censored.
So, death from toxicity are censored.
Now, if the patient progresses and dies as
a result of progression.
That would count.
But all other deaths are censored.
So, from the FDAs point of view, the FDA
considers overall survival to be the best.
Progression free survival to be next best.
And of course progression free survival
matures more
quickly because there are more events.
And then, time to progression, as less
desired than progression free survival.
So there you have it, a quick primer on
how to read Kaplan-Meier curves.
Thank you very much.