Good morning, students.
This is Kaplan-Meier part two.
How to read Kaplan-Meier curves.
For this video, we are going to look at
two sets of data.
From the actual clinical literature.
So here we go.
This is the result of a clinical trial
comparing two chemotherapy regimens after
surgery for colon cancer.
And the two regimens are given here by the
gold and blue lines.
One is the control arm,
5Fu, plus Leucovorin and the other is the
experimental arm
which is 5Fu plus Leucovorin plus the
experimental drug Oxaliplatin.
And what is being measure here, is
disease-free survival.
In other words, the patient has had
surgery and there is no evidence of
disease following surgery, but of course
there's a risk for recurrence.
And so the patient may have a recurrence.
So the question is,
what is the proportion of patients who are
disease-free after surgery.
And the time axis shows data up to four
years following surgery.
Now, the first thing we notice is that the
curves are very smooth.
And in fact, it's a pretty large clinical
trial.
The number of patients enrolled in the,
study are shown here, 1,200, and 1,207
patients in both of, in each of the arms.
You see a difference between the blue and
the gold curves and
you want to know whether that's
statistically significant.
That's given here by the P-value of .0034.
So what we need to know is what is the
P-value.
Well, the P-value is this,
the P-value equals the probability,
that, this result would
occur under the null hypothesis.
Null hypothesis, what is that?
The null hypothesis is, the hypothesis
that nothing is going on.
So, the P-value is, .34%, of that,
there's a .34% likelihood that what you
see here would have occur
with Oxaliplatin actually having added
nothing to the 5Fu Leucovorin, so
the P-value is pretty low so it looks like
this is highly statistically significant.
The usual cutoff for clinical trials is
that something is significant if it
has a P-value of less that .05, .05 would
be considered borderline, or .04.
So being significantly less than that
suggests that this is good clinical trial.
Now, what is the size of a benefit that's
confirmed by Oxaliplatin.
That's given by the hazard ratio so,
the hazard ratio [SOUND] is a ratio
of hazard rates [SOUND] for the two
groups.
Okay, what is the hazard here?
The hazard here, is the hazard that the
disease would recur.
And, the way hazard ratio is defined, is
the conventioning, is the numerator,
is the experimental group, and the
denominator is the control group.
And the hazard ratio uses all the data
here, calculated by a very clever formula.
Calculated by Cox Proportional Hazards.
And what Cox Proportional Hazards does is
it makes use for
the fact that there's incomplete
information in this trial.
So, another way of looking at hazard is in
addition
to the Cox proportional hazards, you might
want to explain to your patient, say what,
what are the chances that this treatment,
Oxaliplatin, which is not benign at all.
There is significant side effects with
Oxaliplatin,
most notably pain and tingling in the
fingers and
toes, which actually can become permanent
in some cases.
So, what what is the likelihood that
you'll actually get
benefit from the Oxaliplatin plan in terms
of preventing recurrence of the disease?
And you, you could say to the patient,
let's look at the two year mark, and at
the two year mark,
the chance that you would remain
disease-free with just 5Fu and Leucovorin,
the chance you would remain disease-free
here would be 75%.
[SOUND] However what would be the chance
that you would be,
remain disease-free had you added the
Oxaliplatin and
that roughly here is about 80%.
So, by adding Oxaliplatin, you increase
your
chances of being disease-free from 75% to
80%.
So there's a 5% benefit here.
That means that if you
take the Oxaliplatin, there's a 5%
improvement in your disease-free survival,
but there's a 95% chance that you wouldn't
have benefited at all.
In fact, you, even without the
Oxaliplatin,
there's a 75% chance you would remain
disease-free.
And, even if you took the Oxaliplatin,
there's a 20% chance that the disease
would come back anyway.
So that's another way of looking at it.
Now, moving on, let's look at a second
curve.
This is a randomized clinical trial
comparing Crizotinib
against standard chemotherapy in patients
with metastatic lung cancer.
And what he, there's, looking at here is
progression-free survival.
And they're measuring it over a period of
months,
because the metastatic lung cancer has a
pretty dismal prognosis.
And what you can see from this clinical
trial immediately is that
it's a much smaller clinical trial for our
fewer patients are at risk.
But the P-value is quite good, 0.001.
And not only that, the hazard ratio is
0.49, again, a very good number.
What you can see is that at the end,
because this is a very small clinical
trial, the curves are coming together.
But, we should ignore that part of the
curve,
because actually, the number of patients
at risk, is very small.
Now, what is Progression-free Survival?
Progression-free Survival is, will
measure, the survival of the patient.
The patient's still alive without
progression of disease.
So, censor, censoring here would
occur for the various reasons that we
discussed in part one.
Lost a followup, moved away.
Late entry into the study, or left the
study due to toxicity.
Now, the events are progression of tumor.
So that, each event causes the curve to
drop,
progression of tumor, okay, as
progression-free survival.
But also death.
And, and death from any cause, death from
cancer.
Death from toxicity of chemotherapy or
even death in a car crash.
Now.
[COUGH] This is progression-free survival,
okay?
So there's another thing that we talked
about in part one.
Overall survival.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And overall survival simply uses as events
death, it doesn't care about
progression of tumor, it just measures
death, with other reasons.
Obviously a whole list of reasons for
censoring, which we had gone over.
Now, there's yet another way of measuring
things, and
that's called time to progression.
Time to progression is almost the same as
progression-free survival, but not quite.
And the reason it's not quite, quite the
same as in time to progression.
One of the reasons for censoring in
addition to all the other
reasons, is that deaths are censored.
So death from toxicity are censored.
Now, if the patient progresses and dies as
a result of progression, that would count.
But all other deaths are censored.
So from the FDA's point of view.
The FDA considers overall survival to be
the best.
Progression-free survival to be next best.
Of course, regression-free survival
matures more,
quickly because there are more events.
And then, time to progression as less
desired than progression-free survival.
So, there you have it, a quick primer on
how to read Kaplan-Meier curves.
Thank you very much.