The second type of probability we can
calculate with counting method is
something where we don't have replacement.
And these are going to be things like when
you're dealing with decks of card.
Once you take a card out of a deck, it's
no longer available.
So, it's without replacement.
So, here's a simple example,
what's the probability of drawing two aces
from a standard deck of cards?
What would be the probability of drawing
two aces?
So, let's use the counting method to solve
this.
Again, there's more than one way to solve
to this, but
we're going to use the counting method
here.
So, what's the probability of drawing 2
aces?
So again, we're going to make our
demonator all the possible outcome, and
we're going to make our numerator all the
ways in which you can draw 2 aces.
So, I'm going to start with the numerator.
And literally, I'm just going to write out
how many different ways can you draw 2
aces when you draw 2 cards from a deck.
And I literally just draw them out.
So, you could get ace of clubs and ace of
diamonds.
You could get ace of clubs and ace of
hearts.
You could get ace of spades and ace of
And notice that I am counting it
differently, if it's ace of clubs, and
then ace of diamonds versus is it's ace of
diamonds, and then ace of clubs.
So, we're considering order in the
numerator right now.
We're considering the order.
The order matters.
I'm counting it differently if there, if
they have a different order.
I don't have to do that to solve this
problem, as we'll see in a minute.
But if I count order in the denominator,
I've gotta count an order in the
numerator, and vice versa.
So, for this first iteration of solving
this problem, I'm going to consider order.
So, that's the numerator.
There's 12 ways you can draw ace aces, and
literally, I've just written them out.
How about the denominator?
The denominator, turns out that there are
52 times 51
different two-card sequences that you can
draw from a deck of cards.
And again, I'm considering order here.
And why is that?
Where did I get that?
Well, you can again, draw out some kind of
tree, just like we did for the dice.
So, the first thing that can happen is I
can get any one of 52 cards.
Let's say that in the first card, I draw,
say an ace of hearts.
Okay.
If I draw an ace of hearts,
then I can enumerate all the possibilities
that are left.
Well, once I've drawn that ace of hearts,
there are only 51 cards left.
I can no longer, the ace of hearts is
gone.
So now, there is only 51 choices.
So, if I draw out all the possible two
card sequences,
once I'm on the ace of hearts branch,
then,
the all, there's only 51 possible things
that can happen after that.
So, we start with 52 branches, but
whichever branch you go down, the next
node is only going to have 51 branches.
So, you start with 52 choices.
But then, because one of them has been
lost, it's been pulled out of the deck,
there's only 51 left next.
So, the prob, the total number of
different two card sequences you draw,
you can possibly draw is going to be 52
times 51.
And notice again that if you look at all
the branches that will come out here,
the ace of hearts followed by the ace of
diamonds will be different,
a different branch, than the ace of
diamonds followed by the ace of hearts.
So again, we're considering order here.
So, the denominator here will be 52 times
51.
Then, we can just divide the numerator by
the denominator to get the probability.
So, the probability that you draw two
aces,
when you draw two cards out of a deck is
12 divided by 52 times 51.
So, that's one way to solve this problem.
Again, it's not the only way.
We can also try to solve the problem
ignoring order.
A lot of people feel like oh, I don't, why
should the order matter.
It doesn't matter for the hands that you
have in a card deck.
So, there are card games, so lets ignore
order.
So, we can solve the same thing ignoring
But if we ignore order in the numerator,
we've got to ignore order in the
denominator.
So, if I ignore order, there's actually I
can write out that's
there's 6 possible different pairs of aces
where I'm not considering order.
So, my numerator will now be 6.
For the denominator,
the only way to get rid of the order is
simply to divide out the order.
So, I'm literally going to just divide by
2 here.
Because there was 52 times 51 different 2
card sequences.
If you want to divide out all the repeats,
you just divide by 2 here.
So then, the denominator becomes 1326.
So, we can divide the 2 of those,
the numerator by the denominator to get
the probability.
Of course, it's the same probability that
we got when we considered order.
We're, we're hopping to get the same
probability no matter how we
approach the problem.
I'm just going to throw.
Okay.
There's one more way to solve this.
As you can see,
probability is tricky because there may be
multiple ways to get the same answer.
So, here's another way that you can get
the right answer, and this way's
probably the way that most people find the
easiest, but is something that we're
going to be talking about more in Module 2
than in this particular module.
So, this is not a counting method, but
rather,
you could just say look at it this way.
What's the probability of drawing an ace
on the first draw?
Well, that's 4 out of 52.
.We calculated that before.
So, you can calculate that probability.
And then, you can ask, well, now that I've
drawn an ace on the first draw,
what's the probability of drawing an ace
again, a second event?
Well, once you've drawn one ace outta the
deck,
now you're down to 51 total cards in the
deck and only 3 aces.
So, the probability that you draw an ace
on the second draw as well,
is now 3 out of 51.
It's different because something already
happened.
You could say the the probability of
drawing an ace on the first draw is
4 out of 52.
The probability of also drawing an ace on
the second draw is 3 out of 51.
And we could just multiply those together
because in probably and means multiply.
So, the probability of both of those
things happening to calculate that,
you're going to multiply those together.
So, notice that when you multiply those
together you get
the same exact probability as we got
before, 12 divided by 52 times 51.
So, it doesn't matter which way you
approach this,
there's multiple ways to get the same
answer.
And again, we're going to talk more about
using this multiplication rule,
multiplying probabilities together in
Module 2.
This is technically not a, a counting
method that we've done here.