Some other empirical probabilities which
are interesting to look at,
we have really good data in the US on
cancer.
And so, we can say things like,
what's the probability that a US male will
develop cancer in his lifetime.
It turns out to be 44.8%, so that's pretty
high, right?
The probability then a man dies from
cancer is 23.1%.
We can also look at the statistics for
individual cancers.
The probability that a man develops
prostate,
prostate cancer in his lifetime is at
16.2%.
So, about a third of all those cancers
that men
are developing are prostate cancers.
And by the way, the,
the, the overall probability of cancer
does not include non-melanoma skin cancer.
So, this is excluding non-melanoma skin
cancer.
Notice though, that the probability of
developing prostate cancer, 16%.
But the probability of dying from prostate
cancer is much, much lower.
That tells you a lot of those prostate
cancers are not killing the men.
Compare that to lung cancer.
So, the probability for
a man of developing lung cancer in the US
in his lifetime is 7.8%.
The probability from dying from lung
cancer however is 6.7%.
Those are very close.
So, most people who get lung cancer are
dying from it.
We can see the same statistics for women.
Interestingly, women have slightly lower
chances of getting cancer or
dying from cancer.
38% and 19%.
That's largely because of smoking and
drinking.
More men smoke and drink, and those are
linked to cancer.
Breast cancer is the most common cancer
for women.
Her lifetime risk of getting breast cancer
is 12 point 12%.
But her lifetime risk of dying from breast
cancer is much lower.
Only 2.8%, sort of similar to the prostate
cancer for men.
In contrast, a woman's lifetime risk of
developing lung cancer is 6.4%,
slightly lower than for the men.
But that's, that gap is narrowing as more
women are smoking relative to man.
And her probability of dying from lung
cancer is 5%.
So again, it's a very,
lung cancer is a very deadly cancer,
compared with breast cancer.
So now, let's do some actual calculations
of some theoretical probabilities.
I'm going to show you a few examples of
how to use what
are called the counting methods for
calculating probability.
These apply when you have situations where
all the outcomes are equally likely.
And we're literally going to be counting
up all possible outcomes.
And we're going to be
counting the ones that fulfill the event
that we're interested in.
And so, literally that's why it's called
the counting method.
Things that have equally likely outcomes
are things like cards.
When you draw a card out of deck of card,
all the cards have an equal likelihood of
being picked.
Or, if you're rolling the dice,
all the sides of the dice have an equal
likelihood of coming up.
So, these counting methods are for this
type of situation.
So, let's just practice these.
Again, these, I think these are fun to
calculate.
So, they're great for gambling too.
So, a lot of, you know, if you really want
to know how to calculate poker
probabilities, you need to know the
counting methods.
If, again, if the outcomes are equally
likely to occur, we,
we say is that the probability of A
occurring?
You're, you're going to put in the
denominator,
you're going to count out the total number
of possible outcomes.
And then, you're going to put in the
numerator out of all those total number of
outcomes, which of those outcomes includes
A occurring?
So, we're literally going to count those
out,
both in the numerator and the denominator.
And these counting methods are pretty
challenging.
They're also sometimes called permutations
and combinations.
Some of you may have done these before.
Most people find them to be pretty
challenging.
I'm just going to, in this module, give
you a few basic examples.
If you want to delve into more details,
there's an optional module which will go
further into the counting methods.
So, here's the first example.
We're going to calculate the following
probabilities.
And note that all of these are what we
call with replacement examples.
So, when you roll a die, if you roll a die
once and
you get a six, and then you roll the die
again, you can still get a six again.
If you roll the die again, you can get a
six again.
So, all your outcomes are allowed to
repeat.
This is in contrast to something like, if
you've got a deck of cards.
If you draw the red you know, the ace of
diamonds out of the deck,
if somebody's already drawn that card, it
doesn't repeat.
There isn't another ace of diamonds in the
deck.
So, that would be without replacement.
But things like dice and coins have
replacement.
You can keep rolling heads.
You can keep rolling sixes.
So, what's the probability of getting one
six when you roll a die?
So, that one's not too hard.
So, again, we're going to use the counting
methods here.
So, think about what's my numerator and
what's my denominator.
So, how many possible outcomes are there
when you roll a die?
So there's six possible outcomes.
One, two, three, four, five, or six,
that's our denominator.
How many outcomes are there that involve
getting a six?
Well, there's only one way you can get a
six, right?
So, there's one six out of six, so the
probability here is one out of six.
So, that one's pretty straight forward.
The second question is what's the
probability of getting two sixes when you
roll 2 dice or you roll, you know,
the same dice twice what's the probability
that you're going to get 2 sixes?
So, this one is slightly more challenging.
I want to start with the, again, the
counting method way of solving this.
There's actually more than one way to
solve this, I'll show you both.
That's one of the, the hard things about
probability is.
There is many ways you can get the right
answer.
So, it's often tricky to know which one is
the, is the most efficient.
So, let's start with the counting method,
though.
So, what's the probability of getting two
sixes when rolling two dice?
So, our denominator here is going to be
all possible outcomes that can occur,
when I roll two dice.
So, what can happen when I roll two dice?
Well, let's draw out a little tree to help
us with this.
So, when I roll a die once, there are six
possible outcomes,
each with equal likelihood of occurring.
Those outcomes are you going to get a 1, a
2, a 3, a 4, a 5, or a 6.
So that any of those can occur on the
first roll.
Whatever happens on the first roll,
I'm allowed on the second roll to have all
of these repeat.
I can get a 1, a 2, a 3, a 4, a 5, a 6.
So, let's say I get a 1 in the first roll.
Then, I could get a 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, or 6 on
the second roll.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, or 6.
If I toll a 5 on the first roll, roll of
the die,
I could again get 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, or 6 on
the second roll.
You can draw out these little trees just
to kind of help you enumerate all
the possibilities.
I'm not going to draw out the full tree
here, but you start to get the idea there.
Six possibilities on the first roll.
There are six possibilities on the second
roll, because everything repeats.
So, if you drew or
drew out all these branches, you have to
make all the possible branches here.
You would could that there are 36
branches.
Well, how do we get that?
There are 6 possibilities on the first
roll,
times another 6 possibilities on the
second roll.
So, my denominator will be 36 here.
There are 36 possible outcomes when I roll
two dice.
And I'll just point out here that notice
when I'm counting, here's 1, 1, here's 1,
2, somewhere down another branch, we'll
have the outcome 2, 1.
So, I'm counting getting a 1 first and a 2
second as different than
getting a 2 first and then a one second.
That means that we're, what, we call in
probability considering order.
And all you have to know is that if you
consider order in the denominator,
you're going to consider it in the
numerator.
So, you have to be consistent.
So, there's 36 possible outcomes here.
How many of those outcomes involve getting
2 sixes?
Well, there's only one way you can get 2
sixes.
You have to get a six and you have to get
a six again.
There's only 1 branch if you did the
entire tree.
So that probabilities going to be 1 out of
36.
Finally, what's the probability of getting
a sum of 6 when rolling two dice?
So, what is, what I mean by sum of 6, so
that is you roll 2 dice.
And what's the probability that if you add
up the values from both of
those rules that that value will equal 6.
So, notice that our denominator is going
to be the same here.
There are 36 possible things that can
happen when you roll two dice.
So, the denominator is the same.
But to get the numerator here, there's no
way
to get the numerator other than just to
count out all the ways that you can get 6.
You can get a 6 by rolling a 1 and then a
5.
You can get a 6 by rolling a 5 and then a
1.
You can get a 6 by rolling a 3 and a 3.
You can get 6 by rolling a 2 and a 4, or
by rolling a 4 and 2.
So again, that the numbers on both of dice
have to add up to 6.
Those are all the possible you should get
a sum of 6.
I've enumerated them.
I've written them out.
There is five of them.
So, the probability of getting a sum of 6
is 5 out of 36.
And notice, to solve the, the numerator in
this particular problem,
there wasn't any formula I could rely on.
There's no formula I can give you.
You just literally have to think it out.
And again, that's what's really
challenging about probability problems,
is that I can't give you a pat formula
that works for everything.
In all of the problems, you really have to
think about the problem, what's going on.
And that's the great part about it,
because it really makes your brain work.
But students find that challenging,
because they want me to just give them
some kind of formula they can plug into.
Well, that's not going to be the case
here.
You're actually going to have to really
think.
So, that's the first type of example.
This is with a replacement, the dice can
repeat.