The final example that I wanted to review
is what's called a combination.
So this is where we are going to stop
considering order,
formally stop considering order, that's
called a combination.
And combinations are really good for
things like solving,
what's your probability of winning the
lottery?
The lottery is one of my favorite things
to talk about in statistics because
it's a little counter-intuitive and a
lottery, so, a typical lottery,
here's one type of lottery, and one of the
common lotteries works by picking,
you pick six numbers from 1 to 49.
So you can imagine you've got a little
punch card and they,
it has all the numbers from 1 to 49, and
you get to punch any six of them.
So there is no replacement here.
You can't pick the same number twice.
So you're picking six numbers from 1 to 49
without replacement.
And order doesn't matter.
It doesn't matter if you pick them in any
particular order.
You're you just want to get the right set
of six.
You want to match the set of six
[INAUDIBLE] the lottery authorities get.
So what's your probability of winning that
particular lottery?
So for the numerator, we're going to say
how many ways you can win?
Well, there's only one way you can win.
You have to match all six numbers, so
there's only one way you can win.
In the denominator, we have to count out
how many different sets of six
numbers can you get when you're
considering the integers from 1 to 49.
And it feels like, most people feel sort
of intuitively like, well,
there's 49 numbers, 1 to 49, and you get
to pick six of them.
You kind of feel like you're, you're
covering a lot of the space, right,
6 out of 49 doesn't seem that small.
You're picking six numbers out of 49.
But, in fact, how many combinations,
how many sets of six numbers are possible
here?
The answer is rather surprising.
In order to be able to calculate that
answer,
we actually need to know something called
the combinations formula.
If you want to know more about where this
formula comes from, and
you want to see the derivation in is,
you're going to have to watch the optional
module that goes into that in detail.
But, there's a function out there called
the choosing function.
And, what the choosing function does is it
says,
if you've got a situation where you have a
set of n objects, you want to
say how many different possible sets of r
of them can you form?
That is a choosing function, it's n choose
r.
And we write it with this parentheses with
the, the n,
the, the total set, at the top and the r,
the smaller set on the bottom.
So if I have r objects taken from a set of
n objects without replacement and
ignoring order, this is a combination.
If I want to know how many different
samples,
how many different sets are possible,
that's an n choose r function.
And you have an n choose r function.
It's just a mathematical function, so what
you do, is you apply this formula.
It's n factorial.
Divided by n minus r factorial times r
factorial.
So that answers the question.
If I've got 49 numbers to choose from and
I want to say how many different
set of six numbers are, are, I can draw,
from within those 49 numbers.
I can just apply the choosing function.
So this will work for solving this lottery
question, and
it works generally, anytime I've got this
same situation, n choose r.
So, let's actually apply it to the lottery
question.
So this take 49 choose 6, function.
How many different combinations of 6
numbers can be formed from those 49
integers, it's a 49 choose 6.
So I just apply the combinations formula,
49 factorial divided by 49-6 or
43 factorial, then divided by 6 factorial.
And we can just do out the factorials
here.
We can do out the numbers and
surprisingly, it turns out,
that 49 choose 6 is almost 14 million.
In other words, there are almost
14,000,000 different
sets of 6 numbers that you can derive from
just the 49 integers.
There's 14 million different combinations
that can come out in the lottery.
So, of course, that means that your
probability of winning the lottery
is one out of almost 14 million.
This is a good argument for not bothering
to play the lottery.
We're going to talk more about the lottery
as well, next week.
But your probability is really, really
surprisingly small.
I'm actually very happy that the
probability that my probability of
winning the lottery is extremely small
like this.
My philosophy on it is, I'm glad there are
really great things in life that
are attached to a very, very small
probability because it turns out there
are also some really horrible, horrible
things in life that are also attached to
extremely, extremely small probabilities.
For example, your probability of dying in
a commercial airline crash is about one in
14 million as well.
So I'm really extremely glad that I'm not
going to win the lottery because that's
the only that I can be confident enough to
get on an airplane is that I know my,
I'm very confident and I'm not going to
win the lottery,
so I can be confident that my airplane is
not going to crash.
So I'm glad for very very very small
probabilities like this.