In this next module, I'm going to show you
how to calculate some basic probability.
So first of all, what is probability?
So, probability is the chance that an
uncertain event will occur.
And it's always a number between 0 and 1.
You can't have anything lower than a 0%
chance,
you can't have anything higher than a 100%
chance.
I am going to be using a few symbols this
week.
They're really just a shorthand to make it
faster to write things.
So, let me just review these symbols now.
So, when I want to write the probability
of something happening,
like the probability that event A will
occur.
I'm going to shorthand that by writing a
P, and
then I'm going to write a parenthesis.
And put in the parenthesis whatever I want
to know the probability of.
So, like P(A), you would read that as the
probability that event A will occur.
And again, this is just a shorthand.
It just makes it faster for
me to write these things down and do some
calculations.
An example would be if I put P (red card),
I would be asking for
the probability of a red card.
Say when you're pulling cards out of a
deck,
what's the probability of getting a red
card.
I'm going to use the little symbol tilde
to represent not,
the probability of something not
happening.
We also will sometimes call this the
complement.
So, if I put probability P tilde A,
that's the probability of not getting a
event event A.
And here's an example.
Like if I put P tilde red A card, that's
the probability of not getting a red card.
Again, it's just a short hand.
Also show you what are called some joint
probabilities,
like the probability of A and the B.
That's the probability that both things
will occur together.
So, this will be something like the
probability of getting a red
card and an ace.
In other words, the probability of getting
a red ace,
both of those things happening at the same
time.
That's called the joint probability, and I
represent that with an ampersand.
So, let's do a couple of examples.
So, let's say you draw one card from a
standard deck of cards.
Let's say that the deck of cards doesn't
have any jokers.
For all the problems this week you can
assume that there's no jokers involved,
just a standard deck of 52 cards.
What's the probability that you draw an
ace?
So, how would you solve that?
So, you have to think about the way cards
work.
So if you've got a standard deck, there's
52 cards.
There are four aces in a deck, so
the probability that you would draw an ace
would be 4 out of 52.
You then, the denominator is the total
number of cards.
There's 4 that are aces, so 4 out of 52,
that's probably about 7.7%.
Again, I've used the P parenthesis to
shorthand the probability of
drawing an ace.
Let's do a few more examples.
So, let's say that event A is drawing a
red card and event B is drawing an ace.
So what is, for
example, the probability of A, what's the
probability of drawing a red card?
So, if I have a standard deck of cards
with 52 cards,
half of the cards are red and half are
black.
So, there's 26 red cards out of a total of
52 cards.
So, the probability of A, the probability
of drawing a red card, would be 1 half, or
26 out of 52.
What's the probability of drawing an ace?
Well, we just actually calculated that.
That's 4 out of 52.
And we can simplify that down to 1 out of
13.
One out of 13 cards in a deck is an ace.
What's the probability of not drawing a
red card?
So, the probability of not drawing of
drawing a red card would be
the probability of drawing a black card,
right?
So, there's 26 black cards in the deck.
In other words, half of the deck is black
cards.
So, the probability of not getting a red
card is also 1 half.
What's the probability of not drawing an
ace?
So, for this one, there's a couple of
different ways to solve it,
but here's the easiest way to solve it.
We've already calculated the probability
of drawing an ace.
The probability of not drawing an ace is
going to be 1 minus the probability of
drawing an ace.
In other words, you either draw an ace or
you don't draw an ace.
The probability of drawing an ace is 1 out
of 13.
And the probability of not drawing an ace
is 12 out of 13.
There's a little rule embedded in here,
which I'm just going to write out.
The probability of A happening or A not
happening has to be equal to 1, right?
Because either A happens or it doesn't
happen.
One of those things has to happen, so the
sum of their probabilities has to equal 1.
So, I've used that little rule to solve
for
the probability of not drawing an ace
here.
Finally, what's the probability of getting
a red ace?
Of both getting a red card and an ace
card?
So, what's the joint probability?
What's the probability of getting a red
ace?
Well again, we have 52 cards in the deck.
How many red aces are there?
Well, there's the, the ace of diamonds and
the ace of hearts, so there's two.
So, that probability is 2 out of 52.
Now notice, with a lot of probability
problems,
all we're doing to solve them is just
reasoning things out.
That's a lot of why probability is hard
because it's a lot of just thinking
things out.
All the probability problems you can think
of, there are.
All the sorts of different probability
problems have different ways of
getting at the answer.
And that's what makes it really
challenging.
There isn't one formula I can give you
that works for all probability problems.
You really just have to think.
That's why I love probability problems,
too.
So, this slide just summarizes the answers
I had on the last slide.
Again, there's a rule that the probability
of A plus the probability of
not A always has to sum up to 1.
One of those things has to happen.
Either A happens or A doesn't happen.
Those two probabilities have to sum up to
1.
You can use that rule as we're going to
see later this week.
That's a very helpful rule in calculating
probability.
I just want to mention a little bit of
philosophical here.
The type of probability that I'm talking
about this week,
we're taking what's called a Frequentist
View of Probability.
So, you can think of probability as the
frequency with which
an event occurs over the long run.
So if I keep playing many, many hands of
cards.
Eventually, over many, many times of
drawing cards out of a deck.
It would be the case that I would be
getting 1 in 13 times I'd
be drawing an ace, for example.
That's conceptually how we're viewing
probability.
This is the, this is not the only way to
view probability.
But, this is conceptually how we're
viewing it this week and
for a lot of this course.
The frequency with which an event occurs,
over the long run.
When we talk about what's a P value and we
talk about statistical inference.
I'm going to be saying a lot of if you
could repeat this experiment over and
over again.
This is the same view of how,
how frequent do you expect something to
occur over the long run.
So, just tuck that in the back of your
head,
that that's kind of the basis of a lot of
the calculations we're doing this week.
I want to make one little distinction for
you.
because there are two types of
probabilities that we're going to
deal with in this course.
There are what are call Theoretical
Probabilities.
A lot of what we're going to
calculate this week are just theoretical
probabilities.
So, these are based on theory.
That as we understand how a deck of cards
works or
we understand how a die works, or better
understand how coins work.
By the way, because we're doing
probability this week,
there's going to be a a lot of dice, and
coins, and cards.
And that's simply because everybody
understands how those work.
They make good examples for calculating
probabilities.
So, those are theoretical probabilities
though, because I don't have to go out.
And collect data in order to be able to
tell you what the probability of
drawing an ace is, or the probability of
rolling a two on the die is.
I just know those from understanding how a
die works.
That's in contrast to what are called
Empirical Probabilities.
A lot of what we're going to deal with in
medicine are empirical probabilities.
We use the theoretical probabilities to,
to build up the theory of statistics.
But in fact, when we go out and
measure things, we're measuring empirical
probabilities.
These are based on data.
So for example, some geologists have
collected a bunch of
historical data about earthquakes in the
Bay area.
And using that data, they said that the
probability of
a major earthquake happening in the Bay
Area by 2032 is 62%.
Well, they didn't figure that out by
understanding how earthquakes work.
They figured that out based on some data.
Similarly, if you ask about say the
probability that somebody who
smokes over their lifetime will develop
lung cancer.
It's something like 15%.
We didn't arrive at that, but I understand
how smoking interacts with the lungs.
That's from looking at lots and lots of
people over time.
And seeing what percent of smokers
actually develop lung cancer, so
that's based again on empirical data.
So, we'll be doing some calculations of
probability from both empirical data and
just from a theoretical standpoint.
So, here's an example of probability using
empirical data.
So, here's some data on blood type.
Somebody nicely organized this chart so
that there is,
it's easy to read the chart.
So, if you have 100 donors,
somebody's figured out the prevalence of
different blood types in the population.
And out of 100 people, you'd expect 84 of
them to be RH positive and
16 to be RH negative.
And then within those, we get a breakdown
of type O,
versus Type A, versus Type B, versus Type
A and B.
And so, it's a very easy chart to read.
Because rather than giving percentages or
decimals, the person who put this chart
together made the denominator a nice even
hundred so it's easy to read this chart.
So, for example, what's the probability
that a random donor will be AB Positive?
Well, as we see in the chart, 3 out of 100
donors are AB positive, so
that answer will simply just be 3%.
You can see this is quite easy to
calculate when you set up the charts so
nicely like this.
What's the probability that a random donor
will have a blood type of O?
This one is just slightly harder to
calculate.
Because you have to recognize that there
are O positives and
there are O negatives, and we have to add
those up.
So, 38 O positives and 7 O negatives.
In other words, there are 45 people total
who have an O blood type.
So, out of a hundred, 45 out of 100.
That means that there's a 45% chance of
the donor having an O blood type.
So again, those are empirical data
probabilities.