[BLANK_AUDIO]
Great, well Carly we have a kit right
here, in front of us.
Why don't you go through it for me and
show me some of the features.
Sure, so this is how I like to set up my
arterial line kits.
I use the board to place under the
patient's arm to keep it in
the correct position.
Then, I clean it with a sterile cleaning
solution, and
cover it with a sterile drape.
This is our arterial catheter that we use.
Your's may differ at your institution.
At ours it's similar to our IV catheters
in which it
has the small plastic catheter over the
needle.
Once you insert that into the artery, you
can then put a line,
the wire through the plastic portion,
collecting any blood that may
spill out in the gauze, and once the line
is in, then you connect
the soft plastic portion to the sterile
saline flush that you have preset up.
If you're doing the arterial line under
awake conditions you can use
the lidocaine drawn up with a straw and
use a small bore needle to inject it so
the patient is comfortable while you're
doing the procedure.
We then have a sterile adhesive locking
device and
a sterile occlusive dressing that you
place over the arterial line once it is in
place and, and the ceiling has been
flushed.
>> Okay Carly, well it looks like we have
another kit in front of us,
this one looks like its for a central
line,.
Why don't you take us through it?
>> Sure.
So, I like to be very organized when I
put together my central line kit.
I have my disinfecting swab, then my
sterile dressing, and I
always have my ultra sound probe cover in
addition to the sterile ultra-sound gel.
You'll have an assistant to put those
together when you're,
when you're doing your central line, it's
very important.
Then, I set everything up in my kit.
I have the catheter here, which is your
triple-lumen catheter.
Now, it will come with these attached.
What I do is I take them off and I put
these blue Claves on,
as you see on the blue and the white port.
The brown part I leave open so that the
wire can go through,
and I always have a third clave ready for
when I have the line inside.
>> Now, tell me Carly why you do that.
>> It helps with our sterile technique.
The claves are they prevent any blood from
coming back, but
they also allow you to use alcohol or some
other sort of disinfectant so
that the line stays clean and the patient
doesn't get an infection.
The other things you'll find in you kit
are,
a syringe with a needle attached to it.
Some people prefer use this syringe,
there's others in the kit.
Whatever you preference and your
institution's preference is.
The blue syringe will have a whole in the
back here so
that you have the option of placing the
wire through.
This is the wire.
We put the wire in through the syringe or
through the needle, after you've placed
the central line.
It is mobile here.
As you saw in the video, the steps can be
quite complex.
So, we'll reference you back to the New
England Journal video, for
the exact steps.
Other things that are contained in the
kit, are the dilator here.
Which goes over the wire and can help open
up the skin for placement of the line.
This is also true of the scalpel which is
quite sharp and
should always be covered and used safely
so that no one gets injured.
The other things that come in the kit are,
a transducer probe,
which we don't use very often at our, our
institution.
You can check with your attendings and
other teachers at your institution to use
that.
You'll also have an 18 gauge needle, as
well as some staples for
fixing any of your ultrasound covers or
anything you might need to.
There's also lidocaine and
a syringe if you every need to put in a
central line wall the patient is awake.
Things which also come in the kit are the
needle with a needle driver to
secure the line after it is in place and
then we also have our sterile reclusive
dressing and a patch which helps
again with sterility to make sure that
the, the area that the line is placed.
Does not have any bacteria that can go
into the patient.
>> Okay, Carlee word, we have another kit
in front of us.
It looks similar to the last one but a
little different.
Can you explain it to us?
>> Sure.
It is similar, but there's a few things
we'd like to point out.
So, first of all, you'll recognize the
sterile dressing.
Again, this is line that should always be
placed under a sterile technique.
You'll also have this syringe and the
needle that you will use
to place the the central line, and other
things you'll recognize are the lidocaine
if you do it under sterile conditions
however there's some very different items.
This is a large introducer catheter.
You'll notice it doesn't have the triple
lumens like we have in the other one.
It has one large one.
And it's nine French.
So it's used more often for transfusing
large volumes.
It also is handy, because you can place
what's called a pulmonary artery catheter.
We have one curled up here.
It's quite long, and this goes into the
patient.
Much like you saw in both the New England
Journal video.
As well, in our lecture, we talked about
some of the indications and reasons.
Things that are different are, will have a
balloon on the end.
Which actually is able to be pumped up
with a syringe that
attaches specially here, and has a little
locking device.
So if you do blow the balloon up, and you
can lock it in place so that it stays.
>> Now Carly, let me ask you a question.
>> Sure.
>> If you don't happen to have a 3 CC
syringe, can you stick a 20 CC syringe on
that?
>> Absolutely not.
It's a good question, but no, it's really
important that you don't do
something like that and you use only the
syringe that comes with the kit or
a small syringe, because you don't want to
over fill the balloon while it's in
the pulmonary artery, because you can
actually rupture the artery.
>> Okay, well we don't want that.
>> We don't want that, absolutely not.
Other things that you'll notice in this
kit are again,
your scalpel which you use to help cut the
skin, and then you can insert the dilator.
Again, you'll notice that this is a larger
and longer dilator.
Which is necessary because as we mentioned
before,
this is a much larger catheter that you'll
place.
Other things that are different and this
is something that
I always forget you have to remember, make
a note to remember to place this little
protective sheath onto your pulmonary
artery catheter before you place it
in the patient otherwise you have to take
it out and start all over again.
Again you'll notice that there's three
different ports here.
Aside from the one that you used to blow
up the balloon, so
you can inject medications and infusions
like we do normally.
And that's basically it.
That's the big differences between this
one, and, and the center line.
>> Can I see the wire there too.
>> You do have the wire here, and again,
at our institution we actually on our
checklist have a note.
That we make to remove all of the wires
and all of the dialaters so that we
all verbally confirm with ourselves and
the nurses and the surgeons that all of
those have been removed from the patient
so we don't have any of them left inside.
>> Wonderful.
Well I thought it was really helpful to
look at those kits.
Cause it's always great to get a sense of
the equipment that you're going to be
working with, and I encourage you,
out there watching, to take a look at your
own institution's kits.
They may be the same, they may be slightly
different, but
it's great to have a look at the equipment
that you'll be using so you're familiar
with what you're going to be working with
when you start doing these procedures.
Now to recap what we learned in the
segment,
the first thing is that we really try we
really understood the indications for
when we want to use monitors and lines.
For instance, an arterial catheterization
is useful when you want beat to
beat monitoring of hemodynamic, and you
may consider in,
central venous lines when you want to,
infuse medications,
or also consider lines when you want to,
get frequent blood draws.
We also talked about the importance of
having help when you place a line.
Someone to monitor the well-being of vital
signs, the hemodynamics of the patient
while your attention is focused on the
procedure and the task of placing lines.
Of course, also consider using checklists,
and
also keep in mind the importance of
sterilities,
because avoiding line infections is really
our responsibility as practictions,
physicians who are placing these lines to
avoid iotragenic complications and
injuries to our patients.
Your institutions may have checklists to
help insure that
these safety measures are followed, and I
encourage you to look.
Into your own institution's policies and
checklists to make sure that as youre
learning these techniques, that you're
doing them in the right way and following
the expectations of your institution.
So we hope you learned a lot on this
episode and we'll see you soon.
Thanks so much.
[MUSIC]