[MUSIC]
Hi, I'm Dr. Larry Chu.
>> Hi, I'm Dr. Lauren Cornella.
>> And I'm Dr. John Fox.
>> [SOUND] Well in this segment,
it's really our chance to say good bye to
you as sad as that is.
I've had a fantastic time doing this
course.
I know that you guys have gotten a lot out
of it and
that you are feeling more prepared for
your cardiac anesthesia rotation.
Lauren on behalf of the cardiac anesthesia
team here, do you have any last words for
our students before we send them on their
way?
>> Well, we know this course has provided
a really good introduction to
the cardiac anesthesia pod.
I think that some last tips of advice
maybe would be
to take everything you can from this
rotation.
I think you're going to learn a ton.
I think you're going to really take care
of, patients really well and
you're going to learn a lot of techniques
and
tips and knowledge that's going to take
you even in your non-cardiac OR rotations.
I think something you'll find across the
board about your rotation is
that everyone will be very happy to teach
you.
Cardiac anesthesia attending fellows are
really looking forward to teaching you.
There's so much to learn and so I think
you're going to learn a lot.
I think you'll also find that everyone
else in the room will be
really receptive to teaching you as well.
I know that the fusionists have really
taught me a lot.
The nurses know a lot of information and
so
really try to get the most you can from
every single day and every single case.
And on behalf of everyone, we wish you
well.
We know you're going to love it.
>> Wonderful.
Well, again, it's been a blast.
I can't wait to do this again,
maybe on a different cardiac anesthesia
course in the future to come, hopefully.
And we'll see you later.
Have fun in cardiac anesthesia rotation.
[MUSIC]