[MUSIC]
Hi, I'm Larry Chu.
>> Hi, I'm Carla Guthrie.
>> And in this segment, we're going to
learn about lines and
monitors, and what you need to know for
cardiac anesthesia.
So Carly, tell me a little bit about what
students can expect to learn from you and
your lecture in this modual.
>> So, what students should expect to
learn from this module is the indications
and the reasons why you should put in an
atrial line and a central line,
and we'll also go through some of the
basics of what is in a kit and how you can
expect to set that up so you're prepared
for your first day in cardiac anesthesia.
Wonderful.
Well you know, one of the things that
people really get experience with on
cardiac anesthesia is line placement, is
learning how to do those,
get a lot of experience in doing central
lines, in doing arterial lines.
So let's, let's dive in and watch a
lecture.
>> Hi, my name is Carly Guthrie, and today
we're going to talk about arterial and
central lines.
First let's start by talking about
arterial lines.
Some of the indications for arterial line
placement include the need for
continuous direct blood pressure
monitoring, or, if your indirect blood
pressure monitoring fails, the need for
frequent arterial blood gas sampling, or
measurement of the blood glucose or
chemistries.
Let's talk about the arterial line
waveform, first of all any time
you're placing an arterial line; you
should place it under sterile conditions.
The waveform that you'll see once you
place the arterial line,
will show a high pressure,.
Which corresponds to the systolic pressure
as seen in the image to the right, and
the lowest pressure, which will correspond
to the diastolic pressure.
The main arterial pressure is a calculated
number, and
it's calculated by the equation MAP is
equal to two times the diastolic pressure.
Plus the systolic pressure divided by
three.
Additionally, you'll notice that the
waveform has a small dip or
the dicrotic notch or incisure which will
coincide with the aortic valve closure.
You can see that also in the image to the
right.
That about sums up arterial lines.
Now, let's talk about central lines.
Indications for central line placement
include any patient in which you
will need to use vasopressors.
Patients that may have difficult
peripheral access.
Measurement of the central venous
pressure, especially any time
you'll have hypovolemia or large fluid
shifts during a case.
Administration of TPN or
hemodialysis, and any time you'll need to
do frequent blood draws.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Normal CVP values will be,
five to ten centimeters of water in a
spontaneously breathing patient, and
three to five centimeters of water higher
in a mechanically ventilated patient.
In a normal patient, we believe that the
CVP or
Central Venus Pressure closely corresponds
to the left,
atrial pressure, and therefore the left
ventricular and dystolic pressure.
However, this is true only in the absence
of right ventricular dysfuntion,
in the absence of abnormla pulmonary
resistance, and
in the abseonce of valvular disease.
Let's go through the CVP wave form.
First of all, the A wave corresponds to
the atrial contraction and diastole.
The C wave is due to isovolemic rate of
ventricular contraction,
when the tricuspid valve closes and bulges
back into the right atrium.
This occurs in early systole.
You'll notice that the C wave occurs after
the QRS on the EKG, and
the A wave occurs after the P wave.
The way is caused by filling of the atrium
with blood from the [UNKNOWN].
This happens while the [UNKNOWN] valve is
closed during late [UNKNOWN].
There are two descents.
Firstly, the X descent is caused by HR
relaxation.
Which causes a decline in atrial pressure
during ventricular contraction.
This occurs in mid-systole, so
you'll notice it occurs just before the T
wave on the EKG.
So y descent is caused by a decrease in
atrial pressure as the tricuspid valve
opens and blood begins flowing from the
right atrium into the right ventricle.
[SOUND]
Some tips to remember when you're looking
at CVP Waveforms.
First of all, three of the waveform parts
are systolic events.
The c, the x, and the v.
Two of the waveform [SOUND] portions are
diastolic events.
This is the a wave and the y this time.
We use EKG to properly identify the parts
of waveform and
where they occur with reference to the
cardiac cycle.
Its terms systole and diastole always
refer to ventricular events.
Let's move on and talk about pulmonary
artery catheters.
[SOUND]
How many artery catheter's are Triple
lumen catheter's, which have a proximal
port for measuring the rate atrial
pressure, and distal port for measuring
the pulmonary artery pressure, and
the thermistor for calculating cardiac
output by thermodilution.
Some values that you can get directly from
your PAC line,
include the [UNKNOWN] caplet.
CVP, the right ventricle pressure,
pulmonary artery pressure, and
pulmonary capillary [UNKNOWN] pressure.
Also, you can get SVO2 and temperature
directly from your PA see line.
Indirect measurements, include cardiac
index,
the stroke find resistance, and the stroke
find.
Pulmonary capillary wedge pressure is used
to approximate left ventricular end
diastolic pressure.
Again, some normal values include a CVP of
zero to eight millimeters of mercury.
Right ventricular pressure of 15 to 30
over zero millimeters of mercury.
Pulmonary artery pressure 15 to 30 over
five to 15 millimeters of mercury.
Pulmonary capillary wedge pressure of five
to 15 millimeters of mercury.
Indications for pulmonary artery catheter
placement include: signficant left
ventricular or right ventricular
dysfunction.
Significant valvular heart disease,
pulmonary hypertension,
if you think you'll have a long operative
or bypass time, or a recent or current MI.
Again, let's go through the wave form that
you may see with pulmonary artery
catheter placement.
You can see the wave form to the image to
the right as you path, pass through.
First the right atrium, then the right
ventricle.
Pulmonary artery, and then, when you
finally wedge your catheter.
Typical depth of catheter insertion, from
the right IJ axis,
include the Right Atrium at 25-25 cm.
The Right Ventricle at 30-35 cm,
the Pulmonary Artery at 40-45 cm, and the
Wedge at 45 to 55 cm.
The corresponding Waveforms as you see
there,
the Right Atrium, and then you'll have a
large increase in your
systolic pressure when you go into the
Right Ventricle.
The Pulmonary Artery will then have a
increase in your diastolic pressure, and
then the Wedge pressure will have
decreases in pressure, as you can see.
That concludes our brief discussion of
central lines,
pulmonary artery catheters and arterial
lines.
Thank you very much for your attention.
Please feel free to see the corresponding
video about how to place them and
kit setups.
Thank you again very much.
Carlie, that was a great lecture, thank
you so much.
I do want to ask you, though, what if our
viewers out there really want to get more
of a sense of how this is actually done on
real patients, how lines are placed.
What can we do to help them?
>> Sure.
We thought of that.
So what we'd like you to
do now is go to the New England Journal of
Medicine's website.
An look for their examples on how to place
atrural and central lines, and
then you'll come back and talk more about
it.
>> Okay, great.
And we've put those links on the course
website so you can click through
those links now, and then when you're
finished viewing those videos, come back,
we're going to show you how kits look that
we use for placing lines.
So we'll see you in a little bit.