Hello students, we will learn about the
polymerase chain reaction.
PCR can amplify a single copy of DNA into
millions of copies.
It is a chain reaction that uses DNA
polymerase.
Unlike the uranium chain reaction, which
created the boom of an atomic bomb.
The polymorase chain reaction, created
bloom for biomedical research.
So what makes PCR go?
You need several components.
One, DNA.
Two, all of the nucleotide primers.
Three, deoxynucleotide triphosphates.
Four, DNA polymerase, of course.
And five, thermal cycling, where the
temperature changes in
a cycle to allow the proper reactions to
occur.
So, I've drawn at the top of the figure
here a double-stranded DNA
molecule with the five prime and three
prime ends labeled.
And the three prime end at the arrow
heads.
The first step is to raise the temperature
to denature the DNA molecules.
So, I'll draw them, the two strands
separated as if they are denatured.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The second step is to lower the
temperature
to allow the primers to anneal.
So the primer, one primer will anneal at
this point, and
the other primer will anneal at this
point.
And then, the third step is to elongate.
And then as a result, the DNA polymerase.
We'll copy the template strand, and extend
from the primer.
Now we have two DNA molecules.
And we simply repeat the same sequence of
events of, in a second cycle, cycle two.
Where we denature, anneal, and elongate.
So I am going to draw the four strands in
order.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You can tell the strands by the, the
length here in the diagram.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, that's the denatration step and now
we are going to anneal the primers.
So here's one primer annealing here,
always in the same place.
Must be four.
And then DNA polymerase will be logged
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, after 20 cycles you'll
have just about 1 million molecules.
And virtually, all the molecules will be
the same length.
They will be the length of the DNA spanned
by the two primers.
Okay, so that's the basics of the PCR
reaction.
Now, there are some variations on that
theme.
First of all, you may have other DNA
present in the mix
that is completely different.
Except, it happens to have sequences that
are close enough to the,
to, to the sequence in the primers that
there can be hybridization of the primers.
[SOUND]
So, for example,
you can have a primer
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hybridizing there and the second primer
hybridizing there.
If that occurs
[BLANK_AUDIO]
then we'll get elongation
And copying of a different template
strand.
So that after 20 cycles,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We would have DNA fragments that will have
the sequence of the original primers.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
But spanning
a completely
different DNA
sequence.
Sequence which I have marked in green.
Another bad thing can happen.
And that is the two primers may actually
be complementary at
their three prime ends.
If you haven't designed them properly.
And so they could actually hybridize nose
to nose.
And if that happens, after 20 cycles.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You could have what's called a primer
dimer.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, the primer dimer, of course, is
going to be a different size from
the amplicon that you're looking for in
the target DNA.
And similarly, the mismatched sequence of
the, the mismatched,
sequence, from the other DNA fragment in
green will have a different size.
And you can distinguish all of these by
doing gel electrophoresis.
Which would separate all of the different
species according to size.
Now, there is another variation and
that is that the DNA, the target DNA may
actually not be intact.
So, in that situation, you would have a
primer hybridizing here,
and a primer hybridizing here.
And then, you would get extension, or
elongation.
But on the bottom strand,
the elongation will only go up to the gap
because the pointers can't jump the gap.
But after 20 more cycles, [SOUND]
you would have
[BLANK_AUDIO]
A 1 million fragments of your original
target DNA
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So.
In summary, PCR has many desirable
properties.
It's sensitive.
Extremely so, because you can get a
million copies of a single DNA molecule.
It's quite specific, but not precisely, as
we explained.
And it's robust, because the DNA doesn't
have to be perfectly intact.
But it has to be reasonably intact.
So there you have it.
The Polymerase Chain Reaction.
Thank you.