Hello students we will learn about the
quantitative chain reaction or QPCR.
This measures the amount of target DNA in
the sample it does this by
measuring fluorescence production by
magnification of the target DNA.
What makes QPCR go well you need the usual
PCR reagents.
DNA, primers, DNTPs, DNA polymerase and
thermal cycling, but you'll also need an
extra ingredient.
One example of that extra ingredient is
the intercalating dye, SYBR-Green.
This is how SYBR-Green works.
In free solution it does not glow.
In the presence of double stranded DNA
however the SYBR
green will interrelate in the DNA and glow
green.
SYBR green does not interact.
With single stranded DNA such as the DNA
in the, all the nuclei type primers, so,
in the presence of the primers, it will
not go green,
it will only go green in the presence of
double stranded DNA, so
this is how the SYBR green strategy
works,.
Look up here, we've got a solution of SYBR
green, and
as we amplify our target DNA, the SYBR
green has an opportunity
to intercalate and glow green, and as we
get more DNA.
The saccharine has more opportunities, to
intercalate and pro-create.
So the saccharine will, is an indicator
for
how much double stranded DNA is being
amplified.
Now, there's another strategy.
That uses, a reporter oligonucleotide.
[NOISE] And this reporter oligonucleotide.
Is complimentary to the target DNA, and
will hybridize, but
it's specially constructed so that one
nucleotide on the reporter contains
a quencher, and another nucleotide on the
reporter contains a fluorescent dye.
Because the flourecent dye is close to the
quencher it fails to glow.
But on release from the oligonucleotide it
is no longer close to the quencher and it
can glow red so here's how.
The reporter of the nucleotide works.
Suppose we have the target DNA, and we
have a.
Poly oligonucleotide.
In addition to that, suppose, the reporter
oligonucleotide also,
finds, to the target DNA.
DNA polymerase comes along, and bumps into
the re, reporter oligonucleotide.
The DNA polymerase that's used in the
reaction in addition to
having a five prime to three prime
polymerase activity also has a five prime
to three prime exo nucleus activity.
So as a result, the polymerase
can chew through the reporter
oligonucleotide,
releasing the reporter oligonucleotide.
First, releasing the oligonucleotide bound
to the fluorescent dye but
now that's free and no longer near the
clincher, and
then it releases, the other single
nucleotides.
Until it reaches the quencher which is no
longer close
to the fluorescent dye and therefore
unable to quench it, and as you,
go through multiple cycles of PCR, there
are more and more opportunities for
reporter oligonucleotide to hybridize to
the target DNA,
and more and more opportunities for it to
release its fluorescent dye.
So, the either of these strategies capable
of,
reporting on the amount of DNA in any one
of several reactions.
So you can search around for say a plate
with lots of wells so
you can do lots of experimenting in
parallel.
And look, down here.
Here is a 96 well plate.
Well I'm going to use it and put a whole
bunch of reactions into the 96 well plate,
and each reaction is somewhat different,
and I expect each reaction
will have different amounts of the target
DNA.
So if I were using SYBR green for example
some of
the samples will glow a bright green and
other samples.
Glow less brightly indicating different
concentrations of the target DNA in each
well.
And there is a way of doing this that
allows you to be very quantitative.
Here's an example of QPCR data for five
different samples.
Each sample was run in triplicate so for
example.
The green sample had the highest
concentration
because it reached the threshold signal in
the fewest number of cycles,
and the turquoise sample over here at the
lowest concentration.
Because it required the greatest number of
cycles
to reach the threshold.
So, in summary,
there were two strategies for
quantitative PCR, one.
Was the SYBR green strategy, and
that's cheap because all you need is a
fluorescent dye with the right properties.
The second was the reporter
oligonucleotide.
Strategy and that's much more expensive
because you
have to synthesize chemically synthesize
an oligonucleotide tailor made for
the target sequence you're interested in
and therefore it costs more.
However the reporter oligonucleotide.
It's more specific, because,
a signal is produced only
to report our olignuc, oligonucleotide
hyperdizes to the target DNA sequence.
So you need, you have the specificity of
the.
Two [UNKNOWN] type primers plus the
reporter of the oligonucleotide.
So, there you have it, quantitative PCR.
[BLANK_AUDIO]