This presentation is about respiratory
viruses and
specificall, I'm going to talk about four
families of respiratory viruses,
the rhinoviruses, the coronaviruses, the
adenoviruses,.
And the parainfluenza viruses.
I'll make a few comments about the
epidemiology of these viral infections,
their classic clinical manifestations and
ideas about management.
With regards to rhinovirus, we've al had
plenty of experience with rhinovirus,
the most prominent cause of the common
cold.
[COUGH] We know there's not much you can
do about them.
And in the wisdom of Sir WIlliam Osler, he
said,
there's in fact only one way to treat a
cold, and that is with contempt.
These viruses are a member of the
picornavi, picornavirus family.
And they enter our body after they've
attached to so
called intracellular adhesion molecules,
ICAMS.
They then are internalized in those
particular host cells and replicate and
spread to other cells.
There are more than 100 serotypes of
rhinovirus that
circulate in a random fashion over time.
We rapidly acquire these infections during
early childhood.
Childhood, in fact it is common in the
first few years of
life to have three to six rhinovirus
infections per year of life.
These viruses often, optimally replicate
in colder environments,
the nose is a colder part of our body than
most other parts,
hence they tend to hang out in the nose.
Their acid [UNKNOWN] will not pass through
the acid heavy stomach and
be excreted in the stools, they are rather
inactivated.
These viruses are difficult to culture in
cell culture and
there's no rapid test available to make
the diagnosis.
But we don't really care because the
diagnosis is made clinically.
The clinical manifestations of Rhinovirus
usually start
after an incubation period of two to three
days.
So you come in contact with an infected
individual and two to three days later
you might have the onset of mild symptoms
that may persist for five to seven days.
The mild symptoms include a runny and
stuffy nose.
A sore throat perhaps with some hoarseness
perhaps a cough.
Very rarely there will be a fever, but it
is important to recognize that there
is often sub pulmonary clinical
involvement and
you might have noticed this in yourself.
If you are an aerobic exorsizer you may
have noticed that you
can not run as fast or as far as when you
don't have a cold.
And that is because cytokines are causing
some lower.
Respiratory track impairment.
These viral infections may be more severe
in certain populations for example,
in persons with chronic lung disease like
chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.
They may cause exacerbation transiently
worsening the pulmonary findings.
These Rhinovirus infections may be
complicated by a bacterial infection,
a super infection with manifestation of
ear infection.
otitis media or sinusitis.
Some hosts are susceptible to worse
rhinovirus infections than others.
Especially true of heavy smokers or the
elderly or
those who are immunocompromised in some
fashion.
Another cause of the common cold are
corona viruses.
And these have not garnered much
attention, or
did not garner much attention, until 2003,
when there was a worldwide
epidemic of Severe Acute Respiratory
Syndrome, or SARS.
And that really got the attention allowed
attention to go towards a coronavirus,
because it was a type of coronavirus that
caused SARS.
More recently MERS, which stands for
Middle East Respiratory Syndrome, has also
emerged.
And that also is a coronavirus.
They're called coronaviruses because under
electron microscopy they have
a crown appearance in their outer
membrane.
They have peplomers on their surface and
other than SARS and
MERS as I've already mentioned, these
mostly simply cause the common cold.
When SARS emerged, the CDC Director at the
time Julie Gerberding.
Made the following comment.
If the virus moves faster than our
scientific communications and
control capacities, we could be in for a
long difficult race.
The race is on, the stakes are high, and
the outcome cannot be predicted.
Fortunately there was rapid scientific
discoveries made with
regards to the coronavirus.
Including that it was a corona virus, how
spread could be prevented and
epidemics control, so the 2003 epidemic
did end quite quickly.
However well it was varying strong it was
noted that the virus was quite severe.
20% of infected individuals were admitted
to the Intensive Care Unit and
the mortality rate was 10%.
An important core morbidities were
identified and
advanced age was recognized as a risk
factor.
Ultimately and before the epidemic ended,
there were about 8,000 cases with about
774 deaths.
Around the world.
I mention MERS corona virus has recently
emerged.
This picture of the world from the time of
the SARS epidemic was published in 2011.
And it shows the countries that had
different numbering cases for
Coronavirus infections and you can see on
this map that the countries with the most
infections were Hong Kong and
Taiwan and Vietnam to the East and Canada
to the West.
Allot of investigation followed the
outbreak of coronavirus to try to
figure out where it had come from, and
without going into detail,
ultimately, the bat was implicated as an
important vector.
The bat.
Spread the infection to the so, the Civet
cat the Civet cat through
ingestion of the cat and other mechanisms
spread the infection to humans and
in human to human transmission followed
that.
Moving to a different virus, Adenovirus.
Adenoviruses cause a lot of different
illness beyond the respiratory tract, and,
but I'm going to focus on the respiratory
tract.
These viruses are double stranded, non
segmented DNA viruses.
There are many serotypes, more than 50
causing infections in humans.
They have some distinguishing physical
characteristics.
They can be isolated in tissue culture.
And there are rapid antigenic tests
available.
In certain populations have a particularly
high morbidity and
even mortality caused by adenoviruses.
These include Native Americans, military
recruits, new born infants, and
some who are immunocompromised for other
reason.
The Myriad illnesses are listed in this
particular slide, but
the ones that are would underscore that
are most typical in suggestive of
adenovirus are pharyngoconjunctival fever
and epidemic keratoconjunctivitis.
So pharyngoconjunctival fever is what it
sounds like.
It's infection and
inflammation of the pharynx and the
conjunctiva associated with fever.
Quite common with certain adenoviruses.
An epidemic keratoconjunctivitis causes
epidemic that is
widespread red eye or pink eye.
And the picture that is shown on this
slide indicates an individual suffering
from adenovirus, conjunctivitis.
Adenovirus can cause a number of other
illnesses listed on this slide as well.
Finally, parainfluenzavirus is a member of
the paramyxovirus family,
it's a single stranded RNA virus, there
are four types.
And this virus has a non segmented genome,
when put in to tissue culture, it
causes very limited cytopathogenic effect
although it change the cells in tissue
culture to, want to absorb red cells if
they're poured on to the tissue culture.
Something called hemadsorption,
which maybe used in viral diagnostic
laboratories.
Different parainfluenzaviruses has
different seasonality patterns.
Serotype 1 is mostly in the fall months,
and
this is the virus that causes
laryngotracheobronchitis or croup.
Croup is ,.
You will, hear patients with croup from
down the hallway, They go, Huh, huh.
And they have that barking like cough.
These parainfluenzaviruses, in addition to
causing croup,
can also cause other infections of the
respiratory tract, including.
Bronchitis and pneumonia, laryngitis and
pharyngitis, or they might just call cause
an undifferentiated febrile illness,
which interestingly can go on for a long
period of time.
Immunity to these viruses is imperfect.
So reinfections occur.
Croup is distinctive, I've tried to
exemplify that distinction with my barking
cough, other manifestations are shown on
this slide, and the only treatment for
croup is to actually support the patient,
try to relieve their apprehension,
give them oxygen if necessary, and mist
therapy may be helpful.
This schematic shows the classic
radiographic finding associated with
croup, the so called steeple side.
Or the narrowing of the airway, and
you can see it schematically represented
below.
And this picture is trying to demonstrate
the subglottic narrowing that
occurs with croup and causes the barking
like cough.
This final summary table outlines the
principal features of this virus for
your reference.