This presentation is about respiratory
viruses, and the specific objectives are,
to focus on Respiratory Syncytial Virus,
RSV, and Metapneumovirus.
Describing briefly their epidemiology, key
clinical manifestations and potential
complications, and how to manage these
particular respiratory viral infections.
So RSV is an extraordinarily important
virus.
For pediatricians and physicians who take
care of children.
It is one of the most important viral
pathogens during the first year of life.
It's a member of the Paramyxovirus family
of viruses and
there's only a single serotype of RSV.
There are two subtypes, A and B.
But a single serotype.
These viruses are relatively labile so
when transporting from
the patient to the laboratory, for example
trying to grow the virus and
tissue culture, the specimens need to be
handled with care.
The virus may be isolated in tissue
culture.
And after incubating on the tissue culture
for.
For three to seven days, they form
distinctive syn, syncytia in cell culture.
The CB cytopathogenic effect, shows
syncytia hence the name of the virus.
There are rapid techniques available for
diagnosing RSV, imunoflorescence for
example.
And these rapid techniques tend to be even
more sensitive than cultures, again,
because the virus.
Is, fickle.
This virus and tissue culture does not
agglutinate red blood cells in
contradistinction to the parainfluenza
virus.
And the virus has two very important
surface proteins, F which stands for
the fusion protein and G which stands for
the attachment protein.
This schematic of RSV demonstrates the
viral structure showing in the core,
the RNA of the virus.
The lipid membrane is illustrated on this
picture and the different surface proteins
that I've mentioned are also indicated on
this schematic picture of RSV.
The types of illnesses caused by RSV occur
during the winter and
spring in North America.
And the peak age of infection is between
two and
five months, the infections start at about
two months,
because antibody transferred from the
mother across the placenta.
Begins fading at about two months, and the
baby then becomes susceptible to
the RSV infection because there is no more
maternal antibody.
About 70% of the population is infected by
their first birthday, and
the remaining are infected by their fourth
birthday.
Viral shedding may occur for several weeks
in very young and sick infants.
So the babies may be infectious for a long
period of time.
Viral infections transmitted by droplets,
but
also could be transmitted on fomites and
infections occurring within
closed environments like hospitals,
nosocomial infections.
Are common and they may result in severe
disease.
The main patho, the contributors to the
pathogens of RSV infection include
transmission of a virus from cell to cell
down the respiratory tract.
And as the virus moves there is
substantial epithelial necrosis with
outpouring of cellular debris and mucus
that can result in airway plugging,
especially the small terminal airways, and
that plugging can result in air trapping.
Air comes in during inspiration and can't
get out as the airways collapse during
expiration, aggravated by the mucus and
cellular debris.
There's also a robust inflammatory
response that the host raises to
this virus, with lots of cytokine release
and other mediators, and
this can result, in these [UNKNOWN]
dilatation and
constriction of the respiratory muscles
around the terminal bronchials, ultimately
impeded gas exchange exchange hypoxia and
sometimes the need for ventilation.
Bronchiolitis is the term used to
describe,
RSV infection or infection of the terminal
bronchials.
Other viruses can cause bronchiolitis, but
RSV is by far the most prominent member.
bronchiolitis.
Because it involves small airway disease,
these babies are often referred to as
little wheezers.
They sound just like an asthmatic
individual.
But, they're very young and the process
has been stimulated by a virus.
They may get lung involvement, parenchymal
involvement,
in addition to airway involvement.
So you can actually have a bronchial
pneumonia associated with RSV.
RSV infections in little people is a very
common reason for
emergency room visits and for hospital
admissions.
During the peek season.
There also may be some long term
complications to
RSV infection early in life.
There's some, thought that RSV may
stimulate the subsequent development of
asthma, but it's a bit of a chicken and
egg argument.
It may be that children prone to asthma
have bad RSV infections as opposed to
the bad RSV infection actually causing the
asthma.
Because immunity is not perfect after an
RSV infection,
reinfections may occur later in life.
But these reinfections tend to be mild as
I
said with upper respiratory tract kind of
illnesses.
And so the clinical manifestations of
broncialitis.
After an incubation period of four to six
days the child begins to
have upper repository type symptoms.
A stuffy nose a runny nose perhaps a
little bit of a cough.
And then there is variable progression of
the illness over a period of one to
seven days.
A variable, variable progression meaning
some.
Progressed that more severe disease,
others actually, begin getting better.
Fever is quite common with RSV infection
and
it does not imply that there's a secondary
super infection.
it may simply be a result of the virus
itself.
As the virus causes problems in the lower
respiratory tract,
there maybe begins breathing more quickly.
grunting, which is a way to exert positive
airway pressure and to try to
keep the airways open, nasal flaring,
retractions of the intercostal muscles.
Wheezing and the baby may become blue as
they become hypoxy, hypoxic.
Apnea may be a manifestation of RSV as
well,
even if there's not severe lower
respiratory tract involvement.
The apnea may be centrally mediated, that
is, through the immature brain,
hence it's a bit more common in babies who
have been born prematurely.
Some patients, will have predictably more
severe disease than other patients.
specifically, extremes of age.
So babies who contract RSV in the first
six weeks of life,
which is not as common, as two to five
months of age.
But if they do, they tend to have more
severe disease,
probably because their airways, are
already quite small.
The elderly also may have severe RSV
infection,
probably because of waning immunity.
Children, who have congenital heart
disease,
especially congenital heart disease,
associated with cyanosis,
tend to have more severe RSV infection, as
do children with chronic lung disease.
Such as those with bronchopulmonary
dysplasia, or BPD.
Which is a consequence of severe
prematurity.
Otherwise, compromised children, such as
transplant recipients or
children with cancer getting chemotherapy,
may have bad outcomes with RSV infection,
and those who are neurologically impaired
may have bad outcomes with RSV.
The treatment and
prevention of RSV infection has fueled
many debates over time.
so, for example, for a while, it was
popular to have babies with RSV inhale
epinephrine and cause vasoconstriction and
try to reduce some of the inflammation.
This is not generally recommended.
There's a worry that the baby may get even
more
worse after the epinephrine has stopped
with rebound.
So it's really not recommended.
Bronchodilators are tried by, many.
If they actually seem to cause some
relief,
then it's recommended that they may be
continued while a child's hospitalized.
If they don't work, they shouldn't be
used.
Steroids have had inconsistent results and
are not recommended.
The antiviral agent Ribavirin, which is
active against RSV and some other virus,
has really had inconsistent results in
terms of substantial benefit.
It costs a lot of money, it's difficult to
administer, and is not widely used.
Immunization would be great if you had a
licensed vaccine but we do not.
and one of the original vaccines cause
more severe illness in
the recipients than the natural disease
itself which is not a good thing.
A passive antibody is effective in helping
to prevent and ameliorate RSV infection
and in the high risk host that I mentioned
previously giving passive antibody.
Through the first, and or second year of
life to try and prevent RSV is used.
The passive antibody is either given
intravenously, or
now more commonly intramuscularly at,.
Monthly intervals during the, RSV season.
And, of course, supportive care can never
be argued with.
If the child is hypoxic, for example, they
should receive oxygen.
A metapneumovirus is more or less like
RSV.
It's an RSV look alike.
It is a member of the paramyxovirus.
Family.
It also has one serotype.
It doesn't grow in tissue culture as well
as RSV, but it can be diagnosed with PCR.
And its clinical illness, although less
common, is virtually identical or
can be virtually identical to RSV.
And this final slide simply [INAUDIBLE].
It, depicts the key features of RSV and
Metapneumovirus in a summary table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]