Good morning students, today we're going
to talk about Retroviral Integration.
So here we go.
I'm going to draw for
you, retroviral genome here.
And this is the retroviral genome after
reverse transcript phase has converted the
retroviral RNA into double-stranded DNA.
And the retroviral genome
has a long terminal repeat of the same
sequence at both ends.
And for the purposes of this discussion.
This will be the HIV, you know?
[SOUND]
Because
of its medical importance and we will have
a little blow up of the HIV genome.
And I would just draw a few nucleotides
here for illustration.
That's the upper strand, and here's the
lower strand.
And these two nucleotides right
here are critical for
whats going to happen next.
Because it's going to turn out that the
retroviral
integrase [SOUND] will remove two
nucleotides
from the three prime ends, both three
prime ends.
So I'll remove two of the nucleotides from
this particular end,
[COUGH] leaving us with a, recess three
prime hydroxyl.
Now I'm going to draw the target of the
retroviral integration event.
And that'll be the host genome, the retro
virus wants to jump into the host genome.
So we will draw the host genome for you.
Double stranded DNA there.
And I'm going to show you the retroviral
genome curled up.
And it's curled up because the retroviral
integrase will hold on to both LTRs.
So we've got the two unpaired nucleotides
at
the five prime end of the upper strand, in
the previous diagram.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And the unit three prime hydroxyl here and
then, two unpaired
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Nucleotides with high prime and of the
other strand, the lower strand,
from the previous diagram, ending in a
three prime hydroxyl, there.
And, these three prime hydroxyls will be
used by
the integrase to catalyze nucleophilic
attacks, on the host DNA.
So, we will draw that.
And the nucleophilic attacks occur,
offset from each other, and the offset
here, I'm going to put in black brackets.
And those that bracketed sequence between
the two sites of nucleophilic attack is
going
to be destined to become a short direct
repeat,
and you'll see that by the time we're
finished.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So [COUGH]
Just to review the integrase.
[NOISE]
Catalyzes
nucleophilic
attacks, on the host DNA.
Both strands of the host DNA.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[COUGH] And I'm going to show you
the results of that, those nucleophilic
attacks.
So, starting, and this time I'm going to
start with the lower.
I'll draw the diagram from the lower
strand, three prime end of the host DNA,
moving over to that side.
And then, that nucleophilic will attack
actually
creates a covalent bond with a retro viral
DNA.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Five prime in [COUGH].
Now, if I do, draw in.
Let me finish drawing the bottom strand
here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here's the end of the bottom strand five
prime.
Now, starting from the three
prime end of the upper strand,
we'll show you results of the nucleophilic
attack at the upper strand.
And the lower strand, the upper strand, I
am sorry.
Let's draw it in blue.
It's all the way up to there.
There we go.
[COUGH] So,
this configuration is a little hard to
see.
So what we need to do is to pull the DNA
ends out so you can see everything.
I'm not going to, I'm not going to change
anything.
All the bonds are still there.
It's just the geometry will change for
ease of viewing.
So again if I start with the three prime
end of the lower strand.
Of course, we want to keep our color
coding.
So we're, if we're talking about the three
prime end
of the lower strand, we want that host DNA
to be blue,
it's going to be covalent linked to
retroviral DNA.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There's the retroviral DNA, and
it's protruding five prime and,
[COUGH] the same thing goes, and then
well-
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The continuation.
The continuation of the host DNA over
here.
I'm leaving a gap there on purpose.
You're going to see why I have to do that,
[COUGH] because, if I draw,
start drawing the five prime end of the
retroviral,
upper DNA strand, that only goes up to
this point.
Let me, draw a little more carefully, only
goes up to that point.
Because, it doesn't reach all
the way over because there's a gap, that's
exactly the distance,
that between the two nucleophilic attacks
on the upper part of the diagram.
And if I continue drawing the retroviral
DNA
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I come up to here.
Let me curl this thing down to make it a
little easier for you to see.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay.
And then we have the point of covalent
attachment there.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Voila.
We've got another gap over here.
[COUGH]
So
that is the previous diagram, stretched
out.
Nothing has changed.
What happens next is, that nuclease comes
along and removes
the protruding two nucleotides at the five
prime ends, the unpaired two nucleotides.
And then post polymerase.
We'll draw that in blue,
host polymerase, DNA polymerase and
ligase.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Repair the gaps.
Okay, now, I'll draw that.
Here's the polymerase coming along, and
then the ligase finishing the job.
Polymerase coming along, ligase, finishing
the job.
And, voila, you've got the retroviral DNA
integrated into the host genome.
And the epilogue is, of course,
understanding retroviral integration has
led to the development of HIV inhibitors,
which are now being used to treat patients
with HIV infection.
Thank you so much.
[BLANK_AUDIO]