Welcome to the first R module.
In this video we'll be going over the
solutions to the first R exercise.
If you prefer,
there's also a written version of these
solutions on the class website.
Now this first R exercise was really
designed to get you to
explore the different options in Deducer.
So if you found yourself struggling a
little bit, don't worry.
It's going to get easier from here.
The first step is actually not question
one.
The first thing we need to do is open up
Deducer.
So to do that I'm going to click this
shortcut.
[COUGH] And there are two windows here.
There's the console window on the left.
And the data viewer window on the right.
In order to open up my data, which is,
provided to you as an Excel file on
the class website, I'm going to click on
the open data icon
on the data viewer window on the
right-hand side of the The screen.
This will allow you to navigate to
wherever you have that Excel file saved.
In my case it happens to be on the
desktop.
And I'm going to select it and open it.
Because our data is only on one worksheet,
the first one,
I'm just going to click okay here.
And I see that deducers was able
to load in the data correctly, I'm
going to scroll to the right.
Make sure everything's there, good.
I'm going to scroll down to make sure I
have 50 rows, great.
So at this point, we are now ready to
start the exercise.
The first question reads that,
varsity, the variable varsity is currently
stored as type double.
You want to change this continuous
variable to a categorical variable.
R denotes categorical variables as
factors.
The way we're going to do this is using
the data viewer window on
the right-hand side, I'm going to click on
Variable View here,
which will list all the variables in a
column.
Along with their type and something called
factor levels.
And so I'm going to go to varsity.
Click on Type, and then select Factor.
And notice when I do this that The factor
levels column gets populated for
that variable.
It shows two factor levels.
Level 0 and level one.
That's because varsity only has two values
in it.
I do want to caution you.
That when you're doing variable
conversions in Deducer,
like I did just now, that you don't go
back and forth too many times,
because Deducer will make assumptions
about what types of variables you want,
and what you want certain values to be.
So just be aware that Deducer makes
certain assumptions and
to always check your data.
After changing anything.
For question two we want to sort two
different variables.
Varsity and writing love.
In different orders.
So first we want to sort varsity in
ascending order.
And then, eh, writing love in descending
order.
Okay.
So the way I'm going to do that, I'm
going to click back to data view, for now.
The way I'm going to do this is by going
now to the console window on
the left hand side here.