Welcome to the third and final R video
module.
In this session,
we'll be reviewing the problems from the
third set of R/deducer exercises.
And as before we'll be working with the
same data set,
mock class data which is provided to you
in Excel format on the class website.
So I'm going to start off by opening
Deducer and loading the data.
[SOUND] So again we have our 2 familiar
windows here, the console window and
the demo-viewer window, and I'm going to
click on Open Data and
navigate to where I saved.
Our data set on my computer, which happens
to be on the Desktop.
And, I'm going to wait for r to load the
data.
Great.
So, now that the data's been loaded, and
I've checked to make sure that everything
looks correct to which it does.
We're ready to begin the exercise.
The first question asks for
the piercing correlation coefficient
between the variables politics and Obama.
It asks us about the p value for this
correlation coefficient.
And it also asks us to draw a scatter plot
for this data.
So the way I'm going to do this is to go
to Analysis Correlation.
And I'm going to drag over Both politics
and Obama into the variables box.
I want to point out that the box below it
will correlate that variable with
all the variables in the box named
variables.
So for example, if I put in let's say as
an example, varsity.
It would correlate varsity with politics.
And varsity with Obama.
Okay?
So that's another option for you to use if
you want to.
So I want to scatter plot.
So I'm going to go to Plots.
Here.
I'm going to select Scatterplots.
And I'm going to unselect common axis.
I think it's actually a little bit easier
to interpret when you don't have a lot of
variables correlating with each other.
To not have a common axis.
So, then I'm going to hit Okay.
I'm curious about what Options has, so I'm
going to click on that now.
I see that it has options for different
sets of output that we want.
So this has options for whether we want a
two sided P value or
a one sided P value, and what confidence
level we want our output to be set at,
and then of course the N, the confidence
interval.
The test statistic and the P-value.
We want all of these in our output, so I'm
going to leave them checked.
Pearson's correlation is selected by
default, so that's good.
And we are ready to run our test.
So you'll notice a few things happen here.
First of all, Deducer generated a few
scatter plots First,
and then we also have our output on the
left-hand side in the console window here.
Just scrolled up a little bit to see it.
So a few things to notice.
The output is structured to correlate with
the scatter plots on the right-hand side.
So, you'll notice that the data for let's
say Obama being on the X axis and
politics being on the Y axis is in the
upper right hand corner of the output,
and that same scatter plot is in the upper
right hand corner of
the correlation array on the right hand
side of the screen.
So, that's how to read this.
And so, what we're interested And is
looking at the correlation coefficient.
The correlation coefficient is 0.7789.
The p value is very low, so low that it is
expressed as 0.0000.
Suggesting that it's extremely
significant.
And the scatter plot also reinforces this
by
showing a marked dependence between the 2
variables.
Please note that the graph in the upper
right corner gives you
the same R-value, P-value.
And graph as the figure shown in unit 8,
slide 12.
So this is one way of replicating
something that you
saw in the lecture slides.
So the second question asks us to do
another Pearson correlation
coefficient between two different
variables, math love and writing love.
So let's do that.
So the first thing I'm going to do is
close this plot.
I'm going to go to analysis correlation
again, and uncheck politics and Obama.
And replace that with Math Love and
Writing Love.
And then bring those two over, Pearson's
is great.
I don't need a, scatter plot this time, so
I'm going to unselect that,
and then I'm going to leave the options as
we had them before.
I'm going to hit Run.
And I'm going to look at our output.
So the correlation coefficient in this
case is 0.1303.
And it has a high p-value this time,
meaning that it is not statistically
significant.
Notice that the p-value is greater than
0.05, it's 0.3936.
Indicating that there's no statistically
significant correlation between the two
variables Mathlove and WritingLove.
So the next question, question 3 asks us
to
check the normality assumption of
Pearson's correlation coefficient.
So it's asking us to check the normality
for the variables that we've used so
far in this exercise, Mathlove,
WritingLove, politics and Obama.
The easiest way to do that is to plot
these variables and
to look at the distribution to see if
they're approximately normal or not.
The way I'm going to do this is to go to
plots and select plot builder.
And I'm going to bring down Histogram.
And I'm just going to look at each
variable one by one, and
to comment on the distribution.
So Obama looks okay.
It looks skewed on the left hand side
here.
On, so that's something to keep in mind.
Then looking at politics.
Politics looks a little bit bi-modal.
With a peak here around 40.
And another peak here around 80.
So, I'm less excited about politics here.
Math love, let's see what that looks like.
Math love I think looks okay.
It looks the most normal out of the two,
all the variables that we've looked at so
far.
And then finally, let's look at writing
level.
And again, writing level looks a little
bimodal,
with a peak around 20, and another peak
around 70 or so.
So, I don't think that we violated the
normality assumption egregiously,
but there could be an argument made that a
different test or
a different kind of correlation
coefficient could be used.
Based upon the fact that our variables
aren't exactly normally distributed.
Question four asks us to perform a linear
regression of President Obama's approval
scores versus student's impression of the
new healthcare reform law.
What are the values, for the beta and the
intercept; are they
statistically significant; what's the
value of R squared.
So a lot packed into this question, but
very little that we need to do in R to
answer them.
And so what I'm going to do is first exit
out of Plot Builder and
I'm going to go to Analysis Linear model.
That's going to give us the linear
regression.
The outcome that we want to look at here
is President Obama's
approval rating and so we're going to
select that as the outcome.
The numeric variable that we're interested
in is health care and
I can, going to, I can hit continue now.
We're not interested in effect
modification or
interactions of any kind, so I'm going to
skip this screen as well.
And linear regression output comes in its
own special screen,
it's not in the console window.
We're going to scroll down to look at what
I'm interested in, which are the values.
For the coefficients, the estimates for
the coefficients.
And we see that the intercept is about
55.25.
The beta is 0.3182.
Both are statistically significant.
And the r-squared value a little bit below
that next to Multiple R-squared,
here Is 0.15 with an F statistic of
approximately 8.2.
Question 4 asks us to perform a linear
regression of President Obama's approval
scores versus students' impression of the
new healthcare reform law.
It asks us what the values for the beta
and
the intercept are, as well as whether they
are statistically significant.
And the values of the r squared for the
linear regression as well.
So that's a lot packed into one question,
but
it's actually very little that we have to
do in deducer to get that output.
So the first thing we want to do is run a
linear regression, so
I'm going to go to Analysis and select
Linear Model in order to do that.
The outcome variable that we want here is
Obama.
Which represents President Obama's
approval ratings in this cohort.
And I want the independent variable to be
the attitudes towards his healthcare
reform law.
So I'm going to drag that over to the as
numeric box.
And then I'm going to click continue.
And then because I'm not interested in
interaction or
effect [/g] modification I'm going to
continue.
And, here we have our linear aggression
output.
Notice it's not in the console window.
It's in it's own window.
In order to get at what I'm interested in
I'm going to scroll down.
And here I see, the different coefficient
estimates.
So the intercept is about 55.25.
The beta estimate for health care is .32,
and they both
have a p value of less than .05, meaning
that they're statistically significant.
But what does that really mean?
So that really means that health care is
associated with President Obama's approval
ratings in this, in this cohort, and for
every one unit that President Obama's
approval ratings increase,
the attitude for healthcare, the unit for
healthcare, goes up by 0.31.
So that's what that's really saying.
The r squared value, which is listed
a little bit below that, Is 0.1542,
and the f statistic is listed as 8.2,
which is significant.
The next question asks us to do something
similar, but
add in one more variable into the
regression.
And one reason we might do this is if we
think that the relationship between,
someone's attitude towards the healthcare
reform law,
may be confounded by something.
So, maybe it's not a real association, and
then.
Of that association, or
rather that that observed association is
driven in fact by some other variable.
So, to do this, first I'm going to exit
out of this.
The question asks us to include the new
variable politics.
Essentially, the student's political bent.
And repeat what we just did.
So, I'm going to go to Analysis and Linear
Model.
I'm going to drag Obama into the Outcome
box,
and the healthcare variable into the As
Numeric box.
But also politics into the As Numeric box.
I'm going to click Continue.
And again, we're not interested in
interaction or
effect modifications, I'm just going to
continue here.
And our output is displayed in this screen
once again.
So, scrolling down, a few things to notice
here.
So let's, I'm going to read out the
estimates of the estimate, estimate for
the intercept is Is 22.2.
For healthcare is 0.13 and for politics is
0.62.
What should be noted as different from
before first of all
is the magnitude of the intercept for
healthcare.
In the previous regression the beta was
0.31 or 0.32.
Rather, in this one it's 0.13, so
it's greatly reduced, and second, it's no
longer statistically significant.
So what does that really mean?
It means that the observed association
between
someone's attitude towards the health care
law and
President Obama was actually driven by
their political beliefs.
Politics here has a beta estimate of 0.62
and
the p-value is statistically significant.
So another way of interpreting that or
thinking about that is really that.
The student's political beliefs
represented by the variable politics stat,
is statistically significantly associated
with their views on Obama.
One other way, again, of saying that is
that.
Their political beliefs can accurately
relate to, correlate with,
are associated with, predict, Their
attitudes towards Obama.
Okay?
And to just finish this up the R squared
value again you see at the bottom is about
0.63 and the F statistic is still
significant at 36.53.
One other thing to keep in mind compared
to the previous
regression is that the beta estimate for
healthcare changed more than 10%.
So when this changes more than 10% this
suggests.
That there was confounding.
OK.
This isn't a very, this isn't a hard rule.
It's not like there's some mathematical
theory behind that,
but it's more of a rule of thumb that when
the beta estimate changes by more than 10%
after adding in another variable, that
that observed relationship
Previously was due to a confounding
factor.
The last question in this data set, asks
us to do another linear regression.
But this time instead of using a
continuous variable as our
independent predictor, we're going to use
A categorical variable.
That variable in this case is varsity,
which happens to be binary,
0 or 1, but that's still two categories,
and we're going to be using dummy coding,
to run this regression.
Which is a bit of a departure from what
we've been doing before with our
continuous independent predictors.
So the first step as before, is to click
on Analysis and
select Linear model for our regression.
The dependent variable we want in this
case is exercise, so
I'm going to move that into the outcome
box,
then I'm going to move varsity into the as
factor box.
Now, before we were moving everything into
the As Numeric box, that was for
continuous variables.
When we want to treat something as a
factor, or as a categorical variable,
we're going to move that variable into the
box labeled as Factor.
OK, and then I'm going to click Continue.
We're not interested in effect
modification interaction at this point so
I'm just going to click continue and
scroll down to look at our results.
So a few things here.
So the beta estimate for our intercepts is
3.57.
The beta estimate for the variable varsity
is 0.975.
The r squared is 0.03 and the f statistic
is 1.5.
The s statistic is not significant.
Probably the most thing in this output is
the p-value.
And the row for the varsity variable.
It's 0.227.
It's not statistically significant.
Which means that our conclusion is that
varsity is not
statistically significantly associated
With,
the amount of exercise that you, have
right now.
So that concludes, this third exercise
and,
this third R video module.