Welcome to the first R module.
In this video, we'll be going over the
solutions to the first R exercise.
If you prefer,
there's also a written version of these
solutions on the class website.
Now, this first R exercise was really
designed to get you to
explore the different options and deducer.
So if you found yourself struggling a
little bit, don't worry.
It's going to get easier from here.
So, the first step is actually not
question one.
The first thing we need to do is open up
deducer.
So to do that, I'm going to click this
short cut.
And there are two windows here.
There's the console window on the left,
and the data viewer window on the.
On the right, in order to open up my data,
which is provided to you as an Excel file
on the class website.
I'm going to click on the Open Data icon
on the Data Viewer window,
on the right hand side of the screen.
This will allow you to navigate to
wherever you have that Excel file saved.
In my case, it happens to be on the
desktop, and I’m going to select it and
open it.
Because our data is only on one worksheet,
the first one,
I’m just going to click OK here.
And I see that deducer was able to To load
in the data correctly.
I'm going to scroll to the right, make
sure everything is there, good.
I'm going to scroll down, to make sure I
have 50 rows.
Great.
So at this point we are now ready to
start the exercise.
The first question reads that varsity,
the variable varsity is currently stored
as type double.
We want to change this continuous variable
to a categorical variable.
R denotes categorical variables as
factors.
The way we're going to do this is using
the Data Viewer window on the right
hand side.
I'm going to click on Variable View here,
which will list all the variables in a
column.
Along with their type, and something
called factor levels.
And so, [COUGH] I'm going to go to
Varsity,
click on Type, and then select Factor.
And notice when I do this, that the factor
levels column gets populated for
that variable.
It shows two factor levels, level zero and
level one.
And that's because varsity only has two
values in it.
I do want to caution you, that,
when you're doing variable conversions in
deducer like I did just now.
That you don't go back and forth too many
times.
Because deducer will make assumptions
about what types of variables you want.
And what you want certain values to be.
So just be aware, that deducer makes
certain assumptions.
And to always check your data, after
changing anything.
For questions two we want to sort two
different variables.
Varsity and writing login different
orders.
So, first we want to sort varsity in
ascending order.
And then writing log in descending order.
Okay, so the way I'm going to do that.
I'm going to click back to Data View for
now.
The way I'm going to do this is by going
now to the Console window on
the left hand side here, and then clicking
on Data, then Sort.
This brings up a new window, the Sort Data
frame, and what this allows
us to do Is sort data in either ascending
or descending order.
So I'm going to click on Varsity, and then
move it over.
And then also move over WritingLove.
You can also just drag these variables
over, and
varsity is in ascending order, or
increasing here, and that's what we want.
But we want WritingLove in decreasing
order, so what I'm going to do is
highlight WritingLove, and then click the
button on the left here.
And that will change writing love to
decreasing, as you see.
Now, before I hit OK, it's important to
visualize what's going to happen.
So, we know varsity only has two levels,
right?
Or two different values, zero and one.
And so what this is going to do is
organize varsity,
such that all the zeros are on top, and
the ones are all on the bottom.
And then for each category.
So, within all the rows for which varsity
is zero,
writing love is going to be organized in
descending order in decreasing order.
And then again for varsity, for rows that
have a varsity value of one.
Writing love is, once again, going to be
ordered in decreasing value.
So we should see a jump, in WritingLove,
in the values of writing love when varsity
changes from zero to one.
Okay, so I'm going to hit OK.
And we'll see if that actually happens.
Great.
So the data changed here.
[COUGH].
We see Varsity.
So as you can see here, all the zeros were
grouped together.
And all the ones were grouped together
for, the varsity variable, and
all the zeroes were put first because we
wanted varsity in ascending order.
We want them to go from zero to one.
And the other thing I want you to notice
is that the row numbers on
the left-hand side here are all jumbled
up, because the original row numbers.
Stuck with each row as it was sorted by R.
So then let's keep that in mind,
that varsity switches from 0 to 1 between
ID 31 and 30, here.
And then go look at what happened to
WritingLove.
So I'm going to scroll to the right, and
we see that WritingLove is sorted in
descending order until we hit between row
31 and 30 here.
Where it goes from 20 to 19 to 10, and
then there's two cells With missing values
denoted as na.
And then we start over at 98.
And then, again WritingLove is sorted in
descending value.
So, I'd like to talk a little bit about
missing values, in R.
So, note that missing values are denoted
as NA.
The important distinction here, between R
and
other statistical programming packages,
like for example, SAS or STATA.
Or SPSS, whatever you might use, is that
na is not given a value in r.
In those other packages missing values are
given either a very, very,
very large positive value, or a very,
very, very large negative value.
And there are reasons for this, but it's
important to know that in r,
missing is just missing and it's not given
a large value.
Moving on to question three, question
three reads, filter the data,
such that you create a dataset.
With only records of students who have
MathLove scores greater than or
equal to 70.
So what we're going to do is go to the
Console window, go to Data, and
then select Subset.
What this is going to allow us to do,
is to create an expression that selects
only for those students.
So first I'm going to double click on
Mathlove, and
when I do that you'll see Mathlove
populate the subset expression box.
And then we have all these logical
operators over here.
And, we're going to want to select the
greater than or
equal to button, for greater than or equal
to 70.
And then we can simply type in 7,0, and
hit OK.
So what did this do?
It essentially created a new dataset.
For students or IDs that satisfy that
condition.
If we go to the Data Viewer window now, on
the right hand side, and under Dataset.
We click the drop-down menu, we see that
there are two options now,
Mock Class Data, which was our original
dataset, and now mock.class.data.sub.
And selecting that second dataset,
we see that it's a truncated version of
our original dataset.
And if we scroll over to the right, we
notice that all the values for
Mathlove are greater than or equal to 70.
Question four reads click on Extras,
Extras then Data Summary, for
a quick summary of all the variables in
your dataset.
How many missing values does Carter have?
Okay, so I'm going to go back to our
original dataset, mock.class.data.
And then I'm going to follow the
instructions and
go to Extras, actually extras is not an
option on the Console window right now.
So this is actually a good example of
something you might encounter.
The way to deal with this is to click on
Packages and Data.
Click on Package Manager.
And then select Deducer Extras here.
And if you followed the instructions in
the installation video these should
already be selected.
Okay, now that we do that.
We see that extras pops up here in the
Console window.
So that'll allow us to select Data
Summary.
And then it'll allow us to select our
Dataset.
I'll hit Run.
Now, if I spread this out a little bit, it
makes a little more sense.
And we can see that it gives us summary
information for
all the variables in our Dataset.
Now, to specifically answer the question
about how many missing values we have in
the variable Carter.
I go to, affine carter, I go to that, and
then I look at NA's, or
number of missings, in other words.
And I see that we have 12 missing values
in the variable carter.
The next question asks us to create a
histogram.
In dark blue for the variable, coffee.
And so what I'm going to do is go to Plots
and select Plot B uilder.
I'm going to click on Histogram and
actually drag it down to this space right
here.
I'm going to let go and
then again I'm going to click on coffee
and drag it to the Variable window.
And once you drag the variable coffee over
variable will turn green.
I'll hit OK.
And this is going to plot a histogram of
coffee drinking.
Now, I want this histogram to be in blue,
and
this template that it offered me didn't
offer me that choice.
So what I'm going to do is Delete this for
now, and
then select the Geometric Elements tab.
And then I'm going to select histogram
from here.
Now this is going to offer me a few more
options as you can see.
I'm going to drag coffee over again under
X.
This represents the variable you want
across the X axis you'll see the X
turn green once I did that.
And then, this option allows me to set the
Fill and the Color.
Color just means the color of the line.
So I'm going to click on Color, and then
select some kind of blue, hit OK.
And I'll do the same thing for Color.
And then I'll hit OK.
And then you'll see that it now plots me a
histogram of coffee drinking, in blue.
Moving on, now we want to create a scatter
plot of hours of exercise, or
in other words a variable exercise, versus
hours of homework.
One reason you might want to do this,
is to see what the distribution is for
people.
Or rather with what happens to the amount
of time you spend exercising as
the amount of time you spend on homework
increases, right.
So you can imagine that if that was your
question,
this might be a first step into looking at
that relationship.
So what I'm going to do is first let me
exit out of this plot builder,
I'm going to go to Plot Builder again,
Plots, Plot Builder.
And then from templates I'm going to
select Scatter Smooth.
So again what I'm going to do is, simply
click here and
drag this down into this space.
Okay, and I have two options here.
I can drag a variable onto the x amount of
the y, and as you've probably guessed,
that means that I can specify what
variables I want on what axis.
But this question, it doesn't really
matter.
I'm just going to move exercise to the x
axis, and homework to the y axis.
The questions specifies that they want a
smoothed curve.
So I'm just going to leave that there.
And I'm going to hit OK, great.
And so now we see this relationship.
So as you can see here the trend line is
pretty flat.
I wouldn't say there's a really dramatic
trend at all.
There might be a slight trend or
small correlation between having a lot of
homework and exercising less.
But again, that would be a very weak
effect here.
And I don't notice any egregious outliers,
as well.
So, these are all things you sort of want
to keep in mind as you look at
these different plots.
Moving on to question seven,
question seven is asking us to create a
histogram for the variable milk.
And then it gives us a little more
information, so
let's, let's just do that first.
So I'm going to go to Plots and Plot
Builder again.
Drag down histogram, drag over milk,
whoops.
Hit OK.
And now I see this histogram for milk.
I'm going to continue the questions now.
So, the question says, you notice that's
there's one person who
indicated [COUGH] 50 which seems like an
outlier compared to the rest of your data.
After going back to the data collection
forms you verify in fact that 50
was miscoded and that the true value
should have been five.
This happens all the time.
You decide to fix this problem, by
creating a new variable called milk fixed.
And so presumably now, that's our
exercise.
To create a milk fixed variable that
removes or
recodes, this value 50 into the value 5.
The way I'm going to do this is first to
close the Plot Builder window.
Then I'm going to go to data, and select
recode variable.
And what I'm going to do is first drag
over Milk,
then I'm going to highlight Milk and
select Target.
And then it's going to ask me to recode
Milk into something, so
I want to recode this variable into Milk
Fixed, hit OK.
So now you see that this changed the
notations in this window.
Now it says milk into milkFixed, okay?
I'm going to select Define Recode, so this
is sort of the rule for
what I want, or how I want to recode this
original value variable of milk.
So what I can do here is simply type in
50, here, and 5 here, and select Add.
So, what this is saying is when milk
equals 50,
change that into five, for milk fixed,
okay.
Were going to hit OK, hit OK hm-mm.
So I'm going to scroll overall the way to
the right here and
you see that there's this new variable,
milk fixed.
And I'm going to scroll down, actually let
me go find that 50 first.
Where is that guy, row 30.
Okay, subject 30, or patient 30.
And I'm going to scroll over to milkFixed,
and I notice that when I go to
patient 30 and I look at this value that
it's indeed recoded as fixed.
Now, how do I know that nothing else has
changed?
Well, I don't really unless I run some
tests, but just as a sanity check let me
compare the first three values with the
first three values for each variable.
So the first three values for milk are 16,
0 and 4, first three variables for
milkFixed are the first three values I
should say, are 16, 0 and 4.
So, you know, you should always check.
What the, you should always check the
composition of
your variables after making a change like
this.
But for this exercise, I'm pretty
satisfied that my recoding worked.
Moving on to question eight, question
eight is asking for
the mean, the standard deviation.
The median number of hours of sleep in
this Dataset.
So, that's a lot to ask for.
but, there's a really handy function in
this program that allows us to
generate all three.
So, what I'm going to do is go to
Analysis, and
then Descriptive, and then drag over
Sleep.
going to hit Continue.
And then I can select what I want, what
sort of descriptive variables I want.
I'm going to select Median and also drag
that over.
So now if I hit Run, I'm going to get the
mean, the standard deviation,
the number of valid records for that
variable and the median for sleep.
And indeed, in the Console window we see
that the output is 6.97 for
mean sleep standard deviation of 0.7 and
the median is seven hours.
The next question is asking us to perform
a stratified analysis of mean outlook on
life by alcohol consumption.
Or set a different way, what's the mean
score for outlook on life for
each amount of alcohol consumed.
The way I'm going to do this is to go to
Analysis and then Descriptives.
And then I'm going to move sleep back over
here,
because we're not interested in that
anymore.
And instead select Optimism.
And what I'm going to stratify by, is
alcohol.
Because what we want to see is the sort of
mean of optimism, or different val,
different descriptive values for optimism
by level of alcohol intake.
So I'm going to drag alcohol to the
Stratify By window, click Continue.
And I'm pretty happy with this, I don't
really need to see standard deviation.
But mean and median are good things to
look at, so
I'm going to keep those and hit Run, okay.
Now, I'm going to widen this window a
little bit, and I see that for
each value of alcohol, the program
calculated the mean optimism.
The number of optimism records that had,
that alcohol value as well as the median
optimism for that value.
And so, to get back to the question the
questions specifically asks the mean
score for those who indicated that they
had five drinks.
So I'm going to go to alcohol 5, mean
optimism is 74.5.
The next question asks us, how many people
consider themselves street smart?
Now, just faced with that question, you
might not know where to begin.
But, to phrase that a different way,
that's like saying,
what's the frequency of people who
consider themselves street smart.
And that sounds a little more statistical.
Basically that gives you a hint that we
want to go to Analysis and
select Frequencies, okay?
Then I'm going to move over the
IsBookSmart variable, and hit OK.
So, this gives me, an output that
generates frequencies for
the different values of IsBookSmart.
Now, IsBookSmart is binary, it's either
YesBookSmart or NoBookSmart.
In the case of no,
it means that you're street smart, that's
how the question was phrased.
And so we see that there are nine people
who consider themselves street smart in
this dataset.
And 40 people who consider themselves
booksmart in this dataset.
Just by convention, I should mention, that
0 means no, and 1 means yes.
That is sort of coding convention.
The next question asks us to create a box
Plot for the variable fruit veg.
And, it asks us what the black dot in the
figure represents.
Well, first, we need to generate the
figure.
So that's what I'm going to do, as you
probably guessed,
the way I'm going to do that is by going
to Plots > Plot Builder.
And then selecting, simple box plot, and
dragging that down here.
And then selecting the variable, fruitveg,
right here.
And dragging that into the variable box,
clicking OK, and, here we go.
Let me expand this a little bit.
So here's the box plot.
It looks a little trivial by itself.
It's not giving me too much information,
but the black dot.
So what does the black dot represent?
It's defined usually in box plots as data
points that are either more than one and
a half times the interquartile range.
The interquartile range is basically the
length of the rectangle.
The interquartile range represents
everything from
the 25th percentile to the 75th percentile
of the data.
So if your 1.5 times that range, then
you're usually considered an outlier.
So, I'd say that that black dot represents
an outlier in our dataset.
The last question in the exercise asks us
to reexamine the relationship of
mean outlook on life by alcohol
consumption, using a group box plot.
So, I'm going to stay in the Plot Builder
window,
the way I'm going to do that is to select
Group Box plot and drag that down.
Under Variable, I'm going to move
Optimism, and
then under Group, I'm going to move
alcohol.
And the reason I'm going to do that is
because I want to look at the values for
optimism for each different alcohol group.
All right, so then I hit OK,
first I might need to Delete the simple
box plot from before.
And then I see this box plot, that is
stratified by
all the different values for alcohol in
the dataset.
And if there was some sort of trend let's
say between optimism and alcohol.
If you drank more, maybe you were more or
less optimistic about your outlook on
life.
You would see this box plot, this visual
will show you that.
But in this figure we don't really see any
sort of trend like that.
But it's just a nice way, it's another way
of visualizing that text heavy data,
that we were looking at before.
So that concludes the exercise.
One last note I want to make is that there
are a lot of different ways you
could have approached these problems.
And you might have found, let's say the
mean or the median for a variable,
in a different way than I showed in this
video, or that I wrote in the solutions.
And that's absolutely fine.
There are many, many different ways of
arriving at the answer.
This is just one example, or one
suggestion, of how to do that.
And that concludes this
first R video module.