Welcome to the second R module.
In this video, I'll be walking through the
solutions to the second R exercise.
You'll also be able to find a written
version of these solutions on
the class website.
The first thing I'm going to do is to
start Deducer.
In this exercise, we'll be using the same
data set as in the previous exercise.
The data set's called mock class data, and
it's provided to you in Excel form.
We see two familiar windows on the screen.
On the left we have the console window and
on the right we have the data viewer
window.
Window.
In order to open the class data,
I'm going to click on the Open Data icon
on the Data Viewer window, and then I'm
going to navigate to where I have the mock
class data set saved onto my computer.
For me, that's on the desktop.
So I'm going to select that and hit Open.
then Deducer prompts me, asks me which
worksheet should be loaded.
Since our data only has one worksheet, I'm
going to just click Okay.
And then we see that Deducer was able to
load all of our data, I'm going to scroll
all the way to the right just to make sure
everything was loaded, and scroll down.
I have 50 rows.
Excellent.
So now we're ready to start the exercise.
The first problem is asking us
whether those people who are varsity
athletes in high school.
Currently exercise more than those people
who
were not varsity athletes in high school.
And so, question 1A is asking us what
statistical test we would use to
make this comparison and why.
And so, the thought process is that we are
comparing two unrelated groups,
varsity athletes and non-varsity athletes
on a continuous measure.
So that's the amount of exercise they
have.
And so these 2 things taken together leads
to the conclusion that we
want to use the 2 sample t-test, otherwise
known as the independent samples.
T test.
Again the reason why we're using this test
instead of the Paired T
test is that these two groups are not
correlated.
Then the questions asks us to perform the
statistical test,
report the P value for that test, and
to also plot, the relationship between
each group.
That's 1-C.
We're just going to do both at the same
time here.
So, the first step is to look at the
consult window and
select Analysis, and two sample tests.
This brings up the two independent sample
tests menu.
The first thing that we're going to do is
to split up
our cohort into varsity athletes and
non-varsity athletes in high school.
So, we're going to select varsity and drag
that over to factor.
And then we're going to click on split.
I am going to select 0 into group 1 and 1
into group 2.
Now in this situation it doesn't really
matter on
where the 0 and 1 go, so I could have 0 in
group 2 and 1 in group 1.
Boyd realized that this is a neat way
[UNKNOWN]
said you had more that two Two levels.
This a neat way of selecting which two
comparisons you wanted to make.
So we're going to hit okay.
In the outcomes box, I'm going to drag
over the exercise variable.
Because that's what we're trying to
compare.
In the lower left corner of the menu we
see
See that the t-test is selected by
default.
So that's good.
I'm going to click on the wrench here just
because I want to,
or the gear here, because I want to see
what options we have.
It seems like we have the option to run
the t-test assuming unequal variances or
equal variances.
For now I'm going to leave this as unequal
variances.
I hit Okay.
Then you also notice that there's a plots
button here, so I'm going to click that
and click on horizontal, so that it
generates a plot for us.
And I'm going to hit Okay, and then Run.
So notice, a few things happened.
One is that we have a window that shows
two box plots, and
we'll address that in a moment.
What we also see on the left-hand side
that there's an output in
the console window.
So spreading that out, we see a few
things.
So we see that the mean of the mean level
of exercise for those people.
That have a 0 coded under varsity.
So in English that means the mean hours of
exercise for
non-varsity athletes was found to be
3.575.
So approximately 3.6.
And that the mean or the mean for varsity
athletes or
the mean of level 1 for varsity was 4.55.
And so we know that, we see that there's a
difference here in the means.
There's a difference Of about, you know
one hour of exercise on average.
But then we look at the p value which is
in the row below that.
And we notice that that p value is .21.
So our conclusion is that there's no
statistically significant
difference Between the means of these two
groups.
So, said another way, our conclusion is
that there's no statistically significant
difference in the amount of exercise.
That people who are varsity athletes in
high school.
Get right now versus non varsity athletes.
To reinforce that conclusion what we're
going to do is look at our plot here.
It's always a good idea to visualize your
data just to make sure.
You understand what's going on.
It can sort of act as a very good sanity
check.
On the x-axis here we have exercise.
And on the y-axis we have our two groups,
varsity and non-varsity athletes.
And we can tell that although the averages
are different.
There's a significant amount of overlap in
how the data is distributed.
And so it's not surprising that we came to
the result that we can not reject the
null.
Moving on to problem two, now we're
interested in comparing whether
students love math more, or whether
students love writing more.
And the way we're going to do that in this
data set is to compare the math
love variable and the writing love.
Of variable, pretty convenient.
And so the first part of this question
asks us what
statistical test we would use to make this
comparison and why.
Well, in this case, what we're going to do
is we're going to use a paried t tes.
And the reason we're using a paried t test
this time is
because these two variables actually are
correlated.
They are related.
And they're related because the same
student answered both questions.
So student A you can imagine would fill
out writing love and math love.
And if student A really liked school he's
going to, he or
she is going to score those two variables
very highly and so they're related.
So the second part of this question asks
us how this statistical test differs from
the test in question 1.
So in question 1 we used the independent
samples T-test.
And in this question we're using the
paired samples T-test.
Now how are these two different?
In question 1 if you remember what we were
doing was we
were comparing the mean exercise values.
Or the mean exercise levels for two
separate groups,
varsity athletes and non-varsity athletes.
So you can imagine what Deducer or
what R is doing in the background is that
it's calculating the means separately for
both groups and it calculates a standard
error for that mean.
Or a standard deviation.
And based on that variation it's able to
compare these 2
means to say whether there's an actual
difference.
In a paired t test because we want to
maintain the correlation,
we want to maintain the relationship
between the two variables,
writing love and math love, what our
deducer's actually doing is that it's
taking the difference between math love
and writing love and
seeing if that, if the mean of that
difference is different than zero.
Let me say that a different way.
So in the first question, with the two
samples What we're
doing is we're comparing the two means
between each other.
And in this question we're calculating a
difference between, between
the two variables and then we're comparing
that mean difference with zero to
see if it's statistically significant.
To see if there's a statistically
significant
difference.
Between that mean difference and zero.
So, third part of question two asks us to
perform this statistical test and to
report the PRE for it and
to state on average how different are
these quote-unquote love scores.
So let's do that.
I'm going to click Analysis.
And then go to the Paired Test option
here.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to
select both Math Love and Writing Love.
And drag those into the boxes labeled
first and second.
It doesn't matter in to which category you
drag each variable.
Just keep in mind that the mean difference
is going to be flipped.
The sign of the mean difference is going
to be flipped,
in the output if you flip these two.
So, T-test is selected by default, so
that's good.
And then I'm just going to hit run, and
we have our output in the console window
here.
We notice that our p value is 0.098, which
means that we cannot reject
the null hypothesis based on an alpha
level of 0.05.
We would need the p value to be less than
Than 0.05.
So, our conclusion is that there's no
statistically significant difference
between how much people in this cohort
like writing versus math.
Notice that we come to this conclusion
even though
the mean difference between the two groups
is about seven and a half points.
Which is illustrated a few lines below the
p-value output.
Question three asks us for an assumption
of the previous two tests.
And that we check this condition for the
variable riding love visually.
And so what the question is implying is
that the variables for
a T-test need to be normally distributed.
That's one of the assumptions of the
T-test, it's a parametric test.
As a side note actually the paired T-test
does not
assume normality for the variables, but it
assumes normality for the difference.
Between the 2 variables.
So just keep that in mind.
So we want to check normality for the
writing love variable.
And to do that what we're going to do is
plot that variable.
So I'm going to select Plots, Plot
Builder.
I'm going to drag down Histogram here and
select riding love, and just visually look
at our output.
And so we notice that it doesn't look very
normally distributed.
It actually looks pretty bimodal with a
peak centering around 20% riding love,
and another peak around 70%.
So I would say that this doesn't look Very
normal.
Question 4 leads us to then
investigate this relationship further by
using a non parametric test.
So, question 4 asks us to
run the non parametric version of the test
in question 1.
So, what statistical test will we use to.
To make this comparison.
Well the non-parametric version of the
independent samples T-test is
called the Wilcoxon Rank Sum Test.
And it's asking us to perform this
statistical test.
So I'm going to hit cancel here, and the
way to do this would be to
go to Analysis and then go back to Two
Sample Test.
You'll see that our variables are still
where we left them,
exercises under the outcomes box, and
varsity is in the factor box.
What we need to do here is to uncheck T
test and
check Wilcoxon here because we want the
Wilcoxon Rank Sum Test.
Then I'm going to hit Run.
You'll notice it generated a plot for me
again because I didn't have it unchecked.
The plot should look identical to our
previous plot.
We look at the p-value in the console
window under the Wilcoxon rank sum test.
Heading, and we see that the p-value is
equal to 0.19.
So this does not change our conclusion.
If you remember previously, we had a
p-value of 0.21.
So it lowers it a little bit actually but,
it's still greater than 0.05, so we can
not reject the null.
Question 5 is asking us
What menu option we would select to
perform an ANOVA?
So, it's basically asking us how we would
perform an ANOVA and Deducer and R.
Well, if you think about it, an ANOVA is
kind of like an extension of a t-test over
multiple groups.
So it makes sense to have it near the
T-test option.
So if we're hunting for this, I would go
under Analysis and
try to look somewhere near the Two Sample
Test.
And I notice that it says the K-Sample
Test, well what is that?
So K-Sample Test actually just means
multiple independent samples,
so K just being a random number.
So a random number of samples And to back
this up we also see in the bottom
left-hand corner, the default test here is
a one-way ANOVA.
So to run an ANOVA in Deducer even though
we won't actually run one now,
you'd go to Analysis.
Select key sample test and then select
your variables in this menu.
Moving on to question six.
So we're now interested in seeing whether
there's a difference in whether one
considers themselves book smart or street
smart.
Based upon whether you played a varsity
sport in high school.
So, 6A asks us what statistical test we'd
use in this situation.
What's different about this question.
Is that the variable for book smart or
street smart is categorical, okay?
It's not a continuous variable here
because there are only two options.
A categorical variable could have more
than two levels.
So it just so happens that there are only
two levels here.
It's yes book smart or no book smart.
Which means you consider yourself street
smart.
And so in this situation we wouldn't want
to use a T test.
We would want to use a chi-square test.
So let's do that.
So I'm going to close the plot here.
And in order to run a chi-square test I'm
going to go to analysis.
And click on Contingency Tables.
And again it doesn't matter which
variables I put into the row or column for
the chi squared test, so I'm going to drag
over Varsity, as a row.
And I'm going to drag over IsBookSmart
into the column section.
And, there are a bunch of menus on the
right hand side, here.
Let's explore these for a second.
So cells allows us to ask for certain
percentages.
Or certain values related to the
Chi-Square test that we want.
For now I'm going to leave these
unchecked.
Under statistics we can ask for different
tests.
The Chi-Square test is selected by
default, but
we also do the likelihood ratio test,
Fisher's exact test.
And even do a Mantel-Haenszel test.
I'm going to leave all those unselected
for now as well.
Results let's us save the results.
I'm going to also leave that blank.
It's good to know what these menus do.
I'm going to hit run for now and see what
we have here.
So you see this two by two table.
You see that we have a Chi-squared
statistic and
a p-value associated with that.
But what should jump out at you is the low
number of cells in the.
First column here.
So because the cell numbers are low,
and because one of them is less than 5,
I suspect that maybe the chi square test
is not the best test to use here.
And that we should instead be using the
Fishers exact test.
Now I remember seeing that in the menus
before, so I'm going to go select that.
So I'm going to click on Analysis, and
then go to Contingency Tables.
The variables are still where we left
them, but
I'm going to click on statistics and Also
select Fisher's exact test.
Now the criteria for using Fisher's exact
test is really a rule of thumb.
There's no hard and fast rule, or
statistical rule,
I guess I should say, where you need to
use Fisher's exact test.
But I guess it's more accurate to say that
Fisher's exact test does a better job of
calculating the p-value when the expected
cell values are less than five.
I'll say that again in a different way.
So, the Chi-Square test does not do a good
job of approximating
the Key value of the relationship between
two variables when the expected cell
value in any of the cells of the
contingency table is less than five.
To illustrate that point, I'm going to
also select the expected cell
counts by clicking on Cells and checking
Expected.
going to hit Run.
You'll notice it generates the same table,
as before,
but there's additional output this time
because we had Fisher's exact selected.
We see that the chi squared p value is
3.19, and
the Fisher's exact test p-value is .367
You'll
see that the Fisher's exact test
attenuates the relationship a little bit.
And that the Chi-Square test does not as
good of
a job when the cell counts are low.
Let me scroll up a little bit here.
There are extra rows for the expected cell
count, and
you'll notice that these are definitely
less, that 3.67 is definitely less than 5.
So it's correct here to use the Fisher's
exact test, or I guess I
should say it's more accurate to use the
Fisher's exact test in this situation.
Our conclusion, of course, is that there's
no relationship Between these two
variables, and that or said another way,
there's no
relationship between whether you played a
varsity sport in high school and
whether you consider yourself book smart
based on the data in this data set.
The last question asks us to calculate the
risk ratio and the odds ratio for For
this relationship.
This is just a bit of an, a review
exercise here.
If your remember the risk ratio is defined
as
A over A plus B, and C over C plus D.
Now the 2 by 2 here is arranged a little
bit differently,
if we wanted to calculate the risk ratio
for, the risk of...
This is a little funny saying it this way,
but it's the risk of considering yourself
book smart.
Given that you played a varsity sport in
high school What you
would need to do is flip the rows, and
flip the columns,
such that the box in the uppe-, upper
left-hand corner,
corresponds to yes booksmart, yes varsity,
okay.
So the formula for this Is 25 over 29
divided by 15 over 20.
And so that gives us a risk ratio of about
1.15.
The odds ratio is defined as AD
over BC.
And in this case it would be the same if
we flipped the rows and columns.
So, we can just do 25 times 5 divided by
15 times 4.
To generate a value of 2.08.
And as a review, we see that the odds
ratio in fact does.
Inflate the risk ratio.
And that's the end of the exercise.
And the end of this, our module video.