This is the first video of a series of
modules that will explain how to
use a Deducer.
Which is a graphical user interface for
the program R to conduct your statistical
analysis.
R is a really powerful statistical
program, but for
those who have never coded before it can
be quite challenging.
What Deducer does is it creates a
graphical user interface, or
a gooey, for R users.
That simplify a lot of the coding that you
would otherwise need to learn.
This first module, we'll go over how to
download and install these
programs onto your computer so that you
can use them in the subsequent exercises.
So let's begin.
The first step is to open up your Internet
browser and go to www.deducer.org.
OK.
And then click on Download and Install in
the middle of the screen here.
And there are three different options for
different operating environments.
This computer that I'm working on is a
Windows machine.
So I'm going to click on Windows.
And then I'm going to click on Download
Installer.
So a few things I want to say while we're
waiting for this installer to download.
One is that all the,
instructions in this video are in written
form posted on the class website.
So, if that's easier or faster for you,
please follow the instructions there.
The other is that.
Deducer will require Java to run on your
machine, so
if you don't have Java, you're going to
need to install that first.
So it looks like the installer is
complete, so
I'm going to click on that and hit Run.
Want English, going to click Next, Next,
Next.
It's telling me where, it wants to install
R,
which is basically the statistical engine
that Deducer is going to run through.
OK, R already exists on this machine, so
this prompt comes up, it should not come
up.
When you're installing R on your computer.
I'm going to hit Yes.
I'm going to hit Next.
One thing I do want to point out is that
if you're on a Windows machine and
you're using the installer, then Java is
included in this package.
So, this package should have everything
that you need.
I do not want to customize, the
installation.
And I'm just going to keep clicking next.
I'm going to leave, Create a desktop icon,
checked.
don't really want a quick launch icon.
And that's that.
I do want to point out while we're waiting
for this to install,
that there are instructions for existing R
users in the background here,
on the Chrome page where we downloaded the
installer.
So for those of you with R already on your
machine,
you should feel free to update R first.
And then install the correct packages, in
order to run Deducer.
Okay, so the Java runtime environment has
been found.
That's because deducer's uh,been on this
computer before.
This should not come up for if you're
installing this for the first time.
So it looks like it's completed.
What I'm going to do is minimize this for
now and then go to the Deducer shortcut.
So this is what it looks like on the
screen here.
I'm going to double-click that, and I see
two windows pop up here.
So one's called the console.
And one's called the data viewer.
Okay.
So the first thing I want to do is select
Packages in data.
And then go to package manager.
And the reason why I want to do that is
because I want to select,
the check boxes next to Deducer extras.
Again, what I did was I went to Packages
in data.
I selected package manager.
Okay and I selected the check boxes under
the columns, default, and loaded.
So both checkboxes next to Deducer extras.
And what that's going to do is create a
whole nother menu for us,
that offers, statistical tests and options
that we didn't have before.
So we're going to be using those in the
exercises, so
it's a good idea to just include that
right now.
So believe it or not, that's it.
Now you have Deducer and R both running on
your computer.
So now that we've installed R and Deducer.
Let's try to open up the class data and
see what it looks like.
So, not shown here, but I've gone to the
class website and downloaded this
Excel spreadsheet called mock class data,
and saved it to my desktop.
So what I want to do now is click on the
open data icon in the data viewer window,
on the right-hand side of the screen here,
and then navigate towards the desktop,
or wherever you saved mock class data, and
hit Open.
And I want, there's only one worksheet.
[INAUDIBLE] here with data, so I'm just
going to hit Ok.
And here we go.
So the data has been loaded.
There should be 50 rows.
Good.
It's always good to check your data and
look across it to make sure everything's
been loaded correctly.
And so just scrolling left and
right and up and down, I see that
everything's been loaded.
And you're essentially ready to go at this
point.
So if you,
a few things that I want to point out
before you jump in the exercises.
There are two tabs here data view and
variable view.
Data view is the spread sheet view it's
almost like you're
looking at an Excel Spreadsheet or
something like that.
You can directly change data here by
clicking on random cells.
So please be very very careful that you
don't do that.
okay.
I was just demonstrating that by
selecting random cells and hitting
numbers.
In variable view, in this tab we see a
list of all of
the variables in the data set as well as
their type.
So, variable types can range between a few
things.
So you can have character variables which
are otherwise known as strings.
So letters essentially are the conventions
actually is just
keep all variables that you don't plan on
doing any math on as character variables.
So, things like zip codes or reference
numbers.
Is things like that.
That you don't want to do math on.
Even if they're numbers you generally
want to make them character variables.
Just to prevent any mistakes from
happening.
Now things like age where you might
want to take the average of it in
your data set.
You can keep those as a numeric varialbe.
And the numeric variables here are double
and integer.
Factor is r's way of describing a
categorical variable.
And you'll also notice that there are
different options for
date and time variables ,okay?
You can have multiple data sets open at
the same time.
And the way to navigate between them is to
click on
the drop-down underneath Data Set in the
center.
And I only have one data set open, so
only one drops down here, but you can
image having two or three open.
And that's essentially the data of your
window.
The console window is where you're
going to have more of your meaty
statistical options.
So the tabs that we're going to be using
in our exercises are the Data tab.
The Analysis tab, the Plots tab, and the
Extras tab.
Okay.
So these 4 tabs are going to have 95% of
everything that we're interested in.
One last thing I want to note before
ending the video is
that sometimes you might have an issue
importing an Excel file.
The first time that you run reducer.
And if that's the case that's the case
there's a little there's a little trick.
So, for Windows, Windows users, what you
can do is type in a certain command,
so that is, and I'll show you here.
Type in
install.packages("XLConnect")
So if you hit that, this [INAUDIBLE] will
come up.
Just select USA and then the state that
you're closest to,
or really where ever in the world you're
closest to.
And hit OK to download and install that
package.
And that package is going to help you
import Excel files.
Okay?
If you're on a Mac and you experience the
same problem it's similar code.
But it's a little more involved.
So you want to Basically do the same
thing.
Type in install.packages("rJava").
So run that.
Hit Enter.
I'm not going to do it here.
Here and then one more.
So do install.packages again.
And then ("XLConnect" like we did before,
except this time you're also going to also
put in comma space
type=
Open quote source and close quote, close
parentheses.
So, and hit enter.
Okay?
So that should install this package that
you need to import Excel files.
Now if your R is up to date, and your
Deducer is up to date and you're
using the most up to date packages for
everything, this should not be a problem.
But this is something that commonly
happens so
I just wanted to show this in the video
just in case.
Okay, so that wraps up the download and
installation video.
Hope that was helpful.