Today we're going to be talking about a
virus that
infects virtually every child in North
America before their second birthday.
And the most common disease that this
virus causes in little people,
is a condition called RSV bronchiolitis.
RSV or respiratory syncytial virus can
cause a minor cold in an adult,
but physicians usually see this infection
when it's causing an infection of
the small airways bronchiolitis in a child
under the age of two.
So, let's use our frame work to help us
understand what's going on with
this little guy.
An eight month old boy whose being brought
into the hospital ER
on a snowy December night.
His mother is scared because he has a high
fever.
And seems to be struggling to breathe.
Because of this, he hasn't been able to
sleep or feed well for the past 24 hours.
You can see right away, when you first
meet this child, that he's irritable,
breathing faster than normal, and it works
like he's working pretty hard to breathe.
The muscles of his neck and abdomen are
clearly trying to help out,
even his nostrils are flaring, and there's
clear rhinorrhea, or
fluid running out of his nose.
The nurse in the ER has taped a monitor to
his big toe,
to detect the amount of oxygen in his
blood.
And she tells you, this baby's oxygen
saturation is slightly below normal.
When you examine him you also hear a
wheezy sound as he breathes and you've
noticed that he seems to be grunting a
little bit when he breathes as well.
Your preceptor tells you that given the
time of year and the baby's symptoms.
It's highly likely, this little guy has an
RSV infection.
RSV is an enveloped RNA virus with two
large glyco proteins, F and
G, that are important for immunity and
pathogenesis.
The F protein is involved in fusion of the
virus and host cell plasma membranes,
forming the sinsisha that can be seen in
vitro with specific cell cultures.
This explains where RSV got its name.
To definitively diagnose RSV, you could
ask a virology lab at the hospital to
test for RSV in a swab or aspirate from
the nasopharyngeal space.
Because RSV doesn't usually live in or
colonize healthy people.
Finding it in any of the respiratory
secretions means the patient has
the infection.
From late October to early March, lots of
babies are brought to the E.R.
with these symptoms.
Some of them will even die from this
disease.
This child's dad has also been sick, but
only with a minor cold.
He may have sneezed nearby and our patient
breathed in the virus.
This is one of the reasons we see so many
RSV infections during the winter months.
When people spend more time indoors, in
close quarters.
Once the RSV got inside of our patient,
his immune
system recognized a viral invasion and
deployed some chemical messengers.
Things like cytokines and leukotreines to
try and protect him.
And as a result, the upper respiratory
tract started secreting mucus to try and
stop the virus from moving further down
the respiratory tract.
The, the blood vessels in this area also
became a bit leaky and blood flow to
the upper respiratory tract increased as
well, so that white blood cells and other
protective factors could get to the virus
in the hopes of stopping it in its tracks.
The extra mucus and the vasal dilation in
the baby's nasal
passages cause the congestion and the
runny nose that's making him so miserable.
And the chemical messengers also caused
his temperature set point to rise,
giving him a fever.
But unfortunately in this case,
the virus kept moving down the respiratory
tract despite the efforts of
the respiratory cilia in the airways
trying to beat it back upwards.
And also despite the increased respiratory
secretions and blood flow to that area.
Now these weren't the immune system's
efforts to stop the virus from
causing more harm.
But all of these changes also contributed
to the symptoms that
brought this little guy into the hospital.
If the virus had been stopped at any of
the early stages in the nasal passages for
example.
Our baby would have ended up with a milder
Upper Respiratory Tract Infection or URTI.
A rhinitis, a pharyngitis or a laryngitis,
depending on where the virus had stopped.
But because the innoculin, or
the amount of virus that our patient first
breathed in, was pretty substantial.
And, because his immune system wasn't
strong enough to
win this battle in the early stages, the
virus managed to move
deeper into the lower respiratory tract,
invading the bronchioles and the alveoli.
In the bronchioles, this child's immune
system kept on trying to protect him.
Trying to prevent the virus from going any
further.
The epithelium of the small airways began
to sluff off.
More mucus was released into the lumen.
And the walls to the bronchials became
swollen as blood flowed to
the area increased.
All of these things were immune system
attempts mediated by
chemical messengers to block the further
passage of the virus into the lungs.
But they also made it really hard for our
little patient to breathe
because the diameter of each tube was made
so much smaller.
The narrowed airways also caused the
wheezing sounds that you heard when you
examined him.
And his grunting was actually an effort to
create positive pressure to keep those
small airways open.
Often, this narrowing of the bronchioles
can trigger prolonged coughing spells
as a child tries to clear some of those
secretions from his airways.
This bronchiolar hyperreactivity might
make you think about asthma and
the two can be very similar in terms of
their clinical presentation.
In fact, there is an ongoing debate about
whether or
not RSV bronchiolitis is maybe just the
first manifestation of
asthma in a child who had an underlying
predisposition to the disease.
Or whether the RSV broncholitis caused
some kind of
damage that predisposes a child to asthma
attacks later on.
When RSV gets down in to the bronchioles
and
the alveoli the lungs can't do their job
of oxygenating the blood very well
because the diffusion interface gets
thicker than it should be.
And this is because of the increased
secretions and
the edema at that interface.
This means that carbon dioxide and
other waste products in the blood, can't
get out as efficiently.
And oxygen in the inhaled air can't
diffuse into the blood as
quickly as it should.
Remember the nurse who told you that this
baby's oxygen saturation was slightly low?
Well, it's likely that this baby's lungs
we're able to exchange gasses as
efficiently as they do when he's healthy.
The good news is that RSV doesn't change
much from year to year and while we don't
yet have an effective vaccine to routinely
prevent RSV infection in all children,
we do have a way of protecting some high
risk babies from this infection.
By giving them passive antibody protection
from the virus during the winter months.
The difference between these two methods
of prevention,
is that the first kind, vaccination,
involves triggering the immune system to
mount its own long-lasting.
Testing response by exposing it
to an inactivated version of the original
pathogen.
Passive antibody protection involves
giving
a child the product of an immune response,
the kind of immunoglobulins that.
Are typically made to fight a virus like
this.
The only downside is that these passive
anti-bodies don't last very long, so
they need to be given monthly to high risk
children during the winter months.
Babies who are at risk of getting really
sick from an RSV infection,
fall into a few categories.
If they were born prematurely or if they
have some degree of chronic lung disease,
and that's often a result of the
prematurity.
If they have a form of congenital heart
disease,
that reduces the oxygen saturation of
their blood to start out with.
So a further reduction due to an RSV
infection would really cause trouble.
And then, there are children who are born
with neuromuscular disorders like
cerebral palsy, who lack the muscular
strength or
coordination to cough out the secretions
and successfully clear their airways.
These are also considered high risk
children.
And finally, if a child is immune
suppressed for any reason, these are all
children who would be good candidates for
monthly doses of immunoglobulin.
Luckily, even though our patient was
suffering from bronchiolitis,
he did well on supportive therapy in the
hospital.
He received supplemental oxygen delivered.
Through a face mask.
And, he received fluid and some glucose
through an intravenous line.
So, you can see from this baby's ordeal,
that knowing the characteristics of the
microbe RSV, how it enters and
exits the host, as well as the fact that
the virus has a tendency to colonize,
persist, and replicate in the small
airways of a young child.
This knowledge can inform our prevention
efforts and our treatment strategies.
Similarly, recognizing that the immune
systems early efforts to
eliminate the virus can actually cause
many of symptoms of the disease.
This can facilitate the timely diagnosis
and
treatment of patients like this little
boy.
[BLANK_AUDIO]