[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module,
I'm going to do a demo edit of a student's
essay from a previous course.
This will give you a chance to see how I
approach editing an entire essay.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now take a minute, pause the video, read
through this essay once or twice.
I've also provided the essay as a separate
text file, so
you can read through it there as well.
And if you have time it'd be even a great
exercise to try to edit it on
your own before you restart the video and
watch me walk you through it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This essay is on a biological topic.
It has a lot of nice features to it, so
one of the good things about this essay,
one thing the author has done really,
really nicely, is it's very clear what the
main point of the paper is.
And, in fact, there's a nice sentence
right at the end of
the first paragraph that says exactly what
the main point of this essay is.
In a landmark study, published in the
journal Plant Cell, Tanaka and
colleagues recently uncovered and
additional role for reactive oxygen
species as regulators of symbiosis.
So right in there in a nutshell, we get
exactly what this piece is about.
And the author does a great job of
sticking to that theme.
The essay is also really well organized.
The flow is very good, it follows along
very logically, so
you'll see as I'm editing this, I'm
actually not going to reor,
arrange any sentences or paragraphs as I
often will have to do in an edit.
The main thing that I'm going to focus on,
in this essay is just streamlining,
trimming a few words,
a few technical things here and there,
maybe changing a few nouns into verbs, and
that kind of thing that we've been talking
about in this course.
So starting with the first paragraph,
that's a great first sentence,
I'm actually going to leave it exactly as
it is.
Reactive oxygen species are highly
reactive chemicals often associated with
escalating warfare between pathogens and
their hosts.
So we get this picture right off the bat
of the reactive oxygen species as
a bad player.
And I think most readers will be familiar
with reactive oxygen
species because they're being talked about
pretty widely even in,
in popular media these days, and everybody
kind of knows they're bad players.
The next sentence gives some examples of
the use of ROS in biological defenses.
This sentence it just has a slight awkward
thing at the very end,
the to ward off of microbial infections
doesn't flow perfectly nicely here.
So this is a good example where a couple
of dashes might help us out.
So I'm just going to set off the examples
of
the biological defenses here with dashes.
That will just make it flow just a little
more smoothly here, and
then we have to change the to ward off, to
that ward off,
so we get that ROS are integral to
biological defenses.
Such as, here's a couple of examples, that
ward off microbial infections and
then, I'm going to change infections to
invaders just to
go along with this theme of the warfare
here.
It's a little bit, more exciting than
infections.
I'm going to make one small tweak to that
last sentence.
In a landmark study, published to the
journal Plant Cell,
I'm going to add the in 2006 here and take
out the word recently.
Mm, technically 2006 isn't totally recent,
so
I think it'd be better just to give the
date here.
So, the first paragraph works really well.
They get the point across.
It's nice, good, vivid language there.
The next paragraph gives the background
for
the Tanaka experiment, and I think again
it's really well organized.
It's the right thing to come next.
The only thing I'm going to do in this
paragraph is just to
take out a few extra words, and
a few technical details that we probably
don't need in the context of this essay.
So, for example, if we're kind of reading
along here,
we get that this fungus lives
endophytically (i.e.
inside).
Well, let's just say the word inside.
We can get rid of the technical term here.
This is not an essay that's about the
fungus,
really the fungus is just a vehicle for
this ROS discovery.
So we can get rid of technical terms that
have to do with the fungus for sure.
The same thing in the next sentence, I'm
just going to say the fungus,
let's not talk about the mycelium or the
hyphae or any of that.
I, I don't think its important in this
particular essay since the main focus is
really the ROS discovery.
So that, the fungus, we can get rid of all
of this detail.
I'm going to move this.
This is kind of a long sentence and it
ends with and
grows in perfect synchrony with the leaves
of its plant host.
I'm going to move this idea up.
Because that's really the symbiosis that
they grow in this perfect synchrony.
So, I'm going to say that the fungus rose
in perfect synchrony
with, we can probably just say, with the
plant, not with the leaves of the plant.
We're going to get the leaves next.
So with the plant and then colonizing.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oops, colonizing.
All of the leaves of the plant.
And we don't need to repeat the plant, so
colonizing all its leaves.
Get rid of of the plant.
Again, we get can rid of the details about
these hyphae.
But actually, we don't think we can use
the never here,
but never reaching cell walls or
membranes.
So just kind a, just kind of tucks that
sentence a little bit.
It all comes together a little bit faster
so
that fungus, grows in perfect synchrony
with the plant colonizing all,
its leaves, but never reaching cell walls
or membranes.
I think that gets across all the ideas
just a little bit faster.
In the next two sentences the author uses
the word harmonization twice.
I'm going to get rid of one of those
harmonizations.
I don't think we need to say it twice.
We can just say, explicitly what the plant
and the fungus do for
each other, so let's just say that very
explicitly.
Another thing to notice about this next
sentence is their you know,
it has the plant growth directs resources
to the production.
So we're getting growth directing
resources to production.
There's probably a way to use verbs here
to make that a little bit smoother,
a little bit more lively.
So I'm just going to say that the plant
directs resources.
It's really the plant that's directing the
resources to the fungus.
The plant directs resources to the fungus,
and then what does the fungus do?
Well, the fungus produces, so let's turn
production into produces,
produces toxins that protect the symbiosis
from herbivores, I might say both species.
Symbiosis sounds a little technical, so
maybe that protect both species from
herbivores.
But now this harmonization, so now we can
get the word harmonization.
If the author wants we can even put that
back, that exquisite harmonization.
The author obviously has a great
appreciation for this symbiosis.
So we can put that word back in.
But how does, exquisite harmonization is
achieved, and
what it's underlying mechanisms are, have
remained a mystery.
We probably don't need to say both.
How it's achieved and
what its mechanisms are, that's probably
all under the guise of a mechanism.
So we could just use the word mechanisms.
it's, I also want to put in a but until
Tanaka here,
because I feel like, well Tanaka solved
some of this mystery, right?
So some of this, it's, a lot of it is a
mystery, but
probably some of it is not anymore.
But until Tanaka, I want to just say
mechanisms
underlying this exquisite harmonization
remained a mystery.
So it was like a complete mystery before
Tanaka's paper, and
then it's made less of a mystery now.
Then we get a nice transition to address
this question, so we know exactly that
the next paragraph is going to lead us
into the the experiment that Tanaka and
coworkers did to address this question.
Again, I think there's a few things we can
streamline here.
So, the first sentence, it says, they
generated random mutations.
The second sentence says, how they
generated random mutations and why.
I think we can actually put that all into
one sentence, so
address this question, Tanaka and
coworkers, let's just say,
inserted, random pieces of DNA into the
fungal genome.
Then we can put in parenthesis.
A method called insertional mutagenesis.
So the author wanted to mentioned
insertional mutagenesis, what it was.
Well we can cut it.
That's kind of extra to put that actual
term in, but
we can put it in parenthesis there.
They insart, inserted random pieces of DNA
into the fungal genome in the hope of dis,
disrupting a gene.
Then, then we can shorten this a little
bit.
Instead of a gene resulting in observable
changes in growth changes in symbiosis,
write, I think the reader can infer, you
know,
that if you disrupt a gene that interrupts
growth you'll be able to.
To observe it, so we could just say in the
hope of disrupting genes,
critical, to the symbiosis, that are
critical for the symbiosis.
Critical for, critical to the symbiosis.
So we get all of that, all of those
concepts just in one quick sentence there,
and I think that's as much as the reader
needs and
the reader can get all the information
there.
They indeed found a mutant showing a
highly unusual growth pattern.
Colon, I like to use the colon there.
I might switch the indeed and they,
the order there, although that's more of a
personal preference.
Indeed, they found a mutant showing a
highly unusual growth pattern.
I might say a mutant strain, maybe with a
And then after the colon, we get unlike
the synchronous growth of
the wild type fungus, well we've been told
that it has a synchronous growth so
we don't need to repeat that.
So, we can just say exactly what's
different about its growth.
Indeed, they found a mutant strain with a
highly unusual growth pattern.
The mutant fungal cells.
Again, I'm going to avoid the word hyphae,
because it's kind of technical.
Showed profuse and abundant proliferation.
Well, this is one of those instances where
we've gotta show pro,
proliferation, where we could just say
proliferate or even simpler, grow.
So how about just grew profusely
throughout the grass.
And then I'm going to fold this last
sentence about the plants right into this,
this other sentence.
I think we can fold both of those ideas
together, so
that mutants fungal cells grew profusely
throughout the gla,
grass, then what happened to the plants
and, the infected plants.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And again, the author originally had
showed growth, showed poor growth.
We could just say grew poorly or grew
slowly, grew slowly and often died.
So I'm repeating a lot of what the author
had here but
just tying it into, folding it into that
last sentence.
Moving along, the authors then say, this
sets the stage for
the next step, finding the genetic changes
that cause these aborations.
Actually, I don't think we need any of
that.
The logic, the order here is so good,
that the reader can infer that once we
found a new that has aberrant growth.
That the next step would be to figure out
the genetics behind that.
I actually don't think the reader needs
quite as much hand holding here,
we can just jump right into the, what the
researchers did.
It's, again, makes logical sense that
they'd next go after the genetics.
So we can just start with, using molecular
genetic tools.
And I'm going to even condense this a
little bit further.
Using molecular genetic tools, the
researchers.
How about just found?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That in it, that an insertional event in a
single gene.
And then we can go right to the had
caused.
I'm just getting rid of some extra word
here, extra words.
And then an insertional event in a single
gene had caused this abnormal growth.
Yeah, no, I think we can just say this
aberrant growth.
Since I cut the word aberrant before I can
put it back in here, this aberrant growth.
And we can end, end the sentence right
there.
I got rid of the concept that, somehow it
was surprising.
I'm not sure exactly what was surprising.
Is it surprising that it only mutated one
event?
If that's an important detail, the author
need, would need to,
like, explain it a little bit better for
the reader, but I just cut it out.
Then I'm going to make a really short
sentence.
Sometimes it's nice to have kind of a long
And then just punctuate it with a short
sentence, so
I'm just going to make a tiny sentence
here, they called the gene, or
they named the gene, maybe named, they
named the gene NoxA.
We could just leave it at that.
We could just leave it at that, they named
the gene NoxA.
So it's a real short sentence, sometimes
nice to to break things up with kind of a,
just a short sentence in the middle of, of
a lot of long sentences.
So they named the gene, NoxA, and
then, I'm going to fold this paragraph
right into the next paragraph.
I want to combine the two,
we don't need, this doesn't need to be a
whole separate paragraph.
And the next paragraph talks about what
NoxA does, so
let's just put these two paragraphs
together.
Again, we don't really need the transition
to get an idea of
what the encoded protein does because we
can it,
the reader can kind of infer that once
you've discovered the gene, the next
thing you would be doing was trying to
figure out what the protein does.
We, you can just say what they did and
what they found in one sentence for the
next part.
So we can say, when they or when the team,
when they compared, its sequence,
as we've just said, the gene is NoxA, we
can say its sequence with those of
enzymes with known activities, and then we
can combine these two sentences.
They noticed that NoxA was very similar to
NADPH oxidases, enzymes,
how about say enzymes just that generate
ROS in cells.
So now we get, we get back to the
beginning of
the essay where they were talking about
these reactive oxygen species.
And, I'm actually going to end this
paragraph,
this whole paragraph right now, to kind of
emphasize this over back
to here's where they realized how ROS
suddenly appears in symbiosis.
And so this is kind of the key point,
they finally, this is how they got upon
the concept of ROS.
So I'm actually going to kind of end the
paragraph here,
just to kind of punctuate that,
and make, put a little bit of emphasis on
the fact that here's where we get that
connection back to the beginning of the
essay and the main theme of the essay.
I'm going to make one other little tiny
edit here.
They noticed that NoxA was very similar.
I've told you not to use adverbs like
very.
I'm going to put in an adverb here.
How about strikingly similar?
The fact that it's strikingly similar,
just kind of draws the reader in a little
bit.
You could have just no adverb there as
well.
You could just say was similar, but
somehow strikingly similar makes it
seem more exciting so I am going to leave
that in.
Then I am going to start a new paragraph
down here
where the author starts with indeed.
This author likes the transition word
indeed.
Cause we've already used it once before I
think I'll just say
further testing revealed, like this is
kind of the follow up studies to
their first discovery of the link with
ROS.
So further test, testing revealed that.
And then we can shorten things a little
bit here when the researchers next
looked at ROS production in the plant,
they observed.
I think we just say what they observed.
We don't have to say that they looked for
ROS production in the plant,
because that's sort of implied by the fact
that they observed it, so
we can get rid of all of that.
So, that, they observed that ROS further
testing revealed
that ROS accumulates in plants infected by
the wild type fungus.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That should just be a single little hyphen
in there and
plants infected by the wild type fungus.
And not those infected by the NoxA
disrupted mutant fungus, and we can say
but not those infected maybe just
by the NoxA mutants, just to make that a
little bit shorter, by the NoxA mutants.
So further testing revealed, that ROS
accumulates in plants infected by
the wild type fungus, but not those
infected by the NoxA mutants.
This confirmed that I'm going to change
this to the scientists concluded that.
The only reason I'm doing that is that
confirmed sounds like as if
we've know this for a while, but this is a
really a totally new discovery.
So I'm going to say that they concluded
that NoxA,
is involved in ROS production, requiring
for proper functioning of the symbiosis.
I think we can shorten that to the
scientists concluded,
that ROS is a critical player in
symbiosis.
ROS is a critical player in the symbiosis.
This is kind of the proof of what was said
at the very beginning of the essay that,
hey, this new role for ROS.
We get down to the last paragraph,
they had the tantalizing questions that
this discovery raises.
I'm going to fold together the first two
sentences here.
The, it raises tantalizing questions, the,
this is the main question,
we can put that all in one.
So it's just, how about, how ROS enables
symbiosis remains an open question.
Because that's really what this paragraph
is about,
is it, exactly what are the mechanisms
that ROS uses to help in the symbiosis.
And then we can say since I've deleted
Tanaka and
colleague, maybe I'll say Tanaka and
colleagues here, or Tanaka's team.
suggest, now this is kind of in the past
at this point because it was a 2006 paper,
so how about Tanaka's team speculated that
ROS may be involved.
I'm going to use may here,
because then, to be parallel with the next
sentence, which uses a may.
That ROS may be involved in establishing
physical connections between the cell
walls of the plant and fungus.
So that's one explanation.
Alternatively, ROS may play a role in
symbiotic signaling.
And I prefer a semicolon here to a colon
because the second part of the sentence
just adding information, it doesn't really
build on the first part of the sentence.
So, just personal preference I prefer a
semicolon here.
Their short half life predisposes them for
cellular communication perhaps
facilitating an interspecies Morse code
that helps maintain the symbiosis.
I think we can dump a few words here.
So their short half life makes them a
perfect candidate for
an interspecies Morse code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
For an interspecies Morse code.
We don't I don't think we have to repeat
that helps maintain the symbiosis since
this whole paragraph is about exactly how
ROS maintains the symbiosis.
If so, identifying the plant sensor and
signaling pathways involved, that's
kind of long.
How about we just said if so
breaking the code, as we've just referred
to this Morse code.
Breaking the code could provide deeper
insight into how plants recognize and
interact with their symbiotes.
And and just to be parallel, we've got
could provide deeper insights into how
plants recognize and interact and
distinguish.
We don't want want to have and
can distinguish just because that wouldn't
be parallel.
Then I feel like we need just a tiny
paragraph here to wrap up
the the, the essay.
I've got these open questions, but
remember, the big point here
is that Tanakas Group discovered that ROS
has this Is entirely different role.
We used to think that they were just bad
players, and
now it turns out they do these good things
for symbiosis.
So I feel like we need a little bit of
wrapping up that and
reminding the reader of that fundamental
point.
So, maybe something like,
Tanaka's paper fundamentally changed
scientists' views of ROS.
These chemicals, and
I'm going to, now kind of wrap back to the
beginning metaphor of warfare here.
These chemicals are not only weapons of
biological warfare.
Also agents of peace and cooperation.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So just kind of getting back to that
metaphor.
Notice that I've told you never to use
nots.
Well, I didn't say never to use nots but I
said you know, to try to avoid nots.
I've chosen to use a not here.
These chemicals are not only.
So sometimes, for effect you might choose
to use a not, but
just think carefully about it before you
do so.
And then I wonder if maybe, there's some
wider implications for biology.
This discovery seems important to me.
I've heard that, you know, ROS are these
bad players,
what does it mean that they might have
important good roles too?
So is there some wider implications for
biology in general that the reader, that
the author could add here just right at
the end to give the reader a taste of why
this paper is so important?
[BLANK_AUDIO]