[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, I'm going to edit a
student's essay from a previous course.
This will give you a sense of how I would
approach editing an entire essay.
Take a minute now and pause the video and
read the entire essay.
I've also provided a text file if you
want to read it there.
If you have time, try to edit it on your
own.
And then restart the video and I'll walk
you through how I would approach the edit.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So this essay deals with a really great
topic a phobia of dentists.
I didn't realize that there was a formal
phobia of dentistry.
It's called odontophobia.
But great topic, really draws the reader
in.
I, I was interested to read about this.
The main thing that I'm going to suggest
for
this author, the one thing that this essay
needs a little work on is that,
I'm not entirely sure what the main point
of this essay is.
The author is going to need to add a
paragraph,
probably right after the first paragraph
that tells the reader
exactly what they're trying to accomplish
in this essay.
What is the point of this essay?
And I can make some guesses about it,
but it's unclear if it's about the paper,
the treatments, is it advice for
dentists, it's a little unclear exactly
what the goal of this essay is.
So the author will need to add a paragraph
here to to bring that out.
And I'm going to make a guess about what
their intention might here,
be here but just for the purposes of
illustration.
The other thing is I'm going to reorganize
this essay a little bit.
Because I'm not entirely sure what the,
the main point of this essay is
the organize strikes me as needing a
little bit of reorganization to make the,
the, flow, and of course the exact flow
and
organization will depend on what the main
point of the essay is.
Other than that though, language is fairly
easy to understand.
I didn't have any trouble understanding
this, so that's what I'm mainly going to
rearrange, I'm going to, make a few
changes here and there to
improve the language, but mostly just
going to deal with organization and focus.
So, starting with the beginning,
60% of the world's population is afraid
somehow to go to the dentist.
I'm not sure that we need to be so exact
here.
I'm not sure where this 60% comes from.
So, maybe we can just say what everybody
knows to be true,
which is most people are afraid to go to
the dentist.
We don't need the word somehow, of course,
here.
Most people are afraid to go to the
dentist.
Perhaps we don't have to give the exact
statistic here because I'm a little
skeptical about where that came from.
But, 15 to 20% and maybe we say exactly 15
to 20% of whom?
I'm going to say, maybe adults worldwide.
I get the sense that this is a worldwide
focus here, so
maybe 15 to 20% of adults worldwide suffer
a more severe fear.
[SOUND].
Colon, it's getting used to the colon,
odontophobia.
And, you of course, are giving an exact
statistic here, this 15 to 20%.
We're going to need a reference to say
where that came from.
Perhaps that came from the World for
Health Organization, which is mentioned in
the next sentence, but it's unclear, so
we actually need the reference right there
for that particular statistic.
Actually going to delete this next
sentence about
the World Health Organization recognize it
as this severe fear.
I've already said what it is, that it's a
severe fear in the first sentence,
I don't think we need a second, a separate
sentence for that.
The main thing that the author is trying
to achieve in this first paragraph,
I think, is to differentiate for the
reader, which is very important,
what's the difference between just having
a normal fear of the dentist and
having odontophobia, which is as more so
your fear?
What's that what's the line between those
two things, and
I think the other's done a good job of, of
giving us some sense of why those two
things are different and how odontophobia
maybe is even diagnosed.
They may, the author may want to give a
little bit more if there's some diagnostic
criteria or something but I think I would
probably just recommend moving the
sentence about the symptoms to right after
the first line, because they mentioned,
you know, most people are afraid, but some
people have a more severe fear.
Maybe just describe right there what that
more severe fear looks like, so
this is kind of a list of a lot of medical
jargon so
I am also going to eliminate some of that
medical jargon.
So maybe we say sufferers just jump right
in to what they experience.
Sufferers may instead of hyperventilation,
let's make this into a verb,
hyperventilate.
They may hyperventilate tachycardia
hypertension sudden drop in blood pressure
some of those are medical jargon, so let's
change all of that to may hyperventilate,
experience sudden changes in heart rate
and blood pressure.
Transpiration is just sweating, so let's
say, just say sweat.
And I'm just going to truncate this and
say and vomit.
Cypher sufferers may hyperventilate,
experience sudden changes in heart rate
and blood pressure, sweat, and vomit.
Or, or vomit.
We should probably put, because they may
not experience all of these symptoms, or
vomit with just thinking about the
dentist's chair.
And then, I might move the words sweat up
here because this is kind of
a long description, experience sudden
changes so
it flows a little better if we put
hyperventilate, sweat, and then this
kind of longer description, or vomit when
just thinking about the dentist chair.
I don't think we need to, to be, list all
of the symptoms here, I think we just need
to give enough to give the reader a sense
of that this is pretty severe.
Then because we referred here to
sufferers,
we can say instead of this fear often
leaves people, we can just say they avoid,
the sufferers which we referred to in the
last sentence, they avoid.
So this is another thing that
distinguishes odontophobia from people who
just have kind of a normal fear of the
dentist, the people who have it,
actually avoid going to the dentist until
emergencies happen.
I changed this to until,
until it's an emergency, although I can go
either way on that one.
And then at which time, I changed this to
at which
time they may require invasive treatments.
This should be a that instead of a which,
invasive treatments that reinforce, I
don't think we need the can there.
That reinforce and then we don't need to
repeat fear of dentistry.
We could just say that reinforced their
phobia.
And I even added the word traumatic in
here so, I don't know if that's necessary
but they avoid going to the dentist until
it's an emergency at which time they may,
may require traumatic invasive treatments
that can reinforce their phobia.
So that first paragraph gives us a nice
summary of what odontophobia is,
what it looks like.
And then in this next paragraph, I'm
actually going to add a paragraph here
because I feel like I need to know where
this essay is going.
So we've got the description of
odontophobia but
what's the point of this essay?
Is it to describe new treatments for
Odontophobia, is it to give advice for
dentists, I'm going to just put something
in here,
which I think could be the focus, I'm not
sure.
Maybe something like, fortunately dentists
have many options,
because this seems to be going through a
litany of different treatment options,
have many options for treating and
managing their patients with odontophobia.
I'm a little bit targeting this essay as
if it's, you know,
targeted towards dentists.
The other doesn't have to do that.
If that wasn't their intent it would be
very easy to,
to take out the dentist part here.
But that's what I thought maybe they are,
they were trying to do here.
And I think what's really interesting and
what the others spent the most time
on here is they talk about all these kind
of simple, low cost interventions that you
can do instead of like having to go to a
psychotherapist or
take drugs, so I think that maybe that's
the main focus, the main point here.
So I'm going to say besides a conventional
therapy, so the author here had refer,
refered to behavior and pharmacological,
pharmacological approaches,
I'm going to call that behid, beside
conventional treatments.
Call that treatments because I'm going to
use therapies in the next second here, and
then in, in, set off with dashes which
includes, you know,
behavioral therapy, that's your,, your
typical psycho,
that's psychological therapy, behavioral
therapy and drugs.
So I'm just putting those examples in
dashes some surprisingly
simple, no cost intervention may also be
quite effective.
[SOUND].
So I'm just making a note to the author
that they need to clearly state the main
point of the essay here and if I haven't
got it quite right they may want to
treat this a little bit, but I think that
the idea is that,
besides conventional treatments, there's
some surprisingly simple,
low cost interventions out there that
might be an, quite effective as well.
The one that struck me was this idea of
pumping the smell of coffee and
fresh bread through the dentist's office.
That seems like a great idea.
So that's a, you know, a simple and low
cost.
So this next paragraph that in terms of
organization, I'm going to make the next
paragraph just be about a whole bunch of
simple things that the dentist can do to
improve their office to make it more
friendly for these types of patients.
So I've already kind of said,
pharmological and
behaviorals, get rid of that.
The next sentence talks about the
sensorial stimuli, and
the sentence after that talks about the
sensorial stimuli, so
I thought we could combine those two
sentences.
This sentence here is just a description
of the types of
sensorial stimuli that you can use, so I'm
going to start with a recent study from
the National Italian Union of Dental
Industry, showed that sensorial stimuli,
and let me give you some examples here,
with using, setting this off with dashes.
So those would include things like the
pleasant smells, so sensorial stimuli, so
pleasant odors, like fresh bread or
coffee, warm colors of the place, we don't
need of the place, just warm colors.
Pleasant music, or beautiful paintings on
the walls.
So those are all the examples, and then,
getting back the dash here.
And then we get our decisive from the
psychological perspective of
the patient and can be preferable than the
use of anti, these are anxialytics or
anti anxiety drugs.
I think we can say there's a little bit
more crisply, so maybe just our work
as well, work as well as anti-anxiety
drugs, for many patients,
I don't know if that's true, I'm assuming
that this study kind of talked about the,
the effectiveness of these, if we, if
they, if that's even been ever researched.
So I'm just kind of guessing here, but
maybe they work as well as anti-anxiety
drugs for many patients or
maybe patients prefer them or it, give
something about exactly what
the study tells us about the effectiveness
of this, of these stimuli.
Then we get a list of drugs, I,
since I'm going to make this paragraph
about the simple non-drug interventions,
I'm going to move the drug list down to a
lower paragraph.
I'll get back to the drugs in a few
minutes here.
This next paragraph is about, again,
simple steps the dentist can take in the
dentist office.
So I think we can fold this next paragraph
right here into the,
to the previous paragraph.
They're still talking about that same
Italian study.
The study concluded that, so I think it's
fair to kind of put this all into one.
So, I'm going to start with Dentist's, and
also ease patient's fears by,
and then they had this, the author had a
nice colon here followed by a list.
I think we'll just stick with that.
So I'm just going to introduce this list
very directly.
This is our other simple steps the dentist
can take.
Can also ease patient's fears by, now I
need, like, ing verbs, gerunds.
So I'm going to change this to by
transmitting by telling and
showing, by offering it, and we have to
make sure that we
keep this parallel advice starting each of
these items with an ing verb.
So transmitting serenity and friendliness,
I don't think we need by taking the time
just to chat with a patient.
I think we can, that's just extra.
By telling and showing, I think we can
just make that a little bit shorter by
saying by explaining what is going to be
done.
Offering earphones to isolate them from
external sound and at the same time
provide music therapy, and we can just
say, and provide music therapy.
It's doing both at once.
adjusting.
Look, I'm making these all ing verbs to be
parallel.
Adjusting the chair to the patient
dimensions.
I, I think that probably the point of that
is to improve comfort.
So I might be, just say what the point of
adjusting the chairs,
adjusting the chair to improve comfo,
fort, providing an image.
How about projecting an image rather than
providing,
just a slightly better verb there,
projecting an image of quality.
And professional and feed, de, demeter,
[SOUND] and
offering a well illuminated place with
plenty of space and,
again, this last item here is the drug, so
I'm going to pop out drugs later.
So now I get one paragraph that has all of
these different simple interventions that
the dentist can do right at the dental
office.
If you scroll down for
a minute to the very last paragraph, the
author brings up a, a new idea right in
the last paragraph about the idea of
internet based treatments.
And it seems to be a potentially low cost,
simple intervention, so
I'm actually going to move this whole idea
up about the internet based treatment and
delete it from the last paragraph, and
give it its own paragraph
following along this theme of low cost,
simple interventions.
So, researchers are also studying, so
are now focusing on, I think that you
could say are,
also studying, the use of internet based
treatments.
I don't think we need to repeat
confronting and
anxiety, we know anxiety's involved here.
So, we're also studying internet.
These treatments and online
support communities, just to describe what
those internet based treatments entail.
Online su, support communities may help
odontophobics, and
I feel like we need some more information
about these studies.
So, if this, you know, author is trying to
tell us about these low cost simple
interventions, and these new, potential
treatments, we would want to add some more
details about this about this here, about
these studies on internet based therapies.
So that should be kind of it's own
paragraph I think.
And then, we will get in the next
paragraph,
we'll get finally back to the drug
therapy.
So, I think we do have to mention the drug
therapy because probably some patients,
have to have drugs to do this.
So maybe, you know, even in addition to
some of these great simple or
past intervention, some patients are still
going to be traditional drug therapy,
some patients will, you know, still
require drug or
drugs to manage, anxiety or pain, and then
those drugs would include so
what we can pharmalogical options, these
aren't all,
you know, drugs you would take by mouth,
so as a pharmalogical options include,
and here's, the list of them, intra,
intraligamen,
I can't even pronounce that word, that's
just anaesthetics that you take.
That are ejected into the teeth, so we
could just say, local anesthetics, or
anesthetic injections.
I'm not sure what computer controlled
injections are, and how that differs from
anesthetic injections, so I think I'll
just get rid of that for now.
sedation, so anesthetic injections,
sedation with nitrous
oxide anti-anxiety drugs, which I took
away from,
I had mit, took that out of an earlier
place, I'm going to put that back.
So anti-anxiety drugs and then finally
general anaesthesia is the other one,
right, I mean, general anesthesia would
be, would put somebody completely under.
So that's another option.
So those are all the pharmacological
options.
We probably need some more details to
flesh out this paragraph here about just
what are some potential harms if we're, if
this essay is about alternatives to drugs,
what are some potential harms for drug
therapy.
Do they maybe not always work.
So maybe more details about the risks and
benefits of drug therapy.
[SOUND].
And then finally we will need some kind of
concluding paragraph that gets,
again, the concluding, concluding
paragraph may depend a little bit on
what is the actual focus, the theme of
this essay.
But I like the sentence here,
oral hygiene continues to be the best way
to avoid going to the dentist.
Making that point, I think, is important.
I would say yeah, but, good oral hygiene
continues to the best way to
avoid going to the dentist but that
doesn't solve the phobia.
Indeed you know, even if you're great at
oral hygiene, you still might have to go
to the dentist for an emergency as the
author alluded to earlier.
So we still need to solve this problem
about the phobia.
I added, I wasn't quite sure how to
conclude this because again,
I'm not quite sure of the, the exact focus
of this essay, but if it's,
we're focusing in at dentist, that advice
for
dentists you could say something like
dentists should consider the wide range of
options for helping patients with
odontophobia.
To successfully, receive dental care, so
maybe this essay, the point is just to
let dentists know about all these wide
different options that are out there.
Maybe we need a little bit more of a
conclusion, again,
if the, if the essay is trying to make a
point, if there's a clear point here,
it would be nice for the author to wrap up
here with kind of
restating that the point of the of the
essay.