Good morning, students.
Today we are going to talk about
retroviral integration.
If you want to get more information on
this I've got a reference at
the bottom of this slide.
So, here we've go, I'm going to draw for
you retroviral genome here.
And this is the retroviral genome after
reverse
transcriptase that's converted to
retroviral RNA into double stranded DNA.
And the retroviral genome has a long
terminal repeat of the same sequence at
both ends.
And for the purposes of this discussion,
this will be the HIV genome.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Because of its medical importance, and
we will have a little blow-up of the HIV
genome.
Now, let's just draw a few nucleotides
here, for illustration.
That's the upper strand and here's the
lower strand.
And these two nucleotides right here are
critical for
what's going to happen next, because,
it's going to turn out that the retroviral
integrase,
[SOUND] will remove two nucleotides from
the three prime ends, both three prime
ends.
So I'll remove two of the nucleotides from
this particular end.
[COUGH] Leaving us with a,
recessed three prime hydroxyl group.
Now I'm going to draw the target of the
retroviral integration event.
And that'll be the host genome.
The retrovirus wants to jump into the host
genome.
So, we will draw the host genome for you.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Double stranded DNA there.
[COUGH]
And I'm going to show you the retroviral
genome curled up.
And it's curled up because the retroviral
integrase will hold onto both LTRs.
So, we've got the two unpaired nucleotides
at the five prime end of the upper strand
in the previous diagram, ending in a three
prime hydroxyl here.
And two unpaired nucleotide of five prime
end here.
Other stand, the lower strand on the
previous diagram, ending in the three
prime hydroxyl there, and these three
prime hydroxyls will be used
by the integrase to catalyze nucleophilic
attacks on the host DNA.
So, we will draw that.
And the nucleophilic attacks occur offset
from each other.
And the offset here, I'm going to put in
black brackets.
And those that bracketed sequence between
the two sites of nucleophilic attack is
going to
be destined to become a short direct
repeat,
and you'll see that by the time we're
finished.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, [COUGH] just to review,
the integrase catalyzes
nucleophilic attacks
on the host DNA, both
strands of the host DNA.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And I'm going to show you the results of
that, those nucleophilic attacks.
So starting, and this time I'm going to
start with the lower.
I'll draw the diagram from the lower
strand,
three prime ends of the host DNA, moving
over.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
To that site.
And then, that nucleophilic attack
actually creates a covalent bond with the
retroviral DNA.
Five prime
[COUGH].
Now, if I do, draw in, let me finish
drawing the bottom strand here.
Here's the end of the bottom strand.
Five premium.
Now, starting from the three prime
end of the upper strand will show
you result of the nucleophilic attack.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
On the upper strand.
And the lower strand, the upper strand,
I'm sorry, let's draw it in
blue, goes all the way up to there, there
we go.
So, this configuration's a little hard to
see,
so what we need to do is to pull the DNA
ends out so you can see everything.
I'm not going to, I'm not going to change
anything.
All the bonds are still there.
It's just the geometry will change for
ease of viewing.
So, again, if I start with the three prime
end of the lower strand.
Of course, we want to keep out color
coding.
So we're, if we're talking about the three
prime end of
the lower strand, we want that host DNA to
be blue.
It's going to be covalent linked to the
retroviral DNA.
There's the retroviral DNA.
And it's protruding five prime end.
[COUGH] The same thing goes and then.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The continuation, the continuation of the
host DNA over here.
I'm leaving the gap there on purpose.
You can see why I have to do that.
Because if I draw, start drawing the five
prime end of
the retroviral upper DNA strand, that only
goes up to this point.
Let me draw it a little more carefully.
It only goes up to that point.
Because, it doesn't reach all the way
over because there's a gap, that's exactly
the distance that,
between the two nucleophilic attacks on
the upper part of the diagram.
Now if I continue drawing the retroviral
DNA.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I come up to here.
Let me curl this thing down to make it a
little easier for
you to see.
Okay.
And then we have the like point
of covalent attachment there and voila.
We've got another gap over here.
So, that is the previous diagram stretched
out.
Nothing has changed.
What happens next is that nuclease comes
along and removes
the protruding two nucleotides at the far
front ends, the unpaired two nucleotides.
And then, host polymerase,
we'll draw that in blue, host polymerase,
DNA polymerase and ligase repair the gaps.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay now, I'll draw that.
Here's the polymerase coming along and
then the ligase finishing the job,
polymerase coming along and ligase
finishing the job.
And voila!
You've got the retroviral DNA integrated
into the host genome.
And the epilogue is, of course,
understanding retroviral integration has
led to the development of HIV
inhibitors which are now being used to
treat patients with HIV infection.
Thank you so much.