Microbiology is the study of microscopic
organisms.
Some of which, can cause the most serious
diseases encountered by humans.
When a microbe causes disease,
Physicians around the world are called on
to intervene.
In many developing parts of the world,
access to resources like clean water and
basic sanitation is limited.
And in those same areas, higher rates of
malnutrition, especially among
children often lead to immune suppression,
meaning that the microbes, in for
example, contaminated water can more
easily infect their human hosts.
Today we're going to be talking about a
bacterium that measures only about
two microns in length but if it's brought
into an area where it can easily spread.
This microbe can sweep through a community
causing potential
deadly infectious disease.
The most powerful protection we have
against infectious diseases like this one
is our knowledge of how microbes cause
disease both at
the level of the community and at the
level of the microbe.
In order to effectively prevent and treat
infectious diseases.
We need to understand the environments in
which they're more likely to spread and
how the actions of microbes result in the
clinical disease.
This knowledge can lead to interventions.
That protect the health of the individual
and
the society in which they live as we see
in this case.
Felipe is an eight year old boy living in
Chapoteau,
a village located on an isolated spit of
land in Haiti.
Since the earthquake that shook the region
in 2010.
Clean drinking water and sanitation remain
scarce in Haiti.
There are no sewers here and even latrines
are rare.
Because of this, Felipe and his brother
have already seen firsthand the health
consequences of living without access to
basic resources.
Their father passed away from dehydration
due to diarrheal disease three
years ago and determined to protect the
health of his family in the future,
Felipe's older brother Yan had left home a
year ago
to study medicine at the University of
Haiti in Port-au-Prince.
He was the first boy in his village to
attend medical school.
On a visit home last April just after the
spring rains had begun in
Haiti the two brothers were playing
soccer.
When Felipe took a drink from a nearby
communal tap, that night Felipe
started having stomach cramps and began
having terrible watery diarrhea.
Yan was alarmed when he helped his brother
to the makeshift latrine that
hung over the water near their home.
At about two in the morning and he saw his
brother passing what seemed like litres of
stool and the stool reminded him of cloudy
white rice water.
Yan immediately suspected that his younger
brother was suffering from cholera after
contracting vibrio colerae, the tiny
bacterium that infects the small
intestine causing a sudden onset of
violent gastrointestinal symptoms.
He remembered hearing from his mother that
several homes in the area had
recently reported family members suffering
from a terrible form of diarrhea.
Yan thought back to his first year of
medical school and
remembered learning about the father of
Epidemiology a physician by the name of
John Snow who had noticed the similar
clustering of cholera in a London
neighborhood and had linked the disease
back to a contaminated water supply.
Remembering his young brother's choice of
water supply that morning.
Yan began mentally mapping the families
who had been reported ill.
They all collected water from that
communal source.
Yan knew that his next steps would be
critical to his brother's survival.
Several cholera treatment centers had been
opened in
Haiti since the disease was first
introduced into the area,
likely by UN peacekeepers, who came to
Haiti from Nepal.
But the nearest cholera treatment center
would've required a two hour trip
including a river crossing and Yan knew
that infection with vibrio cholerae could
cause rapid dehydration and death in a
matter of twelve hours if left untreated.
In order to result in disease a relatively
large number of
the comma shaped vibrio cholerae bacteria
need to be
ingested because most of them are killed
in the acidic environment of the stomach.
Vibrio cholerae,
they have recently been shed by another
human are hyper infectious,
meaning that they're better able to
survive passage through the stomach.
Once inside the small intestine,
the bacterium uses its flagellum as a
propeller and guided by Chemotaxis.
It swings toward the surface of the
intestine and
avoids being cleared by peristalsis.
When the bacteria reach the surface, they
need to overcome another protective
mechanism, the thick mucous net that's
made by goblet cells to keep bacteria
away from the surface of the epithelial
cells lining the intestinal tract.
Labile cholerae makes enzymes use some
measures that digest the mucus and
allow the bacteria to penetrate the mucus.
Next the bacteria need to attach to the
epithelial cells and
this is mediated by thread like appendages
that grow out of the bacterial surface,
called pili or fimbriae.
Once the bacterium attaches itself to the
cell.
It begins producing a toxin that's
engulfed by the epithelial cells.
Inside the cells the cholera toxin
disrupts the functioning of chloride
channels in the cell, allowing large
amounts of chloride ion to leave the cell,
followed by large amounts of sodium ion.
Water in the lumin of the small intestine
is no longer able to be absorbed and
patients shed liter volumes of stool.
With the stool, the colon loses
bicarbonate base and
infected patients become dehydrated and
acidotic.
The copious amounts of diarrhea seen in
cholera patients is actually beneficial to
the organism that causes the disease.
Vibrio cholerae replicates rapidly inside
the small intestine and the watery stools
allow the newly minted bacteria to exit
the host and be transmitted to another.
Usually via fecal oral contamination.
This is why in parts of the world where
running water and
sanitation aren't available, cholera can
spread quickly and easily.
Back at home, Yan sees Felipe
deteriorating rapidly.
His eyes are sunken.
His skin turber is low and he's too weak
to walk.
The young medical student fashions a
Cholera cot out of a rusted deck chair and
asks his mother to begin sterilizing water
by boiling it over the kerosene stove.
When the water has cooled, Yan mixes six
teaspoons of sugar and
half a teaspoon of salt into one liter of
sterile water,
trying to stay calm as he remembers the
correct proportions of salt, sugar and
water for a homemade version of oral
rehydration solution or ORS.
ORS is considered first line therapy for
cholera and it's sometimes all
that's necessary to send an infected
patient on the road to recovery.
The sodium and glucose in ORS make use of
a different transporter to replenish
electrolytes in the host.
This allows for rehydration and recovery
to occur.
In Felipe's case, the ORS saved his life
and
allowed his family to transform him to a
satellite clinic operated by
a nonprofit organization about an hour
from their home.
At the clinic, Felipe received rehydration
therapy.
And the family was given chlorine bleach
and
advised to sanitize the home and safely
dispose of all fecal waste.
Yan contacted local government officials
and warnings were posted around
the contaminated water source with
directions on how to decontaminate
the water used by Yan and Felipe's
neighbors oral rehydration therapy
can reduce the risk of dying from Cholera
from 20% to 1% in many parts of the world.
By understanding the interactions between
socioeconomics and
the pathogenesis of infectious disease,
medical teams can develop strategies for
treating and preventing infectious disease
around the world.
And health outcomes, like Felipe's
complete recovery,
can become the norm in said of the
exception.