For those of you who want a few more
mathematical details about
the relationship between the odds ratio
and
the risk ratio, it's pretty easy to show
the mathematical relationship.
So I'm going to do that now.
So if we wrote out the risk ratio, I'm
going to use a few symbols here.
So if we say that the risk ratio is equal
to the probability of
getting the disease and some exposed
group, I'll call that P exposed.
So that's like my smoking group.
That's the probability of getting the
disease in, say, my smoking group.
And then my risk ratio compares that group
to some reference groups.
So that's what the probability of getting
the disease in the reference group.
We'll call that P ref.
That's what our risk ratio is.
If we wrote off the odds ratio in term of,
in terms of P exposed and
P ref, the odds ratio is equal to the
probability of
getting the disease in the exposed divided
by one minus that probability.
That's the odds for the exposed group.
And then, we have to divide that by the
odds for the reference group.
So, that would be P-ref, divided by 1
minus P-ref.
So then if we wanted to make a formula
that
showed us the relationship between the
odds ratio and the risk ratio,
we could simply say, well what's different
between the odds ratio and the risk ratio?
Well the risk ratio is the probability in
the exposed group divided by the
probability in the reference group.
So the odds ratio is simply the risk ratio
times a factor and that factor is 1
minus the probability of the getting the
disease in the reference group,
divided 1 minus the probability of getting
the disease in the exposed group.
So that's the relationship between the
odds ratio and the risk ratio.
What you notice is that the odds ratio is
always the risk ratio times this
additional factor, this what I call a
distortion term.
If the outcome is rare, that means P ref
is small and also P exposed is small.
So for example, let's say that P exposed
is 2%.
So the exposure the probability of getting
a disease in the, say,
the smoking group is 2% and in the
reference group, it's 1%.
Those are fairly rare outcomes.
Well, if the probability of getting the
disease is 2% then,
the probability of not getting it is 98%.
If the probability of getting the disease
is 1%,
then the probability of not getting it is
99%.
So in that case, this distortion term,
1 minus P ref divided by 1 minus P exp,
exposed would just be 99% divided by 98%.
That would be the distortion term.
Well that's awfully close to 1.
So if that's the case, if you have
something that's rare the distortion term,
what you're multiplying the risk ratio by
to get the odds ratio is extremely small.
But compare that now to the situation
where the the [INAUDIBLE],
the, the risk of getting your outcome is
actually much higher.
So compared to this situation where, say,
the risk of getting the outcome in the
exposed group is 50%.
And the risk in the reference group is
25%.
Those are common outcomes.
So now the risk of not getting the, the
outcome in the expose group is 50% and
the chance of not getting it in the
reference group is 75%.
So now, what's our distortion factor, 1
minus P ref divided by 1 minus P exposed,
that distortion factor is now going to be
75% divided by 50% or 1.5.
So our, our odds ratio now will be 1.5
times the risk ratio.
If we have risk ratios that are below 1,
that if,
as if we're dealing with protective
effects,
what will happen is that this distortion
term will be a fraction.
And so the odds ratio will always be
smaller than the corresponding risk ratio.
That means that the, the protective effect
will look larger.
[BLANK_AUDIO]