So for those of you who want some more
mathematical details.
You want me to derive the formula that
I've just showed on the last slide.
Let me rewrite that formula so you can see
it written out.
To save myself some writing here,
I'm going to use Po to represent the
probability of the disease,
in the reference group, what I was calling
P ref before.
So that's the formula that we're trying to
derive.
So, It's just really algebra to derive it,
but for
those of you who are curious, let me do it
out here.
So we can write that.
The probability of getting the outcome in
the exposed group.
Another way to write that is just a risk
ratio times the probability of
getting the disease in the unexposed
group.
So if you multiply the probability of
getting the disease in the unexposed group
by the risk ratio,
that gives you the probability of getting
the disease in the exposed group.
So that's a useful piece of information to
have.
And then we can write out what the odds
ratio is.
What is the odds ratio in terms of all of
these things?
The odds ratio is the odds of getting the
disease in the exposed group divided
by the odds of getting the disease in the
unexposed group, in the reference group.
So, since we said that the, that p exposed
is just equal to the risk ratio times Po,
that's the probability of getting the
disease in the exposed group.
The probability of not getting it there is
for 1 minus that.
So that's the numerator for the odds
ratio.
So that represents the odds of getting the
disease in the exposed group.
The odds of getting the disease in the
unexposed group, the reference group is
just Po divided by 1 minus Po.
So then we can just do a little bit of
algebraic rearrangement here, right?
So what I'm going to do is a just a little
of algebra.
So I'm going to multiply both sides of the
equation by Po over 1 minus Po.
So that will then give me the odds ratio
times Po
over 1 minus Po is equal to that.
So now if you noticed,
both sides of the equation have a Po in
the numerator so
I'm going to cancel that will make things
easier.
Then I'm going to cross multiply both
sides by the denominators of
the other side.
So OR times 1 minus RRPo is equal to RR
times 1 minus Po.
Next I'm just going to multiply
across that odds ratio, using the
distributive property.
That's OR minus OR, times RR, times Po,
equal to RR, minus RRPo.
And then I'm trying to isolate the RR, so
I'm going to add this term to the other
side to get all the RR's, the risk ratios
on one side.
So that's plus OR
times RR times Po.
So now we get the, the odds ratio is equal
to the risk ratio minus
RRPo plus OR times RR times Po.
We can then take the risk ratio out of all
of that.
So that's 1 minus Po plus OR times Po.
And that's equal to the OR
and then all we have to do is divide both
sides by that term so
we get what we're looking for, 1 minus Po
plus OR times Po.
So there it is.
There is the derivation.
If your a so inclined to like that kind of
proof.