Welcome back.
In this module, we'll give you a tour of
how SAS is laid out.
SAS is a tool that allows users to code,
point and click, and analyze data.
It's relatively user friendly.
For this class,
you most likely will be using SAS
Enterprise Guide on a remote server.
>> Let's start by opening SAS Enterprise
Guide.
You first click start, and then click SAS
Enterprise Guide.
The first thing you' will see is a Welcome
to SAS Enterprise Guide screen.
Here, you will have the choice of opening
a project or creating projects.
In this case, we are going to open an
existing project so
that we can explain how SAS is set up.
In essence, a project is just a record of
everything that you do in
SAS during a specific analysis.
It keeps track of the data sets that are
used,
the particular tasks that you have run,
and the results that you've output.
Here's the main screen, which is called
the workspace.
On the left of the screen, you have a
project tree.
The project tree shows you a view of the
project you are working on.
When you import data, run tasks and
analyze your data, you will see new icons
added to this area.
In essence, it is simply a hierarchical
view of the project you are working on.
You can easily reorder, rename, delete and
edit the individual items in your project.
The Process Flow window is considered a
relationship window.
It takes the components of the project
tree, and creates a web of interactions.
Arrows are added between different icons.
For example, if you've imported a dataset
and run a specific analysis,
a line will be drawn from the data to the
new analysis icon.
I'm quickly going to show you how to
change the format of SAS Enterprise Guide.
Right now, we're in single view, which is
the standard for SAS.
If you go to View > Workspace Layout, and
then click Side by Side,
you will get your process flow on the left
and your output data on the right.
>> So here we have a data set.
A data set is just like a spread sheet
that you are probably used to
seeing in Excel.
In SAS, we typically use separate columns
for
different variables, and we have separate
rows for different subjects.
In this dataset, each row is a different
person in our study.
Reading across the columns,
we have all the different variables that
we measured for that individual person.
For example, here we have a record for a
70 year old woman,
with ID number 161, and these are all the
measurements that we recorded.
SAS allows us to explore our dataset, run
statistical tests, and
create graphics to visualize our data.
So, why use SAS instead of Excel?
While Excel can perform advanced analysis,
it does not keep a clear record of what
you've done.
When you conduct research,
it's really important that your methods
are reproducible and well documented.
SAS provides a systematic way to keep
track of all the steps in your analysis,
so you know exactly what was done to your
data.
When we run a statistical analysis,
we frequently work with datasets that has
hundreds or
even thousands of rows, which can make it
very cumbersome in programs like Excel.
With SAS, we can use code or the point and
click interface to handle all these big
datasets with ease.