[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, now you've done a root cause
analysis.
If you figure out what the system process
issues, you have implemented solutions.
Now how do you, how do you roll things
out.
And then, double check to make sure things
are maintained or sustained.
Some implementations of how you think
about permanent changes to
the way work is done.
And as such involves building the change
into the organization.
Hard wiring is a phrase we often time use
because you're
talking about changing behavior.
You're talking about changing process.
You're talking about changing culture
sometimes in order to
make sure that the bad event never occurs
again.
Sustaining is making sure you lock in
those processes that the organization's
have already have put into place, and then
continuing building on it.
And that's the Institute of Healthcare
Improvement, IHI's, approach.
And making sure that those actions are
actually hard wired or
put in place to make sure it doesn't
happen again.
So, some considerations or some
suggestion,
maybe consider doing a test of change,
where you take a couple of staff in
a particular area to use the revised form
or process, whatever is that was changed.
We actually implementing a change, now
you're looking at everybody involved in
a particular area to use a particular form
or that particular process.
And it is constantly reassessment or
remeasuring the process to make sure it's
working.
And of course going to the staff who's
involved with the process to make sure
that you get feedback from them regarding
what's working, what's not working.
This fine tuning, this tweaking, is where
the improvement concept actually falls
in because it's just like patient care.
When you're doing these improvements, and
you have a patient who presents what's a
elevated, glycosylated hemoglobin, or
that they come in with elevated blood
pressure.
And you have 'em on meditations or if you
did a procedure and
then, then quite correct it then you need
to back and do it.
That process itself is a performance
improvement program that you
are doing with the patient.
So, you know, keep in mind that, it's the
same concept that we
are talking about from a clinical care
standpoint, that you
are actually implementing in terms of a
larger macro level system process issue.
Some of the tools that we'll have
available through links on this program,
includes the Stanford University Medical
Center National Patient Safety Goal
badge cards.
One of the tools that have been used in,
Stanford's hospital and
clinics, periop region is the WHO Surgical
Checklist.
SBAR communication situation background
assessment and recommendation,
was something that was developed by Kaiser
Permanente in Colorado.
And it's used pretty much, world wide now,
as a way of communicating urgent emergent
situation among team members.
The High Reliability Organization article
that's kind of a landmark article,
that Joint Commission uses, that was
authored by Dr.
Chassin the President and CEO of the Joint
Commission with Gerald Loeb.
There's Culture of Safety article that
were included,
as well as prevention of Medical Error
articles that you'll have available.
One great resource that's been around for
almost ten years now is a AHRQ funded
program that was
done through the department defense is the
concept of TeamSTEPPS.
And TeamSTEPPS is a whole communication
culture system that many
organizations have adopted, that could
help facilitate team
communication among interdisciplinary and
interdisciplinary team members.
And the website is listed on the slide.
You may want to check in terms of the tons
of resources they have available.
And programs that are available that we
put on across the country.
So with that we've had an opportunity to
review a little bit of the history about
medical error and the movement about the
patient safety initiative.
We've talked about the high reliability
organization and
where that fits in health care today.
We've reviewed the process of conducting a
root cause analysis.
And review some case scenarios,
where they're actually adverse medical
error events that has actually happened.
And some of the learnings and system
processes that were put in place.
We hope that you found this program
informative, helpful.
And if there's any question please feel
free to contact me.
And I look forward to hearing from you.
Thank you, very much.
[BLANK_AUDIO]