Let's look at some of the example data,
from my Stanford students.
So here's the distribution of homework,
again, in hours per week.
And we saw that the, in an earlier module,
the mean homework was 11.5, 4,
11.4 hours, the standard deviation for
homework was actually 10.5 hours.
So that's a pretty big variability.
Right?
So
when average students are doing about 11
hours of homework, but
the average variability is 10.5.
So that means many students were doing
down towards zero and
many students were doing 20 or more hours
per week.
So pretty wide or pretty large variability
here.
Lets look at our feelings about math from
my Stanford students.
So again pretty wide variability here.
I asked the students to rate their
feelings about math from,
zero being really hate math to 100 being
they really love math.
And the mean in this particular variable
turned out to be 61.
So on average people are favorable,
although,
not highly favorable towards math.
But the standard deviation here was really
high, it was 21.
So you can see, you know, on average,
people are 61, but, you,
it easily goes down to 40 or up to 80, so
there's a fairly wide spread here.
Now, I mentioned in an earlier module,
that the feelings about math variable,
actually is roughly, follows a bell curve.
It's not a perfect bell curve by any
means, but of the variables I've talked
about this week, it was one of the closest
in terms of following a bell curve.
So I just want to pause for a minute, and
I'm going to revisit a,
a rule I told you about earlier this week
about bell curves, about normal curves.
So, remember I mentioned that bell curves
have this predictable behavior.
If you're on a perfect bell curve,
you follow something called the 68-95-99.7
rule.
68% of the observations lie within one
standard deviation of the mean.
95% of observations will lie within two
standard deviations of the mean.
And 99.7% of observations will lie within
three standard deviations of the mean.
If you're on a perfect bell curve, and
a bell curve is just a mathematical
function, if you follow that perfect bell
curve mathematical function, those will be
exact.
Of course, real data is never going to
follow a bell curve, perfectly like that.
So let's look, see how good this rule is
for
some real data that looks kind of on a
bell curve, but certainly not perfect.
How good is that rule for some real data,
that's not even perfectly on a bell curve?
So we can test that out.
So the mean here was 61, so one standard
deviation below the mean, and
the standard deviation was 21, so one
standard deviation below the mean is 40.
One standard deviation above the mean is
61 plus 21, which is 82.
So if you're going from one standard
deviation below,
to one standard deviation above the mean,
that's anywhere between 40 to 82.
So I actually went into my data set, and I
looked and
counted up how many of my 50 students fell
between values of 40 and 82.
I actually counted it up.
And it turned out there were 34 out of 47;
in fact,
three people did not answer this question.
So I had only 47 total for this question,
but 34 of them had values between 40 and
82, that's 72%, so it's not 68%, but it's
pretty close.
If you go out 2 standard deviations from
the mean,
that gets you out to 100 on the right
side.
because you can't get a by, higher than
100, and
it gets you down to 19, so 61-42 is 19, 19
on the other side.
And if I count out the number of students
that fall between 19 and
a 100 in my data set, it was 46 out of 47,
or 98%.
So again, on a bell curve, in a perfect
bell curve is going to be 95%, but
real data that was kind of a bell curve,
it's pretty close, it's 98 percent.
And of course If I go out up three
standard deviations above and
below the mean, I cover the entire range,
0 to 100, and of course that means a 100%
of my students fell within that range.
It's suppose to be 99.7%, 100% is really,
really close.
So, hey, this rule for, for a perfect bell
curve is 95, 68, 95, 99.7.
For my real data that's not a perfect bell
curve,
it came out to be 72, 98, 100, so it's
pretty close.
Now I mentioned in an earlier module,
that binary variables can be thought of as
0 1 variables.
You can code them as 0 1's.
And think of them as 0's and 1's as
numbers.
And we saw that a binary variable has a
mean and a median.
Does it also have a standard deviation?
Sure, of course, if you think of it as 0
and
1s you can also calculate the standard
deviation.
So, here again, is my binary variable,
whether or
not you played varsity sports in high
school.
And I have 30 who did, and 20 who did not.
How would we calculate the standard of
deviation here?
We calculated in an earlier module that
the mean is 0.6.
So we can subtract a each observation from
the mean.
The mean is 0.6 and everybody is either a
1 or a 0.
So it actually makes this calculation
fairly easy to do by hand.
So if your a 1, if you played varsity
sports in high school and
you subtract 0.6, that's a value of 0.4.
You then square it, and there's 30 people
that have that identical value.
So we can just do that once, and multiple
by 30.
If you're a 0,
if didn't play varsity sports, then your
deviation is negative 0.6.
You square that, and there's 20 of those,
so we multiple that by 20.
We add all those up, and divide by 50
minus 1 n minus 1.
And then we square root it to get back to
the standard deviation,
we come out with a value of 0.49.
So what does that 0.49 mean?
Well remember the, the average here is
0.6.
Everybody is either 0 or a 1.
So you're either a 0.6 away from the mean,
or 0.4 away from the mean.
So, you know, 0.49 is kind of the middle
of those.
Just to help you understand standard
deviation even a little better,
let me just represent to you three simple
little mock data sets.
And they all have the same mean of 15.
They're just a couple, there's just 8
people in each of these data sets.
But they all have the same mean.
But they have different standard
deviations.
So in the first data set, data set B, over
to the left of your screen.
The mean is 15, but everybody's really
clustered around the mean.
So the standard deviation is only 0.9.
In the middle one, data set A,
the mean again is 15, but there's more
spread around the mean.
So that standard, increases the standard
deviation to 3.7.
In the final data set, data set C, over to
the right of your screen.
The mean is 15, but the standard deviation
is 5.1, because you
can see nobody's even close to the mean,
everybody's way out in the tails.
I mean, that can happen in a distribution,
so
that's going to make the standard
deviation even bigger.
So that's a, giving you a sense of what
the standard deviation means intuitively.
Now, we're going to talk a lot about
something called
the standard error in this class.
But I just want to point out now to you,
the difference between the standard
deviation and the standard error, because
a lot of people get these confused.
And we're going to, again, I'm going to
come back to this, so
this is not the last time you're going to
hear this.
But it's worth me putting this in your
head right now,
as we're talking about standard
deviations.
So what's a standard deviation, and what's
a standard error?
So, a standard deviation that we've been
talking about today,
is a measure of the variability of a
trait.
So that would be if we're measuring, like,
the variability of how much homework you
do per week.
The standard error, is measuring the
variability of something very specific.
It's measuring, it's a measure of the
variability of a statistic.
So, where, when you talk about standard
error,
you're talking only about the variability
of a statistic.
And what does it mean for a statistic to
have variability?
So, again as I mentioned earlier this
week,
statistics actually follow distributions.
But that's a theoretical construct,
it's something that we're going to talk a
lot about in this course.
But statistics follow distributions, so
statistics have a shape of the
distribution and they have a variability.
That variability is called a standard
error.
Different statistics have different
standard errors.
So you may have the standard error of a
mean.
You may have the standard error of an odds
ratio, you may have a standard error of
a regression coefficient, those will all
be different.
Again, standard error is about the
variability of a statistic.
And we usually reserve the term standard
deviation to talk about the variability of
a trait, so that we don't get it confused
with standard error.
I don't expect you to completely
understand that yet, but
just tuck it away in the back of your
head, and
we're going to return to this concept a
lot in, in future weeks.
Okay, another way to measure the spread or
variability of the data, is just to rank
the data and look at percentiles.
We did this when we looked at box plots.
So, you could talk about things like 90th
percentile of data.
Where does the 90, 90th percentile lie?
That will some information, some feeling
about the data.
So, the 90th percentile is the value for
which 90% of observations are lower.
You can talk about the 10th percentile of
the data.
That would be the value for which 10% of
the observations are lower.
We've already talked about the median,
that's the 50th percentile,
half are above and half are below the
median.
So sometimes we'll just talk about where
those different percentiles lie,
to give ourselves a sense of the spread of
the data.
Percentile will not be affected by extreme
values, as we saw with the median.
So that's going to be different than
standard deviation.
So that might be a reason that you focus
on percentiles, is if you have extreme
value and skew data, the standard
deviation might be a little misleading.
You might instead focus on percentile.
And in particular, one a measure that
based on percentiles that we use a lot for
describing the variability of data, is
something called the interquartile range.
And we saw this, when we talked about box
spot already this week.
The interquartile range, is just the
distance between the 75th percentile and
the 25th percentile, or also known as the
third quartile and the first quartile.
The middle 50 percent of the data.
And again, that interquartile range is not
going to be affected by outliers.
Because the middle 50% of the data is
going to be same middle 50% of the data,
no matter how high or low the minimum and
maximum values are.
We saw the interquartial range when we
looked at boxplot.
So here is the boxplot of political bent
in my Stanford students.
0 was the most conservative.
100 was the most liberal.
And again the middle 50% of the data laid
between 68 and 85.
So most students in the liberal and
democratic range.
And so we would subtract those two values
to get the interquartile range,
which I abbreviate as IQR, and that value
comes out to be 17.
So that gives you a sense of the spread of
the data as well.
That that middle 50% of data in this case
is pretty tight.
So I just want to summarize here,
wrap up with all the symbols that I've
thrown at you.
Because I will be using some of these
symbols a throughout this course.
So I, when I talked about the sample
variance I abbreviated that as S squared.
When I talked about the sample standard
deviation, I abbreviated that as an S.
I want to throw out here now, because
sometimes when I talk about variance or
standard deviation, I may instead use
this, the Greek symbol, sigma, and
sigma squared.when I'm using a sigma or
a sigma squared I'm talking about a
variance that's not calculated from data.
It's something that's a theoretical
variance,
like if you Knew the exact distribution.
When we talk about probability this may
come up.
Or if you knew the true variance in the
population, not from a sample but
from everybody, you would abbreviate that
with a sigma.
So that's the distinction there, that you
that may come up.
When we talk about the the sample mean,
we represent that with an X bar, so a
little a bar over my X.
That represents the sample mean.
Again, mean calculated from data.
When I talk about a population or true
mean, which is usually a theoretical
thing, I might use instead the Greek
symbol mu which is represented there.
And again the interquartial range I'll
represent with IQR.