This question compared the effect of
calcipotral cream versus ultra based cream
on the reduction of skin lesions.
We had p values of .017 for
the calcipotral cream versus p value of
.056 for the ultrabase base.
The answer to the first question is D, the
difference between the creams may not be
significantly different even though the p
value for one is less than .05 and for
the other is greater than .05.
It appears that there was some reduction
on the placebo side.
That would just missed statistical
significance because we know that the p
value is slightly greater than .05.
It's unlikely that the between group
difference will be significant here.
The next question asked us the unit of
observation for the study.
Because we were studying the side of a
face, that is the unit of observation and
that's the answer to this question.
This study does involve correlated
observations because we are studying two
sides of the same person's face and these
obviously will be correlated.
This question has the authors running a
lot of tests, so
they have 15 different levels of black
tea, coffee, decaf coffee.
They have two diseases [UNKNOWN].
They also have two types of participants,
pre menopausal versus postmenopausal.
In such a large number of test that are
run,
we would expect to find a few p values
that are less than .05 just by chance.
The fact that we have a couple of values
that are less than .05 does not
reflect actual correlation in this case.
Because this study examined individual
women,
the unit of observation here is a person.
The observations in this study are not
correlated.
This is because this study examined
independent women.
This question gives us the increased risk
for
various diseases comparing two groups,
exposed versus unexposed.
We can see that the, the risk ratios in
case B and D are very close to one,
which tells us that these are not really
very clinically significant.
And thus the answer to this question is A,
C and E where we actually do see a
significant departure from 1.
For the risk ratios to be statistically
significant at a .05 level.
We should have the confidence intervals
such that one does not cross them.
Which means that one should either be
lower than the lower bound or
one should be greater than the upper
bound.
The only two cases for which this is true,
is A and B.
Thus these are the only risk ratios that
are statistically significant at
a .05 level.