In this unit we are going to actually
spend a little bit of time about talking,
about what are some of the different
methods or tools, that are available to
assist you with communicating in a
situation that requires some action.
And so one of the things that we wanted to
spend a little time looking at
is looking at some tools that have been
used an other healthcare organization,
that at least has some degree of a track
record and some success.
To enhance or improve communication
between temp team members in the event of
a, medical situation.
TeamSTEPPS, which stands for Team,
Strategies, and
Tools to Enhance Performance and Patient
Safety.
It's an initiative that was actually
funded by
the Agency for Healthcare Research and
Quality.
The intent of the course program, the
TeamSTEPP program is to give organizations
some tools to be able to work more
effectively, in reducing medical events.
The Department of Defense Army and Navy
and Airforce installations.
Were involved with developing the concept
because they recognized,
early on how critical it was that, there
was a standardized methodology of
communicating between the team members
involved with taking care of patients.
The, core focus of the program is actually
to improve the teamwork,
as well as having methodology to improve,
improve the team communication.
And what they had developed was basically
a standardized tool kit
through a series of training sessions to
actually get
the team members involved together to go
through these vignettes or
scenarios, so that they can understand how
their communication methodologies.
How how and what they're communicating can
be taken so that the staff
involved can be able to act appropriately
based on the information they're given.
Since AHRQ had funded the initial
initiative, they have,
had hundreds of organizations participate
in, master trainer, type
courses that they have held throughout the
country over the last several years.
And the whole concept behind these master
trainer courses, which are at this
moment free to teams of folks coming from
different facilities to register and
participate in these two day programs.
The intent of the master trainer courses
is to train trainers, so
that they can go into their individual
organization, and
work with their own team, in terms of
rolling out the TeamSTEPPS concept.
Many organizations have applied this
concepts over the past ten years,
with a fair amount of success, and
primarily because this is evidence based,
research based information in terms of
changing the attitude of team members,
improving the team communication among the
team members.
The two challenge rule was designed by the
airline industry to help
airline pilots prevent disasters when
basically excellent pilots
experience a momentary lapse in judgement
or decision making,
because of the volume of information
inputted into the individual.
You know, all the red lights are going
off, the alarms are screaming,
people are yelling and shouting, you can
imagine in a crisis situation with
an airplane, you know, the pilot's trying
to make the right decision.
And doesn't always hear or process the
input of information that you may
have in terms of dealing or addressing the
issue on hand.
So, the process works out by actually,
if you're the one whose aware of the
situation or aware of record data or
key data, you should be able to voice a
concern by basically advocating and
asserting, at least twice if the initial
assertion is ignored.
So you know, ability to be able to call
something else, raise the flag,
raise the attention, you know is part of
this two challenge rule process.
Realistically, we're talking about the
first challenge really should be
a question.
So this could very well be something like,
you know,
do you need assistance with starting that
line?
Especially if, you know, you have a
patient who may be septic and
you're trying, you know, you're trying to
get some fluid boluses,
performed to try to raise the patient
blood pressure.
The second challenge,
really should be able to provide some
support to your concern.
You know, you're very focused on dealing
with the very overall care of the patient.
Do you want me to go ahead and start that
line as per protocol?
So, you know, you provided some,
restatement of the original issue and
then provide some support for your
concern.
The key thing about this is that,
remember that you're always thinking about
advocating for your patient.
And the individual who is leading that
particular response in an urgent or
emergent situation is probably momentarily
locked up or
frozen with all the amount of information
and decision making process that
needs to be involved with taking care of
the situation.
The second part of the two challenge rule
is what they said,
what they oftentimes describe as making it
happen.
And, in some cases, that you know you're
in a clinical event, requiring critical,
key decision, and if you have knowledge
and experience and know what to do,
then the third part of this two challenge
rule is actually, you know,
making it happen, providing it is safe.
And for the patient and you do know what
needs to be done, very precisely, so,
that's the two challenge rule.
The analogy that the airline industry
makes reference to, is many times you have
a pilot and a copilot, and they're dealing
with all kinds of issues and events.
At some time a pilot is so focused on what
is going on, that sometime a question
to cause a pause in what is going on, can
be a rebooting or retriggering of
the thought process that needs to be done
to address the crisis situation on hand.
The same could be said in an operating
room, an ICU, and
emergency department, that sometimes what
it takes is that pause, that question.
We've all seen the television shows and
the movie where somebody literally slaps
that person in the face, and we're not
suggesting that, but the idea is to take
them out of there lock-up moment, and to
get them restarted or recharged so that,
they can be able to address the situation.
SBAR, some of you might have heard of
SBAR,
which actually was derived from the United
States Nuclear Naval Program, and
it was really designed to be a concise
standardized approach method for
communicating key information in a moment
of urgency.
This information is usually crisis or
urgent type in nature,
the mundane, the routine thing, may not
have a place for SBAR.
But is pretty standard in healthcare, many
organization including
Stanford Hospital and clinic, has been
using SBAR for several years.
Folks say, well hey in an urgent situation
give me an SBAR or can, you know, can, can
you give me SBAR that actually highlights
or focus in on what the issue is.
For those of you that are not familiar
with SBAR, S stands for
what's the situation?
Basically a quick to the point state the
problem, state the issue,
B, the background, brief relevant
information.
We don't necessarily need to have the
entire patient's comprehensive, you know,
history and physical examination but it
may be relevant information as
pertained to the reason why you're calling
for assistance.
A stands for assessment, what do you think
is going on or, and or
what is the problem?
Recognizing that, you know, many of us, we
come up with a differential,
differential diagnosis that may list
everything under the sun.
Maybe you want to think of the two or
three key things that might be
contributing to what's causing this
situation to occur.
So it kind of gives the receiver of that
information a little guidance or
a little idea that.
You kind of thought through the process,
you've evaluated, and
now you're coming up on what you think's
going on, and that leads us to the R,
which is recommendations.
Basically those are offers of suggestions
or
requests, you know, it could be anything
that you think may be pertinent or
relevant to be able to address the
situation.
So, SBAR is a very common methodology,
it's often time used in the nursing world,
those of you who may end up you know,
doing work within the kaiser system or
the BA system may find yourself giving
SBAR's and taking SBAR's.
And that's really a quick way to actually
communicate core information,
especially if you're dealing with an
emergent situation.
CUS, no we're not talking about bad
language,
we're actually talking about the concept
of using signal words,
such as danger, warning, caution that
might be common in the medical arena.
Basically, whenever these words are
spoken, the idea is that all
the team members, would understand clearly
not only what the issue is, but
also what the magnitude of the issue on
hand.
So, typically CUS is actually used where
you have a situation where, you know,
you may have a little conflict between you
and the team member, or
your lead attending or your chief
residents or whoever that's involved.
You know, maybe heading in a direction,
and
you have a slight disagreement, well
what's going on.
And so this is a bit of a challenging,
methodology to kind of challenge
the situation on hand or what the state of
mind is on hand with some key information.
CUS stands for,
you need to state your concern, you know,
what is going on from your standpoint.
Hey team members, based on my impression,
you know,
I believe this patient may be manifesting
signs of Septicemia.
Sure, the patient's lactate you know,
isn't over 4.0, but
the fact of the matter is, is that patient
is showing all the signs and symptoms of
the fever without showing the lab signs or
symptoms, so I have a concern.
The second part of it, you know,
especially if the issue is not addressed,
and you know, that you know, this could be
leading down the path for
that patient that is very undesirable, you
need to
state the reason why you are uncomfortable
well, whatever the situation is.
So first you state your concern, then you
state why you are uncomfortable.
It could be everything from in my previous
experience.
I've seen, you know, this kind of case
before and
you know, I think we may be barking up the
wrong tree.
War based on what I have evaluated, based
on my analysis,
no I don't think we're heading in the
right direction.
And then finally, if no action is taken
after you've stated your concern, or
state why you're uncomfortable, if this
issue isn't resolved then you may want to
state that there is a safety issue.
Or you have a safety a patient's safety
factor going on here,
that needs to be addressed.
So, CUS is really used as a methodology,
especially in a, situation where there
may be a little difference of opinion
about what's going on.
And that because the crisis situation, the
key member or
the lead person in charge of the case, may
not be recognizing all of the information.
And you, as a party to the activity, or
maybe in a, as an observer,
you may want to consider using the CUS
methodology to be able to state your,
you know, state your point.
State your concern, then state why your
uncomfortable, and
if it's not resolved, state that there is
a safety issue, and
it may require escalation to get
additional help.
So, CUS is not a bad thing, but
it's actually a good methodology to be
able to address the issue.
And, once again, if the issue hasn't been
addressed through this CUS methodology,
you may need to be able to call for
assistant or escalate for
additional help or raise it to your next
level you know, attending or
whoever in order to try to get the patient
taken care of.
So, remember the whole intent behind CUS
is.
Just not to have a, situation where you're
having a battle between the team members,
but is to be able to state a point about
any issue,
that you have concerns about, to be able
to do the right thing for your patient.
Conflict resolution is a big issue of what
we deal with among team members, and
many times people don't feel comfortable
with raising those issues.
Especially if they have been beaten down a
couple times whenever a situation
present itself.
So that leads us to another acronym DESC.
And DESC is a methodology that you may
want to
consider if the conflict becomes potential
low personal.
DESC can be used in more conflicting
scenarios when which reasonable behaviors
are practiced, hostile, and harassment
type of behavior is ongoing,
and ultimately patient safety, or a safe
patient care is suffering.
So what is the acronym stand for?
Well it starts with a D, and you probably
don't want to do this in heat of
a critical situation, this is probably
best reserved for, after the event is,
is, has occur, or the situation has been
managed, or its desecrating.
To be able to have a one on one
conversation, with whoever it
was that you were having this conflict
with, and it starts off with.
Hey, you know, can I speak to you about a
couple things,
about that case we were dealing with?
So you want to set aside, a little time,
make it clear to
who you're working with that you need to
have a, you know, a little bit of quiet,
a one-on-one conversation about, you know,
what had just occurred.
You want to start off with describing, the
spe, specific situation.
Hey, I want to talk to you about how that
case went, do you have a minute?
Oh, sure, great, let's get together and,
and go get something to eat, or
get something to drink, and you can tell
me what's on your mind.
Well, once you get something to eat or
drink, or you're in a room, he says, you
know, I wasn't, I wasn't quite comfortable
in terms of how that case was handled.
Well, what, what's up, what, you know,
what are you talking about?
Realistically you, you know, when you
stepped in, you started barking out
instruction, you could get a sense that
the dynamics of the team changed,
some the team members not familiar with
how you approach things locked up, and
you were yelling at them even more to do
more things.
You know I'm really kind of concerned
about the way that our communication is
going on that we don't get everyone on the
same page.
So E stands for expressing your concern
about whatever the action was.
S suggesting other alternatives, and this
is really hard because some people are not
ready to even talk about these things or
if you don't even see a pattern or you
don't even see, an issue with how their
behavior was in that particular situation.
They may not be open to any feedback, but
you need to at least try to provide a
little feedback so maybe they can
change their behavior the next time an
event like that was to occur again.
So, this means suggesting some other
alternative, whether it's, like,
hey, you know, just to let you know,
people were kind of shocked in
terms of how you're yelling and screaming
things at people.
I think people might feel a little better
if you were just, give them a pointer or
two, about what needs to be done, or
shorten the request a little bit.
You ask that one staff person probably 12
things in a matter of,
like, 30 nanoseconds, and it probably
would help that person out is that,
you know, you gave them one or two things
at a time so that they understand.
What needs to be done and they can carry
all those actions out,
rather than hitting what 20 or 30 things
in a very short period of time.
C, consequences which should be stated and
this is a tough one because in many cases,
you know, you don't necessarily know what
consequences can be stated.
But, certainly hostile and harassing
behavior,
which is counterproductive to most teams,
can lead to additional types of
things that can adversely affect patient
care down the road.
Consequences may include, you know, hey, I
need to report this out to the chief of
staff, or I may have to report this out to
the the attending, or
I may have to call this out if this
doesn't change.
Usually most of us know, there are certain
patterns and
trends with people's behavior.
And, you know, departments like the
quality patient safety department or
your guest services department often times
get complaints about individuals,
in terms of how they communicate or how
they act with, you know, patients.
And when those things are looked at in
aggregate,
like many institution now have programs
that looks at professional behavior.
or, appropriate care, you know, many, or,
many organizations are actually collecting
data to see if there's patterns and trends
with, you know, the care providers,
whether it's a doctor, a resident, a
fellow nurse, a pharmacist, anybody.
You know, they're actually looking at that
kind of
data to see if there's pattern and trend.
It's pretty well known that when you have
problems with folks, feeling intimidated,
or threatened, or have had previous bad
experience, are not inclined on,
you know, engaging in a situation just
because, they don't want to go through,
that kind of a hassle in the next time
around.
So, people avoid raising those issue or
challenging, you know, the individual,
even though they may have core
information relevant to preventing that
event from having a bad outcome.
We mentioned this earlier in our program,
that, you know,
there are probably 40 plus wrong site,
wrong site wrong procedures wrong patient
procedures done across the country.
It's interesting that, you know, there's
been literature has shown that there's
been at least one person in that room that
actually was aware of what was going on,
but because the culture of that setting,
did not elect to speak up,
to prevent the bad thing from happening.
[BLANK_AUDIO]