The correct answer here is b, if our
probability is 0.5, then our logit is
going to be, remember our logit is the
natural log of p divided by 1 minus P.
So that's 1 minus p will be 0.5.
We did the natural log of 0.5 over 0.5,
that's just the natural log of 1 so
that will come out to be 0.
If the logit, again,
the natural log of P divided by 1 minus P,
then the log odds is equal to 1.0.
What's the corresponding probability
going to be?
Well, you could use some algebra to solve
this.
You can also see that in some of the
modules I alluded to that.
There's a little formula to solve this
that will that will give you if you
put in the the logit where I, where x is
here, that will give you the probability.
But we can solve this algebraically.
So you would just exponentiate both sides
here,
that's where we get the exponential in
here.
And we would exponentiate both sides, and
then you could multiply both sides by 1
minus P so we would get that P is to e
raised to 1 times 1 minus P, in this case.
So P is equal to e minus e times P and
again e raised to 1, I should carry that
over.
And then we were trying to isolate here
what's the probability, so
I'm going to do P plus e raised to 1 times
P is equal to e.
I'm just adding that to both sides of the
equation.
Then I can divide out here, this is equal
to P times 1 plus e
raised to 1 and then I can cancel that on
both sides of the equation.
So there's a little general formula.
Again, if x is the logit here, you would
just plug in e raised to
the logit divided by 1 plus e raised to
the logit.
And we've kind of solve that here.
So I plug in 1 here.
We actually get that that is equal to a
probability of 0.73 so
the correct answer here is 73% which is e.
An ROC curve with an area under the curve
of
50% has absolutely no predictive ability,
no better than chance, so
an ROC curve with a, an area under the
curve of 52% is, is bad.
So that C is correct, the model has poor
predictive ability.
The researchers fit a model here that the
log odds of hypertension,
that's our binary outcome is equal to our,
our intercept is 0.2 and our slope is
negative 0.2 times the sleep duration.
This is a cons, a continuous predictor.
So, what does the intercept actually mean
here?
Well, the intercept alone is only going to
be applied when our sleep duration is
equal to zero, that will make this whole
term go out.
So the intercept here represents the
predicted logit,
the predicted log odds of hypertension for
someone who sleeps zero hours per night.
Of course, there, it's physiologically
impossible to sleep zero hours per night,
so this person doesn't really exist, but
that is what the intercept would
represent.
So we're given a logistic regression
equation here.
The beta coefficient is negative 0.2.
That is a direct interpretations as an
odds ratio, so we just exponentiate
the beta coefficient of negative 0.2, that
gives us an odds ratio of 0.82.
So C, 0.82, is the correct answer here.
So first we have to calculate the
predicted logit here.
So our predictive logit,
again, our intercept is 0.2, where minus
.2 times the sleep duration,
which here is 6, that's going to give us a
predicted logit of -1.0.
So that's our predicted logit of
hypertension, that is the log odds.
We have to then convert that logit back to
a probability.
We can convert to a probability by
remembering that e raised to the logit
divided by 1 plus e raised to the logit,
yeah, is equal to the probability.
So, we would just plug in here the
predicted logits of -0.1 or
-1.0, excuse me and that gives us a
predicted probability of 27%.
So somebody who sleeps six hours per night
is predicted to have a 20%,
7% chance of hypertension.
The correct answer is A.
The correct answer is B here.
The units for the odds ratios are one
standard deviation increases in BMI.
So, in one standard deviation increasing
BMI corresponds to an odds ratio of 2.05.
It doubles your odds of breast cancer, so
B is correct.
Odds ratios can exaggerate effect sizes.
They exaggerate effect sizes when you're
outcome is common.
Well fortunately, breast cancer is one of
the most common cancers, but
it's still not very common.
The the general rule of thumb is if the
prevalence is less than
10% then that's considered sufficiently
rare,
that an odds ratio will be close enough to
a risk ratio, will be close to risk ratio.
So the correct answer here is B, breast
cancer is
sufficiently rare that the odds ratio and
the risk ratio will be simillar.
So, in this question, we're given two
logit plots, and
the logit plot depends on the bending in
order to be
able to calculate the percentage of people
with the outcome.
And therefore, the logit, the log odds of
people with the outcome,
you have to bend people in your data set,
group them.
So I've done two graphics here.
One with 12 bends, and
one with four bends, just to give us a
sense of the relationship here.
What we're doing in a logistic regression
is we are fitting a model where our
predictor here, our continuous predictor
is the number of menstrual cycles per
year, and we're fitting a line with the
logit.
That's what we do in a logistic
progression model.
We lo, the, we fit a line so we have an
intercept and
we have a beta and then in this case,
our, our continuous predictor is the
number of menstrual cycles per year.
Well, the line is going to be something
like this and something like this.
Of course, of course neither of these is,
is exact because we can't plot the logit
exactly it depends on the bidding.
If you just kind of eyeball it,
you'll see that only on the left graph do
we go through 0,
through the y, x equals 0, through the
y-axis, that happens somewhere around 1.
It's not going to be it's more closer on
this graph to 1.1, but
it's not going to happen exactly there,
because of course when you fit a line,
it's not going to go exactly through that
point.
So somewhere around 1,
the correct answer has to be somewhere, an
intercept of somewhere around +1.
Then to calculate the slope, we can use
both graphics and
just say what's the change in y over the
change in X, roughly here.
Well, I'm just sort of eyeballing it.
For the first graph, it looks like maybe
we go down about 2.5.
We're going down, so it's a negative
slope.
At the, for the y, and we go from zero to
12 in x,
so somewhere around maybe -2.08, somewhere
around that for the slope.
For the other picture, we can also
estimate, again,
it's somewhere, I'm estimating that it
goes down about 1.7 in x y and
x changes from 3 to 12, which is a change
of 9.
So that also gives us a slope of around
-0.2.
So the correct model here would be about 1
minus 0.2 times x here,
which is the number of menstrual cycles
per year.
So the correct answer would be c.
So, this picture is showing us potentially
interaction because it's showing us that
there is a bigger slope for
the people who are not depressed than for
the people who are depressed.
The dotted line are the depressed people.
They don't seem to get as much benefit, in
terms of a reduction in inflammation.
As the depress, the non-depressed people
do, that's the darker line.
The non-depressed people get a big drop in
inflammation if they
drink occasionally or regularly.
So there seems to be a difference in the
relationship between drinking and
information levels for depressed people
versus non-depressed people.
That would indicate an interaction.
But what would the actual proof of
interaction be here?
In order to prove interaction, what would
prove it here is that the slope for
this group would be significantly
different from the slope for
the non-depressed group.
So the slopes actually have to be
significantly different from one
another to prove that there really is a
significantly different
relationship between those two group.
So the correct answer here is B.
So I'm asking you about how these hazard
ratios where calculated here you,
these are going to be dummy-coded.
So, the obese overweight underweight is a
four-level categorical variable.
They're being compared to normal weight
women.
So we have a four-level categorical
variable that we're going to
have to dummy-code.
If you read carefully, it also tells you
that we've been, that these have been
adjusted for age and education if you read
the top of that column.
So you know that your natural log
of your hazard rate here is going to be
equal to we're going to have
an intercept plus we have to have a beta
for obese plus a beta for
overweight plus a beta for underweight.
And plus, we have to,
also, we're adjusting for age and for
education which are continuous variables.
So we have the dummy-coded variable.
It's a four-level categorical variable so
we need three binary variables in
the model to, to, to, to represent that
plus we're adjusting for agent education.
So the correct answer here would be B.
So the correct answer here is A.
We would interpret this odds ratio of
1.59,
the reference group here is the normal
weight women.
This is the relative increase in in the
rate of dementia, of developing dementia.
So, women who were obese at midlife had a
significant, and this is significant
because it does not across 1.0, the 99%
confidence interval does not cross 1.0.
So it's a significant 59%t increase in the
rate of developing dementia compared with
women who were normal weight at midlife,
and it is adjusted for age and education.
So A is correct.
One of the key assumptions of the Cox
Regression model is
something called the Proportional Hazards
Assumptions.
And what that says is that the relative
difference in
the hazard rate between different groups
has to be constant over time,
we have to have proportional hazards.
That hazard ratio which we are seeing here
can't change over time
because we're representing it here as a
single hazard ratio.
So the answer D here would be correct.
The relative differences in the hazard
rates between the different weight groups
must be constant over time.