The correct answer here is D.
The correlation coefficient is going to be
somewhere around negative five.
How do you know that?
Well, a lot of these choices are obviously
incorrect so
negative one and positive one, clearly all
the dots don't lie on the line.
The correlation is also not zero, because
you can see that the line has some slope.
And E would be incorrect because you can
see that the line has some amount of
modest correlation here.
It's certainly not strong but it's
negative, because our slope is negative.
And it's 0.5 here, although as the line is
going down as 0.5,
because it's kind of a modest correlation.
The correct answer here is B, a covariance
of zero indicates no correlation.
A covariance is a standardized covariance,
not correlation coefficient, that's why A
is incorrect.
A correlation C is incorrect, because a
correlation coefficient with a highly
significant P-value does not necessarily
indicate a strong correlation in terms of
the magnitude of the correlation.
You can have an R of 0.001 that was highly
statistically significant if
your sample size was big enough.
And D is incorrect because it's the
correlation coefficient that's unitless,
the covariance has units.
So, in this, question we're given an
outcome of cholesterol that's,
linear regression equation.
Which has an intercept of 150 plus two
times, our age past, 42 is our slope here.
Notice the units are in age past 40, so
you have to be careful about that.
If we wanted to get the predicted
cholesterol for a 60 year old his or
her age past at 40 is only 20.
So we would plug 20 in to the model here.
So our yi hat, our predicted value for
this person would be 150 plus two times
20, which is equal to 190.
In this question, you have to pick out the
regression equation from the output like I
did in some of the videos.
So what is our model here?
Our model is that our outcome, our
optimism score,
is equal to the intercepted 77.97, I'm
finding that right here.
Plus our Beta is 0.276 and our exercise is
in units of hours per week.
So, which of the following is true?
So, A is actually correct, because it says
a person who exercises 0 hours per week,
is predicted to have an optimism score of
77.97.
Well that's indeed true, you can just plug
in zero here.
This is actually going to go out of the
model.
So that's what an intercept means.
The intercept is the value for
which you get at an exercise level if the
x variable is zero.
That's your where it crosses the y axis.
Show 77.97, that would be the correct
answer here.
B is incorrect, because exercise is not
significantly related to optimism.
Our P value came out to be 0.12.
C is incorrect, because every additional
hour of weekly exercise was
associated with with a 0.276 increase in
optimism, not decrease.
Otherwise, it would have a negative sign,
and D is incorrect, because, that is give,
the intercept is, is mis, constring/g, the
intercept.
The intercept is 77.9, not the slope.
So, we're given here that we have a
regression equation cholesterol is
equal to 150 is the intercept, two is the
slope.
Our units are aged past 40.
So if we have 60 year old then we would
say his age past 40 is 20, so
we've plug 20 into the model.
That would give him a predicted value of
yi hat of 190.
This is asking for the residual, so what
is his observed, his actual value?
The residual is your observed value minus
your predicted value.
His, observed value, his actual value is
250.
His, predictive value is 190.
So he would have a residual of positive
60, which is A.
In this question, we're told that we've
run a model with DSST scores or
outcome variable.
And our first model contains vitamin D and
age as predictors.
The Beta for vitamin D we're given is
0.30, and
we're given the 95% confidence interval,
0.2 to 0.4.
Which means we know that it's
statistically significant at
the 0.5 level.
We then run another model in which we add
an additional predictor into the model,
we add exercise.
The new Beta for vitamin D turns out to be
0.15, and
the confidence interval goes from 0.05 to
0.25.
So, by adding exercise to the model, we
drastically reduced the size of
the Beta coefficient, the slope between
vitamin D and DSST.
It was reduced by 50%.
That's an indication that we have
confounding, exercise is a confounder of
the relationship between vitamin D and
DSST score.
So, A is correct here.
If you picked B, you got misled by the P
values here.
So we are, we do have a statistically
significant Beta in both cases.
That is, the relationship with vitamin D
doesn't completely disappear when we
adjust for exercise.
But we don't look at the P values for
judging confounding.
We look at the magnitude of the slope of
the Beta coefficients.
In this question we're given the mean
blood pressure of three groups.
So for the high exercise group it was 120.
For the medium exercise group it was 125.
And for the low exercise group, it was
135.
If I fit a linear regression model where I
don't have anything else in
the model other than this categorical
predictor.
What's the resulting linear equation,
regression equation going to look like?
Well my outcome here is systolic blood
pressure I have to choose something to be
my reference group.
I'm going to be dummy coding this
categorical predictor.
Well, which one am I going to choose to be
the reference group?
Well, you could choose any of these to be
the reference group, but
you're limited in your choices in the
multiple choice question.
So, you can see that in most of them, I
picked 120.
The lowest blood pressure with the high
exercise group to be my reference.
So I need this one my reference group,
because it happened to have the lowest
blood pressure.
So the intercept becomes the mean for the
reference group.
then I'm going to have two dummy coded
predictors in my model.
I'm going to have a dummy coded predictor
for
if your in the medium excercise group,
versus anybody else.
Their mean is 5 points higher than the
reference group.
So there that data is going to have a
value of five.
And we're going to be multiplying that
times one if your a medium exercise,
that's how we dummy code.
Then we're going to have to have a dummy
coded predictor in the model for
the low exercise group.
The difference between the low exercise
group and
the high exercise group in the mean blood
pressure was 15.
So they get an additional 15 for their
blood pressure.
We're going to be multiplying that by one,
if you're in the low group.
Everybody else will get a zero for that
dummy coded variable.
So the correct answer here would be D,
because only D represents the correct
equation.
This next question, we're given unadjusted
means for
three groups, the high, medium and low
exercise groups for blood pressure.
They were 120, 125 and 135, so,
the lowest exercising people have higher
blood pressure.
We then adjusted those data for age.
The adjusted estimates for
the mean, then become 115, 125, and 140.
So what we notice is that when you adjust
for
age, the disparity between the three
groups actually increases.
It looks like there's an even bigger
difference between especially the high and
low exercise groups.
So what does that tell us about the
relationship here with age?
In general I've told you here that blood
pressure will increase with age.
So if blood pressure is increasing with
age and adjusting for
age makes our differences between the
groups look even bigger.
Then what we can conclude is that the high
exercise group actually was older on
average than the low exercise group.
When we adjusted for age there's actually
a bigger difference here.
In other words if in original sample,
where we didn't adjust for age we saw a 15
point difference between the highest and
the lowest exercise groups.
However, when we adjusted for age, that
went to a 25 point difference.
So, what must be happening here,
is that we happen to have some older
people in the high exercise group.
Some younger people in the low excersise
group.
And once we adjust for age we're revealing
that the difference in blood pressure
between the exercises is even bigger than
we saw when we hadn't adjusted for age.
In this question we are told that we've
got a study were we've got a group of
just 14 women, a sub group.
We've run a linear regression model on
just those 14 women, and
we get this miraculous R squared of 99%.
Well if it looks to good to be true, it
is.
Once you stuff too many predictors in the
model,
especially with a small sample size like
this, you're at high risk of over-fitting.
That high R squared value reflects an
over-fit model.
So C is correct here, the model suffers
from over-fitting.