I want to add to the concept.
Now, we've talked about correlation and
I said, as I've said we abbreviate that as
r.
There's another concept that's directly
related to the correlation coefficient,
that's called R squared and it's not hard
to guess what that is.
You just take r, your correlation
coefficient, your Pearson's correlation
coefficient, you square it, and you get a
qua, a quantity called R squared, and
that's going to come up as we talk about
linear regression.
In this case if you square 0.78 you get
about 0.60, 0.61, and
that R squared has a nice little
interpretation.
The R squared give the proportion of
variability in the outcome variable.
That is explained by, I'm putting
explained by in quotes,
because I don't want to imply causality
here.
It might be better to say something like,
is accounted for by the predictor, or
predictors in the model.
It's also when we get to,
multi-variant linear regression, it's also
a model of, measure of model fit.
But so you could interpret in this case,
the r squared is 61%.
One of the interpretations of that would
be that 61% of the variability in
ratings of President Obama, can be
explained by your political bent.
That means 39% is left unexplained.
That's represented by the scatter around
that line.
Just knowing your political bent is not
completely tell us what your,
how your feel, going to feel about Obama.
But once you know a person's political
bent.
You have a pretty good sense of where
they're going to fall on the spectrum with
regards to Obama.
But there's still some unexplained
variability,
39% of the variability is unexplained.
So there was other things besides your
politics that, that determine whether or
not you like President Obama.
And I found this illustration of the R
squared on Wikipedia Commons, and
I thought I thought it was a really nice
illustration, so
I'll just walk you through it here.
On the left hand graphic here, what you're
seeing is y bar is the mean for y.
So this would be the mean of your outcome
variable, so
this is just like the mean ratings for
Obama in my class.
On average if you don't know anything
about persons political bent,
in my whole class, what was the overall
mean, feelings about Obama?
If you compare an individual student from
my data set to the mean.
That difference we can call, a residual or
an unexpected, that's the difference
between that given person in the mean,
that's their deviation from the mean.
If you square that, that's what that, that
square represents there visually here.
If you square that, that's the squared
distance from the mean.
Well, how did we calculate variance for y?
We calculated the variance for
y, as a function of the squared distances
from the mean.
So these red boxes here are represented,
representing
the unexplained variability in these,
representing all the variability,
essentially, of different feelings about
Obama in my sample.
On the right-hand panel here, what you're
seeing is,
now let's throw in a predictor variable.
Now we're going to, we know something
about the students.
We know their political bent.
And we know that there's a relationship
between political bent and
feelings about Obama; we can draw that
line.
Now if you know a person's political bent,
you can say with some error but
not as much error about what you would
expect their feelings of, of Obama to be.
That's what's represented by the line
there.
Now you can see, that if you compare the
distance between an individual person and
the line, the, the what we call a
regression line here,
best fit line, the distance is much
smaller.
Once you know a persons political bent the
distance, the scatter around the line,
represents the remaining variability in
feelings about Obama.
And that's represented,
those squared distances are represented as
blue boxes here.
And you can see that most of the variance
in Obama, if this was Obama, and
of course if this was the relationship
between political bent and Obama.
That you can see that most of the
variability, which is represented by
the red boxes, most of that goes away once
you know a person's political bent.
There's very little unexplained
variability left over, which is
what's represented by the blue boxes, so
this would have a very big R squared.
Most of the variability in feelings about
Obama is explained by political bent.
That's the idea of the R squared, and I
think it's just nicely pictured there.
Last week we saw an example about
chocolate and Noble Prize winners.
So this was looking at a, the per capita
chocolate consumption in a given country,
and the number of Nobel laureates,‎ per
population that they produce.
And it made interesting graphic,
where you can see the more chocolate seems
to be related to more Nobel laureates‎.
And we talked about this as an example of
correlation does not equal causation.
But I had shown in this graphic that the
correlation coefficient here was 0.79.
It was highly statistically significant.
Again, of course it doesn't mean that if
you eat chocolate,
you're going to be a Nobel prize winner.
Wouldn't that be great if that were so.
there's, of course, other variables
explaining this relationship.
If you square R here, if you square 0.79,
you get an R squared of 63 percent.
Again, that would say that 63% of the
variability in Nobel Prize
laureates per in a country, would be
explained by chocolate consumption.
Well again, you have to be really careful
with that language,
because you don't want to in any way imply
causality between the those two variables.
The chocolate consumption is a marker of
something else here.
People like to say, to take the
correlation coefficient and to
try to have a benchmark for what's strong
correlation, what's moderate, what's weak.
There's various rules of thumb running
around out there and, but
little consensus.
You'll, you'll hear different things from
different people, but
a general guide that you might use, is if
your above 0.7
that represents strong correlation between
0.3 and 0.7 is moderate correlation.
Maybe 0.1 to 0.3 would be weak
correlation.
And everything other than that is
basically pretty close to 0.
That's one rule of thumb, one guideline,
again it's just a rule of thumb.
And it depends on a, a lot on the problem
at hand.
So you maybe have cases,
where it's important to explain 5% of the
variance in an outcome variable.
That is a very small correlation
coefficient could actually be important,
because maybe, it's hard to explain it you
know,
it's hard to find to find any predictors
of that particular outcome.
There may be other cases where a
correlation of 0.7
is actually not that good.
So, it really depends on the problem.
And that's just a rough guide,
telling you about the magnitude of the
correlation coefficient.
When we're dealing with correlation
coefficients, of course,
we're also going to want to generate p
values and confidence intervals.
We're going to want to make inferences
about r.
I actually told you about the distribution
of r as an example of
a statistic in unit 5.
For r, the null hypothesis is that r is
equal to zero.
Zero means no linear relationship.
The alternative would be that its not
equal to zero,
which would mean that there's some linear
relationship either positive or negative.
I've already told you of course,
about the distribution of the correlation
coefficient.
You may not remember the details of it, so
I'll review it here.
So it turns out that the correlation
coefficient, like,
all things when we're dealing with means,
has a normal distribution, for large N,
and a T-distribution for small n.
It's a T-distribution throughout, but as
soon as your, you get on a T-distribution
where your n is greater than 100, you
might as well call it a normal.
The mean of the distribution correlation
coefficient, of course,
going to be the true correlation in the
real world, the true value.
The standard error for correlation
coefficient,
I told you was roughly the square root of
1 minus r squared divided by n.
I actually cheated just slightly here, I
left them just to make things simple.
If you really precise,
it's really the standard error of 1 minus
r squared divided by n minus 2.
Of course, if you're talking about an n of
a 100.
Or more, if you subtract two or you don't.
It's not going to make any real difference
in the magnitude there.
But if you want to be precise that n minus
2 is, is there.
So that's the distribution of a
correlation coefficient,
we can use all of that information to
calculate p values and
to calculate confidence intervals.
For, so for large N we're essentially on a
normal curve.
To, to, to do a hypothesis test, you'd
simply be cam,
comparing your observed r, your null value
here is 0.
You're comparing your observed r to a 0
divided the standard error for r.
R divided by standard error gives you Z
score,
and you'd get an accompanying p value.
To build a confidence interval, you take
the observed value of r in your sample,
and you'd add or subtract the, the
confidence limit is
usually that Z value's going to be 1.96
through 95% confidence interval.
But if you wanted and to make 99% or
90% that Z value might change, times the
standard error.
And you be just plugging in here into the
standard era the observed r,
because we don't know the true r.
That's for large N,
for small n you'd have to worry about the
fact that your on a T curve.
You might have to worry for really small
n,
about the fact that it's an n minus 2 in
the standard error.
and again you would just build, you'd do a
t,
you would be comparing r to its standard
error to get a t-statistic,
or you would be building a confidence
interval.
All in the same way that we've talked
about already.
What's kind of interesting about the
correlation coefficient.
If you look at those formulas that I just
showed you,
it turns out that whether or not a
correlation coefficient comes out to
be statistically significant, depends on
only two things.
The magnitude of r that you observed in
your sample, and in n the sample size.
There is nothing else involved.
So you can take the formulas that I have
just showed you,
and you can rearrange them a little bit.
And you can show that there's a direct
relationship between r and n,
there is you can calculate a, the minimum
size for
the correlation coefficient that you would
need to be statistically significant for
every different sample size.
And I, it's approximation here.
But you take the formulas I had in the
past, the last slide.
And basically to be statistically
significant, the,
the minimum sta r that's going to be
statically significant for
a given sample size, is roughly equal to 2
divided by the square root of n.
It's a, it's a bit of an approximation,
but it worked pretty well for
all most all n.
I can just plug in then for example, to be
statistically
significant when you have a sample size of
10, 2 divided by the square root of 10,
gives you that you're going to need to
have a correlation of 0.63.
It's going to need to be pretty big in
order to come out statistically
significant with only 10, to be confident
that that's really different than 0.
With a 100 however, 2 divided by the
square root of a 100 is,
gives you a value of 0.2.
So you can have any correlation
coefficient for
any variables in your study, that comes
out to be .02 or greater,
when you have a sample size of a 100 is
going to be statistically significant.
As you get to very big sample sizes,
as I showed you before, say a 1000,
10,000, 100,000.
The minimum correlation that's going to
come out to be statistically significant,
notice all of these, when your sample size
is a 1000 or
greater, 0.06, 0.02, these are all less
than 0.1 correlation.
That would be considered essentially no
correlation,
it's so small, that it's not meaningful.
And especially when you get to like 0.006,
0.002, you can statistically distinguish
those from 0, but
they're so, so tiny that they're not
clinically meaningful, as we talked about.
So that's where that slide came from.
I just want to mention,
while we're talking about Pearson's
correlation coefficients just quickly,
that if you have a small sample where
you're violating the normality assumption,
you'll want to use an alternative
statistic to the Pearson's
correlation coefficient, called the
Spearman rank correlation coefficient.
And it's just like all the non-parametric
tests we talked about last week.
You're going to be ranking variables, and
building a correlation coefficient based
on the ranks.
So say you're looking at height and
weight,
you would rank everybody on height, you
would rank everybody on weight,
from the lowest to the highest height, the
lowest to the highest weight.
And then you look within a person, you
look at the, the, rank they got for
height and the rank they got for weight,
and
you subtract those to come up with the
difference in the rank.
And the Spearman rank correlation
coefficient is built,
is built around the difference in those
ranks.
Obviously if the differences in those
ranks are extremely small that would
indicate that you were on a the the those
2 variables were strongly related.
If the difference in the ranks are very
large,
that would indicated that those two
variables were not strongly related.
But it's based on rank, so
you don't need to make any assumption
about normality there.