So this first question of the third
homework assignment we're given a
probability question.
So, in 1980, there were about 3.6 million
births and of which 68,339 were to twins.
And 1,337 were due to triplets or more.
Okay?
So, the first part of this question is
asking you about the probability of
having multiples or more in 1980.
So, that is just going to be the number of
twins plus the number of
triplets divided by the total number of
births.
Then, if we do this math out, that's
going to give us about 1.93%.
So that's the probability of having
multiples or more in 1980.
So that number's going to be used in the
next few questions.
So I'm going to save that number.
I'm going to rewrite it up here in the
corner, so we don't forget.
So let's take a look at the next part of
this question.
So the next part of this question reads,
what was the probability of a woman giving
birth to multiples twice in a row?
Okay so if the probability of giving birth
to multiples is 1.93%,
having that happen twice in a row is just
1.93 times o1.93.
Okay?
And that's just going to be 0.00037.
So this is probability of getting
multiples twice in a row.
Another way of printing that is to say
0.037%.
So the last part of this question reads if
a woman had 10 births in her
lifetime what was the chance that at least
one of those births was to multiples?
Okay.
And
we know this is an at least question
because of the wording in the stem.
And I'd just like to remind you that for
these at least questions, right, the trick
is to realize that the probability of the
event happening at least once is equal to
1 minus the probability of the event not
happening at all.
Okay.
So, the probability of having multiples in
one birth,
we know from the first part of this
question, is 1.93%.
So therefore, the probability of having no
multiples,
right, is 1 minus 1.93% or 0.9807.
Okay?
And then, so
that's going to be 10 births, so what we
want to do is raise this number to the 10.
[SOUND] And that's going to give us
0.8229.
Of course, then the last thing we want to
do because this
number represents the probability of no
multiples over 10 births,
we want to do 1 minus that to get at least
one multiple, okay, for over 10 births.
We're going to do one minus 0.8229 to get
17.7%.
Okay.
So if a woman gives birth 10 times the
probability that
she's going to have multiples at least
once is 17.7%.
So the second question reads suppose that
the probability of surviving for
five years, after being diagnosed with a
cancer, is 0.6.
And the probability of surviving for 10
years [SOUND] is 0.2.
Okay?
That's a pretty bad cancer.
So if a person survives five years,
what's the probability that she will
survive ten years?
So you notice this is a Bayes' Rule
problem because it's asking for
conditional probability.
So, conditioned on the fact that the
patient already survived five years,
what's the probability that the patient's
going to survive 10 years?
Okay?
That's one way of rephrasing the problem.
So I'm going to write this in the notation
the Bayes' Rule notation.
It's the probability of surviving 10
years, given each survived 5 years.
Okay?
And so
Bayes' Rule says that we can find the
answer by using a handy-dandy formula.
Okay?
And
I can just substitute in these values, so
we know this is going to be 0.2.
We know this is going to be 0.6.
And the probability of surviving five
years if
you've survived ten years of course is
100%.
So 100% times 0.24 or
1 really, times 0.2, divided by 0.6 is
going to give us about 33%.
So given that you've survived five years,
the probability that you're going to
surive ten years is 33%.
It increases from this number.
[SOUND] Okay.
So in this third question on the third
homework assignment, we're given,
we're provided with a table.
This is responders, non-responders and
test positive, test negative.
What is this all about?
So basically there's a new diagnostic
test,
and to test the parameters of this test
researchers conducted an experiment where
there were 59 known non-responders and 72
known responders.
And basically, they're given this
diagnostic test to
see how accurate this test was.
So this is sort of a typical sensitivity,
specificity,
positive predictive value type problem.
It's important to know before you start
these things,
that if you want to apply the formulas
given for, let's say, sensitivity.
For example, when given a contingency
table like this, if you search for
sensitivity on the internet, you're
going to see a lot of
resources saying sensitivity is simply
equal to a over a plus c.
And while that, while that is true in this
situation, you have to be very careful in
applying this formula because this only
works when this is the gold standard, or
what's considered true.
And this is the diagnostic test.
Okay?
A lot of times,
there are 2 by 2 tables given that have
exposure on this side,
exposure yes, exposure no, and cases and
controls over here.
So in that situation, you can't just do a
over a plus c as the sensitivity.
So first question, what is the
sensitivity?
So, as I said, it's simply 10 over 10 plus
49.
OK.
10 over 59 and
that's going to be equal to 17%.
17% is the sensitivity.
Next part of this question, what's the
specificity?
Okay, specificity is just this number over
the total.
So it's 63 over 72, and that's going to be
equal to approximately 88%.
The specificity of this test is
approximately 88%.
Then the next part of this question is
asking about applying this test to
the general population.
We know that the prevalence of testing
positive for this test is about 50%.
So we want to use this information to
calculate a positive predictive value.
Okay?
And so
in order to do this, we're going to need
to apply Bayes' formula.
We cannot calculate the positive
predictive value directly from this.
Okay.
So, Bayes' formula can be set up
like this.
So, the probability of being resistant to
the antibiotic given the test is positive.
[SOUND] Okay.
Equals the probability of
testing positive given that you're
resistant, okay, multiplied by
the probability of being resistant, over
the probability of testing positive.
Great.
So we can fill these in.
So this is going to just be 17%.
We calculated that earlier.
This is going to be 15%, this is given in
the question stem.
We know that the prevalence of resistance
among the general population is 50%.
And then lastly [SOUND] this part about
the probability of testing positive.
Well we can use an expanded formula to
calculate that.
So that's going to be the sensitivity of
the test times the prevalence,
plus 1 minus the specificity or 1 minus
0.88 times the prevalence in this test.
Okay.
So
that's just the expanded version of what
this is.
It's the probability of testing positive
in two different situations.
Okay.
Applying the sensitivity in 1
minus the specificity.
So doing all this out.
I'm running out of room here.
If you do have this calculation, you're
going to get 59%.
So the PPV of the test in the specific
situation of having a prevalence of
resistance of 50% in the general
population is 59%.
Please note that this value for the PPV is
going to change.
If the prevalence in the general
population changes.
The next part of this question is
asking about the negative predictive
value.
The prevalence of resistance is still 50%
in the general population, but
now it's asking us to predict the negative
predictive value of the test.
And so again, we can't calculate this
directly.
We're going to use Bayes' rule for
this, and we're going to set that up in a
similar way.
So, the probability that the NPV is the
probability that you're a responder,
in this situation, given that the test
result is negative.
Okay?
So, if I set that up using Bayes' Rule
[SOUND] it's going to look like this.
[SOUND].
Okay.
And we can fill these in with the
information we calculated in
the earlier parts of this question.
So this, of course, is just the
specificity.
So this is just going to be 0.88 the
probability that your responder's given in
the question stem, that's going to be 0.5.
The probability of having a negative test.
Again, we're going to use the expanded
definition here.
What we're going to do is multiply the
specificity times the problems rate in
the population.
And add that to 1 minus the sensitivity or
1 minus 0.12.
Excuse me.
I believe [SOUND] it was 0.17.
It's 1 minus 0.17,
multiplied by 0.5, okay?
So this is going to give us the
probability of testing negative.
These represent both situations in which
the test would come out negative.
So if we multiply all this out, and again
I'm outta space, but
if you multiply all this out, the NPV
works itself out to be approximately 51%.
The fourth question is asking about
probabilities again.
So, in a blind taste test,
there're three panelist, that taste five
different pizza brands.
Okay?
It's not important what brands they are.
Let's just say it's a brand A, B, C, D, E.
What's the probability that all three
panelists rate one of these last.
Let's say E.
So what's the probability that all
panelists rate E last purely by chance.
Okay, the question says, assume there's no
taste difference between the five brands,
and this is, that this is purely due to
chance.
Okay.
Well,
what's the probability of selecting E
among these five purely due to chance?
It's just 1 5th.
And for this to happen for
all three judges, it would have to be 1
5th times 1 5th times 1 5th, right?
So, that's going to lead us to 0.008 or in
other words 0.8%.
So, there's very low likelihood that if
all of these pizzas were equal,
that they would all rate one of them last
[SOUND].
So then, we move on to the last question
in the status sentence.
This is again another "at least" type
probability problem.
So let's keep that in mind as we think
about this.
So the question starts out by saying that
the in the early 1980s,
patients received reconstituted clotting
factor derived from human blood.
Okay.
The concentrates were
pooled from about 1,000 donors per lot.
If the prevalence of HIV in this donor
blood was about 1 in
3,000 [SOUND] what was the probability
that a hemophiliac would
contract HIV from a single infusion of
clotting factors.
Okay?
So let me
write this out using word words first.
The probability of having at least one HIV
positive transfusion
in those sort of 1,000 donor lots is equal
to 1 minus
the probability of having no HIV positive
donors.
Right?
And that makes sense.
So you have a lot of chances for having
HIV positive, but
these are all encapsulated by doing one
minus the probability of
having exactly zero HIV positive donors.
And so what is that probability?
So if the probability, if the prevalence
is one out of 3000,
then what we can do is do 1 minus 1 out of
3000.
Okay, to get the probability.
of no HIV positive donors.
And, of course, these are pooled over
1,000 donor lots.
So I'm going to raise that to 1000, and
then,
I'm going to subtract all of that from one
here to mimic this part of the equation.
Okay?
To get at least the probability of at
least,
of having at least one HIV-positive donor.
So it's 1 minus the quantity 1 minus 1
over 3000, raised to [INAUDIBLE] 1000.
And that's going to equal 28.4%.
And that ends Homework 3.