The three images that you're looking at
the slides,
the upper left is the emergency response
team to the airline crash
that occurred at San Francisco
International Airport in July of 2013.
The photo on the right showing the
airplane jet crashing on
the flight deck on a United States
aircraft carrier.
And then, the bottom slides is showing the
nuclear power
plant in Chernobyl that actually blew up.
Each one of these are reflections of an
industry that has undergone significant
changes in terms of attitudes and culture
when it comes to air events.
The concept that we're going to speak
about over the next few
minutes has to do with high reliability
organizations, or HROs.
What exactly is a HRO?
An organization that has succeeded in
avoiding catastrophes in an environment
where normal accidents can be expected due
to risk factors and complexity.
We're going to speak a little bit about
what are some of the commonalities and
characteristics of high reliability
organization.
Now, big question is, does your healthcare
organization fit this definition?
You know, studies have shown that there
are a fair amount of events that occur at
a patient's, majority of whom,
fortunately, do not create harm to the
patient.
But they do occur.
So, the big classic example, the classic
examples of
high reliability organizations, do include
commercial airline industry,
prior to 1980, they were subject to
multiple catastrophic events.
Planes that land where there are no
runways, or
into the side of a mountain big, makes a
bad day for that company's stock.
The middle photo, the nuclear power plants
with all the hazards that can occur.
If someone is not paying attention to the
monitors and
the controls that are in place.
And then finally, the aircraft carrier
flight decks are huge potential for
errors, especially with multimillion
dollar jets being maneuvered into a space
that's smaller than a football field,
carrying gallons of aviation fuel and
explosive devices being loaded and moved
or
directed by young people that might just
have a high school diploma.
So, what are some of those commonalities
of high reliability organizations?
High reliability organizations operate in
an unforgiving social and
political environment.
Each one of these three industries are
heavily scrutinized,
either by a governmental or regulatory
agency and basically, when the slightest
thing goes wrong, it certainly makes the
paper, makes the media and
generally brings bad press to any of these
industries that has such an event.
Another commonality of high reliability
organization is that
the technologies involved are extremely
risky and present potential for error.
Knowing that something potentially can
happen that can lead to
a power plant blowing up can also be
reliant on the technologies that,
in itself ,may be subject to some
variation, or potential some glitches.
Number three, the scale of possible
consequences from errors or
mistake precludes learning through
experimentation.
That is, we can't see how many times we
can blow up a power plant to figure out
how do we need to fix the problem to
prevent it from happening again.
Some of the characteristics that's been
identified in high
reliability organizations has a lot to do
with the culture of the organization.
Number one, there's almost an obsession or
preoccupation with the possibility of
failure.
Organizations that are high reliability
often they're at
times are concerned about well, what's the
potential next thing that can go wrong.
They also have a reluctance to simplify
interpretations or, you know,
simplify information that they're getting
and taking that as face value.
So, there's a tendency for these
organization that dig in, go deeper.
Get down to the nitty gritty to figure out
how do we understand what's going on; to
figure out what the root causes are and
the contributing factors to be able to
correct or solve the problem, and to keep
it from happening again.
The third characteristic is sensitivity to
operation.
Many, many times folks that are involved
with investigating these events
really do drill down to figure out, well
how was things actually carried out?
How are things supposed to be working?
What is the actual steps or process that
need to be done.
And to borrow something out of the
methodology.
The concept of gemba,
G-E-M-B-A, is going to the align where the
work is actually being done.
Number four, these organizations all have
a commitment to resilience.
And that they're flexible and
they will work within the confines that
they have available to be able to
figure out what is the solution to prevent
these bad things from happening again.
And then number five, the deference to
expertise.
So, in this case, it's not the senior
level employee or
management that are actually, they would
rely on,
to give them information on, what's going
on and what had happened.
They would have to rely on the person that
actually,
really does have the best core knowledge,
of whats going on.
Which potentially may not be management,
and may not be the senior most employee.
But somebody who's actually carrying out
the actual task or detail.
So, those High Reliability Organizations
all have those five characteristics.
Now, one would have to say,
well, what's it take to become a High
Reliability Organization?
And there's three core components that we
tend to think about.
The top one is the need to have
leadership.
Leadership's involvement, leadership's
focus, leadership direction.
Leadership, drives a lot of the strategy
of the organization in heading for
the right direction.
The second piece is a safety culture.
And safety culture, we're going to speak
about that a little bit more,
has some technical components that needs
to be in place in order to
establish an environment.
Where an organization is willing to learn
from either it's own mistakes or mistakes
that have been made by others, so that it
doesn't replay or repeat a bad event.
The third component is a process
improvement system,
some methodology to basically enhance or
improve the outcome or performance
of system process issues that may have
been going on in the organization.
Now, let's take a moment and speak about
safety culture.
We talked a lot about this in healthcare.
I'm not totally convinced though.
Many of us know exactly what constitute a
safety culture.
I think that these five bullets are things
to be thinking about in terms of
assuring that folks have a comfort level
and a trust level within the organization.
Starting off with the aim of the safety
culture is not to
establish a blame free culture.
It is really more geared towards
understanding how do we make things,
staff understand that there's
accountability,
in terms of making sure you're doing the
right thing.
Or making sure that you call things out
when need be and that there's some
degree of an accountability for their
particular action or function.
There really needs to separate the
blameless errors, the ones that we
need to learn from in order to correct the
system process issues,
from the blame worthy ones, where the
expectation is discipline,
consistently and equitably applied on a
regular basis when need be.
An, example of that,
if a staff person intentionally violates
the policy, even though they had
been informed that they need to follow a
particular policy and procedure.
That may be considered, potentially, a
blame worthy situation.
Versus in the blameless situation where
the system and process is so bad
that staff, due to production pressure,
are forced to shortcut things.
Due to the organization's request to be
able to either crank out more
procedures or provide more medications or
see more patients,
the shortcuts potentially are system
process issues that can create errors.
The fourth bullet, there needs to be a
uniform process for assessing errors and
the patterns that is learned or
discovered as part of the performance
improvement system.
That is, collecting the data and reviewing
it to assess whether or
not there's a need to improve.
And what's really important is the fifth
bullet,
is the need to establish one code of
behavior in terms of
how the organization will respond, top to
bottom, whenever an event occurs.
I know in management there's a tendency to
knee jerk and
insist that after an event occur, that,
you know, we go fire the staff.
Well, in healthcare today, there's really
an issue with firing all the staff.
Because I know we're going through a phase
where folks have been in
the profession for a long time, more and
more people retiring,
there's not enough people there to be able
to take their place.
So really it comes down to defining, are
we dealing with system
process issue or we dealing with,
intentional negligent behavior.
And, the response that our organization
have to any of
these events really does help establish or
sets the culture of the organization.
So, just like we mentioned, there are
three components for
a high reliability organization.
What are the three key components for a
safety culture?
Well, it starts off with trust.
The little graphic showing the person
doing the trust fall,
whether falling off the platform into the
hands of their colleagues.
You know, does staff, medical staff, house
staff,
administration, do they trust the system
to do the right thing?
The second part, and you can see the red
phone, you know, the, Presidential,
phone that connects to the premier in the
Kremlin during the Cold War.
It's like a hotline between the two
leaders of the two countries.
It's a reporting mechanism, a conduit to
raise the flag so
that the organizations are aware that
there maybe some system process issue or
events that occurred within the
organization.
And then the third piece, which we've seen
earlier in
a high reliability organization, is a
process improvement cycle.
Some way to evaluate whether or
not a change needs to be applied to
process, a process to evaluate whether or
not it will work, and then modification of
the process if needed.
It's interesting, when the organization's
staff, medical staff,
trust the system, you'll get plenty of
reports of when there's disconnect.
But the trust will not be gained or
maintained if the improvement aren't put
in place to address those issues.
So, the core foundation to making this
whole thing work really starts off
with trusting the system.
Staff can feel comfortable reporting
things, if they report things,
the organization needs to respond to
improve things.
And then that helps build trust in the
system.
I'm sure many of us have dealt with
situations where many times you
put in a report about a particular event
that's occurred over and over.
And if nothing is done to address that
issue, then one would have to say,
well, what kind of trust do I have in the
system to do the right thing?
So, it's a, it's a continuous circle where
it's interlocked and they're
interconnected in terms of establishing
the culture of an organization.
[BLANK_AUDIO]