Welcome back.
Now that you have Sas set up,
there are a few things that you need to do
to customize it.
Let's start by clicking on tools, and
selecting options.
>> Under general, go to recent files menu
and set the number of items to 15.
>> Then go to project view.
Make sure the last three are selected.
In particular, make sure to select the
display full path of data and
reference files.
>> Go to project recovery and change the
save interval to 5 minutes.
That way, if SAS accidentally crashes,
you'll have something saved from five
minutes ago automatically.
>> Then go to custom code under tasks.
>> Where it says insert custom code before
task,
click edit and add ODS Graphics On.
Just click here and type it in.
Make sure to include a semi-colon at the
end and then click save.
Where it says insert custom code after
task,
do the same thing except type ODS Graphics
Auth and then a semicolon.
Click save.
Make sure that these two boxes are
checked.
What this will do, is it’ll add nicer
graphics whenever you add.
Then click OK.
These settings should be saved every time
you open up SAS.