So I've given you two different types of
statistics for talking about
the relationship between a risk factor, or
a treatment, and a disease.
Absolute risk differences, and relative
risk differences.
So which of those gives a more clear and
honest picture of the association between
treatment and exposure or disease?
Turns out that, authors love relative
risks.
They're easy to interpret.
You don't have to worry about units.
They, that's what predominates in the
medical literature.
Unfortunately, relative risks are actually
less informative than absolute risks,
and it's often useful to see the absolute
risks in addition to,
or instead of, the relative risks.
Relative risks can mask some things.
For example, you can have a dramatic
increase or decrease in relative risk that
corresponds to a very, very tiny increase
or decrease in absolute risk.
So for example, if the risk in one group
is 0.001% and
the risk in an exposed group is 0.003%.
If you compare those two groups in terms
of a relative risk,
it comes out to be a relative risk of 3.
That sounds large and dramatic.
But if you simply subtract the absolute
risks and you focus on the absolute risks
you can see that the actual increase in
risk is extremely small.
0.002% is a really small increase in risk
for a, for an individual.
So you can see that the picture looks very
different.
Often the relative look, risks look more
dramatic and
impressive but the asset risks are most
honest.
So, let's just give you an example here.
The Women's at Health Initiative was a
large randomized double blind
study looking at the effect of
postmenopausal hormones versus placebo on
a number of outcomes in postmenopausal
women.
And this study was run in the late 1990s
and the early 2000s.
And before the study was done, it was
widely believed that.
Women, postmenopausal women, benefited
greatly from taking hormones.
In particular it was believed to reduce
the risk of heart disease.
Well that study was actually stopped early
in 2002 because it turned out
that the hormones were more harmful, much
more harmful than anyone expected.
It was.
Expected that the hormones might increase
the risk of breast cancer.
We kind of already knew that, of that
association.
But the data on the heart disease actually
came out exactly the opposite of
what people were expecting.
It turned out that they were seeing in the
data already that the hormones were
significantly increasing, not protecting
against heart disease but
increasing the risk of heart disease.
So they actually stopped the study early
as a result.
That was pretty pretty big news, because
at the time they
stopped that study there were 14 million
women taking post-menopausal hormones.
So you can imagine that they must have
thought very carefully about how to
deliver the message to not only to
physicians, but
to the many women in the public taking
hormones at the time.
And, actually somebody did a really,
really great job in
thinking very carefully about how to
present the risk information.
The media coverage was extremely well
done, and this had, largely had to do
with the fact that the press release that
was released about the study to the media.
They, they talked about the risks in a
very particular way, and
the media ended up just repeating what was
in the press release.
And, and it went like this.
They said the data indicate that if 10,000
women take the drugs for
a year, eight more will develop invasive
breast caner,
compared with 10,000 who were not taking
hormone replacement therapy.
Notice they are presenting, presenting the
incidence rates,
the difference in incidence rates.
They're presenting everything also
everything in whole numbers, which is,
you know, again, easier for people to
understand.
An additional seven will have a heart
attack,
eight will have a stroke, and 18 will have
fewer well, blood clots, but there
will be six fewer colorectal cancers and
few, five fewer hip fractures so, they're
also presenting the data on on the things
that were beneficial from the hormone.
So, this was very well done coverage.
It's very unusual because if you look at
the media coverage most of the medical
literature you'll see that they
almost always talk about relative risks
and not, and not absolute risks.
And that's not really the, the fault of
the media necessarily.
That's just the way that these data are
usually presented in medical studies.
So just to, to drill down a little bit
more on,
on the data from this study, so if you
looked at breast cancer,
you can see that the rate of breast cancer
in the hormone group,
the incidence rate was 38 breast cancer
cases per 10,000 women-years.
In the placebo group, that rate was 30 per
10,000.
So the rate difference was eight
additional breast cancer cases per
10,000 women years.
So that's exactly what they presented in
the press release.
However, if you look at the paper, the
paper presented that information.
It also presented the relative risk.
And the relative risk here was 1.26.
The interpretation would be that there
was a 26% increase in the risk of breast
cancer on women taking hormones.
You can see that that's a very different
message if you, if the,
if the press release and the media had
told women that there
was a 26% increase in their risk, that
sounds much more dramatic.
It's not that the number is wrong, it's,
that's the true increase in relative risk.
But, if you look at the absolute risk
numbers, you can see that the risk to
any individual woman is actually really,
really small.
Imagine if a woman hears that she has a
26% increased risk of breast cancer,
that sounds very impressive and scary.
But in fact, her increase or absolute
increase in risk is just 0.08% per year.
So eight out of 10,000 is 0.08%, so it's
actually a very,
very small increase in risk in, for any
particular, one particular woman.
You can see how different the message
looks depending on
whether you give the relative risk versus
the absolute risk.
For heart attacks, the numbers are very
similar with 37 per 10,000 in
the hormone group, 30 per 10,000 in the
placebo group.
So seven additional heart attacks per
10,000 women-years.
But again, the relative risk, if you look
at it as a relative risk.
Is 1.29.
That again looks much more dramatic, but
in fact a much more honest presentation of
the risks would be to say, to look at the
absolute risk differences, or the absolute
rate difference here, 0.07% again is not
really a big increase in risk.
We can also calculate from this data, just
to practice, the number needed to harm.
So, we have the absolute rate differences.
And as, as, I told you before, the number
needed to harm you can
calculate by just doing the reciprocal of
the rate difference.
So, if it's seven additional heart attacks
are going to occur when you
treat 10,000 women with hormones for one
year.
Then to harm one woman, you would need to,
so
it's better to harm seven than to harm
one, you would divide 10,000 by 7 to
get that you would have to treat 1,429
women with hormones.
In order to have one additional heart
attack you would have to
treat a 1250 women with
post menopausal hormones in order to have
one additional case of breast cancer.
So presenting it in that number needed to
treat.
Number needed to harm picture also helps
people to put that risk into perspective.
Now this is, that's a pretty high number
needed to harm, or number needed to treat.
But remember, if you have 14 million women
on hormones,
that translates to several thousand cases
of heart attacks.
And thousand, several thousand breast
cancer cases per year.
So the risk to any individual woman is
small here, but
the risk to society is large.
So, just think about all of these things
when you're presenting risk and
talking about risk.
First of all, most people have an easier
time understanding whole numbers than
percentages and decimals.
So it's great to always try to translate
things into whole numbers.
Absolute risks give a more accurate
picture of the true risk than
relative risks.
Relative risks can look really dramatic
even when the absolute risk
increase isn't, isn't very big.
And then the other take home message from
this study is that,
interestingly, you know, the public health
risk can be large even when the risk to
a given individual is small.
So sometimes, depending on whether you're
looking from the societal perspective or
the individual perspective, those risks
may, you know,
the risk picture may be different.