In this next module,
I'm going to talk about looking at data,
that is graphing your data.
It's always important when you get a new
data set,
to graph each of your variables
individually.
When you do that, there's a lot of things
that you can pick up from the graph.
So you all, want to always plot your data.
And what you're looking for are things
like if you do a, a frequency plot of
your variables, that what we're going to
talk about in this module.
You can immediately pick up things like,
are there outliers?
And outliers are just extreme values, very
high or very low values that
maybe are outside of the range that's
expected, for your particular population.
Outliers, by the way,
are not necessarily data errors, and we're
not going to just throw them out.
But I always get students coming to me and
saying, oh, you know,
can I call this an outlier and can I throw
it out of my data set?
We're certainly not going to throw
outliers out.
But it's important that we know that
they're in there when we're
doing a data analysis.
Because they can be very influential on
some of the statistics,
as we'll see later this week.
The other things that you can pick up off
of a graphic,
are data points that just don't make
sense.
These are usually data entry errors.
So if the data were entered manually, it's
very easy for
a data entry error to be introduced.
Most data sets that are entered manually
will have some of these.
You want to pick those up as early as you
can, in the data analysis process.
Finally, you want to plot your variable,
so
that you can see how the data are
distributed.
What's the shape of the distribution?
Where's the center?
What's the variation?
So you can get a good feel for your
variables.
Just to illustrate the importance of
graphing and
how easy it is to pick up some of these
things from the graphic.
I had a variable in my data set on my
Stanford students, where I
asked them to report how many servings of
fruit and vegetables they eat every day.
So I went into the data set and made one
data entry error.
I took one of the values, where someone
said that they eat ten servings and
I added a 0.
Just for illustration here.
And you can see that it would be very
easy, and when somebody's entering
data for something like this to happen, is
0 to be added or left out.
You can see how easy it is to pick up this
mistake on the graph.
Right?
it's immediately obvious that that
point doesn't make sense.
You can't have people eating 100 fruits
and vegetables a day.
So you would pick that error up
immediately, and
be able to resolve it right away.
But the thing you're looking for
when you're graphing the data, is just to
describe how the data are distributed.
So, for categorical data's, you want to
pick up information like, what
are the n's, the sam, numbers and percents
in each of the different categories?
And for quantitative data, you're going to
be asking questions like,
what's the shape of the distribution?
Do I have a bell curve, eh, a bell curve
or skewed distribution?
Those are some of the different things we
are going to be talking about in
this module.
Where's the center of the data?
What's the spread or variability of the
data?
The frequency plots that I'm going to be
showing you.
These are for plotting one variable at a
time.
For categorical variables, I'm going to
show you a bar chart.
Most of you are probably familiar with a
bar chart,
they're fairly easy to interpret and make.
For continuous or
quantitative variables, I'm going to show
you about two types of plots.
There's something called a box plot and
something called a histogram.
And I love histograms.
You're going to be seeing tons and tons of
histograms in this course.
So it's important that you pay attention
in this module, so
you really understand what's going on in a
histogram.
You'll probably be dreaming in histograms
by the end of this course.
So first of all, a bar chart is used for
categorical variables.
Again, it shows the frequency, that is the
count, or
proportion of observations in each of the
categories.
For example, I asked the students in my
Stanford data set,
did they play varsity sports in high
school?
30 said yes, 20 said no,
and that's very simple information to pick
up off the bar chart.
Also, I created a categorical variable for
coffee drinking,
I divided people into none, light,
moderate, and heavy coffee drinking.
And you can see the frequency counts shown
in a bar chart here,
the way that I divided the categories I
ended up with,
fairly even numbers in all of those
categories.
Again, very easy to look at and interpret
a bar chart.
For quantitative variables, we're often
going to use a box plot or a histogram.
And again this is to show the shape,
center and
range of variation of that quantitative
variable.
So, we're going to start with a box plot
here.
So, here's the box plot for exercise.
I asked the students to report how many
hours of moderate to
intense exercise that they do every week.
And you can see that my Stanford students
were doing pretty well on exercise.
Most of them are getting a, a decent
amount of exercise weekly.
The way that you interpret this box plot.
So, first of all, the box is the middle
50% of the data.
So if you were to arrange the students
from the lowest exercise per week to
the highest.
That would represent,
the box would be the, those who are right
in the middle 50%.
That is, from the 25th percentile to the
75th percentile.
So the 25th percentile here is 2, the 75th
percentile is 6.
So that means that 25% of my students were
doing less than two hours of exercise per
week, 25%, a quarter of my students were
doing more than six hours per week.
The middle 50% was between 2 and 6.
The line in the box represents the median,
that's the 50th percentile.
It means that 50% of my students were
exercising more than 3 and
a quarter hours per week.
50% of my students were exercising less
than 3 and a quarter hours a week.
The distance from the bottom of the box to
the top of the box,
from the 25th percentile to the 75th
percentile.
That's called the interquartile range, or
sometimes we abbreviate that as IQR.
So I'm just going to subtract 6 minus 2 in
this case.
And we see that the interquartile range is
4.
The middle 50% of my data, the spread of
that is 4.
So that parts actually fairly
straightforward.
The box is fairly straightforward.
It gets a little more tricky when we talk
about the whiskers.
So I'm going to start with the top
whisker.
The top whisker can be one of two things.
It's either the maximum value.
Or it's this other quantity, which is the
75th percentile, or
q3 plus 1.5 times the interquartile range.
I'll calculate what out, out what that is
in, in just a second here.
But you're going to pick out of those two.
For the top whisker, you're going to pick
whichever of those is lower.
If the maximum is lower, you put the
whisker at, at the maximum.
If the other, if the q3 time, plus 1.5
times the interquartile range is lower,
you're going to put the whisker there.
So let me just calculate what that is
here.
So again, the interquartile range is 4, so
1.5 times the interquartile range of 4
gives you a value of 6.
And what we are doing here with this value
of 6,
is we're saying that if you are more than
6 below the 25th percentile, or more than
6 above the 75th percentile, you're kind
of outside the expected range for
this population, and we're going to call
you an outlier.
There actually are no outliers in
exercise.
We're going to see in the,
in another variable, we're going to see
some outliers.
So in this case the third quartile, the
75% percentile accrued at 6 hours, the 1.5
times the interquartile range is also 6,
so this boundary, this value here is 12.
It turns out though, that actually the
maximum value was also 12 here.
So those are equal in this case, there was
a student who exercised 12 hours per week.
Since both of those are equal to 12,
obviously we're going to put this upper
whisker at 12.
For the lower whisker the, lower whisker
will occur at whatever is higher out of
the minimum value,
or, the 25th percentile minus 1.5 times
interquartile range.
You're going to pick the higher of those
two, and put the lower whisker there.
So in this case the 25th percentile occurs
at 2 minus 6 is equal to negative 4.
So this boundary would occur at negative
4,
but of course, you can't have negative 4
hours of exercise per week.
So this whisker will occur at the minimum,
which is 0, there are some students who
didn't do any exercise per week, so we put
the whisker at the minimum.
So, in this case, with this boxplot of
exercise,
the whiskers just represent the minimum
and maximum values.
We're going to see in the next slide,
that sometimes the whiskers represent this
other quantity.
So I also asked my students to report for
me, how they rated themselves on their
political leanings.
And I had a scale that was anywhere from
zero where zero's the most conservative,
up to 100 where 100 is the most liberal.
And I asked my students to rate themselves
on that scale.
You can see by looking at the boxplot that
the majority of
Stanford students cluster in the liberal
range, in the democratic range.
And if we just narrow, zero in on the box
here, the 75th percentile occurred at 85.
The 25th percentile occurred at 68.
So, that means the middle 50% of my
students range between a value of
68 to 85, so that's very much in the
liberal, Democratic range.
The median occurred at 78, so half of my
students rated themselves higher than
a 78, half rated themselves lower than a
78.
The interquartile range is just the
distance from the 25th to
the 75th percentile, so that's 85 minus
68, or a value of 17.
So actually, my, that's a fairly narrow
range here.
My students are really clustered up in
that, liberal, range of values.
Now, in terms of the whiskers here,
the upper whisker occurs at the maximum
possible value of a 100.
So one of my students said that they were
a 100, as liberal as it comes, and so
I'm going to put the whisker there.
If I were to calculate the 3rd quartile
plus 1.5 times the interquartile range,
that's 85 plus 1.5 times 17.
Obviously that's going to be higher than a
100.
So the maximum is the lower of those two
values,
we're going to put the whisker there,
there's nobody who falls outside,
of that 1.5 times the interquartile range
boundary.
For the lower whisker however, notice it's
different.
Because the, the lower whisker here is not
at the minimum value.
So, if you calculate the 25th percentile
minus this 1.5 times
the interquartile range, you get 68 minus
1.5 times 17, that's a value of 42.5.
So, we're going to put the whisker at
42.5, because that's higher than
the minimum value, the minimum value
actually occurred at 27.
So what this is saying is that, given the
rest of the people in
in this sample anything below 42.5 is kind
of unexpected for this data set.
These people, if you're outside,
you're outside the expected range if
you're lower than 42.5.
We're going to call those people who fall
in that range, lower than 42.5,
we're going to call them outliers, and
we're going to represent each person who
is an outlier with a dot.
Now, what do these outliers actually mean?
There's four people here.
Again, the lowest occurred at 27.
So what do those outliers mean?
That doesn't mean that those are not data
errors,
there's not problems with the data.
Those are real people and though, that's
probably really their political bent.
So these again are not errors,
it's just that most of Stanford's students
are more in the liberal range.
So anybody who's at 27, 30, and even the
low 40s,
is outside of what's expected for Stanford
students.
Again we're not going to throw them out.
Those are real data.
Those are real, there are really Stanford
students who are Republican.
And clearly they may be outliers for this
particular population.
But if you went elsewhere in the country,
say you went to you know,
to the midwest of the US, it fact,
it might turn out that, that range is
quite common out there.
And, so people that had values of 27, 30,
40 may not at all be outliers in a
different population.
But, again, it's important we know that
those outliers are there.
Because they can have a lot of influence,
a lot of sway on certain statistics, as
we're going to see this week.
So that's the, the boxplot.
Now, I'm going to show you the histogram.
So I took that same variable exercise, and
I put it into a histogram.
So a histogram, the way you build a
histogram, is you take the,
the range of values.
So in this case, you know,
exercise range from 0 to 12, and you
divide it up in to equal intervals.
So in this case I've made, we call those
bins.
I've made bins of two hours per week.
So I've divided up exercise into zero.
To two, two to four, four to six, six to
eight, eight to 10, 10 to 12, 12 to 14.
And then what this graph shows you
is what percent of my observations falls
within each of those bins.
So the Y axis here is a percentage.
It's the percent of observations that
occur within each of those bin.
And you can see by looking at this graph,
it's immediately obvious that
most of my students, the biggest number of
students fall between two and
four hours of exercise per week.
So it's just a really nice graphic,
because you can immediately see kind of
where everybody lies.
Let me go into a little bit more detail
about how to read this graph.
So again the Y axis is a percentage.
So you would scroll across for example for
this lowest bin, the zero to two bin.
If I scroll across to the Y axis,
I see that intersects the Y axis at 12%,
the height of that bin.
The height of that bar is 12%.
So that means 12% of my students, and
remember I had 50 students so 12% is equal
to a count of six.
So 12% or six of my students exercised
between zero and two hours per week.
And in fact it's actually between Zero and
just up to two, but not including two.
It happens to be that this statistical
program,
the higher value in the bin, is not
included in that bin.
So, it's going to be zero all the way up
to but not including two,
two is going to be anybody who is exactly
two, will be included in the next bin.
So you just have to know that about the
way that this particular program
groups things.
So you read the next bin which has
obviously the highest.
That bar has the highest height as 42% so
that's 21 students.
42% of my students exercise somewhere
between two and just up to but
not including four hours per week.
And you can read across all the bars in
the same way.
I'll just read the very last one here for
you.
So it turns out that there was one
student, 2%,
who exercised exactly 12 hours per week.
That person got included in the 12 to 14
bin,
because again, the 10 to 12 bin does not
include 12.
So 12 to 14 is the bin that actually
includes exactly 12 hours per week, so
there, that represents one student who
exercised 12 hours per week.
Now again you can, there's just so
much information that you can pick up
visually here.
So notice that this distribution,
the shape has what we call a right tail or
a right skew.
All this means is that you know,
most people exercise a couple of hours per
week, but there's a few people who
are really heavy exercisers and they fall
form a tail out to the right.
A couple of high values out to the right,
so
we call this a right skew or a right tail.
I just want to show you what happens if I
change the bin sizes.
So what if I were to set the bin size to
be really small like 0.2 hours per week?
You can see that this graph is not as
visually appealing.
It's harder to pick up the pattern from
looking at this graph.
So this graph really just has too much
detail.
If you make the bins too small, you end up
with too much detail, it's not as helpful.
Similarly if you make the bins too big,
lets say I set them to be eight hours per
week each.
Again in this case there's too little
detail, and
you're not able to pick up all the
important details from, from this graphic.
So it's a little bit of an art selecting
the right bin size.
I, it turns out that most standard
statistical programs have
an algorithm that will choose the bin size
for you.
if you if you don't want to choose it
yourself.
Or you can control that bin size yourself,
to get just the right amount of detail in
there.
[SOUND].
So those are the histograms for exercise.
Let me now show you the histogram for
political bent.
So, again, as we saw with the boxplot.
You had a lot of students clustering in
the liberal democratic range.
That is in between 50 and 100.
And, you can see that this, the shape of
this distribution,
we could say it has a little bit of a left
skew or a left tail,
that is most people are in the 70, 80, 90
range.
But we have a few lower values out to the
left, so
you might describe that as having a left
skew.
You could also describe this distribution
as being bimodal.
That means it has two peaks, or two
groups.
And that's actually pretty informative to
see it that way.
Because what's going on here, is that I
really do have two types of students,
two groups of students in terms of
politics.
I have a large group of Democrats at
Stanford.
And you can see that within that group of
Democrats,
if you just look at the distribution of
political readings within my Democrats,
those those ratings actually follow a
pretty nice bell curve.
So what that says is, Democrats at
Stanford hover around a liberal rating of
sort 80 that's kind of a mean.
But we have some who are more in the 60 or
70.
That's a left tail.
Some who are over in the 90 or 100, that's
a right tail.
So it actually follows a pretty nice bell
curve.
So that represents my Democrats at
Stanford.
But then we also have a second group,
that's much smaller but it does exist.
We have a second group at Stanford
students who are Republicans, we have a,
a number you know a population of students
who are Republicans.
Interestingly, this the,
the political rating within the
Republicans also follows a normal curve.
And it's centered around 40, so
you can see that the Republican group at
Stanford is not highly conservative.
Right?
40 is actually quite close to 50?
So they're a little bit in the
conservative Republican range, but
they're hovering around 40, which is a
rather high in that range.
And then we've got some, who out in the
30s, and down to the high 20s,
and some that are up to, you know, high
40s, and low 50s.
So, again though, it's interesting to see
that there's really two groups here.