Hi, welcome to our module on if then L
statements.
I use these almost every time I work with
SAS.
>> It is a great way to clean, transform
and work with your data.
>> As you maybe have guessed,
if then L statements have two main parts,
the condition and the action.
If a condition is true, then SAS will
perform the specified action.
SAS evaluates each record of the data set
one at
a time to see if it meets the condition
following the if statement.
And then takes the action that you
requested after the word then.
I will use this complicated code to
demonstrate how if, then,
L statements work in SAS.
When you run this code, SAS goes through
the data set one row at a time.
For each row, SAS looks at the first
expression following the first if.
If this condition is true for that row,
SAS will execute the first statement
following the then of that line of code.
If this is the case, SAS will not check
any of the else if
statements that come after the first line
of code.
If the condition is false for that row in
our data set.
SAS will check the condition at the next
else/if line of code.
If this condition is true for that row in
our data.
SAS will execute the second action, and
will not look at the remaining else/if
lines of code.
If the second condition is false for the
row.
SAS will check the condition at the next
else if line of code SASS will continue to
do this until it gets to the very last L
statement you have specified.
Once a row meets the criteria for an if
statement.
Or one of the L statements SAS will
perform the action after the vance
statement and then start the whole process
over again for
the next row in the data set.
>> An important thing to remember is that
event statement must always come after an
if statement.
All of this sounds pretty complicated.
It'll make a lot more sense when we take a
look at an example.
Let's start by looking at a dataset called
people.
As you can see, it has a column for
gender, and a column for weight.
If you take a look at our data you'll see
that one male has a value of 9800
for the weight.
And another subject has a negative value
Weight can never be a negative number, and
9,800 is a pretty unreasonable weight.
These were probably mis-coded whenever the
data was collected.
let's use if, then statements to clean up
our data.
As you can see in our code, we first made
a copy of our original data set,
then we have some if, then statements that
modify the data set.
Remember, when we use if/then statements,
SAS will check each row, one at a time,
for each of these conditions.
So, first SAS will look at row number 1.
Gender is male and weight is 125.
So, SAS will check if this row meets the
condition of the first if statement.
In this line of code,
we can see that the first condition is if
weight is greater than 500.
Since this row has weight equal to 125,
which is not greater than 500,.
Condition is not met and SAS will ignore
the rest of this line of code.
SAS will then move on to the next
[UNKNOWN] statement.
This time the condition is weight less
than zero and weight not missing.
In this case the weight value is not
missing, but it is greater than zero, so
this condition is not met.
This means that SAS will ignore the rest
of this line of code.
Since it reached the end of the if.
And as if statements without meeting any
of the conditions.
SAS will not do anything to Vizero in the
data set.
Now SAS will do the same process for the
second row in our data set.
The second row has male for gender and a
weight of negative 150.
So first, SAS will check it against the
first.
If statement.
Again, this condition is for weight
greater than 500.
This is not the case for the row we're
working on.
So SAS will ignore the rest of this line
and
then move on to the next else/if
statement.
In the next line of code,
the condition is weight less than zero and
weight not missing.
In this case, the weight value is not
missing, and it is less than zero.
So our route meets this condition.
Now SAS will perform the action that we
specify after the then statement in this
row.
If you take a look at this code, we've
written, than delete.
This tells SAS to delete that row from our
data set.
Once it does this, SAS will move on to the
next row of data set,
and start this whole process over again.
Let's run this code and look at the
output.
Here on the left we have the original data
set,
and on the right we have the output from
the code we just ran.
As you can see, it deleted these two rows
from our data set.
Just like we specified in our if then
statements.
>> Let's go over another example to fully
demonstrate the power of
the if then L statement.
Say we were interested in creating
separate and
permanent data set that only included the
males in our study.
Take a look at the codes on the right of
the screen.
Here I told SAS to create a new permanent
HRP
223 dataset called people_males based on
the original people data.
I then asked sas to look at my data one
row at a time.
Just like rom described.
And determine if some one was a female.
If a rona data set fulfills this
conditions,
then SAS will fulfill the action and
delete the observation.
Lets run the code.
On our right, we have our new data set
called people_males.
Notice how SAS has deleted all the female
observations.
So what happened behind the scenes?
So SAS first looked at row 1 of our
original data,
as you can see gender is m for male and
weight is 125.
So SAS checked to see if this row met the
condition of the first if statement.
In this line of code we can see that the
condition is if gender equals f.
Since this row has gender recorded as M
the condition is not met.
And SAS ignored the rest of the lines of
code.
SAS then checked to see if there were any
other [UNKNOWN] statements.
As you may recall from our code, we didn't
include any.
So no actions were taken, and SAS moved on
to the next row in our data set.
Once SAS reached row 3, where gender is
female and
weight is 115, it checked to see whether
the condition if gender equals f was met.
Since this row has a gender recorded as f.
The condition was met and
SAS fulfilled the action and deleted the
observation and moved onto the next row.
SAS continued this process for all the
rows in our data set.