In our final analysis, we're interested in
studying BMI.
We also want to chop up the continuous
variables, so
that we can study them as categorical
predictors.
Let's start by creating a new variable for
BMI.
In our data set, we have weight in pounds
and height in centimeters.
In order to calculate BMI, we need to take
weight in
kilograms divided by height squared, where
height is in meters.
So first, we need to convert pounds to
kilograms and centimeters to meters.
Let's do this in a data step.
First, we create a new data set called
BMI.
And we fill in the data from a clean
diabetes data set.
Then, we create new variables for weight
and height.
Since there is about 2.2 pounds for every
kilogram,
if we divide weight in pounds by 2.2 we'll
convert it to kilograms.
Likewise, since there's 100 centimeters
per meter,
if we divide our original height by 100,
we'll convert it to meters.
Then we use a drop statement to remove the
variables in their original units,
since we don't need them anymore.
As you can see, we now have a new variable
for weight and
height, now in the correct units.
Here we're going to continue working on
our BMI dataset.
We'll use a set statement to fill in the
data we just created.
Now we create a new variable for BMI.
BMI is equal to weight over height
squared, where weight is in kilograms and
height is in meters.
One way to specify exponential in SAS, is
by using a double asterisk.
So here in the denominator we have height,
underscore meters, double asterisk 2.
Which means height squared, just like we
want it.
We also want to reorder the variables in
our dataset.
We can do this with a retain statement.
Remember a retain statement must come at
the top of the data step, or
else it won't work correctly.
So first we'll have the diabetic outcome
variable, followed by BMI.
Then weight, height and age.
And then the rest of the variables will
remain in the dataset,
in their default order.
[SOUND].
As you can see, we now have a new variable
for BMI.
And we've changed the order of the
variables.
>> Now let's chop up our continuous
variables, so
that we can study them as categorical
predictors.
As you may recall, we showed you how you
can do this using PROC RANKS.
This can create groups for continuous
predictors.
Say we're interested in quartiles for age
and BMI.
Let's take a look at the code.
This PROC RANK code might look familiar.
First we specify our original dataset,
BMI.
And then we have to specify an output
dataset using out equals, and
then the name, BMI_quartiles, in our case.
Then, the group statement allows us to
create categories.
Groups equal 100 allows you to create
percentiles.
And in our case, groups equals 4 creates
quartiles.
We then need to specify the variables of
interest using var.
Var analysis we included var, age and bmi.
It's important to remember a rank
statement.
This will create separate variables that
contain the categories for quartiles age,
and quartiles BMI.
Without these, our age and BMI variables
would be replaced by the categories.
Lets run this code and take a look at the
output.
As you can see, we now have two new
variables.
The first variable is labeled ranks for
variable age.
And the second is labeled ranks for
variable BMI.
These categories can now be used in our
analysis.