In this module, I want to show you how to
create a simple box plot,
as well as a simple histogram.
>> Say we wanted to create a box plot for
the white variable, and that we wanted one
plot for males, and one plot for females.
We'll start our code with PROC SGPLOT, and
then specify your data set.
In the second line of code we write, hbox.
Hbox stands for horizontal box.
This statement tells SAS that we want a
box plot.
We then specify the variable for which you
want to make a box plot.
In our case we're interested in weight.
Remember, we want to make a separate plot
for males and females.
We can do this by adding a forward slash,
followed by category equals gender.
If you ever forget this syntax,
you can always check back on the online
SAS documentation.
Let's run the code and look at the output.
As you can see we now have a separate box
plot for males and for females.
>> Now I'll show you how to create a
histogram.
As you can see from our code,
our first line has not changed from our
previous example.
And our second line we have now specified
histogram followed by
the variable we want to analyze, which in
this case is h.
In unit three,
we showed you how to use PROC univariate
to create a histogram for you data.
PROC SGPLOT is nice for
making a histogram, if you need some extra
graphic options.
Let's take a look at the default
histogram.
[SOUND] Now let's take a look at a
histogram with some optional commands.
[SOUND].
>> So this is what the default histogram
will look like.
And this is what a histogram can look like
if you use some of
the optional commands for the PROC SGPLOT
statement.
>> [SOUND]
The more you start experimenting with
graphics,
you'll probably realize that sometimes the
graphics can get a little glitchy.
If you make a title on one plot, it might
carry over onto all your other plots.
[SOUND]
>> For example, in this code, we have two
plots.
The first one doesn't have a title, but
the second one does.
When we run it, we have a title for both
of them.
By adding GOptions, reset equals all,
before each line of code, will flush
out any graphic settings, so that each
plot will be made from a clean slate.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now the plots will look just like the way
we wanted it.
>> Before we end this module,
let's talk a little bit about online SAS
documentation for graphics.
Let's open up our web browser and search
PROC SGPLOT, and
open up our first option from SAS.
We can then open the procedure syntax on
the left,
and pick the histogram statement.
As we can see on this page, we have all
the options for the histogram statement.
All the options will come after a forward
slash.
After the forward slash, we can use any of
these options here.
If we wanted to change the color for
example, we could use this fill attribute
statement.
We use fill attributes equals, color
equals, and then specify a color.
That's just what we did right here.
Fill attributes equals color equals
lavender, and we had that in parenthesis.
That's what made this histogram lavender
as opposed to this one,
which was a light blue.
>> If you ever want to modify your
graphics and
customize certain aspects, feel free to
use this online documentation.
It'll provide with all the code necessary
to make professional graphics.