[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module,
I'm going to introduce you to survival
analysis and tell you about
the statistics that are used to compare
time-to-event outcomes between groups.
We talked about time-to-event variables at
the very first week of this course, so
a time-to-event variable is something that
you can collect only in a randomized trial
or a cohort study where you're actually
following people over time.
It's a hybrid variable.
You're measuring the amount of time that
they contribute to the study before they
have the event, or until the study ends,
or until they drop out of the study.
As well as you're recording whether or
not they actually have the event, because
not everybody will have the event.
This might be something like time to
death, or time to heart attack, or
time to chronic kidney disease.
People who don't have the event are said
to be censored.
And that is recorded as well as the amount
of time that they contribute.
So, the time-to-event variable has a time
part.
That's the time from when enter the study
until you have an outcome, or
you're censored, meaning you leave the
study without having the outcome.
The binary part of the time-to-event
variable is just whether or
not the subject had the event.
And again, subjects who don't have the
event are said to be censored.
For time-to-event outcome survival
analysis, there's a couple of
different statistics we're going to be
talking about in this course.
So, I mentioned already in week two of the
course, we talked about the rate ratio.
I'm not going to go over that again here,
I'll refer you to week two.
This week I'm going to talk about
Kaplan-Meier statistics that's
the unadjusted way of comparing survival
experiences between two or more groups.
In a couple of weeks we'll talk about Cox
regression which is the multivariate
regression technique that's commonly used
for survival analysis.
What is survival analysis?
Again, it's the statistical methods for
analyzing time to event data.
They get a special name because they are,
they're a set of methods.
They combinate data from randomized trials
or cohort study designs.
Again, you have to be following people
over time to collect this type of data.
Here's an early example of a survival
analysis going back to 1669.
This was a curve, that, someone drew,
showing how many out of a 100 people
survive until 86 years of age.
So the way to read this curve is we are
starting at an age of zero,
this is a 100 people born in 1669.
Notice that this, this is survival on the
y axis.
This, this is the percent of people
surviving out of 100.
So it starts at 100%, everybody's born and
then there's a rapid drop off of survival.
So notice that at this is at about 10
years old here, only 64% are surviving.
There was a lot of infant mortality back
in the 1600s.
You get down to about 16 years of age
there's only 40% surviving.
You get down to you know, 20 years of age,
there's only a third of people surviving.
And you get down to 36 years of age.
Only one in six, 16% of people are still
alive.
So if we all lived in the 1600s most of us
would be dead by now.
So it's a really good thing that we live
now and we have modern medicine.
Modern medicine has really,
really drastically improved survival
compared to this.
And this is just a few centuries ago.
But this is an example of survival
analysis.
What we're trying to do.
The goal in survival analysis is to figure
out this survival curve.
We start at 100% and drop off from there.
We're going to draw some curves today
called Kaplan-Meier curves.
And essentially that's what we're trying
to do.
We're trying to, to define what percent of
people are surviving.
Surviving is going to be used loosely
because we're
not always going to be talking about the
event of death.
We might be talking about other types of
events besides death.
But this was developed, these methods were
developed around.
Death, around survival.
And there's all sorts of things we can ask
about this curve like what's the shape of
this function?
This is sort of an exponential curve
you're seeing here.
We can define the curve based on what's
the chance a person survived past
a certain age, past 20, past 36?
When we talk about the Kaplan-Meier curve,
that's essentially what we're doing.
We're saying how many people survive event
free, past certain, time points.
And this is survial analysis.
We're trying to estimate this curve.
We're going to do what's called a
non-parametric estimate of this curve.
An emprical estimate of this curve.
That's a Kaplan-Meier curve in just a
minute.
Again, this doesn't have to be time until
death.
It can be time until any event that you
want, any binary event.