Welcome back.
In the last module, we showed you how to
make your own macro.
Sometimes, instead of making your own
macro,
you need to use one that's already been
made.
>> Here's a macro made by our colleague,
Dr. Ray Belise, which is used for
generating a certain type of graphical
plot.
You'll learn more about this in your HRP
Biostatistics courses.
But, it's interesting to see how they
work.
>> As you can see, this is a really
complicated macro.
It includes several procedures, and has
many parameters that you can specify.
But, it still follows all the rules we
told you about, making macros.
It starts with percent macro, and it ends
with percent mend.
After the macro statement, it has the name
of the macro,
which you can see is logitplot.
This is followed by a side of parenthesis,
which contains four placeholder variables
that are needed for this macro.
We need to specify the input DataSet,
a predictor variable, an outcome variable,
and the number of bins.
You don't need to worry about what all
this code does, but
we'll walk you through the steps you'll
need to use this macro.
First, we'll need to run this macro.
Now, that we've run this macro, we can
invoke it.
Our macro is called logitplot.
So, we can invoke it by typing
%logitplot().
For our DataSet, we'll be using a DataSet
called group.
For the predictor value, we'll use weight.
For the outcome variable, we will use is
diabetic.
We will specify our NumBins as 4.
Remember to separate these parameters
using comas.
You have to specify them in the order that
we have listed in the original macro code.
Now, when we run this line of code, we
will invoke the macro.
And, it'll fit in the placeholder
variable, just like we told it to.
As you can see by the output,
it automatically ran all this code, and
the output is a graphical plot.
Using this macro is a lot easier than
copying and pasting this massive chunk of
code and manually tweaking each instance
of every variable you want to change.
If you want to do that manually, by copy
and pasting it over and over and
tweaking it by hand, it would have been
very cumbersome.
And, you're more likely to make a mistake,
or
a typo, or forget to tweak one of the
variables.
When you use a macro, all of this gets
streamlined.