Welcome back.
In this module we're going to talk about
SASS libraries.
SASS has a few default libraries that you
can use.
On the bottom left of the page, you can
see the server list and all the libraries.
SASS has permanent and temporary
libraries.
By default, SASS will automatically store
all of
your files in a temporary library called
Work.
While this may be ideal for playing with
data that does not need to be saved,
remember that these may not be available
for future SASS sessions.
The temporary work library is cleared out
when you close SASS.
>> A permanent SASS library is not deleted
at the end of a SASS session.
These libraries remain on your computer
and can be accessed at any time.
When it comes to permanent SASS libraries,
it is important that the user has
specified a location so
that SASS knows where to store and
eventually find the file.
>> For most cases,
we suggest that you save your data into
the temporary work library.
You have a huge file, which you only want
to import once.
A homework assignment you want to revisit,
or
if you want to keep a permanent copy of a
SASS data file,.
You want to set up a permanent library.
I'm going to show you how to use point and
click to create a library.
Once we have done this, we will find the
code and
then use this code in future SASS
sessions.
Step one.
You're going to want to create a folder on
your desktop, or
in your documents that you will want to
use for SASS.
For this class, we've already created a
folder on the desktop called hrp223.
We're going to return to SASS and then
click on Tools, Assign Project library.
Here we're going to enter our name,
hrp223, and then next.
Now we're going to click Browse.
Let's open up the C path and look for
users.
[NOISE] Here we will find Rom three.
In your case, you will find your own user
name.
And then look for desktop.
Here is the hrp223 folder.
We'll click OK and then click Next, Next,
and Finish.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, you will see that we have our
assigned Project Library hrp223 in
our process flow.
>> SASS has a useful feature.
Whenever you use the point and click to
create something in the process flow,
you can always see the code that it
created in the background.
This is the syntax for creating your own
library in code.
>> Please write down this code.
In the future, you can just open SASS and
paste it into a new program.
This will point to the same folder you
just specified on your computer.
It is important to remember that the
library reference you created is only for
the current SASS session.
Every time you start a new SASS session,
you can use this code to re-assign the
library reference.