[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module,
we're going to dive right into the
logistic regression model.
We've talked about, when you have binary
or
categorical outcomes, that, that is when
you're looking at proportions.
We've talked about some statistical tests
when you don't want to adjust for
anything that you can use.
So, this is like the risk different,
relative risk, the chi-square test,
the McNemar's chi-square test.
So, we've talked about those.
But what about when you want to do a
regression analysis when you
have a binary or categorical outcome?
In that case, you're going to be using
logistic regression,
which we're going to talk about in this
module.
I want to just give you a little overview
of logistic regression.
So, to remind you when we did linear
regression,
the model looked like the following.
We were predicting the value of some
continuous outcome variable,
call it Y as a function of X.
Here's the simple linear regression model.
We have the intercept alpha and beta is
our slope.
So, that was the simple linear regression
model in
the multivariate regression model.
We can add some additional betas and add
Xs additional predictors.
That makes it than a plane or a higher
dimension thing.
But essentially, we are fitting lines,
linear regression.
Logistic regression actually isn't that
different.
The right-hand side of the equation is
identical in logistic regression.
So, it's going to look something like
this.
There's a linear combination of beta's
and, and X's risk factors.
It looks exactly the same, and everything
is going to be set up exactly the same,
in terms of finding the predictors of the
model.
You put can binary predictors and
you can put continuous, you can put
categorical, you can do dummy coding.
All of that is the same as with linear
regression.
What's different in logistic regression is
the left-hand side of the equation.
We are no longer modeling Yi, the outcome
variable, directly.
Rather, we're going to be modeling a
transformation of the outcome variable.
And logistic case, logistic regression
we're going to
be modeling the log odds of the outcome
and I know that sounds terrible.
That's called a logit function, but don't
worry.
I'll explain why in a minute.
We're going to be modeling this logit
function.
The log odds of the outcome.
That's our outcome variable.
We're going to be modeling that as a line
though.
As an alpha plus a beta X, an intercept
and the slope.
Because we made this transformation, the
beta is just slightly more
complicated to interpret than the beta
from linear regression.
So, for linear regression, the beta was
just slopes.
As X goes up by 1 unit, how much does Y go
up?
So, there was a direct interpretation.
It's just slightly more tricky to
interpret the betas from
logistic regression.
But actually its not terrible because the
beta's from logistic regression,
if you exponentiate them, what it gives
you out is Is the odds ratio.
And I referred to, in the second week of
the course, we talked a lot about
odds ratios, and I told you, hey, logistic
regression spits out odds ratios.
And, and this is where it comes from.
The betas can be directly interpreted as
odds ratios just by exponetiating.
And the reason there's an exponential
involved is because our
outcome variable involves a natural look.
So, this is just the overview of where
we're going.
Just keep in mind that the right hand side
of
the equations the same as with linear
regression.
So, we're still fitting a line.
It's just we're fitting the outcome
variable,
there's something trickier going on.
Let me start here with a simple example,
using that example data set, data set
on my Stanford students, that I've been
using since the beginning of the course.
One of the questions I asked my Standford
students is, whether or
not they consider their selves to be book
smart or street smart.
This is a binary variable.
Book smart if, if the variable is equal to
1.
That means that they consider themselves
book smart.
If the variable is equal to 0, the way
I've coded it,
that means that they consider themselves
to be street smart.
So, we can see that this is the book smart
group over here.
And this is the street smart group group
over here.
And I just as as aside, I've been asking
this question to lots of
Stanford students just for fun over the
years.
And it generally comes out about 80% of my
Stanford students consider themselves to
be book smart, and about 20% consider
themselves to be street smart.
And that was indeed, the case in this
little practice data set.
It's right around 80%.
I wondered if book smart students did
more,
spent more time on homework, were more
studious than street smart students.
And so, I wanted to look at the variable
homework and
the number of hours per week that they
spent on homework.
That's another question that I had asked
these students.
And we can look at that here, and
I've done this, I've looked at this
graphically here.
So, I'm graphing my predictor variable is
just a binary, a yes, no,
book smart or not.
And my outcome variable here is homework,
in the number of hours per week.
And now, surprisingly the students who
consider themselves book smart, as you
can see on this graphic here, actually, on
average, do slightly less homework than
the students who consider themselves
street smart, for whatever reason.
So, it went kind of in the opposite
direction from what I might have expected.
This analysis, this graphic that I'm
showing you here,
actually coincides with a linear
regression.
So, the way I set up the problem now is
I've got a binary predictor variable and
a continuous outcome variable, homework.
And we could model this with a linear
regression.
Using what we talked about last week.
When we have a binary predictor, it's a
very simple linear regression.
Right, that line is just you connect to
the mean for
the street smart group with the mean for
the book smart group.
And if you connect two points with a line,
that, that defines a line.
So, we end up with a very simple line.
So, we could answer this question.
Look at this question in this data set
with a linear regression, or
even a t-test, which of course is a
special case of a linear regression.
This is cross-sectional data, however.
So, I've happened to pick just for the
purposes of illustration, in for
this slide to put book smart as the x
variable as the predictor and
homework as the outcome variable.
But because this is cross sectional data,
I could ask, I could flip that.
I could ask whether or not whether you
classify yourself as book smart,
predicts the amount of homework you would
do.
But I could ask it the other way.
Does the amount of homework you do, amount
of time you spend on homework,
predict whether or not you consider
yourself book smart?
So, I'm just going to flip the x and y
variables.
So, here's the graphic when I flip the x
and y variables.
So, now my x, my predictor variable, is
continuous.
The number of hours spent on homework per
week.
And my outcome variable is this binary.
This yes, no.
Zero is street smart.
One is book smart.
We've got a new graphic.
And we could try to fit a line to these
data.
But look what happens when I try to fit a
line to these data.
Notice that all of my my outcomes are
either all one or all zero.
So, you get this two stripes.
And it doesn't, it doesn't seem optimal to
try to fit a line.
I did fit a line to these data.
You can do it.
You, this is a linear regression line.
So, I fit the linear, the best fit line to
these data.
But you can see that if you look at this
picture,
it doesn't really look like that line fits
the data very well, right?
I mean, when we're doing linear regression
last week, we have these scatter plots and
we were trying to find the line that was
close all those dots.
Well, this line doesn't, you can fit it,
but
it doesn't look very close to all of those
dots.
It doesn't look like a very good fit.
So, a linear regression model is not
optimal here.
Well, what do we do?
Again, I told you were're still going to
want to fit lines here.
So, how can we still fit a line but do
something other than linear regression?
How could we, what could we do?
So, what we could do here is to transform
the outcome variable.
Again, I still want to fit a line
ultimately.
But I don't want a zero, one variable as
my outcome because a zero,
one variable just doesn't fit well to a
line.
It has only two possible values.
So, what could I do?
How could I transform that binary, that
zero,
one variable into something that better
fits a line?
Well, here is one thing.
This is where, just a starting point,
because we're going to go further with
this.
But let's just start with, with some
simple thing that we can do.
So, recognize that instead of modeling it
as a yes no,
a zero, one, what if we could somehow
model it as a probability?
A probability, as you know, is a value
that ranges from 0 to 1,
but it can take any value between 0 and 1.
So, we would do a little bit better.
We would put in all these values between 0
and 1, back into play.
If somehow we could model this as we could
make the outcome variable the probability
of being book smart, rather than yes, no,
you are being book smart.
Just looking at the data here, you can
see,
well, that's not immediate obvious,
immediately obvious how you would do it.
In fact, we're going to do something
called the logit,
which is a function of the probability.
And, in fact, what the computer is
going to do is do a little algorithm
involving some calculus to calculate the
probability or the logit.
But we can kind of approximate it, just
actually looking at the data.
And I think this is the best way to, to
understand it.
So, if I wanted to get a probability here,
rather than a 0, 1 variable.
Imagine I did the following, what if I
just to get a probability,
I'm going to have to look at more than one
person.
I'm going to have to look at a group of
people.
So, what if I kind of arbitrarily look at,
you know, a group of people, let's just
pick, say the, the ten people with the
lowest amount of homework time per week.
Notice that these little red dots here.
Actually, some of these dots represent
more than one person,
because there were a lot of people who had
tied values.
They selected the same number of homework
and
also called themselves, book smart, for
example.
So that, each of these dots may represent
more than one person.
So, imagine that this,
this is what I've put in this box here
represents ten people.
I could look at the, say the ten people
with the lowest amount of homework time,
putting in the lowest amount of homework
time.
And I could count up how many of them
called themselves book smart, and
how many called themselves street smart.
And I could calculate a proportion, a
percentage, a probability.
So, let's say I'm just making this up, but
let's say when I calculate that.
Again, some of these dots are overlapping,
I can't do it exactly, but from the
graphic.
But let's say I count them up, and I find
among them doing the least amount of
homework, let's say that 90% of them,
again, I'm just making this up, let's say
90% of that ten.
Nine out of ten, consider themselves book
smart rather than street smart.
Now, I've got a probability, rather than a
zero, one.
And I could do this for the next group of
ten, the next highest in homework.
Maybe in the next group the probability is
again I'm just making this up, is 85%.
And I can't tell because, again, these
dots are overlapping.
Maybe that comes up to be 85%.
But I could go along and I could group
people.
I have to group people in order to be able
to get a percentage, a probability.
But I could come up with some
probabilities.
And of course, the probabilities I come up
with are going to depend on
exactly how I group them.
But just realize that the grouping is just
for the purposes of illustration.
When you actually do this with calculus,
you don't have to make any arbitrary
groupings.
Of course, we won't, go through the
calculus here, but
the computer does that for you.
So, if I could get that probability now, I
can make a graphic.
Which is my predictor variable is the
number of hours of homework per week,
that is a continuous variable.
Now, my outcome variable is a probability,
a number that ranges between zero and one.
I have fewer dots on this graphic.
I'm going to just, for now, talk about the
graphic on the left side, this 10 groups.
I, notice I've fewer dots on that graphic.
None of these dots are overlapping
anymore.
So, I actually have, I had a my previous
graphic represented 48 people.
This graphic only represents ten
observations.
I divided those 48 people up into roughly
even groups of 10 groups of,
you know, somewhere between of about four
or five per group.
And I got those percentages, and I plotted
them here.
What you notice is this is much more
amenable, this,
this scatter plot, to fitting a line.
Right now, we've got dots all around the
range.
And you can imagine actually fitting a
meaningful line to those dots.
As I mentioned, this is just for
the purposes of graphing, just to show you
the concept.
And so, it's arbitrary how I group people.
So, of course the graphics going to look a
little bit different depending on how I
group people.
So, just to show you that, I also divided
it into five groups.
There's 48 people.
So, this is roughly groups of, you know,
eight, nine, or ten.
And I calculated the proportion who
consider themselves book smart,
that probability, in each of those five
groups and I plotted it here.
By the way when I each of these groups of
course has a range of homework values.
I'm using the mean homework time for each
group.
That's what I'm putting in the plot here.
So, for example, the lowest homework group
on this plot here,
they have a mean homework time of just,
you know, a maybe 30 minutes to an hour.
And there, the proportion that consider
themselves book smart was right about 78%.
So, I'm using the mean just for graphical
purposes.
But the picture looks a little different
depending on how you group it,
but you can get the idea.
Now, we've put back all the numbers
between zero and one into play.
It makes much more sense to fit a line.
But this is still limited, okay.
So, this is not, we're going to go further
than that with this.
Because a probability is a number that's
bounded between 0 and 1.
So, it's still a bounded quantity.
You can't go lower than 0.
You can't go higher than 1.
The problem with that is imagine when we
fit a line.
When you fit a line theoretically, that
line can go anywhere from negative in,
the y value can go anywhere from negative
infinity to positive infinity.
So, with this, it's still not perfect.
So, what we're going to do is instead of
directly having the probability
be the outcome variable, we're going to
make a little transformation.
So, probability is bounded from zero to
one.
If I divide the probability however, by 1
minus the probability,
that of course, is what we have learned
earlier is the odd.
So, divide the probability by the
probability of something not happening.
So, the probability divided by 1 minus the
probability.
That's what we learned in week two of the
course is an odds.
Why would I want to do that?
Well, a probability can't be bigger than
1,
but an odds can go from anywhere, anywhere
from 0 to positive infinity.
The odds has no right hand bound.
So now, we've in all the positive real
numbers back into play.
We're still missing the negatives.
How can we get the negatives back in?
So, here's where the natural log comes in.
So, if I then take the natural log of the
odds, it turns out that when you take
a natural log, any value that was below 1,
now becomes a negative number.
So, this, the natural log of the odds,
actually ranges from negative,
can theoretically range from negative
infinity to positive infinity.
So now, we've put all the numbers back
into play.
So now, this is the most optimal for
fitting a line.
So, the outcome variable for logistic
regression, as I've mentioned earlier is
actually going to be the natural log of
the odds of the outcome.
A little complicated, but it's for
mathematical reasons that we,
we choose that.
And just to illustrate, I took those, the
same groupings,
ten groups and five groups, where I had
calculated the percent,
the probability of being book smart in
each of those groups.
And I transformed that into a log odds.
So, I took the percentage, divided by 1
minus the percentage, and
then took the natural log of that number.
This gives me some numbers like 0.5, 1.0,
1.5, 2.0 the,
the log odds has no inherent meaning to
me.
But that's okay,
because when we eventually will translate
it back into something meaningful.
But now, this outcome variable is a number
that
could theoretically go anywhere from
negative infinity to positive infinity.
Makes a very fit, nicer fitting align.
I'm graphing here the logit for each of
these groups,
against again, the mean homework time in
each of those groups.
And, you could fit a line to that, and
that's what we're doing in
logistic regression, that's the line that
we're fitting.
So, we're going to estimate an alpha and a
beta on intercept and
a slope for that particular line.
As I mentioned, the groupings here are
completely arbitrary.
When you actually do this in a computer,
there's calculus going on.
And so, you're going to get the best alpha
and the best beta.
When I do this graphically, it's a little
bit of an approximation.
You can see that the line is slightly
different when I group it
into 10 groups than when I group it into 5
groups.
These lines are slightly different.
But we can actually kind of look at these
graphics and
just kind of visually approximate the
equation of that line.
So, I'm going to do that now.
This is not as good as doing the calculus
in the computer, but it is,
it will give us a little bit of an
approximation.
And I think it's also good for
illustrating what's actually going on
here.
So, what is the equation of this line?
There's two lines here,
and we can kind of say, the, the real line
is going to be somewhere around these two.
So, first of all, what's the intercept
value?
So, if I just look at the graphic, my
intercept for
this line over on the left side is I guess
about 1.6.
You know, I'm just approximating here.
And the intercept over for
the line on the right hand side of the
page is maybe about 1.8.
So, let's just kind of call it that the,
that the equation for this line, again,
if we're kind of saying there's one line
here, that we're trying to approximate.
Maybe it's around 1.7.
I'm just making, it's somewhere in that
ballpark.
Maybe around 1.7 is the intercept.
How would I get the slopes of these lines,
just visually here?
How could I approximate the slopes of
these lines?
So, what's a slope, it's rise over run.
So, I could say well, how much have I gone
up in the y variable?
And how much have I gone up in the x
variable?
So, I can just kind of assess the triangle
here, and
say, well, what 's the, how, how far did I
go on, on the x axis?
I went from about 0 to 40.
So, the x changes about 40, here, for this
triangle.
On the y end of things, yeah if you kind
of approximate it,
it's maybe going from about 0.3, maybe to
1.6.
I'm going to just call it 1.3.
So, sorry the, you, the, we go up 1.3 in
the log odds.
So, the slope here is going to be rise
over run.
So, 1.3 divided by 40 or approximately
0.03.
So, the slope here is about 0.03.
For this line, we can use the same kind of
logic.
So, for the x, we went over about 35 here.
That's about zero to 35.
On the y end, we've gone up a little bit
bigger, maybe about 1.8 from 1,
to about 1.8.
The slope then would be 1.8 divided by 35,
which is about 0.05.
So, you know, this is somewhere, I'm going
approximate somewhere between 0.03 and
0.05, let's call it 0.04.
And of course, this is negative.
I should emphasize here that this is a
downward slope.
We've gone down 1.3 or down 1.8 in y.
So, both of these slopes are negative.
So, on average, the slopes are somewhere
around negative 0.04.
This is just a graphical approximation,
but
that's what we're doing on the district
regression, that's the line we're fitting.
Now, I'm actually going to put the data in
a computer, and
let the computer use the beautiful
calculus to estimate this perfectly,
to get the actual best intercept, and best
beta slope that fits these data.
And I'll show you that our approximation
wasn't bad.
Here's what the computer comes out with
when it does,
what's called maximum likelihood
estimation.
This involves calculus.
It gives us some maximum likelihood
estimates.
I'm not going to go into the details of
maximum likelihood estimation.
That's for another course, but this is
just the way of using some calculus that
we're getting the best alpha and the best
beta here, the best fit line.
So, when I do this on the computer, the
intercept comes out to be just over two.
So, just slightly different than what we
did, got in our approximation.
The slope came out to be right around
negative negative 0.04, negative 0.039.
So, and where did I get those in the
output?
Here's the estimate for the intercept.
That's the alpha estimate.
Here's the estimate for the beta.
That's the estimate for the slope.
Along with the alpha and beta, we also get
a p value to tell us whether that alpha or
beta is statistically different than zero.
A beta of zero would mean no association,
same as it did with linear regression.
So, the intercept is clearly significantly
different than zero.
Again that's not all that meaningful here
because we wouldn't
expect the intercept to be zero.
however, the, the p value for homework is
not statistically significant.
So, as you might have guessed,
just looking at the picture, there isn't a
strong association here.
So, it's not statistically different than
zero.
Probably meaning, it doesn't look like
there's a lot of evidence that homework
and whether or not you consider yourself
book, yourself book smart or related.
But here's the final model.
The log odds of your chance, the log odds
of your being book smart, or
considering yourself book smart,
is equal to the intercept 2.12 minus the
slope point 0.039.
And we will of course, multiply that beta
times the amount of homework.
So, this is a continuous predictor.
So, we would be multiplying the amount of
homework for
a particular person times that slope.
What's this logistic regression equation
useful for?
So, just like when we talked about linear
regression, there was many,
a couple different potential functions
here.
So, one thing is we could use the logistic
regression equation model to try to
do some kind of prediction.
This is very useful in clinical
applications because often we
want to classify people as having a
condition or not having a condition.
That's a binary outcome.
So, if we're doing that kind of
prediction,
we would likely be using logistic
regression.
So, we can try to come up with set of
predictors that predicts who's going to
have a disease or not have a disease.
So, that's one of the functions of
logistic regression, prediction.
A second function of logistic regression
which is probably more,
used even more often, is just to try to
say is a particular predictor,
like homework, related to the outcome.
In this case, book smart or street smart.
Are those variables related?
Is a treatment related to an outcome?
And that's very useful in an, in an, of
itself.
And of course, we can say, is that
predictor,
that treatment, related to the outcome
after adjusting for potential confounder.
So, that's another very important use of
the logistic regression model.
I'm going to start by talking just briefly
about the first of
these aims which is the prediction end of
things.
Again, here's the logistic regression
model.
We've modeled the outcome variable, is the
log odds of the outcome.
The, we're modeling that as a line.
Let me take that model that we just fit,
and how would we actually apply it to make
some predictions.
So, if you're somebody who
does no homework per week,
zero hours of
homework per week, you could plug in that
value for homework of zero into the model.
You get that your predicted logit is 2.12.
As I mentioned,
most of us don't think in logits.
So, in a minute we're going to
do something with that number to make it
more interpretable.
But if you did 10 hours per week of
homework, you
could plug in 10, the predicted logit
there is 1.73.
If you did 50 hours per week, the
predicted logit is 0.17.
So, the more homework you do, the more the
logit goes down.
Well, I don't want to deal with a logit
because a logit, I,
I can't think in logit.
However, we can get this notice the hot.
There's a probability in there.
What we want to get out is the predicted
probability of the outcome,
the predicted probability of considering
yourself book smart in this case.
I want to isolate this predicted
probability.
Well, it's actually not hard to do, right?
We've got one equation, one unknown, we
can isolate that probability.
So, how do we do it.
First thing that we're going to want to do
is we're
going to want to exponentiate both sides.
So, for example, the zero hours per week,
that person would predicted to have
a logit of 2.12, I can then exponentiate
both sides of those, of that equation.
So, that would tell me that the odds for
somebody who does zero
homework per week is the exponential
raised to 2.12.
That value is 8.33, if you actually
calculated it out.
So, e raised to 2.2 is 8.33.
That's the odds for a person who does,
the odds of being book smart, for a person
who does zero hours per week of homework.
Then, we could exponentiate this 1.73,
that would give me the odds for
somebody who does ten hours per week,
that's 5.64.
We could exponentiate the 0.17, that gives
me the odds for
someone who does 50 hours per week, that
comes out to be 1.19.
So, your odds of being book smart,
again, goes down as you do more homework
per week.
So, the opposite of what you might expect.
But of course, this is not statistically
significant.