In this next module, I'm going to to talk
about
the normal approximation to the binomial.
So whenever you have a binomial
distribution,
you might have noticed in the earlier
modules that a lot of the binomial
distributions when you do out all the
probabilities and
you plot them, they look an awful lot like
a normal distribution.
So it turns out that as long as you're on
a binomial,
where n times p is greater than 5, that
is, the expected value is greater than 5,
it usually looks an awful lot like a
normal.
And we can approximate that binomial,
those binomial probabilities, with a
normal distribution.
Let me just remind you of some of the
examples that we saw.
So for example, we saw this one in the
upper left hand
right corner was the wrinkle study, n here
was 10 patients, P was 0.5.
That, get, exactly gives us an np of five.
And p times p is equal to five, hey,
that looks pretty much like a normal curve
to me.
Right?
That's very close to
a normal curve of course with jagged
edges, but still very close, and,
and n times p is justified there.
When we flipped a coin a 100 times, n
times p [SOUND] was equal to 50.
And that one very much looks like a normal
curve.
When we flipped a coin just 5 times, n was
just 5 and p was just 0.5, so
this one is n times p is less than 5.
But it still looks kind of like a normal
curve, and this one over here,
we had eight cases, and n equals 8, nrp
was 0.6.
So n times p was 4.8, is a little less
than 5, but it still looks kind of close
to a normal, so we're able to pretend,
essentially, that we're on a normal curve,
and calculate probabilities as if we're on
a normal curve.
What's the mean and the variance of that
normal curve going to be?
Well, it's just going to be the mean and
the variance of the binomial.
So the, it's going to be n times p will be
the mean of the normal curve,
n times p times 1 minus p will be the
variance.
So we can literally just view it as a
normal curve, that normal curve will have
a mean of n times p and a variance of n
time p times 1 minus p.
So let's just do a little practice problem
to illustrate this.
So let's say you're doing a cohort study
and
the probability of developing disease in
the exposed group is 25%.
Let's say you sample 500 exposed people,
and you want to make sure that
you're going to get enough people that
develop the disease.
So you might want to know things, like,
what's the probability that I'm going to
get at most 120 people developing the
disease?
Well, we're on a binomial, this is a
binomial.
Each person, there's 500 people,
each person has a 25% chance of developing
the disease.
Am I going to get enough cases of disease,
or
could it be, could that I get 100, less
than 120 or 120 or less?
Well, the way to solve this, once you
recognize it's another binomial,
would be to calculate the exact binomial
probabilities of
getting all the way up to 120.
That would mean the probability of getting
zero cases of disease, one or
two or three, you have to go through,
and by hand, calculate each one of those
individual binomial probabilities.
Well, that's extremely tedious and
of course you're never going to want to do
that by hand.
Of course, a computer could also do it for
you nowadays.
But in general we, we're just going to
avoid that and
instead we're going to say well hey I'm
close enough to a normal curve.
So, let's just pretend we're on a normal
curve with a mean of 125.
That's 500 times a quarter.
And a standard deviation of the square
root of n times p times 1
minus p here is 9.68.
[SOUND] So, I take the standard deviation
and
the mean from the binomial, and I pretend
I'm on a normal.
And now, if I want to know what's the
chance of getting 120 or
less, well that's the, the area to the
left on the normal curve, of 120.
Now that's below the mean, so we know that
that area's going to be less than 50%.
I calculate my z score.
It turns out to be negative 0.52.
I go to my chart, I look up the
probability to the left of negative 0.52.
It's about 30%.
So I have a 30% chance of getting 120
cases more or less.
So rather than having to calculate all of
those individual binomial probabilities,
I can just look at it as normal.
And it turns out that that normal
approximation underlies a lot of
the statistics that we're going to be
talking about later in the course.