In this next module, we're going to talk
about probability distributions.
I'll also call these probability
functions.
So first of all, a probability function,
or a probability distribution It just
gives the probabilities of all possible
outcomes.
So last week we calculated the probability
of a particular outcome.
if you calculate the probability of all
possible outcomes of if somebody
gives you that, those to you, then you
have a probability distribution.
y You can think of it as a mathematical
function.
A mathematical function that takes the
possible outcomes x and
maps them to a probability p of x, so
we could think of this as a mathematical
function that is helpful in some cases.
The probabilities when you have the full
distribution they have to add up to one.
Otherwise you know, if you are mutually
exclusive, exhaustive Outcome.
Their probability have to add up to one.
So that's thing, one thing you can check,
that you calculated probabilities
correctly.
Though if you calculated all of them, they
have to sum up to one.
Now I am going to be talking a little bit
about continuous probability functions,
continuous mathematical functions in this,
this week.
When you're talking about continuous
probability functions, summing up or
adding up to 1 actually means integrating.
That is involving a little bit of
calculus.
So I don't want to scare you.
But if you, if you want to see a little
bit of calculus,
I will be providingt hat this week.
If you have never had Calculus before, or
integrals are just going to throw you for
a loop, don't worry about it.
All we're talking about here is if we have
some kind of mathematical function, so
here's just a continuous mathematical
function.
When I say integrate, all I mean is that
you're calculating,
you're figuring out the exact value for
the area under a curve.
So if you could do that, just by,
kind of, measuring this area under the
curve, you wouldn't need integrals.
But what the integrals do for us is,
they calculate precisely what is this area
under the curve.
So that's all an integral does.
If you don't want to see the integrals,
they're optional, you can just, kind of,
ignore them.
But every time you see integral, just
think of area under the curve.
For those of you who have a background in
calculus and
are a little more interested in seeing A
little bit of calculus tied in here.
The reason I'm going to throw up these
integrals here is just so
you can see precisely how things are
calculated and also to give you
a little bit of an appreciation for what
calculus is useful for.
So, I didn't really appreciate calculus
until I took statistics.
Once I saw how calculus was so
useful in statistics, it gave me this new
found appreciation for calculus.
And my mother is a retired calculus
professor, so
I grew up with calculus all around me, and
I really didn't appreciate it until I saw
how it was applied to statistics.
So that's why I'm going to throw in just a
little bit of calculus here.
Again, if integrels scare you, just think
area under the curve.
Probability functions can be discrete or
continuous, and discrete,
this is the same distinction we talked
about in the first week of the course, so,
discrete means you can only take on
certain values.
So, these would be things like whole
numbers, counts, you're either dead or
alive, treatment or placebo, you throw in
dice, die, can only be,
the outcomes are only, can be one, two,
three, four, five, and six.
So, can only have discrete values.
That's of course as up close to
continuous.
Continuous variables can take on any value
in a given range.
So any, to say any number between 1 and 6.
You can take on 1.2, 1.235.
So these are the things like blood
pressure,
the instantaneous speed of a car.
So continuous things have an infinite
number of possible values.
For the most part this week, I'm going to
focus on a lot of discreet examples,
because they're easier to deal to with,
they're easier to get your head around.
We can then take, kind of understand it,
using the discrete, examples.
And we can, then kind of generalize,
extend it to the continuous case.
Whenever I'm talking about the continuous
case I"ll be throwing in that little bit
of calculus, little bit of integrals this
week.
But I'll try to focus mostly on
the discrete case because it's easier to
grasp.
So let's just take a simple example.
Here's a discrete probability function.
When you roll a die, there are six
possible outcomes.
So I'm just putting those on the x-axis.
They each correspond.
Each of those outcomes corresponds to a
probability that happens to be
the same for all of them.
Just one sixth probability.
So we can draw that out in a graphic.
The Y variable here, variable here is the
probability.
So, that's a very simple probability
distribution.
Notice that those probabilities add up to
one.
Right?
One of those things has to happen so
they sum up to one.
So, all your probability distributions
have to add up to one.
We can write those same probabilities in a
table.
So, this week sometimes I'll be giving you
a table that looks like this.
So, you have x.
Those are the possible outcomes.
P of x, those are the,
the, the probabilities that correspond to
each of the possible outcomes.
Another name we call this table, a
probability mass function.
It just shows you how each of the outcomes
maps to a probability.
We call it a probability mass function
cause each outcome has a,
probability mass associated with it.
Notice that they all add up to 1.
So sometimes we talk about the probability
mass function,
that is the probability of any particular
value.
Sometimes we are actually more interested
in the probability of a range of values,
and when we're talking about the
probability of a range of values.
We call that a cumulative distribution
function.
And, by convention, cumulative functions
always start with the lowest value and
go to the highest.
So here's that same, example of rolling a
dice,
presented as a cumulative distribution
function.
So now we're not talking about the
probability of getting exactly 1 but
the probability of getting 1 or less.
Which is 1/6th, the probability of getting
2 or less is 2/6th, the probability of
getting 3 or less is 3/6th and then all
the way up to the probability of
getting 6 or less is 100% because when you
roll the dice, you have to get 6 or less.
So again, this is just a way to describe
the probability of ranges of values and
by convention we always talk about.
The probability of getting something or
less than that.
The probability is to the left.
So let me just write that same cumulative
distribution function out in a table.
Nothing profound here, again we're just
showing this is the probability of
getting one or less, two or less, three or
less, etc.
We call that a cumulative distribution
function.
This is especially important when you get
to the continuous case, because you're
always talking about ranges of values when
you're doing a continuous function.
Here's another example of a simple
probability distribution.
So, last week I showed you these this
information on blood types.
And this is really a probability
distribution,
it's just presented in whole numbers out
of 100, but you can get out of this,
the frequency probability of each of these
different blood types.
There's actually 2 variables here, there's
RH, status as well as blood type.
So we can make this even simpler by
collapsing it down to just
the probability distribution for blood
type.
So 45% of people have O blood type, 40%
have A, 11% have B, 4% have AB.
Notice that those add up to 100%.
You have to be in one of those categories
of blood type.
So that's yet another discrete probability
function.
Let's see how we can actually use these
probability functions.
So here's a little practice problem.
Suppose that in a particular hospital, in
the emergency room of that hospital,
the number of patients seen in any given
hour is represented here by x, and
x can vary.
In one hour it might be nine patients, and
in another hour it might be ten patients.
And let's suppose that somebody has
observed this emergency room for
a while and they've figured out the
probability distribution for X and
this is our, obviously an artificial
example because we're saying that there's
always between nine and 13 patients coming
into this emergency room.
I'm making it a simplified example.
So, imagine that somehow it's, it's always
that strict.
But somebody's observed and
they've figured out that 30% of the time
it's 9 patients,
30% of the time it's 10 patients, 20% of
the time it's 11, 10% 12 and 10% 13.
And that's the all the possible outcomes.
Notice that those sum up to 1.
If we listed out all the outcomes then the
probabilities have to sum up to 1.
So now we can answer some simple questions
based on this.
Probability distribution.
And notice that this is a lot easier than
what we did last week, right?
Where I made you calculate those
probabilities, now I'm just giving them to
you and it's pretty easy to pick the
probabiltiies off the chart.
So for example if I say,
what's the probability that in a given
hour exactly 13 patients arrive?
You'd just look in, in the table.
Well, it's 10%.
You just grab that right out the table.
What's the probability that at least 12
patients arrive?
So now we're talking about a range of
values.
So that's the probability that either 12
or 13 arrive.
So we would just add those two up.
So the probability that at least 12
patients arrive is 20 percent.
What's the probability that at most 11
patients that arrive.
Well at most 11 would be 9 or 10, or 11 so
I add up those probabilties and
that turns out to be 80%.
There's 80% chance that at most 11
patients arrive.
And this would be a really useful piece of
information.
For people in an emergency room.
If you were the head of the emergency
room,
you need to know about how many patients
you're expecting to come in,
in any given hour, in order to staff the
emergency room correctly.
So this has practical applications.
Some of the important discrete
distributions that you'll encounter in
medical research are the binomial
distributions.
So these are distributions that are used
in many, many cases.
They are very general.
The one that I just showed are a very
specific case, the binomial, is
something that generalizes to any time you
have a binary outcome a yes no outcome.
So whenever you have data that's dead or
alive, treated or
untreated, smoker or non-smoker, that
follows a binomial.
So that binomial distribution which we are
going to talk about.
In a module this week underlines a lot of
the important statistics,
in medical research.
Another important discrete distribution
that comes up in medical research is
the Poisson distribution.
And this is a distribution when you have
things that are counts, so like how many
cases of disease are Occurring in a given
area, those are counts.
Counts follow a Poisson distribution.