[BLANK_AUDIO].
Okay, at this point, we've had an
opportunity to
learn a little bit about the concept
behind medical errors,
never event root cause analysis and
corrective action plans.
S at this point, we're actually going to
spend a little time talking about some of
the actual case studies, or
scenarios that we have encountered that we
can use as examples of this process.
And some of the lessons learned that were
gleaned from the review of these different
events so that hopefully these events will
never occur again in the future.
Let's take a look at this first case.
You probably could imagine it's a usual
heavy OR day.
There's been multiple delays going on.
In this particular case, which was an
elective procedure and
originally scheduled to be a first case of
the day at 8 AM was bumped.
Two different other surgical cases had
bumped this elective case.
There was a hot belly and a tape back post
operative fem pop bypass bleed out,
and so they prioritized the procedures in
the operating room and
elected to push back this elective
procedure.
basically, by the time the case the other
two cases were cleared,
the you know, was probably closer to 3
o'clock.
The anesthesia team, the surgical team
were kind of exhausted from the earlier
cases but elected to stay on to get this
case off and get it completed.
The procedure list was pretty anxious to
get the case started.
He had already had gone back to the office
to see a full load of clinic patients and
was irritated already by the number of no
shows as well as
some cancellations due to it being a
Friday before a long weekend.
The patient was minimally sedated.
And groggy in responding to questions from
the nurses, you know,
as part od the pre-procedure processes.
The nurse in the, in the pre-procedure
area normally uses the consent form
from the clinic, but there were issues of
essentially trying to
find the forms in the electronic medical
record.
During the mean time,
the procedure was pretty confident of the
procedure location.
So, the patient was brought into the
procedure room.
The right side of the patient was prepped
and draped.
The proceduralist started to do the
procedure and
realized the pathology was not present.
And that in the moment, realized that the
pathology was in the opposite side.
So this was kind of brought to the
attention by the nurse who was
surveying the case who actually looked at
a set of x-rays that were up
on the viewing board and noted that the
x-ray was marked for
the other side and that's actually where
the pathology was located.
ultimately, the correct side was
anesthetized prepped, draped, and
then the rest of the procedure had
proceeded uneventfully.
Now, in the whole scheme of things, you
probably say well,
that's a close call near miss.
A bad thing almost happened, but when you
think about this as being a situation
where there was a significant process
variation, could the same sort of
thing happen if you were dealing with a,
below knew amputation, or
if you're talking about doing a lung
resection or a kidney resection, you know.
Is there a possibility of actually
resecting or
removing the wrong organ or the wrong body
part or operating the wrong location.
In those situation,
it could significantly create large risk
management issue that you'll probably
end up spending a fair amount of your time
trying to adjudicate well after the event.
So what were some of the factors that went
into
this particular case that contributed to
this situation?
Well, for starters in this particular
situation, the pre-procedure checklist,
which includes the procedure verification
location verification wasn't performed.
It was done first thing in, in the morning
and somehow paperwork got lost,
patient got, you know, was sitting in the
pre-anesthesia area.
It's a pretty aggravating, frustrating
situation for
the patient who's basically been NPL since
the night before.
And so, you know, people kind of
circumvent or short cut things sometimes
when totally unintended, but this can
actually lead to that bad outcome.
Another factor the procedure site, the
location.
Part of the Joint Commission of National
Patient Safety goal is
to make sure that you do mark your
location site so
that everybody who's involved with the
procedure,
even the anesthesiologist the nurses, the
OR nurses who has to prep the area,
they're, they're pretty clear in terms of
where we're going to be operating.
Now in some cases, you really don't know,
you know, what, you know, what,
what your actual approach is but
even a mark to help, you know, give an
indication of what's being done or
where we're going to go can help minimize
those variation processes.
Time outs, the time out is really, really
critical and it's not just a wrote or
a process that actually is just, intended
to generate more work, but
it's really in geared toward making sure
that the entire team involved with
the procedure is of the single mindset,
you know, we're all on the same page.
The time out is analogous to a American
football huddle where the team gets
together, either offence or defense, and
review what the strategy or the play is.
And then, you know, once everyone knows
what the play is,
you can actually implement or execute
whatever the play is.
Well, the time out is basically the same
thing.
it's, it's literally a momentary pause to
make sure that we're operating
on the right patient, the right location,
doing the correct procedure,
and that everybody in the procedure area
is on the same page.
The next factor, variation in work
process.
As I mentioned earlier in this particular
case,
what normally would have been a first case
of the day,
pretty straightforward, you know, quick
turnaround time, certainly got bumped for
a number of different reasons, and also
the fact of the doctor's own
workflow process had changed because of
this surgical postponement.
So these variations in work processes are
oftentimes the a huge factor in
contributing to outcome variations, in
that any time you
deviate from your standard procedures or
your standard practice or
your standard steps that you would
implement, you're setting yourself up for
particularly the unusual or variable
outcomes.
Production pressure, we all are subject to
production pressure.
It doesn't matter whether you've been, you
know, practicing attending for 40 years.
Or you're a new resident.
You know, it doesn't really matter because
there's some sort of
production pressure inevitably involved
with all of these situation.
It could be the need to see more patients,
do more procedures, quicker turn around
time.
Some of these are, are pretty clear and
obvious, you know,
especially with initiatives that hospitals
have like patient flow.
Some of them are less obvious and, and in
this situation, you know, that you, you
don't always think of production pressure,
but the fact that it, you know, in
this case you had a Friday before a long
weekend, people were making plans there's
certainly the fact that they're trying to
get the case in before the day's over.
You know, those kind of things are
production pressure that
actually generates potential variation in
workflow, work processes.
The next bullet, fatigue and distraction.
There's a fair amount of literature out
there.
This talks about how distraction and
fatigue are connected.
Sometime the distraction stands alone,
sometime the fatigue stands alone, but
both of those are factors that often times
leads to people not having the same
focus on addressing whatever their task is
at hand and as a result,
either aren't paying attention or they
shortcut the process or they skip a step.
And as a result, that leads to an outcome
that you do not want to have.
The other factor in the last bullet has to
do with the culture.
And this is really hard to define.
we, we talk about the concept, but
the reality is that the culture that we're
talking about is how is the team, that's
involved with taking care of the patient
in that moment, actually operating.
It's not uncommon that you know,
folks when they walk into certain types of
setting from one setting.
Say for example, a clinic setting, and
seeing a lot of patient and
then walking into a procedure setting, or
the OR setting or the ICU setting.
You know, there's different cultures that
occur because the team
dynamics are totally different.
It's one thing when you're use to working
with everybody on
a consistent regular basis.
And, and the key factor on culture has to
do with the fact,
do you set an environment where people are
comfortable about raising issues that may
be pertinent to what's going on with your
particular procedure.
What I mean by that, you know, in the
situation of, of this particular case,
you know, it was interesting that the
nurse that was circulating the room
noted that the x-rays were that were up on
the viewing board were,
were labeled for the opposite side, and
was able to say, hey, wait a minute.
You know, I think the X-rays are either
wrong, or
it looks like we're working on the wrong
part where we got the wrong side ready.
In cultures, you know, operating room,
procedure room, ICU ED cultures,
if staff is comfortable with the team and
can raise issues without fear of being,
ridiculed, harassed, yelled at, screamed
at, you know, they're going to be
more inclined on raising the flag to
prevent a bad thing from happening.
I think we might have said in the past,
you know,
nobody comes into our healthcare systems,
into our hospitals thinking that
morning we're going to intentionally
damage or kill a patient.
And the fact of the matter is is that
everyone is geared to trying to do
the right thing and when the right thing
isn't done,
do people feel comfortable raising the
issue and saying hey,
wait a minute, are we sure were doing the
right thing for this patient?
Are we doing the right intervention, are
we doing the right treatment or therapy?
And then the next step of course is that
how does the team respond to
that suggestion?
So, you know, some of the key things that
we'll talk about later in the program,
is some methodologies that you may want to
consider using when communicating to
other members of the team in terms of
issues or
concerns that may arise during the course
of taking care of patient.
So some of the lessons learned from this
particular event is that procedures on
wrong patient or wrong location truly are
preventable.
It's interesting that studies have shown
that at least one one individual,
one person on the procedure team aware
that something was incorrect but
due to the culture of the procedure team
was afraid to raise the issue.
In an operating room setting, a procedure
team is more than just a surgeon and
the assistant surgeon but it also would
include the anesthesiologist,
the surgical tech, circulating nurse,
potentially manufacturer representative.
Many of us in the academics medical
centers have trainees in the room.
They may not know a whole lot, but if they
heard or
saw something that they're not sure about,
you know,
they may be the first to recognize
something may be not quite right.
Team dynamics are fairly significant as we
mentioned earlier.
When everyone's on the same page and
thinking the same, and anticipating what
the next steps are going to be, the
procedure can pretty much go as expected.
When no one is on the same page, the
result can be quite varied.
So why would a culture on a procedure team
be suboptimal?
Well, I think we've already explained that
this could be due to a number of
issues including previous bad experiences.
Many of us, you know, were somewhat
trained in
an environment where sometime part of the
challenge, in terms of enduring your
training program is suffering through the
harassments and the abuse.
Sometimes, [UNKNOWN] dish out, to toughen
us up,
to make us more proficient at what we do
to become better, stronger doctors.
When the reality has shown that this very
same behavior actually do contribute to
communication disconnect and people having
fear in that situation and
when people have fear, they're not able to
react or respond as they would
normally do in a situation where that is
an underlying theme or underlying tone.
The other factors that contribute to the
outcome of a bad culture of a team,
you know, is, is things that when, when
folks are not familiar with each other, or
have different communication styles or
methods.
And other factors like distractions are
all things that actually could be
contributing to the culture of the
environment and
some of that is totally unintentional.
I like the one surgeon that I've worked
with in the past and
part of his pre, pre-procedure briefing is
actually taking a moment and
introducing himself to everybody in the
room and
letting people know what we're going to
end up doing as a group.
He actually does that as part of his
pre-procedure huddle in
the room before they actually start
cutting.
They actually do that as they're preparing
the prep for the patient so
that everybody in the room is aware of
what the game plan is and
the surgeon actually sets the tone in
terms of
how things are going to operate so that,
you know, if anything's not quite right,
his preference is that, hey, let me know,
you know, so we can address them.
And then we can look at it actually
dealing with that issue as a team so
that there's no surprises.
You want to be really familiar with these
factors.
What you say and what you do can really
influence how your team's going to respond
if you're the one that's going to be in
charge or, if you're part of the team and,
you know, a team of individuals taking
care of the patient.
Some of the tools that are out there that
you can easily look up and
will have available, are things like Dr.
[INAUDIBLE],
who developed the WHO, the World Health
Organization surgical checklist.
As a pediatric surgeon, he really believes
in standardized approach to
preventing surgical misadventure.
He actually has a very short little,
book that he wrote called the Checklist
Manifesto.
We highly encourage you to get a copy of
it and, and read it.
It is a very, very quick read and pretty
much discussed how he
came up with the concept behind the
surgical checklist that he advocates.
The joint commission had developed the
universal protocol for
the prevention of wrong patient, wrong
procedure, and wrong site surgeries.
The Universal Protocol, as otherwise known
as the UP,
consist of three core elements, and there
are some similarities between this and Dr.
[INAUDIBLE], WHO surgical checklist.
Number one that there's a pre-procedure
checklist that's used and
the elements of the pre-procedure
checklist is up to the hospital to
define what goes into that pre-procedure
checklist.
The marking of procedure site when
applicable, you know,
especially if you're doing with levels or
[UNKNOWN] or digits, you know,
you want to make sure you're working on
the right toe or finger.
But the key thing is the actual marking of
the procedure site so
that people clearly knows what are
going to be worked on.
The performance of a time map, immediately
prior to the procedure, that huddle or
that pause right, before you actually say,
put a patient under or
push the medication for moderate sedation
or actually insert or start the incision.
So, the intent of that time out, as I
mentioned before is really a quick pause
to make sure that we've got the right
patient doing the right procedure and
we're on the right location, and
we're of the single mindset that we're all
on the same page.
Some preventive strategy that we encourage
is,
you know, is doing a quick huddle to talk
about what's, what is about to be done.
We mentioned that earlier it's like we
don't,
we're not talking about a half an hour,
you know, pre-meet, we're talking about
a few seconds to get together, to make
sure we're talking about the right thing.
That the plan is going to be this and
we're going to be doing that.
Taking responsibility for marking of the
procedure site.
The drug commission has, issued some
guidance on this and clearly the,
individual, you know, the attending or the
fellow or the surg resident who's going to
be involved in the surgical procedure, are
folks that we would encourage and
joint commission requires to be doing the
actual marking of the site.
I recognize that many of you have nurses
that are involved with doing, you know,
assisting with the procedures and
the fact of the matter is is that they are
ultimately not responsible for
doing that procedures, actually the
physician that's involved.
And so the joint commission's expectation
is that the physician involved with
the procedure takes that responsibility.
We also suggest that, you know,
participation in the procedural pause or
the time out really means stop for a
moment.
Put everything down.
Don't be, looking at the paperwork.
Why they're doing the time out or
continue with the set up and the, you
know, procedure area.
Or continue draping the patient or being
on the cell phone.
Or the intent of that pause is really
everyone is stop, focus on who is
leading the procedure pause or time out
and, you know, be engaged in that process.
We will tell you that the federal
government, CMS,
state licensing, drug commission,
surveyors and
evaluators are actually taking the time to
come into the procedure room or
observe through monitors whether or not
everybody around the procedure table or
the procedure, the bed where the
procedures being done,
is actually stopped and, you know,
observing what the right patient,
right procedure, right location discussion
is going on.
This procedure pause or
time out, we're not talking about a lot of
time, we're talking about a few minutes.
Or, excuse me, a few seconds.
It's a few seconds.
And then also be aware of the production
pressure, fatigue, and
communication styles that often time comes
up.
Normally if you're alert, you're fresh,
that's one thing.
You know, your mind's engaged, but if you
have had a long hard day or
you've been on call all night and he's got
a boatload of work to have to
be done the next day, and you've got a
procedure to do, be aware that, you know,
these things can be factors in, in terms
of creating adverse outcomes.
[BLANK_AUDIO]