Hi and welcome to our module on Proc Freq.
Freq, which stands for frequency, is an
essential aspect of data analysis and
SAS enterprise guide.
This procedure creates frequency tables
and contingency tables.
>> If you're taking HRP 225 or
259, you're probably learning about
contingency tables right now.
Contingency tables which are also called
cross tabulation tables show you
the frequency distribution of your
variables.
Well the name Freq may lead you to believe
that all this procedure does,
is create tables based on categorical
data, you'll find that this procedure also
does really important statistical measures
on these tables.
Let's start coding so you can learn about
the more important features of Proc Freq.
>> I want to build a new data set for this
module.
This data set is completely made up so
that we have an interesting outcome when
we start talking about Chi-Square test.
Say we have a clinical trial testing out a
new treatment for a disease.
Let's just call it disease x and we're
interested in finding out if
treated patients have a better outcome
than non-treated.
Treated patients get a one and those not
treated get a zero.
Those cured get a one and those not cured
get a zero.
Now that we've created that data set,
let's start with our first frequency
procedure.
A frequency distribution of the treatment
variable, which tells the percentage of
subjects who were treated and the percent
who are not treated.
This is how to do it in code.
Notice how the code is pretty similar to
previous procedures I have discussed.
You start with the word proc, followed by
the procedure of interest,
which in this case, is freq.
We make sure to specify our new data set,
which is a temporary file called trial.
To create a one way table,
we include the word tables followed by the
variable we want to analyze.
As you can see, we wrote tables isTreated
and then semicolon.
Let's press run and look at the output.
>> Now you can see the frequency, percent,
cumulative frequency and
then the cumulative percent of the
isTreated variable.
The frequency column shows you how many
observation are in each treated group.
There were 18 treated, and 17 non treated.
The percent column shows you what percent
of the data received the treatment and
what percentage did not receive the
treatment.
The cumulative frequency and
cumulative percent and not very
informative in this analysis,
you may find these more insightful when it
comes to dealing with ordinal data.
For example, say you measure the
improvement,
after treatment on the ordinal scale from
one to five.
This table would then allow you to say
what percent of your population had
an improvement level of three or less.
>> See we're all only interested in one
specific aspect of the output.
For example, if you only wanted to know
the frequency.
We could rewrite our code [SOUND].
As you can see, the code's exactly the
same as my initial frequency code.
The only difference is that after
isTreated,
I've included a forward slash with the
words nocum and nopercent.
The forward slash tell SAS that I want to
use some optional settings for
the table statement.
The settings I add in just tell SAS not to
display the cumulative values
and percent values.
There are many code variations that can be
made related to a one way frequency
distribution.
As we discussed in the previous module,
it's best to use the online SAS guides to
figure out specific variations.