So, we also write the binomial.
If I want to shorthand the binomial, I
will write X,
and this little tilda means is distributed
as a binomial with parameters n and p.
So every binomial distribution is defined
by two parameters,
the number of trials and the probability
of it's success.
And sometimes in shorthand I'll write x
tilda Binomial, and
this just my short hand way of saying X is
distributed as a binomial.
Again, the probability that they're
exactly X successes,
is when you have a binomial is this parti,
this formula.
N choose X, P raised to X, 1 minus P
raised to N minus X.
So lets use this now, and solve some
problems.
So I want to return now to the problem
that I set out,
one of the problems I set out in the
teaser.
It turns out that this is a binomial
problem, and
the hardest thing about getting binomial
problems right,
is just recognizing when you're on a
binomial distribution.
Applying the formula is really trivial,
and most days times now,
are days you can just you know do
calculate things on the computer.
The key to getting, to doing well here, is
to be
able to recognize when a problem fits into
a binomial distribution, as this one does.
So, here was the problem.
We had a new anti aging treatment, and we
wanted to test if it did anything.
So let's say we treat ten patients with
wrinkles,
with this new anti-aging treatment.
There's no control group or
anything, it's a limited study here, but
just a very simple study.
The ten patients are photographed before
their treatment and after.
Those pairs of photographs are given to a
blinded independent dermatologist, and
he or she is asked to distinguish the pre
and the post photographs.
The idea being that you call the one with
less wrinkles the pre-photograph, and
the one, or sorry.
The one with more wrinkles the
pre-photograph, and
the one with less wrinkles after the anti
treat, aging treatment the post.
So if the, if the dermatologist can get
that right,
that means that the dermatologist sees a
visible change in wrinkles, and
is able to say that there are fewer
wrinkles after in the post period.
Now, let's say that you do this
experiment.
And your independent dermatologist
actually arranges the pre and
post photographs correctly for nine out of
the ten subjects.
Well, you might think, you know, that's
some evidence.
They're able to get nine right.
There's, that's some evidence that the
anti-aging treatment is doing something.
On the other hand, you also might look at
those data and say.
Well, but, you know, if the dermatologist
was just guessing,
they could just guess their way to getting
five of those right.
Right?
It would be easy to just guess and to get
five correct.
So is nine really that much better or are
they,
just is that, just is that lucky guessing?
So we want to answer the question.
We want to set the problem up in the
following way.
We want to say, well lets assume that the
anti-aging treatment doesn't do anything,
it's completely ineffective.
What's the probability that the
dermatologist could of
gotten at least nine right, purely by
lucky guessing.
And getting ten right would be even
better.
So, we're going to say, at least nine.
If they get nine or
ten right, is that evidence that the
anti-aging treatment works?
Or, is it [COUGH] that it's just, one
could easily get nine or
ten right, just by guessing?
Is it probable or is it improbable?
So, let's take, calculate the probability
that purely by guessing,
the dermatologists could have gotten at
least nine right.
Well, this is a binomial problem.
Right?
It's a binomial with an n of 10, and
again assuming that the anti-aging
treatment doesn't do anything,
we're going to start with that assumption,
the probability of correctly ordering the
photographs then is 0.5.
So, if there's 10 patients, probability of
0.5,
we're on a binomial with an n or 10 and p
of 0.5.
And we want to know what's the chance of
getting at least 9.
Our outcome is getting at least 9 of those
ordered correctly,
that means either 9 or 10.
So again we're on a binomial now.
We have to recognize this is a binomial,
which is the tricky part of this problem.
We're on a binomial where we have 10
trials, 10 patients.
And each time the dermatologist looks at a
patient, for
each of those patients, they're going to,
that dermatologist is going to try to
order the photos correctly.
If the anti aging treatment is really
ineffective,
they have a 0.5 chance of getting it
right.
Purely guessing.
So what's the probability that, by purely
guessing, they could get nine or
even do better and get ten right?
Well, we have to calculate the probability
of getting exactly nine right,
plus the probability of getting exactly
ten right.
When we calculate these types of
probabilities we always calculate all the,
we always think of the, the probabilities
in the tail, in the full tail.
Because sometimes there's many, many, many
possibilities in any
particular probability, may not have a big
probability.
So we always take, calculate the
probability of what we observed, and
anything more extreme.
In, in other words, the entire tail.
So, we're going to calculate the
probability that X equals 9, and
the probability that X equals 10.
Well, we can just apply the binomial
formula.
So, the probability that X is going to
equal exactly 9,
which is what actually happened in the
study, would be 10, choose 9,
0.5 raised to 9, and 1 minus 0.5, which is
of course just 0.5, raised to 1.
The probability of getting exactly 10
right,
is 10 choose 10 0.5 raised to 10, and then
0.5 raised to 0 of course just 1.
Well we can do out the choosing function
just for practice.
So 10 choose 9 is 10 factorial divided by
9 factorial times 1 factorial.
That's just equal to 10, if you solve it
out.
10 choose 10 is just equal to 1.
10 factorial divided by 10 factorial.
So we can calculate this out, and
the total probability here turns out to be
1.1%.
So, if the anti-aging treatment did
nothing, that dermatologist would've only
have a 1.1% chance of guessing of getting
at least 9 right.
And so that's pretty low, so
we might then believe that the anti-aging
treatment is actually doing something.
And this is our introduction to the
calculation of a P value,
which we will start talking about next
week.
But I just want to show you here,
I actually did out all the possible
outcomes, all the probabilities for all
the possible outcomes here, just to show
you the full binomial distribution here.
What are your, what are more of the
possible outcomes.
Well, the dermatologist could've gotten
zero right.
In fact, if he got, if he or
she got zero right, this means that he
miss ordered all of them.
So that in other words, all of them were
put post first and pre second.
That would suggest that the anti-aging
treatment actually had
a negative effect on wrinkles, increased
wrinkles.
You can get anywhere from zero all the way
up to ten orderings correct,
five is the most common if you're just
guessing.
Then I took the br, binomial
probabilities, and
I calculated the probabilities of each one
of those outcomes.
And notice that if you add those up,
they do indeed sum up to one, because one
of those outcomes has to occur.
Another practice problem.
Let's say you're conducting a case control
study of smoking and lung cancer.
And the probability that a particular lung
cancer case is a smoker, is 0.6.
You have a group of eight cases.
I want to know, this is a binomial
probability distribution,
because each case has the same
probability, 0.6 of being a smoker.
So I want to ask, what's the probability
that in that group of eight cases,
you end up with less than two smokers?
What's the probability that you end up
with more than five?
And notice now I'm asking to give the
probability not for
an exact number, but for a range of
values.
That means that you're going to have to
calculate multiple binomial probabilities.
So to calculate the probability of less
than two,
you have to calculate the probability of
zero, and the probability of one.
To calculate more than five, you have to
calculate the probability of six and
seven, and eight.
You can see that doing that binomial
probabilities is a little bit tedious.
For the most part,
you'll eventually be able to do this on a
computer or you can, it turns out there's
a way to approximate binomials that we're
going to learn in a future module.
But let's do this out here.
I actually did out the entire probability
distribution.
Just to remind you that, you know,
there's all these different possible
outcomes here.
There's nine different possible outcomes.
And we can calcu, calculate the exact
probability of each different outcome.
If we add those probabilities all up, they
add up to one.
So, I've just calculated, I've applied the
binomial probability formula here,
to calculate the probability of all
possible outcomes here.
If you sum those up they add up to one.
So, what's the probability of getting less
than two smokers?
That's the probability of getting either 0
or 1, so
we add those two probabilities up.
So, from the chart on the previous page is
was 0.0065 plus 0.008, that
turned out to be a probability of 0.865%,
that we would get less than two smokers.
The probability of getting more than five
smokers is equal to the probability of
getting six, plus the probability of
getting seven,
plus the probability of getting eight.
When you add those up, you get 31.68%.
Now, all probability distributions have an
expected value and a variance, and
the binomial distribution does as well.
The expected value is actually pretty easy
to reason out.
Like if I said you flip a coin 100 times,
what,
what's the number of heads that you'd
expect to get?
Everybody will say 50 heads.
You don't know why you're saying that,
you're just kind of well, you know,
100 coin flips, 50% chance of heads, or
I'm multiplying those together I should
get 50 heads.
So that is the expected value of a
binomial.
You actually are just multiplying n times
p.
And I think makes good Intuitive sense.
So the expected value just turns out to be
n times p, and
I think everybody intuitively will buy
that.
Now, the variance is a little bit less
straight forward, but
it turns out that the variance of a
binomial is n times p times 1 minus p.
For those of you who would like the proof
of that,
I'm going to offer that as an optional
module in a few minutes.
For those of you who are less interested
in this,
a little bit of an algebraic proof.
I'm going to try to get you to believe
this,
just by showing you some computer
simulation in a minute.
Of course, if the variance is n times p
times 1 minus p,
the standard deviation is the square root
of that.
Now, this n times p times 1 minus p, I
think, is just an interesting quantity.
Because, it has, it's a bounded quantity,
p times 1 minus p,
can only get so big, and I think it's a
just worth pointing that out.
So, if you think of p, p is a number
between zero and one it's a probability.
P times 1 minus p is then a function of p,
and
that function p times 1 minus p has a
maximum point.
It occurs when p, is equal to 0.5.
So, these will get bigger and bigger, p
times 1 minus p, will get bigger and
bigger, until, and it will peak at where p
is equal to 0.5.
So you're going to have the most
variability,
in a binomial when p is equal 0.5.
One fifty, we have fifty, fifty chance.
This occurs of course 0.5 times 0.5 is
2.5.
This occurs, the biggest value you can
have is a quarter.
Where p is 0.5, then p times 1 minus p
will be 0.25.
So that means that the variance of any
binomial, has to be either equal to or
less than n times a quarter.
So, a quarter of n is the maximum variance
any particular binomial can have.
So if you're working with a binomial where
you've got a probability of success that's
pretty close to 0.5, and you want to just
kind of estimate the variance,
you could just multiply n times a quarter
to get a quick estimate of the variance.
How would we use this?
Why is it useful to know the expected
value and variance of a binomial?
Well, it turns out to be very useful to be
able to, to know those.
because now, you can say what the
expected, if you know you're on
a binomial problem, you can easily
calculate the expected value.
And you can easily put a margin of error
around that expected value,
because you know the variance.
So just to apply this expected value and
variance concept,
let's take the problem where you have a
coin in that your going to flip 100 times.
If I asked you, what's the expected value
of the variance and
the standard deviation for the number of
heads.
Again, I think everybody would agree,
without knowing anything about binomials,
that the expected value here should be 50.
And indeed if we see this as a binomial
with a n of 100 and a p of 0.5,
if I multiply 100 times 0.5 I get 50.
So expected value's easy, what about the
variance and standard deviation?
So the expected value is n times p equals
fif, 50.
The variance is n times p times 1 minus p,
so that would be 100 times 0.5 times 0.5.
That comes out to be 25.
Remember I told you, that the cap on
variance for a binomial is a quarter of n,
and that occurs the the biggest, when the
maximum occurs when you p is 0.5, so
the variance here turns out to be exactly
a quarter of n.
If the variance is 25,
the standard deviation is the square root
of that, or 5.
So what does this tell us?
How is this helpful or useful.
Well this tells you that if you flip a
coin a 100 times,
your expecting to get about 50 heads.
But of course we know that we're not going
to get exactly 50 heads every time.
We could easily get 49, 48, 51,
it's not going to be exactly heads because
there's some random chance going on here.
So what this standard deviation tells us,
is that we're expecting to
get about 50 heads, and the standard
deviation's a sort of a margin of error.
We're expecting to get about 50 heads plus
or minus 5.
And so it would be totally reasonable that
you could get 45 heads all the way up to
55 heads, and even you could even go down
to 40, and all the way up to 60.
Those are all reasonable outcomes, given
the variability here.
Things that get much smaller or
much bigger than that, turn out to be
improbable.
So because the standard deviation here is
5,
we're expecting on average to be 5 away
from 50.
Now I told you that if you didn't want to
see the proof for
the variance of the binomial, I would try
to motivate that
n times p times 1 minus p is correct, by
showing you computer simulation.
And we're going to start doing a lot
computer simulations next week.
So this coin problem is just a nice
problem to start with,
to illustrate the concept of a computer
simulation.
So, what all computer simulation means,
is that I can have the computer flip coins
virtually.
And I can have the computer figure out the
expected value and
variants, simply by flipping a lot of
virtual coins.
So, this is the logic behind it.
I would tell the computer to flip a
virtual coin 100 times and
count up the number of heads.
That would give me one trial, one answer
to the binomial.
But then I would do that many, many, many,
many times.
Have the computer do that many, many,
many, many times and record all the
results.
The idea is that by doing it many, many,
many times, I'm going to see how
frequently different outcomes occur.
How frequently do I get 40 heads?
How frequently does, do I get 41 heads?
How frequently do I get 70 heads?
Do I even ever get 70 heads?
So I have the computer repeat this over
and over and
over again, an arbitrarily large number of
times.
And I'm going to, I'm going to try 30,000
Why 30,000?
It's totally arbitrary.
I just know that 30,000 is a pretty large
number, but it's not so
large that it freezes my computer.
So, I'm going to have my computer do this
30,000 times, and
I'm going to plot the results in a
histogram.
And here's the results.
So here's what happens when I have the
computer flip 100 coins, 30,000 times.
And every time it flips 100 coins, it
counts up the number of heads.
So what you notice is that the, the most
common outcome was an outcome of 50,
exactly what we expect.
That occurred, though, less than 2500
times.
Because you easily, you could easily get
49 heads, a lot of times we got 51 heads.
And you can see as you get down towards
67, 68 and down towards 33,
32, it's peters off.
Out of 30,000 times,
we never got thing, values that big.
So, that tells you that those values occur
very infrequently, and
they're very in, unlikely.
If you just look at this graphic, if you
look at the,
all the different outcomes here; the mean
is 50 as expected.
The standard deviation for
this data set of 30,000 observations,
turns out to be exactly five.
Exactly what the formula predicted.
The other really interesting thing to
notice here,
is that it makes a perfect normal
distribution.
So even though we're talking about a
binomial distribution,
which is a discrete distribution, it turns
out that in
many cases the binomial distribution ends
up looking like a normal.
And in a few modules we're going to see
that we often approximated a binomial as
a normal for that reason.
The other thing to notice, is because
we're on a normal distribution,
it's actually pretty much a perfect normal
distribution, 95% of
the observations are expected to fall
between two standard deviations below,
all the way up to 2 standard deviations
above the mean.
And indeed, 95% of these observations fell
between 40 heads, and
60 has two standard deviations below to
above the mean.
So it really is on a perfect normal curve.
And this technique again of computer
simulation,
is going to be very useful in the up
coming weeks of this course.