In this next module I'm going to tell you
about the test that are used to
compare means between more than two groups
or more than two time points.
I'll start here with The 1 way anova test.
This is a test that's used to compare
means continous outcomes between 2 or
more independent groups.
The T test was limited to 2 groups the
anova can actually 2 or more groups.
Actually the T is a special case of an
anova.
And remember the T test and anova are both
special cases of linear regression.
So really you could apply, if you had two
groups you could apply an ANOVA, but
if you have more than two groups you have
to apply an ANOVA or a linear regression.
Let me just start with an example here.
Imagine we have a hypothetical trial.
We randomize 33 subjects to three groups.
800 milligrams of calcium supplement, 1500
milligrams of a calcium supplement, or
a placebo pill, and the outcome here that
we're looking at is spine bone density.
We want to see if, at the end of the day
the most supplemented group ends up with
a higher spine bone density.
This is some hypothetical data that I've
made up.
We're going to compare their spine bone
densities.
At one year assuming that all three groups
started with roughly the same
spine bone density.
And here's the results from my
hypothetical data,
showing you some box plots.
The placebo group is a little bit lower
than the 800 milligram calcium group and
that's a little bit lower than the 1500
milligram calcium group.
So it looks like there's some increase as
you add more and
more calcium supplement to the diet.
In terms of spine bone density after a
year.
How do we determine whether or
not the differences that you're viewing
here are statistically significant.
This is where a 1 anova would be useful.
How do I get to a 1 way anova.
Okay, I'm goign to walk you through the
logic here to get you to the right test.
The question is,
is there is a difference in final spine
density in the 3 treatment groups.
What's the outcome variable it's spine
bone density.
Density.
What type of variable is it?
Well, it's a continuous variable.
Is it normally distributed?
Yes, I am telling you that it's normally
distributed.
Of course you would need to, to do some
legwork to,
to figure out if it was normally
distributed but
trust me that I tested it and it does
follow a normal distribution.
Are the observations correlated?
No, we have three independent groups.
How many groups are we comparing?
Well, we are comparing three.
Three groups here, so a t-test is going to
be insufficient.
So, that's why we're going to need a one
way ANOVA.
How does the ANOVA work?
Again, ANOVA's really mathematically the
same as a t-test.
So, the assumptions are the same.
We're assuming that we have a normally
distributed outcome.
I get the a nova is robust against this
assumption and
as long as your sample is big enough.
In fact the central limit theorm kicks in
and so this assumption really matters for
small samples.
We're also assuming equal variance between
the variance between the group.
The way that analysis of variance is
computed.
Is that we are always using a pooled
variance.
There are some, variance of anova that you
can find that allow for unequal variances.
But the standard one way anova when you go
into your
computer will assume the variances are
equal that will pool the variances.
So we want to check on that.
Also, a one way anova assumes that the
groups are independent.
So this is analogous to the two sample t
test.
[INAUDIBLE] Now, you might ask a question
here, why wouldn't I just,
I've got thre groups,oops, why wouldn't I
just run multiple t tests?
The t tests everyone is comfortable with
tje t test,
why wouldn't I just run a t test that
compares the placebo group to the 800
milligram group, and the 800 milligram
group to the 1500 milligram group, and
the 1500 milligram group to the placebo.
Why wouldn't I just run those 3 t tests as
t tests?
Why do an anova at all.
It's a fair question, and the reason is.
Is that remember, we learned last week
that when you run multiple tests,
you increase your type I error rate.
Instead of running one test here, you'd be
running three tests.
And, if these were independent
comparisons.
Of course, there not independent
But it's very hard to calc, to, to figure
out exactly how what this
probability I'm about to calculate is, if
you don't assume independence.
So I'll, I'm going to calculate this
probabilty assuming independence.
It might be slightly different beause
really we dont have indepedence here.
But if the, these were three independent
tests Each one of
those tasks has a 5% chance of a type 1
error.
So what's the chance of making at least
one type 1 error?
That's going to be 1 minus 95% rate to the
third.
Using our little trick in probability,
1 minus the probability of none is equal
to the probability of at least one.
So, we're roughly somewhere around a 14%
chance of making a type 1 error.
That increases our type 1 error rate if we
if we run all those three pairwise tests.
The Inova, on the other hand, runs just
one test, just characterizes one p value.
It's called a global test.
Because it's looking at all those
comparisons essentially at once.
So the null hypothesis for
the ANOVA, for the one-way ANOVA is that
the means of all the groups are equal.
So like the means by mode density.
In the placebo group is equal to that in
the 800 milligram calcium group is
equal to that in the 1500 milligram
calcium group.
That's our null hypothesis.
The alternative is just that the null
isn't truth,
that at least one of the means is
different.
Notice if we reject the null hypothesis
here,
it does not tell you which groups are
different.
It only tells you that some, one of those
groups is different.
At least one of those groups is different.
So this is a global test, because it gives
us kind of an overall,
a single P value To tell us if there's any
difference here,
but it doesn't tell us specifically where
those differences lie.
It's good for controlling the type one
error though because it's
only testing that single hypothesis.
Well here's the general idea of an Anova.
I'm not going to walk you through.
The exact calcuations in the anova if you
want to be walked through that I have
an op I have some optional material on on
it for you but I don't think its important
to be able to calcuate an anova by hand we
never calculate these by hand these days.
Here's the general idea [COUGH] if I have
3 groups say and
I want to compare the means.
For 3 groups, I can, I could do 3
pair-wise ttests but,
as I said, this would increase my type 1
error.
So what I want to do is actually to look
at those,
the difference in means, those 3
differences in means all at once.
How, what's a way I can look at multiple
differences at once?
Actually the variance.
The variance is a statistic that let's me
look at more than once difference at a
time.
The T-test only allowed me to compare, you
know,
one difference, one difference in in
means.
The variance allows you to compare
multiple differences in means at once.
So the anova is going to involve,
it's called analysis of a variance,
because it involves calculating variances.
It involves what's called an F test, so, I
want to know,
is the difference in the means of the
group, the difference of means,
say the 3 groups, is that more than the
background noise?
Is it more than the variability within
groups?
It turns out there is a distribution,
a test that compares the variance between
groups to the variance within group.
So we can summarize the variance between
the group,
that, that represents the differences
between all the groups that won.
That, that variance,
we can compare how different the groups
are between, each other.
To sort of the background, noise.
The variability within the groups.
And this denominator here is analogous to
the pool variance from a t test.
So if we just say,
how much variance is there in spine bone
density within each of those groups.
That represents the variability of spine
bone density.
Does that, does the between group
variance.
The difference between the groups.
Does that exceed that background noise?
That's the idea of the ANOVA.
And the ANOVA It's also called an F test
because a ratio of
variance is follows a distribution called
an F-distribution.
Just for fun, I'm just showing you the
F-distribution.
It's yet another distribution.
We've seen a T-distribution, we've seen a
Z-distribution.
If you have a ratio of two variances, that
follows something called
an F-distribution and it depends on two
sets of degree of freedom, the numerator
degree of freedom and the denominator
degree of freedom because the variance and
the numerator has degree of freedoms.
The variance of the denominator has
decreased the freedom.
This forms a different shapes depending on
the, the degrees of freedom.
So that's why when you see the results
from an ANOVA test you're
going to see that an F statistic, it comes
up with an F distribution.
Ratios of variances which is what we're
looking at here, follow an F distribution.
The F test tests the hypothesis that those
2 variances are equal.
Equal if the variance between the groups
is equal to the variance within the group
set suggests that the groups do not var,
do not differ in their means.
If the F is close to one
suggests that there's no difference in
means across the groups.
However, if the F is very far from one
That was suggest that there
is a difference in the between group
variance from the within group variance in
other words taht there is more difference
between the groups than
within the groups that would suggest that
there is a difference between the means
across the groups.
That's general idea of an anova.
Again if you want the details of the
mechanics that is going to be
optional material.
I just want you to understand the general
idea.
[INAUDIBLE] here.
So let me just illustrate that, going back
to our spine bone density example.
Within group variability is represented
just by the spread of these box plots.
So that's kind of the background noise in
spine bone density.
How much variability in any given group is
there in spine bone density?
And we're assuming that that variability
is kind of the,
roughly the same across the different
groups.
Remember, we have an assumption of
equality of variances here.
Well, it's It, it's close enough.
They're, they're pretty similar.
They're not exactly the same but similar.
We want to know, does the difference in
means between the groups exceed that,
kind of, background noise?
That variability within the groups.
So the between group variants can be
presented by looking at the means of
the three groups.
The means are represented by plus signs
here.
Is the difference in the means of those
three groups,
does that exceed the background
variability?
That, that's what a Nova is set up to
[INAUDIBLE] answer.
And I'll walk you through a brief
calculation here, and
again I don't expect you to be able to
calculate these on your own, but
just understand the concepts here.
So here's some numbers to, to work with.
The placebo group has 11 people in it.
The mean spine bone density at the end of
year one was .92, standard deviation's .1.
For the 800 milligram group the mean was
0.94, the standard deviation is 0.08.
For the high calcium supplement group, the
mean is 0.106 and
the standard deviation is 0.11.
Notice that the variance is the standard
deviation of spine bone density is
roughly the same across the different
groups.
It probably just trying to pool them as
they do Here's how the f test works.
So again, the f test is just a ratio
between
the variance to within your variance.
I'll walk you though how these are
actually calculated.
In this particular example, and so much.
Understand the concepts here.
So the between group variance we calculate
by subtracting,
first of all we have to calculate an
overall mean for spine bone density.
So the means of the three groups were
0.92, 0.94 and 1.06.
The overall mean, therefore, is 0.97.
We're going to compare the mean.
From each group, to the overall mean.
And then we're going to square it, add it
up, divide by 3 minus 1.
Notice we're just calculating a variance
here.
This is how we calculate a variance, but
our observations here are the means.
We're calculating a variance for the means
of the.
The three groups.
but that's what we call the between group
variance.
Obviously if that's big,
that means there's a lot of difference in
the means between the three groups.
So we calculate that between group
variance here, it comes out to be .063.
We then calculate the within group
variance,
all that is Is the average of the standard
deviation of bone density or
the variance of bone density in each of
those groups.
Remember the standard deviations were
0.10, 0.08 and 0.11.
We square them to get the variance and we
just take the average variance.
That's the average variability in bone
density within any given Group that comes
out to be .0095.
The F statistic is just the ratio of those
two variances.
When I put those together here, it comes
out to ave an F statistic of 6.6.
If I took that F statistic to an F chart,
I have to plug in,
I have to tell the computer, the chart,
that I have a numerator degrees of
freedom of 2, a denominator degrees of
freedom of 30.
I can get a corresponding P value.
The P value does come out to be highly
Statistically significant here,
it's something like .00, less than .001.
Because under the null hypothesis the f
should come out to be one.
6.6 definitely exceeds that.
Again don't worry too much about the
details of this test.
All of this will be calculated for you by
the computer.
Just get the variable, the basic idea
here.
Here.
Now, we get this statistically significant
ANOVA here, that tells us that
at least one of the groups differs, it
doesn't tell us which one differ.
If we then want to answer that question
about where those specific
differences lie, we would then have to go
in and do some post hoc tests.
Some actual comparing specific groups but
because we
are comparing multiple groups we then have
to compare multple comparisions.
I mentioned last week that there are ways
to correct your P values from
multiple comparisions and you could apply
those correction to account for
the fact that your doing multiple T test.
Here's some of the names for
some of those types that you might see in
the statistical analysis program.
Here's how to correct for
multiple comparisons, if you want to do
all those pair wise comparisons to
figure out where the differences really
lie.
The most common one that everyone is
familiar with is called the Bonferroni
correction.
It's very easy to plot, to apply.
You're just basically, dividing your
p-value, [UNKNOWN] .05, by the number of
tests you run, to make a more stringent
cut off for a statistical screen.
Bonferroni is very conservative, those
overly conservative.