Hi and welcome back.
In the last module, we showed you that a
macro can simply repeat a chunk of code.
This is a lot easier than manually copy
and pasting the code and
then just tweaking the variables you want
to change.
>> This is actually how a macro works
behind the scenes.
You just have to tell it what things to
tweak and how to tweak them,
and then it will automatically run and
modify the code for you.
Here's the code from last time.
We want to use this code multiple times so
we'll turn it into a macro.
Now I'll show you the syntax for turning
things into a macro.
>> You always want to start a macro with
%macro, and end a macro with %mend.
>> %macro and %mend tell sassy what to
repeat,
this chunk of code that's between them,
every time you want to run the macro.
Before we move on, I'll make a quick note
about making macros.
Notice how when I added %macro and %mend,
the color coding went away?
The color coding is really helpful for
catching mistakes and typos in your code.
If your building macro from scratch, write
the code and test it first.
And then add %macro and %mend.
>> After the %macro statement you can
specify the name of
the macro your creating.
In this case we'll call ours MakeBMI, just
like we showed you in the previous module.
Remember a macro's a function you have to
give it some information and
it will perform operations.
The information that you give must be
enclosed in parentheses.
So let's put some parentheses after
MakeBMI.
For now we're going to leave these
empties.
But soon we'll fill them in with
information.
>> At this point we have a fully
functioning macro.
What we've done so far is tell SAS that we
want to make a macro,
and that we'll repeat this chunk of code.
And I've also said that our macro is
going to be called MakeBMI.
We won't be giving it any information.
It's not a very interesting macro, since
it doesn't make any change to the code,
but sometimes that's all you need.
Every time we run this macro, it'll run
this same identical chunk of code.
Let's take a look at how we can use this
macro.
>> In order to use this macro, we first
have to run the code.
Now that we've run this macro code,
it is temporarily stored in our computers
memory.
Writing this code is not the same thing as
using our macro.
Running it just stores our macro in the
computer's memory so
that it's ready whenever we want to invoke
our macro.
>> Whenever I want to use his macro, I
need to invoke it.
This is how you can invoke a macro.
To invoke a macro,
all I have to do is write %makeBMI [SOUND]
and
then the parentheses, semi colon and then
click Run.
As you can see, we invoked the macro and
SAS ran that chunk of code you wanted.
It's important to note that we can only
invoke a macro if we've already run
the macro code earlier in that SAS
session.
This means that if I close SAS now and
restart it, I'll have to rerun the
original macro code somewhere in my
process flow before I can invoke that
macro again.