Alright, so that's how we use multivariate
analysis to control for confounders.
We put those confounders in the model, we
review, we see, we observe how those
confounders, of putting those confounders
in the model changes the slope,
the relationship between the predictor we
care about and the outcome variable.
Now I'm going to talk about another
function of multivariate analysis.
Which is simply to improve predictions.
Sometimes our goal is to be able to
predict what is it
that tells us who's going to like Obama or
who's going to do homework.
Whatever we are trying to predict.
Putting more variables in the model will
often improve predictions cause if you
know more about somebody That might
improve your
ability to predict how they're going to
fare on a, on a certain test or how
they're going to fare in terms of their
likes or whatever the problem may be.
Recall we had this example of political
leaning and Obama.
So, not surprisingly if your political
bent is more liberal.
That was pretty strongly related to how
you feel about President Obama,
who of course is a democratic president.
So, on the liberal side of things.
The R squared here was pretty big.
It was 61%.
Saying that your political bent, Explains
about 61% of how you feel about Obama.
Again not surprising but then you might
say,
okay I've collected a number of variables
besides these two and
maybe there's something else in my data
[INAUDIBLE]
that also helps to predict who's going to
like Obama above and beyond politics.
Is there something else we can add to this
model to refine to
figure out what is going to predict who
likes Obama.
Well, I kind of hunted through the data
set and some of the things I'm
finding might be due to a type 1 error
because I looked through the data set to
find what other things are associated with
ratings of Obama.
But I found some that actually make pretty
clear sense.
There's a good reason why these things
might be associated.
So they're not surprising.
I'm here showing you the univariate
results from other things that
seem to be associated with your ratings of
Obama.
These are now.
Simple linear regressions with one
predictor in the model.
So the outcome here is Obama rating.
Same outcome as before.
I did a simple linear regression model
with the ratings about president Clinton,
a former U S president, who was also a
fairly democratic.
You can see that when I ran that model The
beta coefficient if 0.4, so
every one point increase in your ratings
of
clinton was associated with a 0.4 increase
in your rating of Obama.
So there is some association here, and the
p-value Value is definitely significant.
And that kind of makes sense if you liked
Clinton you probably liked
Obama notice that this is a simple model
and people who like Clinton are likely
democrats people who like Obama are likely
democrats so this could be due to this.
Simple regression could be due to
confounding by politics.
I also wondered if healthcare,
how you feel about the new healthcare law
passed by Obama.
Some people call it ObamaCare.
If you were in favor of that healthcare
law, if you rated it highly, maybe then
you also Feel favorably towards Obama and
indeed I do find a relationship here so
every 1 point increase in your rating of
the health care law on
a scale of 1 to 100 increased your ratings
of Obama by 0.3 so
it's not quite as strong as the Clinton
effect.
None as strong as the politics effect.
But is still it's still highly
significant.
Of course we always, always want to graph
things, so don't forget to graph.
You need to graph.
So I just did simple graphs here between,
here's the healthcare law on the x axis on
the left hand side here,
and the Obama ratings, so you can see here
there's kind of a moderate association.
Association between your feelings about
healthcare, and your feelings about Obama.
Also with President Clinton, more
favorable ratings of
Clinton tend to decorrelate with more
favorable ratings of Obama.
They're not as strong as the graph I
showed you for
politics in Obama, not surprisingly.
What seems to be some stuff going on here?
I then took all three of those variables,
healthcare,
Clinton, and politics, and put them into a
single regression model.
Predicting ratings of Obama.
Here's the result of that model.
So now I've got a multivariate regression
model with three predictors in there.
Your political badge, your feelings about
healthcare, your feelings about Clinton.
Here's the results, again here's the
parameter estimates.
Here's the p values, which is the thing
we're going to focus on.
What I can see here is that the politics
is dominant.
So the best predictor of your feelings
about Obama is still politics.
The beta coefficient is 0.56.
By the way, all of these things are rated
on a scale from 0 to 100, so
the units are somewhat comparable here.
So, 1-point increase in your politics
bench
towards liberal increased your feelings
about Obama by 0.56.
Healthcare doesn't have to,
this remember the relationship with
healthcare was a beta of about 0.3 before.
It goes down to 0.14 once I account for
politics and clinton.
But it's still bordering statistical
significance and
it's still a little bit of an effect.
So, in addition to your politics, if you
liked that healthcare law, it seems to
add a little bit to your prediction about
how you'll feel, feel, feel about Obama.
The beta is 0.14, so it's not huge.
But it's still maybe a little different
than 0.
Also, interestingly there also appears to
be an independent effect for Clinton.
So even after you adjust for your
political bent and
how you feel about the healthcare law,
There's still some effect left over,
some additional predictive power that get
by Clinton.
There's sort of a Clinton halo here, this
must be why they always want a Clinton to
come and speak at the Obama rallies and
things, people who like Clinton,
do tend to be more likely to like obama
independent of their political bent, and.
Interdependent of how they feel about
healthcare.
So your peeking out a little bit of
additional predictive power here
by throwing Clinton in the model.
Now, I'll show you the R squared here, So
remember the R squared just with politics
alone in the model was .61.
It goes up to .69 when we add healthcare
and Clinton to the model.
We're not doing.
[INAUDIBLE] that much better.
We're only explaining about 8% more of the
variance in, in feelings about Obama.
And in fact, if we account for the fact
that we now have three predictors in
the model, and whenever, you add an
additional predictor in the model,
your R square always has to go up even by
just a little bit so
some type type would prefer to focus on a
measure called the adjusted R
squared which accounts for the number of
predictors in your model.
We want to also always be parsimonious put
the fewest predictors in
our model that gives us the most bang for
our buck.
So, it's probably better here to consider
the adjusted R squared.
It's still, the adjusted R squared of 67%,
is still higher than 61%.
So we're increasing how much of the
variance we can explain here by about 6%,
we're getting a little bit better on our
prediction.
By also considering the independent
effects
of people's feelings about healthcare, and
people's feelings about Clinton.
Those things do seem to.
Independantly to some extent predict
feelings about obama over and
above politics.
I have also written here just the final
model out so
that you can see the final model written
out.
And we can use this model which I've
written out here.
To actually predict for a given person.
If I knew your political rating, and I
knew how you felt about healthcare, and
I knew your rating for Clinton, I could
predict how you were going to rate Obama.
So let's take a particular example.
What I had a person who had a political
leaning of 70 this means that they
are somewhat liberal, they are on liberal
end of things but
not totally liberal remember this is on a
scale of 100.
Their ratings of obamacare were 90 so
they're really in favor of the health care
reform in the US.
Again that's out of 100 so they're very in
favor of that.
And there rating Clinton was kind of
modest a 60 so its favorable but
not super favorable we can take these
individual values for
a given person for a given individual and
plug them into the model to see what their
predicted rating for Obama would be.
We can predict what they how they might
rate Obama.
So the predicted value again I will
sometimes abbreviate that as YI
hat hat meaning that's the predicted value
is equal to our intercept here was.
5.9, we've got an additional .56 points
for every one unit of politics.
So .56 times your political bent.
And actually you just plug in the number
here.
So that the number here.
This person's political bent was 70 so we
can just Plug that right in.
This person's rating of Obama care was 90
and the slope for,
for Obama care for healthcare was .14.
So we can do .14 times 90 plus there,
this slope the beta coefficient for
Clinton was .26.
We can multiply that by their actual value
for clinton which was 60.
You can multiply all of this out you will
find out that the,
their predictive rating for Obama is 67.7.
So, not super high, definitely on the
favorable end, but
not as high as you know, some of the
values which we saw in the data set.
So that's how you do prediction for an
individual based on a regression model.
We of course also want Test the assumption
so we should do
some kind of residual analyses as I talked
about in the third module for this week.
One of the easy ones that you can do is
you can just calculate the residuals.
The computer will calculate the residuals
for you so
these are the predicted values minus the
observed values, for ratings of Obama.
The computer will do this automatically.
This draft was automatically generated for
me.
The I can then take those residuals and
toss them in a histogram and
see whether or not they follow a normal
distribution.
Distribution.
The residuals should follow a normal
distribution.
And indeed it looks really good here,
looks like it follows a nice, normal
distribution.
So, even though the ratings of Obama,
the outcome variable, didn't perfectly
follow a normal distribution.
It was just slightly off.
Because of the central limit theorem, the
means very nicely follow a normal
distribution and we adequately meet that
normality assumption.
Even with a sample size of just 50 here.
The computer also generated for me some
residual plots so
each of the predictors graphed against the
residual for every person in the data set.
Remember we're looking for
random scatter around zero and it looks
pretty good here so we're
not seeing any evidence that we violated
any assumtions of linear In a regression.
I'm going to just do a second example,
just for fun.
Since I've been looking at the healthcare
reform in the US, what some people call
Obamacare, can we also take the variables
in our data set and try to predict.
What things predict that you're going to
like the healthcare reform?
So now, making healthcare reform that,
your ratings on that.
The outcome variable.
Well, obviously, since we already saw
that,
if you liked healthcare you tended to like
Obama.
It makes sense that if you, like Obama
you're also going to like healthcare.
So we can put that in the reverse making
Obama as the predictor here and
healthcare, of course, it the outcome.
So I just did a simple linear regression
here, I did a.
Plot also.
And you can see that indeed, not
surprisingly, that Obama,
your feelings about Obama were strongly
related to your feelings about healthcare.
I then was also looking in the data set
for
other things that might predict your
feelings about healthcare.
Another one that makes a lot of sense is
politics.
So, if you're more liberal in your
politics,
indeed, that was associated with you
liking healthcare more.
And that was statistically significant at
the 0.05 level, not surprisingly.
The democrats tend to support that more.
Of course we showed, as I talked about
before, you know, it wasn't perfect here.
There's definitely some strong liberal
Democrats here that
don't like the healthcare.
And there actually are some strong
Republicans here,
that do like the healthcare.
So not perfect, but there is some
association.
[INAUDIBLE] there.
Another interesting one that I found in my
data set is how much exercise you do.
Now, this could completely be a multiple
testing issue.
A type one error.
It could be a false positive.
So I kind of look through my data set for
things that predict your ratings of health
care.
Exercise happened to pop up.
But since I've now looked at many
predictors.
Potential predictors that help here.
There's bound to be some that pop up as
statistically significant just by chance.
On the other hand, now there might be some
good reason to believe that,
yeah, people who exercise a lot,
would like Obamacare, would like the
health care reform in the U.S.
The health care in the U.S.
tends to focus on preventitive medicine
and people who exercise a lot Based it
may support that so there's its not really
unreasonable that these might go together.
A here's the plot now here's the actual
linear regression model so
exercise was in hours per week so this
regression coefficient represents that for
every 1 additional hour of exercise that
you did per week.
Your ratings of the healthcare law seem to
go up about 2.5 points,
and it is statistically significant.
So those three variables seem to predict
your ratings of healthcare in
the univariate picture, that is one at a
time.
I then want to put them together to see if
we overall can predict with
multiple variables who Who's going to like
the health care law in the U.S.
So I put them all into a single
multivariate model.
So here is the results of that model,
again you gotta focus on
the parameter estimates, that's our model
and the p-values will tell you whether or
not those betas are significantly
different from zero.
Well, looking at that model.
You'll notice that, Obama and
how you feel about Obama was actually a
stronger predictor.
It kind of trumped your political bent.
So, once I put politics and Obama both in
the model.
Obama stands out as being a pretty strong
predictor.
One unit increase in your feelings about
Obama increased your
feelings about his healthcare law by 0.5
points, a half a point, but
politics is essentially down zero, 0.039.
It is essentially zero, non-significant,
so there wasn't any
additional predictive power for politics
once I know how you feel about Obama.
Which, of course, has a lot to do with
your politics,
but seemed to trump politics here.
Once I know how you feel about Obama, then
I was able to,
I can predict how you might feel about
healthcare, but additionally,
Knowing how somebody's politics, political
leanings are above and beyond how they
feel about Obama, doesn't seem to add any
predictive power to this model.
The exercise does though, so your
exercise, how much you exercise does
appear still to be strongly related
independent of how you feel about Obama.
So somebody you maybe doesn't even like
Obama, but
is a strong exercise So likes to exercise
and likes preventive care might be
more likely to like health care regardless
of their policital feelings about Obama.
So interestingly in this one the R squared
is not super great.
So the R squared here turned out to 35%.
So we're only able to explain 35% of the
variability.
How people feel about healthcare and
actually again,
better to look at the adjusted R-squared.
The adjusted R-squared is 30% accounting
for
the fact that we've got three variables in
our model so we're able to
explain about 30% of the variance which
isn't as good as explaining.
We did much better on explaining who likes
Obama but
we've explained some of the variability.
If you, again, look carefully at politics
you see that there really isn't any
predictive power for politics.
Once I've got Obama and exercise in the
model, of course I'll again Obama and
politics are strongly related, we've seen
that throughout this week.
So those we wold call those sort of
collinear, we call them highly correlated.
And so when you put both two highly
correlated things in the model, it
tends to be that one of them is going to
dominate So Obama tends to dominate there.
Once I've accounted for Obama, there's no
additional predictive power for politics.
So I'm actually going to
drop it out of the model because it's not
adding anything.
There's no independent effect of political
bent after accounting For
your ratings of Obama and how much you
exercise.
So we're going to just drop it from the
model.
My final model, therefore, will encode
just how much you exercise and
your feelings about Obama.
Here's my final model.
My R squared is still you know, it's 29%.
It only goes down just slightly when I
drop out the politics from the model.
I'm able to explain 29% of the variants
here.
And of course you always want to test your
assumptions to your residual plots so,
I'm showing you here the residual plots
for the predictors and for
this particular model.