Proc freq is very useful because in
addition to creating contingency tables
like we've showed you before,
you can also write table analysis like a
Chi Squared Test.
let's take at some code.
Here we have the code for a contingency
table like we saw before.
But we've added something new in the
options for the table statement.
If you look closely you'll see CHISQ which
specifies some statistical options.
Let's take a look at the output.
SAS runs a whole bunch of statistics on
our table.
If you look down at this table it says
statistics for
table of isTreated by isCured.
You can see the results of these tests.
The column statistic shows you the name of
the test that was performed.
DF stands for degrees of freedom.
Value shows the value of the statistic for
the specific test that you ran.
And prob gives you the P value for that
test.
The first statistic listed here is a chi
square test.
>> As you will learn in your HRP classes.
The Chi Square Statistic is used to
determine whether distributions of
categorical variables are different from
one another.
In other words the Chi Square Statistics
compares categorical responses between
independent groups.
This test cannot be used to analyze
proportions, percents, means, and so on.
In our example, we have a class square
value of 36.9 with one degree of
freedom and a p value of less than .0001.
This significant P value indicates that we
can reject the null hypothesis that there
is no association between.
Between the exposure and outcome.
In an earlier module,
we showed you how you can setup a two by
two table to calculate a relative risk.
What if we want SAS to calculate this
relative risk for us?
First we need to sort our data in
descending order.
When SAS makes a contingency table with
Proc Freq,
it'll order the columns in the order they
show up in the data.
This will affect how it calculates the
relative risk.
So, first we use Proc Sort to sort our
data in
descending order by exposure and outcome.
This way the ones will show up first in
our contingency table.
Next we specify order equals data in our
Proc Free Statement.
Finally, we include well risk after the
forward slash and a table statement and
everything else in Proc Freq is just the
same as it was before.
So, let's run this and look at the output.
SAS will automatically calculate an odds
ratio as well as a risk ratio.
Depending on the type of study you're
using,
you might not be able to use a risk ratio.
In this case, a risk ratio should work
just fine.
The second row shows the chance of getting
cured in those who
were treated versus those who were not
treated.
And the risk ratio is 2.1.
>> Next we'll take a look at another
example from our data set on marriage.
If we include this where statement, we can
restrict the analysis to women only.
In an earlier module we showed you how to
run a by statement to run an analysis
multiple times for different subsets of
the data based on an additional variable.
If you're using Proc Freq, there's another
way how to do this.
Take a look at this code,
you'll see that we have three variables in
the table statement.
The last two variables, race and
marital stat create a contingency table,
just like we've seen so far.
The first variable functions just like a
by statement.
This will allow you to create multiple two
by two tables of race versus marital stat,
for each level of the gender variable.
Here, let's look at the code.
As you can see, we have two tables.
One of them says controlling for
gender equals zero and the other one says
controlling for gender equals one.