In this next module, we're going to do a
practical example.
I'm going to walk you through how to
interrupt linear regression results in
a medical paper.
We're going to go back to this vitamin D
and
cognitive function study that I mentioned
in the teaser and
that was also the basis of all the
hypothetical data I used this week.
Now, I'm going to show you the result from
the actual study.
So, the headlines that came out in 2009,
this was widely covered in the news media,
was things like Brighten the twilight
years,
Sunshine vitamin boosts brain function in
the elderly.
And the articles made the point that this
is some of the strongest evidence yet
of a link between vitamin D levels and
cognitive function.
So, remember what this study was.
They, this was a large cross-sectional
study of middle-aged and
older men in Europe.
They measured their vitamin D levels at
one time point.
They also had them take some various
cognitive tests to
measure their cognitive function.
There were actually a number of cognitive
tests they took.
I've been focusing so far on the DSST
scores, but
I'll show you some others in a minute.
And they found an association between
those things.
We're going to kind of walk through that
in a minute.
But this study had a number of resolve
linear regression.
There are lots of linear regressions were,
were on.
And the number of the tables involved the
output from linear regression.
So, we're going to walk through it.
We're going to evaluate how strong this
evidence is.
So, here's table two from that paper, it's
rather large and, and cumbersome.
But in a minute, I'm going to go through
it bit by bit, and kind of zoom in, here.
So this table was trying to get at what
are some of the potential confounders
between, that might confound the
relationship between vitamin D level and
cognitive function?
So, what it's showing you here is,
there, each of the columns represents a
different outcome variable.
So, the first column is showing the
results of a bunch of linear regressions,
where the outcome variable was a cognitive
test called the ROCF copy score.
There are, there were four cognitive tests
administered here,
so we get results for the ROCF copy score,
the ROCF recall score, the CTRM score, and
also the DSST score.
The one I've been talking the most about.
And we also get a series of models which
use vitamin D as the outcome variable.
Because remember to be a cofounder, you
have to
be related both to the predictor variable
and to the outcome variable.
So, we're trying to access what are,
which of these third variables is related
to both cognitive function and vitamin D.
And thus, might be confounding that
relationship.
Now, I'm going to walk you through, what,
these are all beta coefficients that
you're seeing here.
I'm going to walk you through what these
beta coefficients mean and
how to interpret them.
Let's start with age.
Age is a continuous predictor.
It's measured in units of years.
And for continuous predictors, you need to
know what the units of measurements are.
And they nicely put that for you in the
table here, so you have it.
There's a lot of data here.
So, I'm just going to go over a couple of
these.
So, first of all, if you kind of scroll
across all the different cognitive tests,
you'll notice that there's a little star
beside each of those estimates going.
As your age goes up, your cognitive
function goes down on all of
those tests and it is statistically
significant.
That's not surprising.
Interestingly, I'll focus, for the moment,
on the vitamin D.
The vitamin D was not that strongly
related to age in the study.
So, the coeffecient here, the beta
co-efficient is negative 0.0135.
So, that does mean that your, as your age
goes up,
you vita, your outcome here is vitamin D.
So, as your age goes up, your vitamin D
level goes down.
For every one year increase in age,
we are decreasing our vitamin D levels by
an average of 0.0135.
So, it's not a big effect, and it's not
statistically significant.
The, let's look at the beta coefficient
for DSST score.
So, for DSST score, the beta coefficient
is negative 0.415.
That says that for every one year increase
in age,
your DSST score is going down by 0.415 of
a point, almost a half a point.
So, that's a pretty big effect.
It is statistically significant.
These models, right here, have not been
adjusted for anything.
The rest of the models that I'm going to
show you are adjusted only for age.
And, and nothing else.
Now, I want to show you an example of a
categorical predictor.
So, they also measured depression on these
men.
They measured depression on the BDI, the
Beck Depression Inventory.
They classified men into normal, meaning
no depression,
mild to borderline depression, and
moderate to extreme depression.
They use those three groups then, in
linear regression.
And again, these models are all adjusted
for age, but nothing else.
I'm going to, let's choose the CTRM score
here, just for
fun to look at something different.
So, the way you would interpret these
coefficients,
everything is compared to the reference
group.
So, the reference group is the normal.
Then, we see that, if you are, have mild
to borderline depression,
compared with being having no depression,
would be normal.
You go down in your CTRM score by 0.849.
And that is statistically significant.
If you're in the moderate to extreme,
the higher depression group, you go down
on average by 1.4 points.
If you're in moderate to extreme
depression,
compared with if you're normal.
And that also is statistically
significant.
Interestingly, let's look at the vitamin
D,
where vitamin D is outcome in those
models.
So, if you go, if you're in the mild to
borderline depression group,
your vitamin D levels go down, 9.641 nmol
per liter.
So, that's a pretty big drop in vitamin D
with depression.
And if you're in the highest depression
group, compared with normal,
your vitamin D levels are 13.93 nmol per
liter lower.
So, those are some big drops in vitamin D.
So, interestingly, if you're depressed,
you're likely to have lower levels of
vitamin D.
You're also likely to have lower levels of
cognitive score.
So, this is definitely a potential
confounder here.
Body mass index, the measure of your, how
big you are,
your size, is also a continuous predictor.
Let's look at DSST score.
So, as your body mass index goes
up,actually,
your cognitive function goes down every
one unit increase in BMI.
BMI is measured in kilograms per meter
squared,
correlated in a 0.115 decrease in your
DSST score.
So, not a huge effect, but it is
statistically significant.
The, for vitamin D, vitamin D was also
related to BMI.
So, as your BMI goes up for every one unit
increase in, in your BMI,
your vitamin D levels goes to down 0.811
nmol per liter on average.
And that is statistically significant.
So again, BMI could also be a confounder.
As yor BMI goes up, your vitamin D levels
go down, and
so does your cognitive function.
There's another categorical variable,
physical activity.
So, this is the low, medium and high
exercise groups.
And, let's look at, let's look at CTRM
score.
So, for CTRM score, if you're in the
middle exercise group,
you are about 1.283 points higher on your
CTRM score than the low exercise group.
And that was significant.
And the highest exercise group was, also
about a point,
a little over a point higher than the low
exercise group, in CTRM.
CTRM score also statistically significant.
So, more exercise seems to be correlated
with somewhat bigger cognitive function.
For interestingly vitamin D, also
correlated with exercise.
So, if you were in the middle exercise
group, you were 5.148 higher in your
nmol per liter and your vitamin D compared
with the normal group.
The high exercise group was on average
7.072 nmol per liter higher in vitamin D.
So, if you're exercising a lot,
you tend to be outside more, you have
higher vitamin D levels again.
It could be a confounder.
Like more physical activity, better
cognitive function, and bigger vitamin D.
How about smoking?
okay.
Well, not surprisingly for smoking.
Smoking a binary variable, so it's easy to
interpret.
Vitamin D goes down with more smoking.
So, if you're a smoker, compared with a
non-smoker,
the reference group here is the
non-smoker.
The smokers are on average 10.95 nmol per
liter,
lower in their vitamin D levels than
non-smokers.
And also, notice that across all of the
cognitive scores,
your cognitive score goes down if you
smoke.
So, another potential confounder.
How about alcohol drinking?
Well, interestingly alcohol drinking is
correlated with slightly
higher cognitive function, at least on the
CTRM score, and the DSST score.
So, if you were a drinker, alcohol was put
it as a binary variable.
So, drinking at least one drink a day
versus less than that was correlated with
a slightly higher DSST score, 2.159 points
higher, and
that was statistically significant.
So, for some reason drinkers tend to have
slightly higher cognitive function.
It might not be due to the drinking,but
those tend to go together.
Similarly, drinkers tend to have a better
vitamin D level.
So, if you're a drinker versus
non-drinker,
your vitamin D level was 8.521 higher on
average.
So again, that one could be a confounder
too.
So, all there's many, many potential
confounders in this,
in this data set that need to be accounted
for.
Now, I'm going to jump to the heart of
this study.
The table that actually shows you the
relationship between vitamin D and
cognitive function which is what this
study was trying to get.
Remember, this is cross sectional study.
I'm going to kind of walk you through this
table.
Remember, the headlines said that this was
the strongest evidence yet
of a link between vitamin D level and
cognitive function.
So, let's see how strong that evidence is.
So, first of all, if you look at the first
row here,
I'm highlighting the CTRM test score and
the DSST score, because those are the two
that had a significant relationship with
vitamin D in this data set.
If you just adjust for age, which is what
that first row is.
This is the result of linear regression
with the cognitive score is the outcome
and vitamin D as the predictor, adjusted
for age only in that first row.
So, when you just adjust for age, there is
a statistically significant
relationship between vitamin D levels, and
both CTRM score and the DSST score.
It's not huge, but there's a relationship
there.
So, for example the 0.318 beta
coefficient,
the way we would interrupt that as is
every 10 nmol per liter increase in
your vitamin D levels, your DSST score
goes up by about a 3rd of a point.
Just for comparison, remember that I made
some mock data sets.
The, the low, in that, in that, those mock
data sets,
the very low relationship when I had a
beta coefficient of 0.5.
So, this 0.318 represents an, an even
smaller relationship than,
than the lowest of those data sets I, the
hypothetical data sets.
I had a hypothetical data set with 0.5,
another one with 1.0,
and another with 1.5.
So, if you go back to those, that, that
very weak relationship was 0.5.
So, 0.318 is even lower than that, but it
is significant.
The next row represents, after you adjust
for a lot of things.
So, if you look at the footnote after you
adjust for age, education, depression,
body mass index, physical activity,
physical performance, smoking, alcohol,
center and season, all these potential
confounders identified in table two.
What happens to the estimates?
Well, look at CTRM test score, once you
adjust for
these confounders, it disappears
completely,
there's no relationship now between
vitamin D and CTRM test score.
That beta coefficient is essentially zero.
For DSST score, it does hang onto a small
relationship, but
notice that the beta coefficient has been
attenuated greatly.
When we adjust for these confounders, it
decreases by more than 50%.
And now, that beta coefficient is pretty
small.
It's a 0.15 point increase in DSST score
for every 10 nmol per liter in vitamin D.
That's a 10th of the hypothetical data set
I was showing you with the slope of 1.5,
which was kind of a moderate relationship.
So, it's a 10th of that relationship.
So, its really, really small.
It does hold on to a statistical
significance.
However, it's a small relationship.
And you have to remember that it really
gets attenuated when you adjust for
confounding here.
There's probably a lot of things that we
haven't adjusted for here.
And we haven't adjusted for them
perfectly.
So, a lot of that 0.15 is almost certainly
also due to confounding.
It's just that we haven't completely
adjusted for it.
So this is not a huge, this is not what I
would call, you know,
rocket evident, you know, great evidence
that that there's a huge link here.
This is also a cross-sectional study, so
we don't know the direction of the of the
causality, if there is any causality here.
It could be that if you have better
cognitive function, you go outside more,
you take better care of yourself.
And that's why your vitamin D is just a
little bit higher.
So, the direction of the effected course
is unknown here.
Just for practice, let's also look at the
vitamin D category.
So, besides looking at vitamin D as a
continuous predictor,
they also broke into potentially
clinically useful categories,
similar to what I did in, in an earlier
module.
They make four categories Sufficient,
Suboptimum, Insuffisient and Deficient.
And the Reference group is obviously the
Sufficient.
So, for example, the Deficient group the
data coefficient is negative 1.4.
So that would say that if you're in a, if
your deficient has a very low level of
vitamin D, compared with normal, above 75,
or what see if what they're
calling sufficient, you are an average 1.4
points lower in your DSST score.
That does remain statistically significant
after adjusting for all these confounders.
But again, it's a fair, it's still a
fairly a small effect.
So, I, I wouldn't call this, you know,
huge evidence of a,
a great straw, big link between vitamin D
and, and cognitive function.