In this next module we're going to talk
about the concept of
expected value which is just a fancy word
for mean which is a concept we've
already alked about in this course but the
expected value is a really great tool for
making good decisions so we're going to
spend a lot of time on expected value.
So what is expected value?
Again, it's just the mean.
It's the mean of a probability
distribution.
And the way that we calculate this mean is
slightly different than the way that we
calculated the mean when we had data.
So when we had data, we calculated the
mean by adding up everybody's values, and
dividing by n.
That doesn't quite work when we have a
probability distribution.
Because, for a probability distribution,
certain outcomes occur more frequently
than other outcomes.
And, we have to factor that in.
So, what we're doing is we're actually
weighting the value of
each outcome by it's probability.
So, it's a weighted average.
That's a little bit different than how we
calculate a mean for
sample data where everybody occurs.
Equally frequently.
And again expected value is just this
great concept.
I love to talk about expected value
because it helps us to
make informed decisions and the idea is,
that we're talking about,
on average, what do we expect to happen in
the long run?
So this gets back to this frequentest view
of probablility.
WE're saying, in the long run How, y'know,
h- -- what value do we think will occur.
That -- so kind of put that in the back of
your mind.
We're talking about if you could repeat
things over and
over again, how often will, will different
outcomes occur.
It's a frequentist view.
So expected value, to calculate it,
all we're going to do is we're going to --
we need the probability distribution.
Once we have that We're going to take each
value of x, each possible outcome,
we're going to take it's value, and
we're going to multiply it by its
probability, how frequently it occurs.
So, outcomes that occur more frequently
will be weighted higher in this sum.
We're going to take those weighted values
and
we're going to add them all up, so, this
is just saying add up.
All the x's times their probability.
All of the possible outcomes times their
probability.
I'm going to show you some examples of how
to calculate that.
Now, I just want to show you.
I'm not going to spend to much time on the
continuous case.
Because it's really beyond the scope of
this course.
But I'm just going to show you how this
extends to the continuous case.
So, in the discrete case, we're adding
things up.
So it's a summation sign.
When you move to the continuous case.
When you have an infinite number of
possible things to add up.
Here, instead of summing, you're
integrating.
So that's the analogy.
The analogy in the continuous case is the
summation sign becomes an integral.
But notice it's otherwise exactly the
same.
For, we're going to integrate over all
possible values of x.
We're going to take x and weight it by its
probability.
But since there's an infinite number of
possible x's,
we have to do an integral here rather than
just adding up Discrete values.
Again, we're not going to talk to much
about the continuous case, so
don't get thrown by the integral.
But, just to give you a sense that it
extends to the continuous case.
It's very easy to calculate expected value
for the discrete case.
So, recall we have this probability
distribution about how many patients were
arriving in the emergency room.
Within a given hour.
And let's say you know, so again, this is
an artificial distribution, but
let's say this was the actual
distribution.
What is the expected value or mean number
of patients in any given hour?
How on average, how many patients are we
expecting to see per hour?
That's an important piece of information
for
determining Resources for the emergency
group.
So just as when we have talked about the
sample mean,
you can think about the expected value as
a balancing point.
If each of those numbers 0.3, 0.3, 0.2
those represent masses on a fulcrum,
on a lever, the mean is the point where
you have to
put the fulcrum to balance those masses,
the same concept.
Now students tend to be tempted.
If I tell students to calculate the mean
here.
Their first instinct is to just add up the
five numbers and divide by five, right?
You're tempted to just go oh,
I have to calculate a mean, so it's nine
plus ten, plus 11, plus 12, plus 13.
Add those up, divide by five.
That's how you've always calculated a mean
all your life.
But that's not going to be quite right
here because 9 occurs more frequently then
13 so we have to wait 9 by the fact that
it occurs more frequently so
to calculate the expected value what we're
going to do is take the value of each x so
of each outcome.
And multiple by it's probablity.
So 9 times 0.3 and then we're going to add
that to each other outcome.
So we're going to do 9 times 0.3 plus 10
times 0.3 plus 11 times 0.2 plus
12 times 0.1 plus 13 times 0.1 when you
add all that out, sum it all up,
it comes out to 10.4.
On average we're seeing 10.4 people in the
emergency room in any given hour.
So we gotta remember when you're
calculating these that you have to
weight them because the outcomes don't
occur equally frequently.
Now a sample mean is actually just a
special case of expected value.
So, remember in the first week of the
course, when we calculated the sample
mean, what we did was to add up the values
for everybody in our sample and
divide by n, that's something you've been
doing all your life.
Well that, if I'm just rearrange the
summation a little bit here,
I can show you that that's the same as
taking every persons value and
multiplying it by 1 over n, and then
adding those up.
So, every person is being weighted by 1
over n.
That's their probability.
That's their frequency in the sample.
It just happens that everybody counts
once.
So, everybody has the same weight.
So, we don't actually have to multiply
everybody by the weight.
We can just divide by n at the end.
But really, that's everybody's weight.
Everybody has a probability in this
sample,
frequency in the sample of 1 over n.
So this is really,
the sample mean is really just a special
case of expected value.
I was, just make sure we're keeping our,
our symbol straight here.
So when I talk about sample means I use
this symbol X bar.
That means we calculated the mean from
sample data.
When I'm talking about calculating means
from probability distributions,
which are theoretical things rather than
from data.
I'm either going to use the symbol mu,
which is a Greek letter or
I will interchangeably use E of x, which
just stands for expected value of x.
Remember, the mean and the expected value
of x are the same thing.
It turns out to be easier on a typewriter
sometimes to write E of x rather than to
find the Greek symbol mu.
So, you'll see a lot of times I'll just
use E x.
Instead 'cause it's easier on my
typewriter, but those mean the same thing.