Sometimes, you may want to look at the
distribution of a subset of the data.
We can do this with a where statement,
just like we used to do with data steps.
Take a look at this code.
Similar to the example we just went over,
we're interested it in the age variable.
We will use a where statement to restrict
our analysis.
This will give us the distribution of age
among subjects with a value of zero for
the variable CHF.
According to our data dictionary, a value
of zero for
CHF indicates that the subject did not
have heart failure complications.
Here, let's run the code.
As you can see,
you now get the distribution of age among
subjects who did not have heart failure.
Let's use another piece of code to
demonstrate that you can do all sorts of
logical conditions in a where statement.
This code gives us the distribution of age
among subjects with no heart failure
complications, and were either males or in
the hospital for less than ten days.
>> If you just want to write a statistical
analysis for
multiple levels of a categorical variable,
you can use a class statement.
Here's an example.
Class is female.
Tell Sass that the column called is female
is a categorical variable.
Sass will run a separate univariate
analysis for
each unique level of the is female
variable.
This variable has two unique levels.
It can have a zero for male subjects or a
one for female subjects.
Let's run the code.
We can see that Sass automatically
provides one analysis that is
restricted to subjects with Is female
equals zero, and
then a second analysis that is restricted
as subjects with is female equals one.
Now, we can easily compare the
distribution of age for men and women.