[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next case study, we had a
situation,
where an elderly patient presented to the
emergency department with
a history of alcoholism, acute
pancreatitis, atrial fibrillation,
degenerate joint disease of the spine and
both lower extremities.
History of deep venous thrombosis.
Social history included intermittent
homelessness, and
has had previous, multiple
hospitalization.
He was a individual who in some, in some
respect,
probably someone who hasn't done a really
good job of taking care of himself.
The review of the patient's medication
prior to admission
was that the patient was taking warfarin,
mini-dose aspirin,
ibuprofen naproxen sodium, and on top of
that, loves garlic.
You know, actually he's an individual that
lives in the Gilroy, California area and
has access, I'm not sure if he actually
bought the garlic but, or dug up
the garlic, whatever, but apparently,
story out of there, loves garlic.
And it was pretty obvious when folks,
was in the process of doing the physical
evaluation with this patient.
So, based on that kind of a history, and
those medications, and
we gave you the key pieces of information,
what do you think this patient presented
to the emergency department with?
And, if you said he was having a GI bleed,
you are right on the money.
He actually per, presented with a fairly
significant GI bleed.
Now, the patient was actually part of the
same healthcare delivery system.
And, actually was seen by several
different specialties,
had been followed in different clinics,
within the systems.
And, all the doctors that were involved
taking care of patients were actually all,
providers in the same health system.
This same health system uses a fairly
comprehensive electronic
medical records system that crosses the
entire continuum that addressed or
it collected information from both, you
know,
within the emergency department, and also
the inpatient and outpatient setting.
So, one of the things about this
particular case is background for you all.
It's like, it's not uncommon for patients
to be mobile, you know, and
they're, you know, living within a
particular area,
they move from location to another
location.
They're getting care within a similar
system, and within that system,
is able to transmit information from one
location to another location, you know,
providing folks have access.
And, the fact of the matter is that the
patient actually was
fairly well managed, for each individual,
one of those medical conditions.
Now, what's interesting is that you know,
when it was reviewed,
that you know, the warfarin was prescribed
by one specialty.
The mini-dose aspirin was prescribed by
the primary care physician.
The nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory was
prescribed by two different specialties,
like orthopedics and podiatry.
And then, he went, the patient, on his
own, went out and
just had garlic in everything.
Now, the system did collect all this
information, but
I think what ended up happening in our
review was that we found that
nobody ever looked at the summary of the
patient's medication regiment.
I know there's been an attitude or a, a
feeling that, hey, you know,
it's like I don't, I'm not involved with
managing that patient's medication so
I'm not really going to focus on, on what
those other meds are.
I'm sure they're appropriate.
If they're prescribed by a physician, that
physician is matching medication.
But the fact of the matter is, is that in
this situation, no one looked at the list
of medication the patient was, was on, in
the process of either adjusting, changing,
or adding medication in this patient's
medication regimen.
So, one of these things, originally, it
wasn't an urgent, emergent situation, but
clearly, you know, one of the factors was,
was that no one ever looked at the
patient's medication list.
Why they didn't do it?
You know, you can, you can look at,
you know, the factors that we've talked
about in the past,
whether it's fatigue, distraction,
production pressure, or culture.
I mean, the expectation is, is that, well,
someone else is
managing that patient's condition and
taking care of the medication.
I'm only worried about taking care of the
patient for
the, a specialist in the area that I'm an
expert in, and
I'm just going to focus on what needs to
be done from my perspective.
So, some of the lessons learned or was
gained from this particular experience was
that the Joint Commission has another
National Patients Safety Goal that has
very specific requirements regarding the
collection and
use of medication information.
There is a requirement of the need to
gather that information upon
entry into a healthcare setting.
This is true whether they're coming to the
emergency department,
coming into the outpatient setting,
getting admitted into the hospital.
You need to gather that information.
And then, this information needs to be
used whenever there's an addition,
a deletion, or modification in that
patient's medication regiment.
That's were the disconnect occurred in
this particular setting because, you know,
when I actually reviewed the patients
prior to admission medication lists,
it was pretty clear what they were taking.
And it was pretty clear that they were
taking medication that was designed to be
treating specific conditions or diagnosis.
But, in aggregate, you know, for whatever
reason,
no one ever put the big picture together
and said, hey, you know, we may be
affecting, significantly affecting this
patient coag status, coagulation status.
And as a result, the patient did suffer
from a fairly significant GI bleed.
Now, knock on wood.
The good thing out of this is that, you
know, the, between
the emergency department, the intensive
care, and the surgical and medical
services this organization, you know, they
were able to clear the patient up.
And, the patient was actually able to be
discharged back out to the community.
But one of the big lessons learned is that
we have all the information in
the electronic medical records.
Really, really important to be able to
review it and use that
information whenever we're involved with
any type of medication management process.
So, the use of that electronic medical
record is a tool that assists in
gathering, but then the other side of it
is being able to use that information and
do the right thing for the patient.
The National Patient Safety Goal also
requires that the patient, and or
the care providers, and or
their family are educated about the
medications that they are taking.
One of the lessons learned from this
particular case is
that the patient knew about the blood
thinner, the warfarin, and
what the purpose of that was to address
the potential for problems from a,
from his AFib, and also the past history
of deep venous thrombosis.
But, for whatever reason, the
communication about the mini-dose aspirin
and the non-steroidal anti-inflammatory
never really was provided.
The patient wasn't aware that when you add
all these medications together,
that it can affect his ability to clot.
And then we also deal with the other sided
of this, where if the patient,
if they had been informed of this, and we
do know a patient who says, well, hey,
you know, if the the one pill a day works
really, really good,
I wonder if two pills a day is going to
make a bigger difference.
And we do know of those situations where
patients, you know,
even though they're given very clear-cut
instructions.
It's in the pamphlet or literature that
they're given.
It's on the instruction on the medication
bottle.
The outpatient pharmacist gives him that
additional instruction.
You know, the different specialists or the
primary care doctors that
the patient's seeing, reinforce or
reiterate the medication regimen.
It is not uncommon, we have patients that
ends up doubling or tripling up on their
medication, thinking that, you know, if
one is good, two is better, three is best.
So, you know, those kind of things, you,
you, you can't prevent from happening, but
you could prevent the fact that they would
even consider that by
providing the education.
And that's where the National Patient
Safety Goal kicks in,
regarding making sure the patient, their
caregiver, their family,
whoever's involved with their care, are
really educated about the medication that
they are taking so that something like
this would not occur.
[BLANK_AUDIO]