In this next scenario, there are a number
of unlabeled syringes at
the procedure table filled with different
medication.
The doctor involved planned on giving the
patient the pre-operative
antibiotic to reduce the chances of
surgical site infection post-operative.
And this requirement is a hospital quality
initiative and
actually reported into CMS and Joint
Commission as a quality metric.
The patient, which originally was having a
great conversation with the doctor,
was no longer responsive to verbal
commands.
That's the physician noticed that the
patient did not appear to be spontaneously
breathing or breathing on their own, and
certainly the patient was not moving.
Patient's eyes were open, but there was no
blink reflex, and
the monitor started to go off, indicating
oxygenation was starting to go down.
Originally, the doctor thought this was an
anaphylactic reaction and
administered medication to respond to this
suspected allergic reaction.
He even had to manually ventilate the
patient for a period of time.
And over the 20 minutes the patient
gradually started to breathe on their own.
But you're probably thinking, well, what
do you think happened if you're the chief
quality officer or the chief medical
officer in terms of doing the review.
As I mentioned earlier, there were
multiple factors that were going on in
this particular event including unlabeled
syringes.
Because, is there a possibility that,
because there are multiple medications
with multiple syringes,
that the wrong medication was accidentally
given to the patient.
Is it possible there was fatigue?
Distraction, once again production
pressure environmental issue,
lighting, noise.
It's not uncommon some surgeons have a
preference for
loud music that make the surgeon more
comfortable or
more in sync with what's going on, but it
could be distracting to other folks
involved in the procedures where there are
potential variations and work processes.
Issues in staff communication, staff
training, teamwork and culture.
What was learned from this particular
experience, and it turned out the patient
did receive a paralytic agent, because the
patient's muscle was paralyzed.
We all know what was completely
operational,
functional, was the patient's brain.
And, specifically cranial nerve number
eight was totally operational.
And, the patient heard everything that
occurred during the moments,
the time period that the patient was
paralyzed.
And in the debriefing, with the patient,
the patient was basically able to describe
what would be considered a paralytic agent
and not an anaphylactic reaction.
What had happened in this particular case
the patient postponed the surgery; they
actually came back the following day to
have the procedure done, and there was no
untoward [UNKNOWN] associated with the
event, other than a lot of time and
energy taken up by risk management, the
quality department, the physician that was
involved, and administration to draw down
the to figure out why it happened.
And in a nutshell, turned out that because
the syringes were not labeled,
it was possible that the doctor picked up
the wrong medication and
administered it and thereby, creating an
adverse event.
Some of the additional lesson learned was
actually reviewing
Joint Commission's National Patient Safety
Goal, which requires that any
time that medication is put into a
secondary container, such as a syringe or
a basin, it needs to be labeled with its
contents if the medication is
not immediately administered into the
patient.
You know, some of you are probably
thinking, well, you know,
if I have to label everything that I'm
giving immediately to a patient,
that's going to seriously affect workflow.
No.
The expectation is,
is that if you're drawing up medication or
using medication out of a container and
directly putting it into a patient,
administering a patient, without a break
in the process.
You know, like putting the syringe down or
going to the computer, doing
documentation.
Or doing something else,
prior to administering the medication, you
do not have to be labeling the syringe or
the container per Joint Commissioner
requirement.
The other issue is that distraction has
been know to be a significant factor in
medication errors.
Now, for the most part in most hospital
organizations,
the individuals are providing the most
medications are going to be the nurses
because they're going to be involved with
doing a fair amount of administration.
But we do know for a fact that many times
the physician, house staff,
you know, are involved with administering
medication to patients,
especially injectable medication.
As well as potentially on occasion PO
medication,
you really do need to make sure you have a
double check system in place to
make sure the right patient's getting the
right medication.
As I mentioned earlier some of the
prevention strategies include
immediately administered medication does
not require to be labeled, but
if you do label it, because there's going
to be
a break in the process between the moment
the medication is drawn up prepared and
giving the patient, it really does need to
be labeled with some key information.
The key information you may want to double
check with your hospital policy and
procedure, but at a minimum, it should
include the name of the medication,
the concentration if there's a
concentration, preparation date, and
then the, any expiration date that needs
to be
put on if it's not going to be
administered immediately.
Labeling should be legible and visible.
So it's not very helpful if you put a
label on, and you can't actually read it.
If there is any doubt about the medication
or
the container, consider doing the
preparation process over.
Emergencies and urgency situation usually
creates the variation in process,
Joint Commission does recognize that, you
know, patient care comes first; that
sometimes in those situations you do need
to expedite things.
But for the most part, you know, if it's
not an urgent administration situation and
you're not sure about the medication or
the container in terms of what is in it,
you may want to consider disposing of it
and starting the process over.
Doing a double check of the label
container is a safety strategy that can
prevent bad outcome.
And of course, that's assuming that you
pulled the original medication,
was exactly what you needed to administer.
We've had situations in many organizations
where because the stocking of
the automatic automated dispensing
machines that holds medication that,
if they're not stocked right, it's
possible that someone
inadvertently stocked the medication wrong
in that particular drawer or
pocket, and even though you pulled it out
of a pocket that said one thing.
Assuming it was that particular
medication,
it turned out it might be another thing.
So, double checking the label the
medication to
make sure you're dealing with what it is
that you want to use in your patient.
[BLANK_AUDIO]