Welcome to week nine of statistics in
medicine.
This is the final week of the course.
So, congratulations on making it this far.
This week we're going to continue our
discussion of regression.
We're going to move beyond linear
regression and
talk about some more sophisticated
regression models.
Specifically, I'm going to be talking
about logistic regression and
cox regression.
These are some more advanced statistical
models that are just a little bit
more complicated than linear regression.
I'm also going to keep talking about some
basic concepts of
regression modelling that apply to all
regression models.
We've covered a lot of this big
statistical chart now.
Last week we talked about linear
correlation and linear regression.
This week we're going to talk about
logistic regression.
This is the regression technique that's
used when you
have a binary outcome variable.
The basic logistic regression model that
we're going to talk about this week is for
independent, when you have independent
observations.
I'm going to briefly mention this week
that there is an alternative test when you
have correlated observation.
And you want to do regression modeling
with a binary outcome variable.
That's something called conditional
logistic regression.
I'm just going to point it out, I won't go
into any details about the model.
I also want to point out now that there's
something called GEE models,
which can also be used when you have
correlated observations and
a binary outcome variable.
I'll also point out to you.
We talked last week about linear
regression with independent observations.
What about the situation when you have a
continuous outcome variable.
You want to do regression analysis but
your observations are correlated in some
way.
Then you're going to need some more
sophisticated models,
called either mixed models or GEE models.
Both of those will work in that situation.
Again, I'm not going to go into any
details, of those models.
They're beyond the scope of this course.
But I'll just point them out to you, so
that you know that there is a test
available in those situations.
And you can take a more advanced
statistical course to learn about
the details of those.
This week I'm also going to talk in great
detail about Cox regression.
That's the regression analysis technique
that you're going to use when you
have time-to-event outcomes.
So when you're doing survival analysis.
The teaser for this week comes from a 2009
study that made headlines.
The study found that eating a lot of red
meat was linked to
an increased risk of death.
An increased mortality risk.
Again, the study made a lot of headlines.
I'm quoting here from nbcnews.com, they
write.
The largest study of it's kind,
finds that older Americans who eat large
amounts of red meat and
processed meats face a greater risk of
death from heart disease and cancer.
So they found that there was the people
who were eating a lot of
red meat were at an increased risk of
dying from heart disease and cancer.
But, this was an observational study, and
it turns out that
people who eat a lot of red meat tend to
do a lot of other unhealthy things.
So, red meat eating clusters pretty
heavily with un,
other unhealthy behaviors.
And this is an example that I actually
showed you
before in week two of the course when I
was talking about confounding.
So this is a very good example of
confounding.
I showed you this table on the second week
of this course.
This is the descriptive table, the table
one,
just on the men, from this particular
study.
The researchers divided the men up into
five quintiles of red meat intake.
So Q1 are the men who are eating the
lowest amount of red meat.
Q5 is the men who, were eating the highest
amount of red meat.
And this table just shows you,
descriptively,
what are the characteristics of the men in
those five quintiles.
If study this table carefully and we look
at it in some detail again in week two of
this course, what you'll see is that all
the sort of bad risk factors for
health go up as you go up the red meat
intake quintiles.
For example, if you look at BMI.
In Q1, the BMI, the average BMI is 25.9.
It Q2 it's 26.7, in Q3, it's 27.1, in Q4,
it's 27.6, in Q5, it's 28.3.
So as you go up across those quintiles,
BMI goes up.
Smoking also goes up as you go across the
quintiles.
Education and physical activity go down.
Fruit and vegetable intake go down.
Calories go up.
Again, all the kinds of things that are
not great for
our health tend to be more common in
people who eat a lot of red meat.
People who eat a lot of red meat just have
a lot of risky health behaviors.
The problem is, this is an observational
study.
These risk factors cluster.
So how do we isolate the effect of red
meat
eating from all of these other variables
that cluster with red meat eating?
That's what we're going to try to do with
regression analysis.
That's what regression analysis is set up
to try to do, is trying to isolate
the effect of one variable independent of
all these other things that go.
All these other confounders that go with
it.
And indeed, that's what the authors did in
this study.
As I said they did find that red meat
eating was
linked to an increase risk of death from
heart disease and cancer.
But, it might surprise you to learn that
they also found that
red meat eating was linked to an increased
risk of death from injuries and accidents.
That's things like car accidents and
firearm deaths.
You might wonder, how is it that eating
red meat would increase your
risk of dying in a car accident?
It doesn't seem like there'd be a causal
link there, yet that's, they can show,
in this study that, the, that red meat
eating is linked to this type of death,
as well as heart disease and cancer.
This is going to get into the issue of how
good can we really adjust from,
for confounding.
How good can we really isolate one.
Risk factor from a cluster of risk
factors.
We'll get to this particular example
towards the end of this week and
I'll give you sort of of a punch line on
that one.