[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module, I'm going to
show you how linear regression
accommodates categorical predictors.
And I'll also show you the link between
ttests, and ANOVA, and linear regression.
So, how does linear regression handle
categorical predictors?
In the case of a binary predictor is
actually really easy.
In the very first beginning of this
course, I talked a lot
about binary variables and thinking about
them as 0,1, as numerical variables.
Well, that becomes useful now because the
way that we
handle binary variables is just to put
them in a linear regression model and
treat them as numbers, as a 0 and a 1.
And that makes it easy to model, and I'll
show you the picture in a minute.
Categorical variables are just slightly
more tricky.
These are variables that have more than
two categories.
We are essentially going to turn them into
a series of binary, of 0,1 variables.
And that's the way we're going to
accommodate them in the regression model.
We call this dummy coding.
And I'm going to get to this dummy coding
idea in a few minutes.
But let's start with the easier case, with
the binary case.
Imagine for the,
for a moment that I wanted to use vitamin
D as a binary predictor.
We have been talking about this example
all week where I've been
treating vitamin D as a continuous
predictor.
But there might be some reason that I end
up wanting to treat vitamin D
as a binary predictor.
Maybe I didn't measure, maybe.
And for some reason, in my data, said I
don't have it as a continuous predictor.
Or maybe, for some reason, I'm clinically
interested in
comparing the insufficient group to the
sufficient group.
So for whatever reason, I'm using vitamin
D as a binary predictor.
If I look in my data set, and let's say
I'm, this is sort of arbitrary, let's
say less than 15 nmol/L is a clinical
reason for calling that insufficient.
More than that we'll call that sufficient.
We're going to code this insufficient
variable as a 1,0.
So, if you're a 1, that means you're in an
insufficient group.
If you're a 0, that means you're in a
sufficient group.
I actually looked my data set and the mean
DSST score,
the mean cognitive score in the
insufficient indeed was lower.
That in the sufficient group it was 32.5,
and in the sufficient group it was 40.
Now you might just think about the
lectures that we had last week.
And you might say oh well, here I've got a
situation where I
have a continuous normally distributed
outcome variable.
I've got two groups I want to compare.
I want to compare the means of that
continuous variable.
Between two groups, why wouldn't I just
use a t-test here?
And indeed, you could absolutely use a
ttest here.
I'm going to show you how to also use
linear regression, and
to analyze these same data.
And then, I'll show you how the linear
regression and
the ttests actually give you identical
answers.
Let me graph this for you.
So again, we're treating our, our binary
variable as a 0,1 variable.
One means you're in the insufficient
group,
zero means you're sufficient, you're in
the normal level group.
The linear regression line here is the
easiest possible line you can draw.
So, what I'm showing you here, these
little individual points represent all of
DSST levels, for all of the people in the
normal group.
Their mean level is right here at 40.
That was the mean in in the normal group,
the vitamin D
insufficient group over here.
This is all their DSST levels.
Their mean, as I mentioned, with 32 32.5.
So, what's this line?
All I did to draw this line was to connect
the two means.
It's really, it's like the simplest line,
line you can possibly draw.
Any two points, you can connect them, and
draw a line.
And it's, we don't have to test the
linearity assumption here.
Because when you have two points, it's
automatically going to make a line.
So, that's nice.
The intercept of this line as you can see
here is 40.
What's the slope of this line going to be?
Well, the x variable only goes from 0 to
1.
So, there's only going to be a one unit
change in x.
What happens to y when x goes from 0 to 1?
Well, y goes from 40 down to 32.5.
So, the slope of this line is It's
going to be 40 - 32.5 or 7.5.
Notice that that's just the difference in
means, between the two groups.
I then took these data and
actually ran them officially in a linear
regression program.
And indeed, not surprisingly, what I get
out in the model is,
here is the parameter estimates.
So the, the intercept is 40, and the
difference in means, the,
the beta here is negative.
Get a 7.5 because we're decreasing as
we're
going from sufficient to insufficient.
It's highly statistically significant as
you can see.
This has just given me back the equation
of that line.
We could also kind of look at the graph
again to,
to see the equation of that line.
And the intercept represents the mean
value in the sufficient group.
The slope here just represents the
difference in means between
the two groups and it is statistically
significant.
Now, I want to show you what would have
happened had we run these data in
a ttest rather than bothering to get fancy
and run a linear regression.
Well, we would have got the same answer
again, and
we have two groups, we want to compare
means.
We can evaluate these data with a ttest.
It turns out that the slope we get from
linear regression is
exactly equal to the difference in means.
Which is the effect of size of interest
for
a ttest and the p-values we get out are
also exactly identical.
So, here's the ttest that we would run.
We would in the numerator going the
difference in mean.
Again which is 40 minus 32.5 or 7.5.
We can calcuate the standard error in the
demoninator that turns out to be the same
standard error that you can in the linear
regression model in the earlier slide.
The T-value comes out to be 3.46, the
p-value comes out to be 0.008.
And actually, if you look at the previous
slide,
you can see that that is the T-value and
the p-value from the linear regression.
So, there's nothing new here
mathematically.
A ttest and linear regression are exactly
the same.
You could say we don't even really need to
have a ttest in the world because you
could always run that problem, that
particular problem, in linear regression.
It's just, of course, that linear
regression is more,
you know, seems more complicated.
A ttest seems very simple, so a lot of
times if it, we have the simplest problem,
we end up just defaulting to ttest rather
than calling it a linear regression.
But in fact, a ttest is a special case of
linear regression.
Now, I'm going to move to the more tricky
concept,
which is what to do when you have more
than two categories.
You have a categorical predictor
with more than two categories.
What we're going to have to do here is to
do some dummy coding.
We're going to translate our categories
into a series of binary variables.
So, that we can deal again with binary
variables.
So what what if our vitamin D variable had
been a categorical predictor rather than
a continuous predictor?
What if there were three levels we cared
about the deficient?
That's, like, the really low people.
Insufficient, kind of mildly low and, and
sufficient.
Sometimes people will divide that up this
way.
I want to know about the difference in
DSST scores between those three groups.
I could analyze those data then within
ANOVA,
a simple ANOVA as we talked about last
week.
And I also could analyze it with linear
regression.
So, let me just tell you what the means,
the mean DSST score in all of these
groups were, so the sufficient group, the
normal group, is still the same here.
The average was still 40.
The insufficient group now excludes the
ones who were lower than 25, so
the average in that group is now 33.13.
And in the deficient group, it turns out
that the mean DSST score is 30.13.
So, it does seem to down across those
groups.
How do we dummy code this?
How do we dummy code these three
categories?
So, here's dummy coding.
If I want to take a three-level
categorical variable.
I can represent it as a series of binary
variables.
I actually only need two binary variables
if it's a three-level variable.
If it was a four-level categorical
variable,
I would need three binary variables and so
on.
There's going to be one group, that's the
reference group, and that's going to
be the variable that has a zero on all
the, on all the binary variables.
Let me illustrate that here.
So, I'm going to make two new variables.
I'm going to create a new variable that is
deficient yes or no.
It's binary here, either in the deficient
category or you're not.
And another one, insufficient.
That's a variable, another binary.
That says you're either in the
insufficient group or you're not.
So, if you're somebody in the deficient
group,
you're going to get a 1 on the deficient
variable, but
a 0 on the insufficient variable.
If you're in the insufficient group,
you're going to get a 0 on the deficient
group because you're not,
you're not deficient.
But, you're going to get a one on the
insufficient.
If you're in the sufficient group,
however, you're going to get a zero on
both of those.
So, notice that two binary variables is
sufficient to uniquely identify all
three of those categories.
Now, we have a reference group and we have
a series of
binary variables that tell us about the
difference between the deficient group.
And the sufficient group, and
the difference between the insufficient
group and the sufficient group.
How do we represent this in pictures?
So, it looks a lot like the pictures we
did for the simple binary predictor,
the insufficient group.
The, again, the mean level of DSST for
the insufficient group was about 33, the
mean for the normal group is 40.
It forms a simple line, the intercept is
40, the slope is about negative 7.
For the deficient group,
same intercept because we're still
comparing against the normal group.
The slope here, the, the mean for
the deficient group is about 30, so the
slope here is almost 10.
Now technically, this is a multivariate
regression.
because we now have two predictors in the
model.
I could represent these pictures on a
plain.
It's just harder to draw that plane.
So, I represented it as, as two separate
graphs here.
I took the, the data, and I put them into
the computer, and
asked it to run a linear regression with
this dummy, these dummy coded variables.
And here are the results that I get.
So here's my model, here's my p-values.
Again, the intercept represents the mean
value in the reference group.
That's 40, that's the normal group.
The beta coefficient, the slope for
the insufficient group represents the
difference.
In the DSST levels between the normal
group and the insufficient group,
the difference from the reference.
So, the insufficient group was about
almost 7 units lower in
cognitive score than the normal group.
The deficient group was almost 10 units
lower in the cognitive score than
the normal, so that should show for them.
Both are highly statistically significant.
That's the linear regression equation
written out.
And we can use that to then predict,
what's the mean value for those in the
insufficient group.
Those in the deficient group, and those in
the, the normal group.
And you're going to see that for
the simple model, it's nothing too
profound, the 40 is the mean.
In that reference group, negative 6.87
represents the difference in
means between the insufficient and
sufficient groups.
And again, negative 9.87 represents the
difference in
means between the deficient and sufficient
groups.
And you can just show this by applying the
equation.
So, if I have got a person whose is in the
deficient group, how do I apply this,
the equation to them.
Well, they get they get the intercept.
They get a zero because they're not in the
insufficient group, and they get a one for
being deficient.
So, when you do 40 minus 9.87, that's,
that just gives you
back what we already knew was the mean in
the in the deficient group.
A person in the insufficient group,
when you apply the equation, they get a
one for insufficient.
A zero for deficient when you add that up
it comes out to be 33.13.
Again, what we already knew was the mean
in the insufficient group.
And the person who's in a su, sufficient
group gets a zero for
both the insufficient and deficient
variables.
So, they're just left with 40, which again
we knew was the mean in the normal group.
So, it's a little like this is an, you
know,
it's just spitting back out the means, it
doesn't seem all that profound.
It doesn't seem, doesn't seem all that
useful but the reason it's going to
be useful is because we might want to
adjust for other variables.
ANOVA is just linear regression, so
the p-value that you would get if you ran
ANOVA here is exactly the same as
the p-value you are going to get for the
overall model set for linear regression.
So again, mathematically, these things are
identical.
So, when you you could argue that you
never needed an ANOVA,
you could always just run a linear
regression.
Again, why is this useful?
We're just getting back up the means, it
doesn't seem all that interesting.
But because it's useful, because we can
then throw other things into the mold.
Multi-variant regression model to adjust
for that, those covariance and
co-founders, or to get better predictors.
For example, let's say I was to throw age
into the model to try to
get age adjusted means for each of those
vitamin D groups.
Age being the potential confounder here.
So to adjust age, I'm just going to throw
age into the model.
Nothing tricky.
And here is the model that comes out when
I add age to the model.
So it's showing these, that again, the
normal group is the reference group so
it doesn't get a beta co-effecient.
Now, I get an effect for age.
And now I get what are age adjusted beta
coefficients,
these have now been adjusted for age.
Interestingly, these are made of data.
And so, in the process of making up the
data,
I've built in something a little funny.
Which is that the deficient group after
you adjust for age,
actually looks like it has more, a higher
cognitive score than the normal group.
So, once maybe that group was totally full
of much older people, which will count for
the fact that their much older than their,
their deficient.
Their deficiency in vitamin D is actually
associated with a greater a DSST score.
That's a quirk, I think, of the fact that
I made up the data, certainly.
So, that's the final model.
But what's great about this is now I can
report age adjusted means for
those groups.
And this is just showing the picture here.
Again, this is showing the slopes in each
of the three groups.
For the relationship between a age and
DSST score.
So that you can see that in all three
groups,
certainly age is we've built this into the
model.
This is just kind of showing you the
So, age, as age goes up, you go down in
your cognitive function, for sure.
Interestingly, as I mentioned though, once
you account for age the deficient group.
Thus, this blue line, actually send seems
to across all
different ages have a little bit higher of
a, of a cognitive score.
Might be quirk of my made up data.
And I can calculate these age adjusted
means the, the easiest way to
calculate the age adjusted mean is just to
imagine that everybody has the same age.
You have to pick an age to plug into the
model.
So, say let's plug in the mean age for the
whole data set which is here 55 years old.
So, I can get the expected average DSST
value.
For a vitamin deficient,
D deficient person who's 55 years old by
plugging all that into the model.
So, we can just plug in this model to find
the expected DSST score for
somebody who's vitamin D deficient and is
55 years old.
So, we're fixing age so that age is the
same across these three groups,
that person has an expected score of 36.
Somebody whose insufficient whose at 55
years old,
based on this model is predicted to have a
DSST score of 29.1.
And for the normal group, a 55 year old is
actually predicted to be lower and
have a DSST score of 27.7.
Again, probably a quirk of my made up
data.
But, it's nice to have these age adjusted
means cause you can then record
the unadjusted means and the age adjusted
means.
So, you can see it totally flipped the
relationship here once we
had accounted for age.
And that might be something funny in my
made up data.