Again, why is this useful?
We're just getting back out the means.
It doesn't seem all that interesting, but
because it's useful because we can then
throw other things into the multi-variable
regression model to adjust for
that, those covariance and confounders or
to get better predictions.
For example, let's say I was to throw age
into the model to try to
get age-adjusted means for each of those
vitamin D groups.
Age being a potential confounder here.
So to adjust for age, I'm just going to
throw age into the model.
Nothing tricky.
And here's the model that comes out when I
add age to the model.
So it's showing me that again, the normal
group is the reference group, so
it doesn't get a beta coefficient.
Now I get an effect for age, and now I get
what are age-adjusted beta coefficients.
These have now been adjusted for age.
Interestingly, these are made up data, and
so
in the process of making up the data, I
built in something a little funny,
which is that the deficient group after
you adjust for age,
actually looks like it has more, a higher
cognitive score than the normal group.
So once, maybe that group was totally full
of much older people.
And once you account for
the fact that they're much older, then
their, their deficient their deficiency of
vitamin D is actually associated with a
greater DSST score.
That's a quirk, I think, of the fact that
I made up the data a certain way.
So that's the final model.
But what's great about this, is now I can
report age-adjusted means for
those groups.
And this is just showing the picture here.
Again, this is showing the slopes in each
of the three groups, for the relationship
between age and DSST scores here, so that
you can see that in all three groups.
Certainly age is when we built this in,
in the model, this is just kind of showing
you the model, so
age, as age goes up, you go down in your
cognitive function, for sure.
Interestingly, as I mentioned, though,
once you account for
age, the deficient group, that's this blue
line, actually seems to, across all
different ages, have a little bit higher
of a, of a, of a cognitive score.
Might be a quirk of my made up data.
And I can calculate these age-adjusted
means.
The easiest way to calculate the
age-adjusted means is just to imagine that
everybody has the same age.
You have to pick an age to plug into the
model, so let's say,
let's plug in the mean age for the whole
data set, which was here, 55 years old.
So I can get the expected average DSST
value for a vitamin deficient,
D deficient person who's 55 years old by
plugging all that into the model.
So we can just plug in this model to find
out the expected DSST score for
somebody who's vitamin D deficient and is
55 years old.
So we're fixing age so that age is the
same across these three groups.
That person has an expected score of 36.
Somebody who is insufficient who's at 55
years old based on this model is
predicted to have a DSST score of 29.1.
And for the normal group, a 55 year old is
actually predicted to be lower and
a have a DSST score 27.7.
Again, probably a quirk of my made-up
data.
But it's nice to have these age-adjusted
means,
because you can then report the unadjusted
means and the age-adjusted means, so
you can see it totally flipped the
relationship here,
once we accounted for age.
And that might be something funny in my
made-up data.