In proc freq, you can specify multiple
tables at once.
In this first chunk of code,
you can get three separate one way
frequency distribution tables.
You'll have one for the gender variable,
one for
the marital status variable, and a third
one for the race variable.
Here we have three tables from that one
chunk of code.
The second chunk of code will give us two
separate two by two contingency tables.
One for gender by marital status, and a
second one for gender by race.
We have two tables now.
Here's an easier way to code multiple
tables at once.
This will automatically make two tables,
just like we specified before,
but you don't have to type out gender
asterisk each time.
This trick will come in handy when you
need to make a frequency table
like a table one where you might have to
make a separate table for
over a dozen covariants.
As you can see, it has the same output as
before.
So far the data that you have been using
has had a separate row for each subject.
Sometimes you might receive data in a
different format.
Take a look at this data set.
We have a binary variable for getting
treatment and another one for being cured.
We have a third variable called count.
>> Instead of having a different row for
each individual subject, we now have a
different row for each type of subject.
Let's go to our data lines and look at it.
As you can see, we have a total count of
56,
which represents all of those who were not
treated and not cured.
The next line we have 34 which represents
the total count for
those who were not treated and cured.
In the third line we have those who were
treated but
not cured with the total count of 23.
In the final line,
we have 90 which represents all of those
who were treated and cured.
If we try to enter this into proc freq
like we did before,
we are not going to get the right output.
When we run a simple code like this,
you will see that the cells in our table
do not actually mean anything.
What we need to do to fix this is include
a weight statement.
Check out this code.
In the third line we've included weight
count.
What we are doing is telling SAS that our
variables only specify the rows and
columns, and that a third variable is
needed to actually populate the cells.
When we run this, we'll get a correct
frequency table.