Welcome back, today we're going to talk
about setting up SAS.
In a few minutes time,
Ram is going to run through how to set up
the SAS remote server.
But first, there are a few things I think
we need to cover.
I want to talk about the options for those
who do not want to use the remote server.
Sometimes the server can be a little bit
slow,
especially during the biostat labs and the
night before homework assignments are due.
While many students in the MS epidemiology
and
clinical research track did not have
problems with the remote server.
You may choose to buy your own copy of SAS
enterprise guide.
For those of you with PCs you can purchase
SAS enterprise guide from
Stanford University for $50.
There will be a separate PowerPoint
presentation for
those of you who want to setup your own
version.
For those of you with a Mac, things get a
little more complicated,
SAS only runs on Windows, so we strongly
suggest that you use the server.
If you really, really want your own copy
of SAS on your Mac, please come talk to
us during the first class lecture and we
will talk you out of it.
Enjoy the lecture.
>> Now I will show you how to
set up access to the SAS server on your
own computer.
The first step is to contact us to get
authorized for server access.
Once we authorize you, you need to set up
the VPN connection.
If you have Windows, follow this link.
If you have Mac, follow this link.
That should have all the instructions you
need for setting up a VPN connection.
Once you have the VPN set up, you need to
connect to the VPN.
If you have Windows, log into the Cisco
client that you just set up.
If you have a Mac, log in through the
network settings on your own computer;
this is located under system preferences.
Once you connect to the VPN, go to
sunac.standford.edu and log in.
Now you need to set up the server
connection, following this link and
scroll down to step 2, option 2.
Specify if you have Windows or Mac, and
click Launch RDP Desktop.
This'll download a file that'll let you
connect to the server.
Now you're all set up to connect to the
server.
Whenever you want to connect to the
server, you need to do three things.
First you need to connect to the VPN.
If you have Windows, use the Cisco client
to connect to su-vpn.Stanford.edu.
If you have Mac, use the network settings
to connect to the Stanford VPN you set
up and enter your password.
The next step is to go to
sunac.Stanford.edu and log in.
And finally watch the RDP desktop profile
that you downloaded, and
enter in your credentials.
Make sure to type win\ before your
username, once you log in, you'll be
connected to the remote server and you'll
be able to run SAS Enterprise Guide.
Whenever you're finished using the server,
please make sure to log off.
If you stay logged in for
too long, you'll hog the server resources
and you might lose unsaved information.