So, in this first question of homework
two, we're presented with a table.
Before we tackle any other questions let's
briefly look at this table.
So, we're presented with two different
groups, the Vioxx group and
Naproxen group.
We're given the number in each group.
The person years of exposure and the
number of heart attacks in each group.
Okay?
So the first question is asking us to
calculate the absolute difference in
incidence rates of heart attacks for Vioxx
versus Naproxen.
And it wants us to put that in units of
1000 person years rounded to
one decimal place.
Okay, cool.
So, what we're going to do is we're
going to treat each group separately,
okay?
So first, we're going to do Vioxx.
So to calculate, the incidence rates.
Or the, the the heart, the number of heart
attacks per 1,000 person years.
We're going to do 20 over 2698 times
1,000.
Okay?
And so, that's going to be 7.4 basically
heart attacks per 1,000 person years.
Okay and then so we're going to do the
same thing for the Naproxen group.
We're going to do 4 over 2699 times 1000.
And I'm going to write that lower here.
So that's going to give us
1.5 heart attacks per 1000 person years.
Okay and to calculate the absolute
difference all we need to do is
subtract 7.4 minus 1.5 to give us 5.9.
Okay so this is 5.9 excess heart attacks
in which group?
It's in the Vioxx group, right?
Okay.
So
that is the answer to the first part of
this question.
Moving on to the second part of this
question.
So the second part of this question asks
us about the absolute difference in
the risk of heart attacks for Vioxx versus
Naproxen represented as a percentage, so.
To calculate this, what I'm going to do.
And this actually might be more
straightforward than the first part of
this question.
Is just take the number of heart attacks
and
divide that by the number of people in
each group, okay.
So I'm going to do 20 over 4047 minus four
over 4029.
To get about 0.0039, which gives us 0.39%.
Okay, so this is the absolute difference
in the risk of heart attacks for
each group, and that's because this is the
probability of a heart attack in
the Vioxx group essentially, and this is
the.
Is the probability of a heart attack in
the Naproxen group.
The third part of this question is asking
us about a rate ratio now
remember whenever you see rate ratio you
think time, okay,
there's a component of time in this.
So, in order to do.
The, in order to calculate the rate ratio
comparing Vioxx with Naproxen.
Okay, what I'm going to do is take these
numbers.
Okay?
So, we're going to do 20 over 2698 divided
by 4 over 2699.
Okay.
And that's, what that's going to give us
is a standardization.
Across the number of person years of
exposure we're standardizing against
the exposure, the number of heart attacks
in each group.
You can think about it like that.
And so the rate ratio here works out to be
5.
The last part of this question is asking
us about the number needed to harm.
And if you remember, the number needed to
harm can simply be calculated as
the reciprocal of the absolute difference
in the incidence rates.
Okay and so we already have that from part
A.
If you remember that was 5.9 events per
1000 person years.
So the reciprocal of this is simply going
to be 1000 divided by 5.9 and
that's going to give us a value of 169.49.
So this is the number of patients, needed
to be treated to receive harm.
So moving onto the next question.
Question we're being presented with this
figure, let's take a look at this.
So there are three categories here a
single pill per day regimen,
a two pill per day regimen and a three or
more pill per day regimen.
And the these are adjusted risks of
hospitalization by each cohort okay.
So moving on to the first part of the
questions asks is asking us
what percent of single pill users were
hospitalized during follow up.
Well that's easy that's given right here
at 7.7.
Okay, the second part of this question, is
saying what percent of three or
more pill users were hospitalized during
follow up.
Well we're just going to look at the bar
for three or more pill users.
And look, oh it says right there 9.9%.
So then the third part is asking us to
calculate the risk ratio comparing
the risk of hospitalization in single pill
users versus three or more pill user.
Okay so, what that's going to be,
is simply, the probability, of
hospitalization, in,
this group, divided by the probability of
hospitalization in this group.
Or, in other words 7.7, divided by 9.9.
Which is, 0.78.
Okay.
So the risk ratio is 0.78.
So this next part is asking us to
calculate the odds ratio now,
of comparing the odds of hospitalization
in the single pill per day
regimen versus the three or more pill per
day regimen.
And so, if you remember the odds in odds
is defined as the probability over
one minus improbability so if you take 7.7
as the probability of hospitalization.
For the single pill per day regimen group
you can represent the odds at
7.7% over 1 minus 7.7% okay and we're
going to do that with the three or
more pill per day regimen group.
So it's 9.9% over 1 minus 9.9%.
Okay, and this is going to give us the
odds ratio.
So if we simplify this, we're going to get
.76.
The odds ratio here is .76.
So let's take a look at this third table
presented to us here.
On homework two.
So there are two groups here.
There's a group that received a weight
reduction of five kilograms or
more, and then there's a group of patients
that experienced a weight reduction of
ten kilograms or more, okay.
And the authors are sort of representing
this in a strange way but, basically
notice that in this placebo group in both
categories there's 45 patients.
Okay?
So, three patients here experienced a
weight loss of greater than or
equal to ten kilograms and those three
also experienced a weight loss of
greater than or equal to five kilograms
okay.
So these aren't mutually exclusive,
they're just representing the data in
different ways because they performed two
different analysis here and here.
And so there's a placebo group and
then there's a group of patients that were
treated with one drug.
I have three different doses at .25
milligrams .5 milligrams and
at one milligram.
Okay?
And odds ratios are presented for
each group.
Okay, so this is of course the odds ratio,
this is the 95% confidence intervals and
this is the p value associated with this
effect estimate.
So now that we have all of that
understood.
Let's take a look at the questions.
The first question asks us why the authors
reported an odds ratio rather than a risk
ratio or rate ratio for these data.
Well, it certainly does seem strange,
given that the study was a randomized
trial.
Which does contain information to
calculate rates and
risks from their data, so the answer's not
C.
Odds ratios are not the preferred measure
of relative risk, okay?
The preferred measure is, of course the
risk ratio.
The data does not come from a case control
study,
because the stem of the question tells us
that it's a randomized trial.
So that leaves us with B, they analyzed
the data with a logistic regression, and
this is the correct answer.
The reason they used a logistic regression
was to control for confounders, okay?
So, you can put variables as,
into a logistic regression as independent
variables in order to adjust for
any confounding effects that you might see
in the output.
Of a logistic regression is an odds ratio.
And so the authors, just reported that
output in this table.
Okay.
The next part of the question,
is asking us to calculate the unadjusted
risk ratio for
the comparison of the five kilogram weight
loss group.
Okay, and we're specifically looking at
the one milligram dosage of this drug.
So the numbers of interest to us are this
number, and this number.
So this is the one milligram dose, this is
the placebo dose.
That's what we want to compare.
And we want to compare it in the five
kilogram weight loss group.
And so to calculate the risk ratio that's
simply just going to be 91% or
you know the probability of losing greater
than or
equal to 5 kilograms of [UNKNOWN] drug,
divided by 29%.
Okay, and that calculation works out to be
about 3.1.
So the risk ratio is approximately 3.1.
The next part of this question is asking
us to calculate the adjusted risk ratio,
based on this adjusted odds ratio that's
given here.
Okay, and we are provided with the
conversion formula, in the problem set.
So I will write that out here, so
the conversion formula's the risk ratio
equals the odds ratio.
Or divided by 1 minus the probability in
the reference group,
plus the probability in the reference
group times the odds ratio.
Okay.
So I'm just going to substitute, what we
know here.
We know that the odds ratio, or the
adjusted odds ratio, rather, is 31.5.
So let me write than in, 31.5, 31.5, okay?
And then we have this probability in the
reference group, variable.
And that's actually just going to be 29%.
Okay, so it's the same thing.
It's, it's we're still looking at this
category of data.
The reference group is the placebo group.
And the probability it represented by this
percentage.
So we're going to write that in.
So this is going to be 29%, 29% or 0.29
right and then, when we
do add this calculation we see that the
adjusted, risk ratio is, is 3.2 and
of course this is the adjusted risk ratio
because we're using the adjusted RR.
To calculate this and to make this
conversion.
The last question in this homework set is
asking us what the best
way would be to represent this very large
odds ratio here, 57.7.
It's very rare to see odds ratios above
like 2 or 3 or something.
So a 57.7 odds ratio here is huge.
So A is incorrect, right?
Because it doesn't 57.7 is an odds so it
doesn't represent that person's chance or
probability of losing at least ten
kilograms on this drug.
The best answer here is C.
Okay the odds ratio is always misleading
it always exaggerates the effect away from
the null when compared to the risk ratio.
So generally speaking it's best practice
to only report the odds ratio, if you also
give the readers or if you also report the
unadjusted or adjusted risk ratio.
It's really hard to understand the odds
ratio, or an odds intuitively.
And so, while B is technically correct.
It is likely to mislead most readers.
And the best answer here is C.