Now, expected value is an extremely useful
concept for good decision-making.
So let's start here,
let's go back to the lottery example which
we started to talk about last week.
The lottery has also been called a,
a tax on people who are bad at math and I
tend to agree with that view point.
I'm not saying lotteries are bad because
most lotteries also go,
some of the revenue goes to pay for things
like schools and parks.
But I'm usually not willing to pay that
tax myself,
because if you do out the math,
the lottery is not really a great deal you
know, there's good reasons not to play.
And remember, we saw the lottery last
week.
A particular lottery works by picking six
numbers from 1 to 49.
You have to punch off six numbers from 1
to 49.
We last week just talked about the
probability of winning.
But let's put some dollar figures to that,
today.
So if it costs a dollar to play the
lottery, and let's say,
on a particular week, the winnings after
taxes are $2 million.
If you play the lottery once, what are
your expected either winnings or loses?
In other words, what's your expected value
here?
Well, we can calculate an expected value
to answer the question of whether or
not it's a good idea to play the lottery.
So, again, we calculated the probability
of winning last week.
So what's the probability of winning the
lotto, lottery?
Well, this particular lottery, there's 49
numbers, so there
are 49 choose six possible combinations
that turns out to be about 14 million.
So your chances if you play one ticket of
winning the lottery are 1 in 14 million.
We saw that that's the combination
function we, we saw last week.
Well, now we can think about this in a
probability as a probability distribution.
There's only two possible outcomes here.
You either win or you lose.
So let's write out the probability
function.
So your two possible outcomes in dollar
values are you either lose a dollar, so
negative 1, or you win $2 million, so
positive 2 million.
The probability associated with each of
those dollar outcomes is
the probability of losing a dollar is
0.999999928.
The probability of winning $2 million is
2.2 time 10 the negative 8.
We can use that probability function to
calculate an expected value here.
So lets do that.
So how would we calculate expected value?
We're going to take each x and multiply it
by its probability, and then add those up.
So, that's easy to do here.
Take the negative 1,
multiply it by this very, very close to 1
probability, 0.999999928.
Take the $2 million, and
multiply it by the chance of winning, the
7.2 times 10 to the negative 8.
When you do that and add that all up,
it turns out to be that your expected
value is negative 0.86 cents.
In other words, you're expected to lose
money.
So in general, if your negative value is
expected, it's not a good idea to play.
If you expect to lose money, it's not a
really good investment for you.
And you might think well cents 0.86, well
yeah,
doesn't sound so bad, but of course, we
can project this over the long run.
On average, for every time you play you
expect to lose $0.86, so if you play every
week for ten years 520 times you're
expecting to lose even more than that.
You're expecting to lose, you know, $447
and
you get the idea, on average, you're
expecting to lose and that increments.
The more you play, the more that adds up,
the more that you lose.
Now of course, some people have argued to
me that
the lottery has some immeasurable values
that we're not factoring in here.
Right.
So for for some people, the excitement of
playing the lottery might be worth that
value, that dollar a week to them.
It's certainly less than we spend on a lot
of people spend on coffees and things.
So, so maybe there's some intrinsic
psychological benefit that people get out
of the lottery.
I probably wouldn't get that benefit since
I'm positive that I'm going to lose so.
Now, let's get back to the Mega Millions
jackpot that I mentioned in the teaser.
So in 2012, the Mega Millions lottery had
gotten up to a record jackpot,
the biggest ever, of $656 million.
So this means that there have probably
been a number of weeks that had gone by in
this particular lottery, where nobody had
won, and so the pot had built up.
And, your choice when you have you know,
when you win the lottery is to take the,
or that amount and, and get it distributed
to you over, say, 30 years.
Or you can get an immediate payout and you
take, you know, you get a lot less, but
you get it right away.
And so that the immediate payout here was
going to be around 474 million.
So somebody had emailed me and said the
following.
If the odds of winning the Mega Millions
is 1 in 175 million,
and we're going to assume that those odds
are correct because it's right from
the Mega Millions website, and
notice that this lottery has a lot worse
odds than the one we just calculated.
That's because there's more possible
numbers involved in this one.
But if the odds is 1 in 175 million, is
there
a significant statistical advantage in
playing a hundred tickets rather than one.
For a half billion with a B dollars, it
almost seems worth it, this person said.
So they wanted to know well the jackpot
gets so
huge does it make suddenly worth it to
play and
even to play a larger number of tickets so
that you increase your chances of winning.
So let's look at this as an expected value
problem.
So we can calculate the expected.
Let's start with the expected value for
one ticket.
So what's your chance of winning?
It's 1 in 175 million.
What's your chance of losing?
It's 1 minus 1 in 175 million or
99.9999994%.
So, we can do other probability
distribution here.
So, in this case, it still costs a dollar
to lose, but now,
the jackpot is 500 million.
Our probability of winning is 6 6 times 10
to the negative 9.
I just converted the negative 99.9999994
to make it easier to write up.
Oh, sorry, 1 minus the,
if you do 1 minus the 0.999999994, you get
this 6 times 10 to the negative 9th.
So [INAUDIBLE] the expected value.
So X times the probability of X, add those
up,
we get interestingly enough, because the
jackpot is so humongous here.
You get a positive expected value which is
a very unusual thing in a lottery.
So you get a positive expected value of
$2.
That's very interesting, because usually
from lottery problems,
the expected value comes out negative.
So let's continue on with the question
that the person who emailed me had asked,
what about if we do this for a 100
tickets?
We're going to have to increase our
expected value,
increase our chances of winning.
We're certainly going to increase our
chances of winning somewhat by a hundred,
buying a hundred tickets.
What will that do to our expected value?
So first of all,
let's calculate the chance that you will
lose if you buy a hundred tickets.
So, what's your chance of losing if you
buy one ticket?
Your chance of losing is 1 minus 1 over a
175 million.
Your chance of winning is 1 over
175,000,000; therefore,
your chance of losing is 1 minus that.
That's your chance of losing with one
ticket.
Now, if you buy a hundred tickets, the
chance of losing is that you have to,
that has to occur, your loss has to occur
hundred times.
A hundred tickets have to not work, work
out, so you have to raise this to 100.
So, 1 minus 1 over 175 million raised to
100 that's
how you calculate the probability of
losing with a hundred tickets.
And that turns out to be it's still a
really,
really high probability of losing, turns
out to be 99.999943%.
So a really, really high chance still that
you
will lose with even with a hundred tickets
not surprisingly.
Let's calculate the expected value now.
So here's the probability distribution,
you're either going to lose a dollar or
win 500 million and here's the
probability.
So, the probability of winning is
0.99999943, so
your probability of losing is sorry, your
probability of losing is 0.99999943,
so your probability is 1 minus that, which
is 5.7 times 10 to the negative 7.
So if I subtract 0.99999943 from 1, you
get 5.7 times 10 to the negative 7.
So, a very small chance, still, of
winning.
Let's calculate out, lay out the expected
value then.
So let's do the expected value.
So, if I calculate the expected value
here.
Interestingly, it comes out to be an
expected value of 284.
Well, that's pretty good.
Because it's a positive.
And, you know, it's a decent amount of
money.
So, one could make the case just looking
at that for maybe for playing.
Now, you're still virtually guaranteed to
lose, right?
Your chance of losing is really, really
high.
But, based just on those things, one can
make a case for playing.
And you can actually work out that the
expected payout only has to
be greater than 176 million for
this particular lottery for the expected
value to be positive.
So, as long as the, the, the lottery
jackpot is greater than 176 million.
Based on the little calculation we've done
so
far, the expected value is going to be
positive.
Of course, there's a but in this.
So we got to go a little further, because
there's more to it than this.
What we haven't considered yet
is that the chance that there could be
multiple winners.
Now, usually, in any given week, the
chance of multiple winners is
pretty small, because the chance, you
know, of one person winning is small,
the chance of two people getting the same
number is small, it does happen sometimes.
But, think about what happens when the
jackpot is huge, it gets, it was,
you know, hugely covered in the media, so
all of a sudden everybody hears about it
and lots of people play.
So when you have lots and lots of people
playing the lottery.
Even though, there is 175 million
different combinations that
are possible when more than 175 million
people play that lottery,
actually, you start to get into having a
high probability of multiple winners.
And multiple winners have to share, have
to split the jackpot.
So it turns out, I went back and tried to
figure out for that
particular Mega Millions lottery, when the
jackpot had gotten up to 656 million.
I've been trying to figure out how many
people actually played,
how many tickets were sold?
I did't find that easily on Google.
But I found some data on the Mega Millions
website which showed how many
people won all of the different possible
prizes, so there's the jackpot and
then there's a whole bunch of smaller
prizes people could win.
And I'm able to estimate to make a pretty
good ballpark estimate that
based on those, the, the number of people
who won those things.
That there are probably about 600 million
tickets sold somewhere in
that ballpark is a rough estimate but 600
million tickets sold.
There are only 175 million different,
only [LAUGH] 175 million different
combinations.
So suddenly, you're realizing that a lot
of combinations got played,
had to have been played multiple times.
And that means there's actually a high,
high chance of multiple winners here.
So what I've done out here is I figured
out the probability distribution for
the number of winners.
So X here is the number of winners for
this record, jackpot Mega Millions,
assuming that 600 million tickets were
sold, here's how many winners we expect.
So the way that I calculated out these
probabilities is,
actually, I treated this as a binomial
distribution, and
we're going to be talking about the
binomial distribution in just two modules.
So tuck that in the back of your head that
the way that I as able to
figure this out was a binomial
distribution.
It turns out that the probability of,
of having no winners when you have 600
million tickets played is only 3%.
The probability of having only a single
winner is 11%.
The probability of having two winners is
19%.
The probability of having three winners is
22%,
and you can see all the probabilities, and
I only went out to 10.
By the time you've got the probability of
having ten winners at once,
that was a pretty small probabilities.
The probability of 11 or more those
probabilities were essentially negligible
because they were so small, so I didn't
bother to keep going.
Well, we can calculate the expected value
of
number of winners here using this
probability distribution.
So I take each value, X and multiply it by
its probability.
Add those up, you come out with that the
expected number of winners,
if 600 million people play or if 600
million tickets are played is 3.4.
And, so you're actually expecting multiple
winners.
And in fact, it turns out that in this
Mega Millions,
particular Mega Millions week, in the
lottery,
there were actually three winners, so the
expected value bore out just perfectly.
So, the expected winnings isn't really 500
million here, because we were expecting
to split the pot by with 3.4 people or 3.4
people are expected to split the pot.
So if you divide the 500 million by 3.4,
it's roughly somewhere around 150 million
that you're actually expecting to win,
while that 147 million puts
us below the figure of 176 million that's
needed to have a positive expected value.
So when you factor in the chance of
multiple winners it turns out that, now,
we're back into that negative territory
for
expected value and I haven't in factored
in taxes either.
I think about half of the lottery winnings
get siphoned off
by the federal government and state
government for taxes.
So that would put our total down to a
jackpot of only $75 million,
which will clearly keep us in the negative
range for expected value.
So just based on expected value, then it
wouldn't be worth playing.
And regardless of expected value, the fact
is you're still almost guaranteed to
lose with near certainty, because the
probability of losing is so, so, so high.
So that's just a fun little problem.
Now, another great example of expected
value is to talk about gambling.
And I think gambling is like the greatest
business model.
Because, it's completely set up to
guarantee that the casino will make money.
And so it's just a great, guaranteed way
to make money, and we can show that.
So, so how does gambling work?
Let me just give you a particular thing
you might encounter in a casino,
a roulette wheel.
Most people are familiar with the roulette
wheel.
So the roulette wheel has the numbers from
1 to 36, as well as 0 and 00.
And you get to bet on one of those you get
to bet on, let's say,
you can bet that an odd number will come
up.
And if you bet, let's say you bet a dollar
that an odd number will come up.
You will win a dollar if the odd number
comes up.
You will lose a dollar if the odd number
doesn't come up.
Now because 0 and 00 are counted as even
numbers, you have,
there are 18 odd numbers but there are 20
even numbers.
So, you have an 18 out of 38 chance of
winning a dollar,
you have a 20 out of 38 chance of losing a
dollar.
So, unlike the lottery now, the chances of
winning and
losing are purposely stacked up to be
pretty close to one another.
But if that's the probability
distribution,
what's the expected value going to be
here?
Well, we can calculate that.
So the expected value is you win a dollar
with probability 18 out of 30, you lose
a dollar with 20 out of 38 probability, so
your expected value is negative cents.
Now, what's neat about gambling is that
they've set
the probabilities close enough that
sometimes you're definitely going to win.
If you play a couple, enough times, you're
definitely going to win sometimes.
So that, of course, is what hooks people
in.
You have to win enough to hook you in.
You have to let people win enough so they
get hooked in.
But on average, if you play over a long
time, and for
every game you play, you lose about a
nickel.
So, on average, the casino is guaranteed
over the long run to win money.
And of course, if the stakes are higher,
the dollar amounts get higher.
So, if it was a $10 game, then the
expected value is negative 53 cents for
the player, which we use positive 53 cents
for the casino.
And let's imagine that the casino played
10,000 games in a night,
it's winning an average of 53 cents per
game,
that means it takes in $5,300 a night just
from the roulette wheel.
So you can see that this is a fantastic
business model,
because the casino, just based on expected
value and
statistics, knows that over the long run
is going to keep raking in money.
And of course,
that means the player over the long run is
going to keep shedding money.
Now, we're turning to the challenge
problem that I set out as one of
the teasers for the week.
So this problem was, you're in a resource
poor area, and
you want to screen the population for some
disease.
But the antibody test is fairly expensive
and you don't have enough money to pay for
antibody tests for everybody.
So people have come up with a clever
cost-saving strategy,
which is to pool the blood from multiple
samples.
So, for every person who comes in and
gets the test, gets their blood drawn, you
set aside half of their blood.
You take the other half of their blood and
you pool it into a, pooled lot of say n
people.
If the pooled lot is negative, so assuming
that the antibody test is
sensitive enough that it will pick up any
virus.
And anybody has the virus, so
if it comes back negative, that means that
nobody has the virus.
If you can get the pooled lot,
if that's negative, you don't have to run
anymore tests on those people because you
know that everybody that you included in
the pool is negative.
So, that saves you n minus 1 tests.
Of course, if that pool blood comes out to
be positive.
Then you do have to go back to the
original individual samples, and
test everybody, to figure out who it is
that has the disease.
That will require you n plus 1 tests.
So you have to, you end up having to do an
extra test.
So if a particular disease has a
prevalence of 10% in a population.
Is this a good case?
Is that, is that rare enough that the
pooling strategy will work?
Of course, if the disease prevalence gets
too high,
then there's not going to be enough
negative lots when you pool people.
So will this pooling strategy work?
And if so, what's the optimal number of
samples to pool for lot?
What's the end here?
How many people should I put?
Did I pool together?
You don't want to pool too many, because
then the chance of the the pooled lot
coming back negative will be too small
that you won't save many antibody tests.
So there's a couple of ways you can solve
this.
You could if you want, and this is a great
thing for
those of you who really want to be
challenged in this course.
You could solve this very elegantly by
writing out
an elegant general solution and solving
for an optimum.
I'm actually not going to solve it that
way.
I'm going to just solve it with brute
force.
I'm just going to try a bunch of things
and
will eventually arrive at the right
answer.
Actually, brute-force is a really good
way,
even if you want to find out an elegant
solution.
Usually, it's a good idea to start with
the brute-force solution, and then,
the elegant solution will kind of
materialize out of that.
So you, at the end of this, you might
want to write down and
figure out the elegant solution.
And I'm also going to just assume that we
want to screen 100 people and
I'm just picking 100 because it's a nice
even number remember sometimes if you
pick 100 it just makes things easy to deal
with whole numbers.
So I'm just going to assume we want to
screen 100 people it doesn't matter how
many we're screening it will, this will
generalize.
So let's just try something.
We'll say, well, what if we wanted to pool
20 people it, 20 people's blood.
Will that save us antibody tests?
So, let's start there.
So, how do we solve this one?
So again, the prevalence of the disease is
10%.
And, we want to pool we're going to try
and see what would happen if we pooled 20
samples at a time, that we use, it says
we're starting with a 100 people,
100 samples, that mean's we'll have five
lots.
How, how many tests are we expected to
have to write, and again, we're
assuming that the test is perfect, the
sensitivity specificity is perfect here.
So we can calculate the expected value
problem.
We can calculate the expected number of
tests here.
So we'll kind of call X is equal to the
number of tests that we're
going to have to run.
And actually, in this case, X can only
take on two possible values.
You're either going to run one test.
That's when it comes out negative.
Or, you're going to have to run 21 test.
So, if you have a pool lot of 20 and that
one comes out positive, you have to go
back and run all the tests on all 20 of
those samples, plus the initial test is 1.
So, you're either ending up running 1 test
if the pool lot comes up negative or
21 tests if the pool lot comes out
positive.
Then we need to figure out, so
we'll call that, it might be nice to put
this in a nice little probability chart,
so here's our two possible outcomes, 1
test or 21 tests.
And then, we need to figure out the
probability of each of those outcomes.
So what's the probability that that pooled
lot is going to come back negative, okay?
So you have to think again, the prevalence
of the disease here is 10%.
[SOUND] What that means is that of any
given person,
a random person, has a 10% chance of
having the disease.
That means they have a 90% chance of not
In order for the pooled lot to come back
negative in this case,
we have to have 20 people in a row who
come back negative.
So, every person has a 0.9 chance of being
negative,
we have to have 20 of those in a row.
So it's 0.9 raised to the 20th.
That's the probability that the pooled
lot will come out to be negative, if you
calculate that out, that's a probability
of 12.2%. So not super high that we're
going to get a negative, and the negative
of course, is what we want here. What's
the probability that the pooled lot is
going to come out positive?
Well, that's just going to be 1 minus
the chance of it coming out negative.
So 1 minus 0.9 to the 20th and
that comes out to be 87.8%.
So that's our probability distribution,
and then,
we can calculate the expected value.
So the expected value here is going to be
12.2 % times 1 plus 87.8
% times 21.
Each x, multiplied by its probability,
add those up.
It turns out that
the expected value is 18.56.
Again, I'm, I'm going to, I'm going to say
what would happen for
a hundred samples just so we can compare
across different pooling strategies and
had make it easy to compare.
So
if we want to do a 100 samples total and
it's 18.56 per lot, then we have 5 lots,
we have to multiply by 5 here.
So that tells us that per lot, per 20
people,
we have to run 18.56 tests on average.
That means per 100 people,
we have to run 92.8 tests on average.
Now, if we hadn't done any pooling
strategy,
we would have had to run 100 tests.
So, we are saving ourselves on
average about seven antibody tests.
It's not a great savings here.
So, but we can, the pooling strategy does
do something here.
So we, we answered the first question.
We know the pooling strategy is going to
be effective here, but
is 20 the optimal number?
Well, it seems like we could do better so
let's try just, you know,
again I'm doing this brute force.
So let's try what would the probability be
if I wanted to pool say, 10 at a time?
So pooling 20, that'is the answer.
As I wrote out on the last screen but
what about pooling ten?
What if you
pool only ten samples at a time?
How would that change things?
Well, it's basically the same problem and
the same logic.
So now, the expected value is going to be,
there's going to be,
you're either running one test now or
you're running 11 tests.
You have a 0.9 raised to the 10 chance of
the lot coming out negative, so
you have that much chance of have, running
one test.
1 minus that is your chance of having to
run 11 tests.
And if you add that up,
you end up with that there are 7.5 tests
expected on average per lot,
and of course if we're pooling ten,
that's, that's 7.5 tests per lot.
But, remember, we have 100 people total
here, so
there's going to be ten lots total.
So we have to multiply that by 10 by 10
lots, so
we'd end up running 75 antibody tests for
those 100 people.
Compare that to what we just calculated
for 20.
For pooling 20, it was 93, we've got it
down to 75.
So we're pooling fewer people is helping
us out.
Well, let's keep going.
What about if we pulled 5, pull 5 people
at a time?
Same logic.
Now you get the pattern.
So it's going to be 0.9 raised to the
five, 5th times 1 plus 1 minus .9
raised to the 5th, that's the chance of
your getting the positive now, times 6,
because if we are going to get positive we
are going to have 5 plus 1 tests.
Now, we are going to end up running about
3.05 tests per lot, but
we have to do 20 lots, [SOUND] because we
got 100 people total.
So we end up with running only 61 tests,
so
we're still gaining as we're going down
here.
Well, let's go down, now, we're really
getting close to,
to pooling, you know, down to one, we're,
so let's go down increment by one here.
What if we pooled 4 together?
So actually, it turns out that the optimum
is at 4, so when you calculate for 4,
it turns out that you would end up using
59 antibody tests.
You would expect to use 59 antibody tests.
Now, remember, this is, otherwise, you'd
have to use 100 if you didn't pool at all.
So this is saving you almost half of the
antibody tests.
This is for the when you have a disease
prevalence of 10%.
So pooling 4 is the optimum, you can keep
going and
show that pooling 3 actually gets you back
up to 60 tests.
So the optimum is hit at 4.
Now again, there's a more elegant way to
solve this.
You could write out a general equation and
solve it, and
you could find that the value is 4, but
you can also use this kind of brute-force
method, and that works as well.
So you can see, there's really a lot of
practical applications in
medicine of understanding a little bit of
basic probability.
I just want to briefly show you for the
concept of expected value,
how it extends to the continuous case.
So here is expected value for the discrete
case.
We're adding up all the values of X times
the probabilities.
Now, as I mentioned this generalizes to
the continuous case, because the summation
becomes an integral we're adding up over
incident with a number of possible values.
So it just becomes an integral.
I'm not going to worry about, in this
class, having you do these integrals or
anything, but I'll just show you a very
simple example.
What's the expected value of the uniform
distribution?
Well again, if you just think about the
expected value of the mean,
as a balancing point.
Another way to ask that is, where is the
balancing point of that distribution?
Where could you put the fulcrum to balance
that?
And I think everybody would agree that you
would just put the fulcrum at 0.5, so you
don't need to do any calculus to get this
one right, that's the balancing point.
Now, if you wanted to do the calculus,
it's actually not terribly hard for
the uniform distribution, so I'll just
show it here.
Remember, the uniform distribution, the
probability everywhere is just 1, so
we would be just taking x times 1 and
integrating from 0 to 1,
that's the, the total range of possible
values here.
When you do out that integral, it does
come out to be 1 half.
So exactly what you would have predicted
just based on intuition.