There are other ways to there's
modifications of the Bonferroni called
the Holm and Hochberg which are a little
bit less conservative.
There are other procedures for
adjusting the p values to reflect the
number of multiple tabs.
Those are called Tukey HFA and again
usually you can just ask
the computer to apply those various
corrections if you want to go in And
figure out exactly where the differences
lie after doing a global ANOVA test.
Now I'm going to say a little bit about
repeated-measures ANOVA.
You use repeated-measures ANOVA when
you've got either more than two correlated
groups or you've got you're following
people over more than two time points.
So there's correlation here.
Here's an example of a study that used
repeated-measures ANOVA.
To analyze the data.
this was looking at a placebo pill versus
a particular treatment for depression.
The outcome here is the depression on a
certain scale.
They're following the two groups, these
are two independent groups over time.
And they want to know did the placebo
group go down less over time than
the treatment group.
It does look like there's a placebo effect
here.
Both groups have an initial improvement in
depression but
only the active treatment group keeps
going down in depression scores.
The p-value here of 0.0002 that you see.
Comes from a repeated-measures ANOVA.
I'm not going to go much into the details
of how the repeated-measures ANOVA
works, but that would be the appropriate
statistical test when you're following
people over time like this.
We have multiple time points, so a paired
t-test will not suffice.
We need instead repeated-measures ANOVA.
So how did I figure out that I needed a
repeated-measures ANOVA?
The statistical quest,
question here is do the subjects in the
treatment group have greater reductions in
the depression scores over time than those
in the control group.
My outcome variable is depression score.
That is a continuous variable, and it is a
normally distributed variable, or,
my sample size here is large enough that
it doesn't matter.
Are the observations correlated?
Yes, I have multiple measurements, many,
many measurements on each person, so
I have correlated observations.
I have more than 2 time points.
So a paired t-test will not suffice.
I'm going to have to use a repeated
measures ANOVA.
I also have multiple groups here.
Which, paired t-test only is going to work
on one group over time.
So I need to use repeated measures ANOVA.
Because I have multiple groups and more
than 2 time points.
Again, I'm not going to go into much
detail about the repeated measures ANOVA.
I'm just going to tell you a little bit
about it, and how it works.
And when it's used.
Again, if we have more than two time
periods,
paired t-test is not going to suffice.
Now you could say, well why don't I just
do multiple paired t-tests?
Well, I could compare time one to
baseline.
I could compare time two to baseline.
I could compare time three to baseline.
I could use a paired t-test for each of
those comparisons, but again.
The problem is that's going to increase
you type one error,
your chances of a false positive.
So we don't like to do a whole bunch of
paired ttests.
We'd rather put everything together in one
global test which is
repeated-measures ANOVA.
And it answers the following questions.
You get a couple of things out of
repeated-measures ANOVA.
So if you've got say two groups or
more than two groups that you're comparing
over multiple- Time points.
It can answer the following question.
First of all, it can answer just whether
or
not there are significant differences
across time periods.
Does your outcome change at all across
time periods?
So, that's the time factor in
repeated-measures ANOVA.
You can also ask whether or not there were
any significant differences between your
groups, if you've got multiple groups
you're comparing over time.
[UNKNOWN] you can ask whether or not there
are significant differences in
the changes over time between those
groups.
So you have what is called a time effect
and group effect in a group by time effect
and usually what we care about like in
that depression example I've just showed
you, we care about the group by time
effect, we cared whether or not there were
differences in the changes in depression
over time between Between the groups.
And repeated measures ANOVA can answer
that question for you.
It's very good for longitudinal data.
So to ask,
is there any change at all over time in
any of the groups, that's the time factor.
If you want to ask if there's any
differences in
the groups at any time points.
That's what we call the group factor.
But the one we really care about.
Is whether or not the two groups differ in
their responses over time,
that's what we call in repeated-measure
ANOVA, the group by time factor.
I'm just going to show you a couple of
different examples of some mock data to
give you a sense of what you get out of
repeated-measures ANOVA.
So these are all examples where I've got
two groups and
I'm following them over multiple time
points, call them group A and group B.
So you can just look at this graphic, and
what you see in this graph, this is mock
made up data.
But group A seems to be going down at a
faster rate, and
this is, let's say this is depression
score.
Group A which is in black there seems to
be going down at
a faster rate than group B.
Group B is actually pretty steady.
It doesn't change too much.
It's pretty stable over time.
So it looks like [INAUDIBLE].
The, the time factor.
For this repeated measured number, we're
going to get a time factor.
And that time factor is statistically
signifigant.
Because, overall.
If you just ignore group.
Overall, there does some to be some change
over time.
Overall, there seems to be, on average.
There seems to be some decrease in time.
The group by time factor is significant
here as well because the two
groups definitely differ in what happens
over time.
One group goes down in depression the
other is stable.
The group factor is not significant here,
we usually care least about
the group factor, but overall if you kind
of just average the depression across all
the time points in group A versus group B
that was about the same Same,
because group A starts a little higher,
but ends a little bit lower,
so the group factor here will not come out
to be significant.
Here's a picture where time is not
significant.
Nobody is changing over time, everybody is
stable.
Time is not significant.
Group by time is also not significant.
Both of those lines are essentially pretty
parallel.
The changes over time are the same for
both of them.
However, the group factor here would be
significant,
because all time points [INAUDIBLE].
One final example.
Here's an example.
Where time would be significant, every
bodies going down over time.
Group is not significant because the 2
groups on average seem about the same.
And group by time does also, does not come
out to be significant because both groups,
those lines aren't perfectly parallel but
both groups are going down.
Group A is going down slightly faster than
Group B but
not enough to achieve a statistically
significantly difference.
The slopes, there.
So that's the basics of repeated measures
ANOVA, there's a lot more to
repeated measures ANOVA, but that will
just give you a flavor for that technique,
that's out there for these kinds of
longitudinal studies.