The next p-value
pitfall we're going to talk about is
something called the problem of
multiple testing.
This problem is best illustrated with an
example.
This is one of my favorite studies in the
medical literature.
It shows why it's great to be a
statistician.
So, this is a 1980s study.
Some researchers at Duke University
randomized about
a thousand heart disease patients into two
groups and that was the end of the study.
See, it's great to be a statistician.
You don't have to do anything too hard.
Right?
They just randomly assign those patients
to either group 1 or group 2.
Essentially, they put their names in an
Excel spreadsheet, as in, as whether or
not they were in group 1 or group 2.
And then the study was done.
This means that we know for sure that
there is no biological effect here.
We know that being in group one can't have
done anything differently than
being in group two.
We know that the null hypothesis is true
because that's all.
There was nothing done differently to the
two groups other than where they ended up
in the excel spreadsheet which obviously
would not effect their outcome.
So, this is a case where we know, we know
that the null hypothesis is true.
Then, the researchers tracked the survival
of those heart disease patients, and, not
surprisingly there was no difference in
survival between group one and group two.
We'd be really surprised if there had been
a difference.
But, then the researchers went on
and did the following.
They started to divide the patients up,
those 1000 patients up into subgroups
based on prognostic factors.
And in a subgroup of 397 patients,
patients who had 3 vessel disease and
an abnormal left ventricular contraction
in that particular subgroup, they were
able to find a survival difference between
those randomized to group 1 and
those randomized to group 2, and the p
value was less than 0.025.
There was a statistically significant
difference in survival between the two
groups, but how can that be?
We know that nothing was done differently
between those two groups.
How can we have gotten a statistically
significant survival difference?
What's going on here?
Well, what happened is that if you parsed
the data up enough ways, so they tried
this subgroup, they tried that subgroup,
they tried 18 different subgroups.
In one of those subgroups,
it's not that unlikely that there would
just be a chance imbalance.
Just by chance, by a fluke in one of those
subgroups we happen to
have a little bit better survival in group
1 than group 2.
It's a chance imbalance.
And we know that the null hypothesis is
true here.
So we know if that we if we reject the
null hypothesis,
we know we'll have made a type one error.
You can get imbalances in your data,
though.
And if you parse your data,
if you start hunting around in your data
enough times, you will
find some statistically significant P
values that pop up just due to chance.
This is the idea of the multiple testing
problem.
[SOUND] Remember, if we set a significance
level of
0.05 we're allowing a false positive rate
for one test of 5%.
That's for one test though.
If you run more than one test, every test
has a false positive chance of 5%.
There is nothing going on [INAUDIBLE] if
there are no effects,
your chances of getting a false positive
if you set up a significance level of
0.05 is 5%, one in twenty.
But let's say you run many tests.
Let's say you run 18 tests.
Then the probability of getting a false
positive is much higher, and
we can actually calculate what it would
be.
So if we compare survival of treatment and
control within 18 different subgroups,
that's 18 comparisons.
There's a 5% chance that any one of those,
each one of those has a 5% chance of
generating a false positive.
When you have 18 though, the chance that
at least one of
those comes up to be a false positive is
much, much, much higher than 5%.
And we can actually calculate it using
what we learned in the probability unit.
How would we calculate that?
Now we have to make a little assumption
here in order to be able to
calculate this easily.
We're going to assume that all the
comparisons are independent.
That's the only way we can solve this
easily.
Of course, these comparisons are not
independent because some of
those sub groups would have overlapped.
So this is sort of a maximum that we're
calculating.
But think about the way that we would
calculate this.
What's the chance of at least one type I
error.
Remember this is one of those at least one
problems in probability.
Well, every test has what?
Every test has a chance of a type one
error of 5%.
So that means it's in at least one case.
So what are we going to calculate?
We're going to calculate one minus the
probability of none.
Well, what's the probability on none here
of getting no false
positives over 18 tests?
Well, that's going to be 1 minus.
And what's the probability of getting no
false positives over 18 tests?
Well, the probability for one test of not
getting a false positive is 95%.
95% chance you're not going to get a false
positive.
But we have to do that 18 tests in a row.
So that's .95 raised to the 18th.
When you do that and then subtract from
one, it turns out
that the chance of at least one false
positive is somewhere around 60%.
In other words,
you're expecting to get at least one false
positive when you run 18 tests.
It would be surprising, you have a 60%
chance,
it would actually be surprising if you
didn't get a false positive.
[SOUND] This is the idea that if you
torture your data long enough,
they will confess to something right.
You can keep parsing up your data until
you find a chance in balance somewhere.
That's essentially what you are doing when
you are doing multiple testing.
If there are no effects you should expect
to get a p-value of less than
0.05 about one in 20 times.
That's what that significance level does.
It guarantees you a type one error rate of
about 5%.
One in 20 times you're going to get a
false positive.
If you run lots of tests you're going to
have more opportunities for
chance findings.
And here there's lots of ways that we run
lots of tests and statistics, right?
Let's say we're doing a study where we
look at multiple different outcomes,
all these different types of cancer.
Well, one of those cancers might come up
significant just by chance.
Or, a lot of times, people get multiple
different predictors.
Or we do sub group analysis.
It's very typical, for example in a
randomized trial,
just like the one I was talking about.
Where you actually have a drug, though,
where you go out do the randomized trial,
and it turns out there's no significant
effect overall on survival.
Then, people start parsing out into
subgroups.
And low and behold,
they get a statistically significant
result in one of those subgroups.
And they come up with a great biological
explanation.
Of why this drug will work for those with
an abnormal left ventricular contraction.
They can come up with an explanation, but
if you parse your data enough,
probably it's just a chance finding.
There's also other ways when people are
analyzing their data,
some of these things are hidden.
Maybe they tried a whole bunch of
different ways for how to define exposure.
Like, how do I define drinking?
Light drinking, and moderate drinking?
I can try it a whole bunch of different
ways.
If I try lots of different ways,
one of those by chance is likely to come
out significant.
Or if I do repeated measures, if I look at
the outcome at multiple time points.
By chance one of those outcomes might come
out significant.
Multiple looks at the data, if we're doing
a randomized trial and
week peeking at the data.
There's so many places, where you can get
multiple testing coming in and
increasing your chances of getting a false
positive, of getting a type 1 error.
So I'd like to illustrate this in my
on-campus class with
the following little experiment.
I do an experiment where I also know that
the null hypothesis is true.
Just like those [INAUDIBLE] researchers
knew for sure that the null hypothesis was
true, they knew that any significant p
values had to be false positive.
I do the same little experiment in my
class.
So I asked my class to fill out a survey
in the begining of quarter that says
that asked them a bunch of questions.
And one of the questions I like to ask is
whether or
not you were born on an odd day or an even
day.
Because presumably being born on a odd day
or
even day really doesn't have anything to
do with anything in, in your future.
So I know that the null hypothesis is
true.
I know that there shouldn't be any
difference,
any real difference between those two
groups.
And then I asked the students to provide
data on lots of
other variables about themselves.
In one class I asked them to provide data
about 28 variables.
I, I want to make sure that I'm going to
get a false positive.
So by doing 28 that's a lot more than 20.
kind of guaranteeing myself a false
positive.
So what I then do, is I take the results
from all of those variables.
I compare people born on an odd day or an
even day with the correct statistical test
and then I record the p-value from all 28
comparisons, all 28 tests.
And I recorded all those p-values from all
those tests, and I put them in
a histogram, so that we can see what the
distribution of p-values looks like here.
Again, we know the null hypothesis to be
true because I don't think being born on
an odd or even day affects any of the
variables I asked them about.
So what do you see here?
This is the histogram for p-values, I did
28 tests and
I'm showing the counts on the y-axis.
The p values range from zero to 1, so
probability has to range from zero to 1.
So what do you notice here?
What distribution does a p value follow
when the null hypothesis is true?
It follows a uniform distribution.
It is completely random if the null is
true,
where the p-value will fall between zero
and 1.0.
And notice when you look at this graph,
you probably, the thing that your eye is
drawn to, is the following two things.
You probably, your eye was probably drawn
to here, and here.
The gaps.
So for some reason, just by chance, I
didn't get a p-value between 0.15 and
0.2, and I didn't get a p-value, any
p-values between 0.75 and 0.85.
It's completely just chance that I didn't
get any there.
But those are the most surprising things.
What's not surprising is that I happened
to get two p-values between 0 and
0.05, so this bar here, I got two
statistically significant p-values.
P of less than 0.05.
But if they hadn't gotten any p-values
there, it would have been surprising.
I'm expecting because p values follow a
uniform distribution, that I'm
going to get some p values that happen to
fall between 0 and 0.05 just by chance.
And, in fact, you can show that p-values
are, follow a uniform distribution.
So what I did, just to show you, so you
can compare.
Here's the p values from my class.
Looks like it follows the uniform
distribution.
When I generate 25 random numbers from a
uniform distribution,
I come up with similar distributions.
This is just showing you that if the null
hypothesis is true,
you're expecting to get anywhere from 0 to
one with equal probability.
That is, values between 0 and 0.05 or
between 0 and 0.1, are not surprising.
They're expected.
In fact, it would be odd is you didn't get
some p values that
were statistically significant at the 0.05
level when you do so many tests.
Let me give you another multiple testing
example from the, from the [INAUDIBLE].
Just show you [INAUDIBLE] a real example
where I think probably what's going on
are chance findings.
So, this was a study researchers were
looking at whether or
not caffeine and coffee drinking and tea
drinking, whether or
not any of that influences your risk of
breast cancer.
There's been some thought in the past that
drinking caffeinated coffee, and
a lot of caffeine might increase your risk
of breast cancer.
So they did a very thorough study.
They looked at, they asked women about
their caffeine, coffee and
tea consumptions, and
they looked at who got breast cancer and
who didn't get breast cancer.
Now, they looked at this in a lot of
different ways.
They looked at Does caffeine, coffee
drinking or
tea drinking, do any of those things
relate to getting breast cancer at all.
They also looked at breast cancer in
multiple subgroups, so
the type of breast cancer, they broke that
down.
They also looked at the type of women, is
it a post menopausal woman or
pre-menopausal women.
So they made multiple subgroups.
So essentially, they ended up running
about 50 statistical tests to
look at all of these different possible
associations.
So notice, a large number of tests here.
Overall, there was no association between
caffeine, coffee, caffeinated coffee,
caffeinated tea, and breast cancer.
However, they came out with 4 significant,
or near significant P-values
with significant statistical significance
at the level of 0.05, in some subgroups.
So, they found that coffee intake was
linked to
an increased risk of breast cancer in
women who had benign breast disease.
That's a particular subgroup.
The P-value there was 0.08, so
not quite statistically significant at the
conventional 0.05.
They also found that caffeine intake was
linked to an increased link of
a particular type of tumor,
estrogen/progesterone negative tumors,
as well as larger tumors, tumors larger
than 2 cm.
The p-values there were 0.02 and 0.02 for
those comparisons.
They also found that decaf coffee was
linked to
a reduced risk of breast cancer in
postmenopausal hormone users.
Notice as I'm reading that the number of
qualifiers that I'm putting in there.
When you start having lot's of qualifiers
like that,
that's when you start to worry about
things like multiple testing.
The P value there came out to be 0.02.
So overall they found you know, coffee,
caffeine pretty safe for breast cancer.
But then they were worried about these
"significant," I'm putting significant in
quotes, significant P values that came
out.
And the media coverage reflected that
[INAUDIBLE]
caffeine consumption was associated.
They, they said caffeine consumption,
overall, not related to breast cancer.
But it was associated with hormone
negative breast cancers.
And breast cancers, tumors larger than two
centimeters.
But the study did uncover an increased
risk of cancer from women with
benign breast disease, who drank four or
more cups of coffee a day.
Caffeine consumption was also linked to an
increased risk of tumors that
hormone receptor negative or larger than 2
cm.
So, in other words, the implication here
was that oh, well, overall it's not bad.
Coffee is not bad for breast cancer but it
does affect these other subgroups.
And we worry about caffeine for those
subgroups.
However, my conclusion from this study
would be completely different.
So here is what I did.
I went through that study and so in recent
time when I went through
that study they had multiple tables with
all these different results and
they had p-values for each of these 50
tests that I talked about,
the 50 different comparisons they did.
I extracted the p-values from all those 50
tests and put them in a little data set
and graphed it, just so I could see the
distribution of the p-values.
So notice what the distribution looks
like,
it looks like a uniform distribution.
Remember, if the null hypothesis is true,
if there's no effects, we expect the
p-value to follow uniform distribution.
Equal probability from 0 to 1.
Notice that the most surprising thing is
as I mentioned earlier,
the most surprising thing on this graphic,
the thing that your eye gets drawn to,
is that there are no P-values between 0.8
and 0.85.
That's the surprising thing, that there's
a gap.
In fact, it would be surprising if we had
found no P-values between 0 and 0.05 or,
or between 0 and .10.
Those are the ones that they mentioned.
It would be completely surprising if we
found none there.
In other words, the p-values that we found
that were statistically significant,
these moderate 0.02, 0.08 p-values, those
are almost certainly,
they're very highly likely to be chance
findings.
They're completely consistent with chance
We're going to get some significant
p-values.
If you do 50 tests, some of those p-values
are going to come out significant.
But those are most likely just chance
findings.
You can also look at other things in the
paper to kind of convince yourself that
these are almost certainly chance findings
as opposed to anything real.
So I looked at the effect sizes.
The, they looked at, they calculated risk
ratios here.
There was no consistent pattern.
So the risk ratios, they weren't big.
They were all close to one.
They range from 0.67 to 1.79.
So, now big values.
No big effect sizes here.
And they jumped around from below one and
above one.
It wasn't like they were all in the
direction of harm.
They're [INAUDIBLE] about half were below
1 and about half were above 1.
So that's, again, a pattern that's
consistent with chance.
There was no dose response pattern when
they looked at the level of caffeine.
So all of these things are implying that
it's almost certain that
those signifigant p-values that they found
there were just purely chance findings.
And you'd actually expect to get a few
significant p-values just by chance here.
So the thing, things you want to look for
when you're trying to decide, is this just
a chance finding?
You're looking for, if you're doing a lot
of exploratory analysis.
Running lots of tests.
If you run a whole bunch of tests, and
only a few pop up to be significant,
that's very consistent with chance.
You're also looking for p-values that are
modest in size.
So, you have a 5% chance of getting, you
know, below 0.05.
But you have a very small percent chance,
say, of getting below a p-value of one in
ten thousand.
So we're talking about modest size, .01,
.02, .05.
Those are more likely to be chance
p-values.
The pattern of effect sizes and
inconsistent would be, would be something
that indicates chance.
Also, if you have a situation where the
p-values are not in anyway corrected for
multiple comparisons.
So it turns out I'm going to talk at the
end of this module about a few ways that
you can correct your p-values for multiple
testing.
So if they've done that, then of course,
this wouldn't apply, but if they
haven't corrected for multiple comparisons
you need to worry about chance findings.
Another place this has come up a lot in
recent decades is with some of
these things like microarray analyses.
High-Throughput Genome.
So when you do something like a
microarray,
you might be comparing two groups, like a
cancer group and a control group.
And they're usually small groups.
But you're comparing the expression of
30,000 genes.
That's a huge number of comparisons.
So let's say there's no differences
between the groups,
there's actually no difference in gene
expression.
If you set your P-value, your significance
level to be 0.05,
well out of 30,000, 5% of those are
going to come out to
be statistically significant at that
conventional level of 0.05.
1500 are going to achieve that purely by
chance.
You're expecting that.
So there are a lot of microarray studies
that came out that were later believed to
just be false positive because you can get
so
many false positives when you run so many
tests.
We had to change the way that we actually
analyzed microarray data to
account for that.
And another interesting question that you
can think about is,
well, if you just look at the literature,
how common are false positives?
Now you might think well, okay,
false positives are 1 in 20 cause I just
said the false positive rate is 1 in 20.
But you have to be a little bit careful
about that because what I've told you is
the probability of getting a p-value of
less than 0.05, if there are no effects.
So that is, if the null is true.
[SOUND].
That probability, of course, is 5 percent.
That's your false positive, right?
When you set the significance level at
0.05.
You're going to get a, statistically
significant p-value just by chance when
there are no effects 5% of the time.
That's the probability that we know.
Of course, to answer the question how
common are false positives in
the literature, we want the reverse of
that condition or
we're going to have to apply some Bayes'
Rule here.
So if I want to switch that,
what's the probability that the null
hypothesis is true?
That is that the effect is not real if I
get a p-value of less than 0.05.
That's a harder question to answer.
We have to apply Bayes' rule to answer
that question.
We don't have that probability in, with
the conditionals in that direction.
We don't have it directly and you have to
make some assumptions.
So you'd have to apply Bayes' rule here
and then make some assumptions, and
of course those assumptions can really
effect the estimate here.
But somebody's done that, and tried to
make some reasonable assumptions.
And one paper said that it turns out that
about one in
two p-values under 0.05 in the medical
literature is a false positive.
In other words,
a half of all the significant p-values you
see out there are just a false positive.
That's their estimate based on applying
Bayes' rule here but
if you look at p-values less than 0.01, it
goes down.
Only one in six are a false positive.
If you look at p values less than 0.0001,
then only about 1 in 56 are false
positives.
So, again, those modest p-values, 0.01 to
0.05 are much, much,
much more likely to be false positives.
If you get a really really small p-value,
it's much less likely to be a false
positive.
Take [INAUDIBLE] point here.
You gotta look at the totality of the
evidence,
there's tons and tons of nonsignificant
p-value, but one significant p value in
a sea of nonsignificant p-values, don't be
that impressed by that.
Authors tend to want to just jump in and
say oh, I'm going to look in my data until
I can find a significant p-value, well,
some of those significant p values are
just chance.
So don't be that impressed by one
significant p-value
out of a sea of non-significant p-values.
Expect about one significant p-value in
about one of every 20 tests if
there's nothing going on in the data, if
there are no effects.
I want to spend just a minute here to
mention p-value corrections because one
of the ways we deal with multiple testing
is to try to
somehow control the type one error by
correcting the p-values or
adjusting the p-value level that we're
going to call statistically significant.
We call these corrections, p-value
corrections,
multiple comparisons correction.
The simplest one,
one that many of you may already heard of
is something called the Bonferroni.
It's the easiest one for me to illustrate.
It's the easiest one for me to apply.
So I'll start with that one.
It's also the most conservative correct
procedure, in other words,
it's a little bit too conservative at
guarding against multiple testing.
And, and what can happen if you apply
Bonferroni is you may end up
with no statistically significant results
as a result.
You may increase your type two error.
But Bonferroni's simple.
So if you have, you know,
just a few tests and you want to do a
simple correction, here's what you can do.
All your doing with a Bonferroni is saying
let's say you want to control your
type one error rate, study wide for all
your tests.
Not just one test, but all of your tests
at, at a level of 0.05.
And let's say you want to run five tests.
If you want to run five tests, one way to
keep your overall alpha,
your overall significant, your overall
type error error rate at 0.05,
is to require statistical significance to
be more stringent.
So if you have, if you want to keep your
overall error rate to be 0.05 and
you're going to run five tests, you could
just divide those two things and
say well I'm only going to count something
as statistically signicant,
not if the p-value's less than 0.05 but if
the p-value is less than 0.01.
So for example, if you had obtained a
p-value of 0.001 and
you would run five tests, you would still
count that as statistically significant
because that is still below 0.01.
So we'd call that significant.
If I ran four tests, then my new
significance level would be 0.013,
0.05 divided by 4.
You could see how easy this is to apply.
You're just dividing 0.05 by the number of
tests you ran to come up
with a new cutoff for statistical
significance.
So let's say you got a P value .011.
You're you want it to be under 0.013 for
statistical significance here.
So that would still be statistically
significant.
How about though if you ran three tests?
Then your significance level if you're
going to do a Bonferroni correction,
you change your significance level to
0.017.
So a p value of 0.019 would now no longer
be statistically significant.
So a conventional statistical significance
0.019 would say that was significant.
But when the Bonferroni correction for the
fact that you ran three tests,
say three outcome, then that's no longer
statistically significant.
And so on and so forth, so if you want, if
you
ran two tests you'd need a significance
level of 0.025, so 0.032 wouldn't cut it.
And if you run one test, of course, the
significance goes back to 0.05.
So Bonferroni is easy to apply, but it's
highly conservative, because it's actually
assuming that all the comparisons that
you're running are completely independent.
And that's usually not the case.
Usually you're running things that are
related to one another.
So, some alternatives to Bonferroni that
you should be aware of are something
called the [INAUDIBLE], the Holm and
Hochberg procedures.
And they, these are a little bit less
conservative than Bonferroni.
But still extremely easy to apply.
So this is the way they work.
You would take all the p-values from all
the tests you ran.
So if you ran 10 tests, then you'd have 10
p-values.
You arrange those p-values from the
smallest.
The most significant to the largest.
And Holm and Hochberg actually are really
the identical test,
it's just the way that you approach it.
Which one is faster to apply?
If you have very few significant
comparisons, the Holm is faster to apply.
If you have many significant [INAUDIBLE]
comparisons,
it turns out the Hochberg is faster to
apply.
But they're going to give you exactly the
same result.
They're really essentially the same test.
One starts from smallest to largest.
One starts from largest to smallest.
So the Holm procedure says you start with
the smallest p-value.
So that's the most significant you came,
p-value you came up with in all your
tests and you compare it to the Bonferroni
pvalue.
So if you ran ten tests, that would be
0.05 divided by 10.
You would need, so lets say alpha is 0.05
and
you ran 10 test then your new cut off
here.
Would be .005.
That's your, just your Bonferroni
correction.
If your smallest p-value is lower than
that boundary,
then you call that one statistically
significant, and you keep going.
If that one is not, your best p-value of
all doesn't make the Bonferroni cutoff,
then you're, then you have no significant
p-values, and you stop.
But let's say, then that means nothing
significant.
But let's say that that best p value makes
the Bonferroni cutoff.
Then you allow the next p-value, you're a
little less stringent.
You then would say that the next cutoff
for
statistical significance would make it a
little less conservative, so
[INAUDIBLE], now, we're going to compare
p2 the next p-value up in
significance to 0.05 divided by 9 rather
than 0.05 divided 10.
In other words you P value cut off is a
little less stringent.
If that next highest P value makes it,
it's significant at that level then you
continue to the next step.
If not, you stop and so on and so forth.
So this is going to be less conservative
than the [INAUDIBLE],
than the Bonferroni because some of
the p-values are not going to be compared
against that most stringent cut off level.
Now the Hochberg is the exact same in the
reverse.
So the Hochberg says start with the
largest.
The least significant p-value and
compare that to just plain old alpha just
the 0.05 your uncorrected p-value.
If that's significant every thing is
significant.
If your worst P value is 0.05 everything
will be significant.
If it's not significant, then keep going.
That one will be called not significant.
Now go to the next one down, the, the next
least significant on your list.
Compare that to alpha divided by t minus
1.
So now we're going to compare that to your
original alpha divided by 2 here.
And so for the second p-value on the list
you would compare p 2.
You would compare that one.
Now it's just a little bit less stringent
than your original alpha.
If that one is significant,
all the remaining smaller p-values are
significant you stop there.
If not, you gotta go on to step three and
for
step three you would have compared the
next least significant p-value.
To say 0.05 divided by three and I guess
more and more stringent as you go along.
So, actually it's going to be the same
answer as the Holm, it just
starts with the least significant rather
than starting with the most significant.
Same idea.
Let's just apply this to a practice
problem.
This is, these are all easier concepts to
see with actually an application.
So, imagine that a large randomized trial
to compare an experimental drug to
nine other standard drugs for treating
motion sickness.
And you do some kind of statistical test,
an ANOVA test.
And it reveals that
there's some significant differences
between the groups.
So an ANOVA test, we're going to talk
about this next week, is a global test.
And that tells you, well, there's some
difference there.
Drug 1 is different than something.
But it doesn't tell you which groups
differ.
So then you need to go in and compare drug
one to all those other drugs.
And we're going to do 9 tests here.
We're going to compare drug 1 to 2, drug 1
to 3, drug 1 to 4, et cetera.
Here's all the p-values that came out of
just writing what, what our T test
comparing the mean motion sickness in drug
1 to the mean motion sickness in drug 2.
We run a T test, we got a p of 0.05.
We do the same thing.
For the next one, we've got a p of 0.3.
Which of those differences will be
statistically significant if we
do a multiple comparisons correction?
So if you didn't do a multiple comparisons
correction,
anyone that was less than 0.05 would be
significant.
But that's not correct for multiple
comparisons.
So if we apply a Bonferroni, or a Holm, or
a Hochberg here, what do we get?
Which ones will come out to be
statistically significant.
So for the Bonferroni we did nine tests.
We divide 0.05 by 9, the new cutoff for
statistical significance is 0.0056.
Using Bonferroni then for, go back to our
list of drugs the only p-values
that came out to be lower than 0.0056 are
number 6 and number 9.
So only six and nine would be significant.
Notice 0.006 here would not be
significant, number 7.
So according to Bonferroni only 6 and
9 would be different than the experimental
drug.
To apply Holm or Hochberg you're going to
arrange the p-values from lowest to
the highest, so the least, from the most
significant to the least significant.
If I apply the Holm correction, then it
turns out that 6 is significant,
9 is significant and 7 is significant.
And then everything else after that is not
significant.
So drug 6, 9, and 7 become significant
according to Holm.
If you apply Hochberg, again, you're
applying any other direction.
It's actually a little bit, takes you a
little bit longer here.
But you find out that seven, nine and
six, the same three are significantly
different.
And again,
just by looking at these procedures you
can see how they're applyed.
You'll notice that Holm and Hochberg are
less conservative because
additionally drug 7 comes out to be
statistically significant in those cases.
It's good to be less conservative because
you end up with if it's appropriate
because you end up with more things coming
out statistically significant.
Again, Bonferroni is only [INAUDIBLE]
appropriate if everything is independent,
which is usually not the case.
If everything is not independent,
Bonferroni is too conservative, and you're
going to miss a statistically significant
effect that you should of found.
In other words that you're going to make a
type two error.