[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next module, we're going to talk
about diagnostic testing,
using as an example that CelluliteDX test
that
I set out as the teaser in the opener this
week.
So when we're talking about diagnostic
testing,
we're talking about things like
sensitivity,
specificity, positive predictive value and
negative predictive value.
I've already used these terms a little bit
this week.
Now I'm going to formally define them, and
we're going to do a little bit formal
calculation of them.
So first of all the senstivity is the
probability that if you
truly have the disease, that the
diagnostic test is going to catch it.
How sensitive is the test?
Specificity is the probability that if you
don't have the disease,
that the test is going to accurately
register as a negative.
You want both of those to be good.
Positive predictive value is the
probability that if you test positive for
the disease, you actually have the
disease.
This is usually what the patients are more
interested in, right?
If you have a positive test, what's the
chance that you actually have the disease?
We calculated this already today for a
couple of conditions.
Similarly, the negative predictive value,
is the probability that if you test
negative for
a disease, it's the probability that you
actually do not have the disease.
Now, unlike sensitivity and
specificity, which actually don't depend
on the prevalence of a disease that
only depend on how good the test is, the
positive predictive value and
negative predictive value depend directly
on the prevalence of the disease.
Of course, as well as how accurate the
test is.
So let's get back to this fun example that
CelluliteDX test.
So this is a test that the company sells
for about $250 a pop,
to, it's a genetic test, to tell women
whether or
not they are likely to develop moderate to
se, to severe cellulite.
So the idea is that a young woman might
take this test before she
develops cellulite, and it would give her
some information about whether or
not she's likely to develop cellulite, and
therefore she and
her doctor might be able to do something
together to mitigate her risk.
So here's the, the pitch the company has
on its website for this test.
They say a patient who tests positive has
approximately a 70% chance of
developing moderate to severe cellulite.
Notice that's the positive predicted
value.
A patient who tests negative,
has approximately a 50% chance of not
developing moderate to severe cellulite.
So that's the negative predictive value.
Now if you're thinking about this
carefully, right away you can see that
this test is not terribly useful right, so
if you test positive you have
a 70% chance of of ha, developing moderate
to sever cellulite, approximately.
And If you test negative, notice you still
have a 50%
chance of getting moderate to severe
cellulite, right?
It's not terribly different, 1 minus 50%
is 50%.
So you, you test positive, there's a 70%
chance.
If you tested negative, it's still a 50%
So right away you kind of see this, mm, is
this really that useful?
Even assuming that there's something you
can do to intervene and
prevent the onset of cellulite, but it
gets even funnier than then this, okay, so
we're going to delve into this a little
bit more deeply into the numbers.
It's a great illustration of,
of diagnostic testing and the, the numbers
come out to be even funnier than this.
So where did the, first of all, where did
this test come from?
So the CelluliteDX test was developed
based on a case control study,
where researchers were looking at a
particular genetic variant.
And they were able to show that this
genetic variant was statistically
associated with moderate to severe
cellulite.
So it was a case controlled study.
Here's the data from that study.
They sampled 200 cases.
These are women who have, moderate to
severe cellulite.
And 200 controls, women who did not have
moderate to severe cellulite.
And then they tested them for this
particular genotype.
And if you carried a D allele, there, that
was associated with a significantly higher
risk of having moderate to severe
cellulite in this case control study.
Here are the numbers.
So, when you get a positive on the
CelluliteDX test,
all that means is that you carry a D
allele.
So let's, that, so again, the same numbers
are used for, if you have a positive on
the CelluliteDX test, that's the same as,
as having this genetic allele.
So now let's look at the test and who, and
the, and the, and
who actually has the disease, and right
from this two by two table,
we can calculate from these data
sensitivity and specificity.
And a lot of times when you're calculating
sensitivity and specificity from
actual data, you might having it, setting
it up in a two by two table like this.
We can also calculate this from a tree and
all those other things we learned, but
let's do it from a two by two table now.
So what's the sensitivity here?
So there are 200 women who truly have
cellulite.
Out of those women, those are the case
women,
168 of them tested positive on this test.
So that would make the sensitivity 84%.
Notice that there were 32 women who
falsely tested negative out of 200 cases.
The specificity is, 26% because if you
look carefully, there were 200 women who
did not have cellulite, only 52 of them
actually tested negative on this test.
So this genetic variant actually really
common.
So it's much more common to get a positive
result from this test then from a,
then to get a negative test.
But the specificity here was 26%.
In other words, there were 148 false
positives.
148 women out of the control group falsely
tested positive on this test.
So that's the sensitivity and specificity.
And if you to the company website, they
have a nice little brochure,
where they lay out the calculation of
sensitivity and specificity for you.
And they did it correctly.
What's really fun about this problem, is,
if I ask you
to calculate the positive predictive
value, it's actually a little bit tricky.
So this is a really good exercise, I
think, because if I just give you
the data in the two by two table, when I
give this to students and I say,
calculate the positive predictive value,
everybody's tempted to say, oh well,
there were 316 people who tested positive,
168 of them actually have cellulite.
So that's the positive predictive value.
That is in fact incorrect, okay?
So why is that not correct?
It's, keep in mind, the study design here.
This is a case controlled study.
So the prevalence of the condition, of
having moderate to severe cellulite,
is different in the study sample, than it
is in the general population.
And remember, positive predictive value
depends on the prevalence of disease.
So we have to factor in, the actual
prevalence of the disease in the general
population here in order to calculate
positive predictive value, for this test.
So that's a little tricky.
To the company's credit if you go read
their little brochure they say,
oh well they knew they had to incorporate
the actual prevalence.
They must have a statistician involved.
So they say, oh yeah we used Bayes' rule
to calculate it.
So indeed they used Bayes' rule to
incorporate the true prevalence of
cellulite in the population.
So, that's a great example of where Bayes'
Rule can be useful.
So let's actually do this.
Let's use Bayes' Rule to calculate the
positive predictive value,
incorporating the true prevalence of
cellulite in the population.
So the company said that the true
prevalence of moderate cellulite in
women was 65%.
That sounds reasonable to me, so we'll
assume that's, that's reasonable.
So now we can use Bayes' Rule to
incorporate that.
Notice that that's higher then in case
control study where's its only 50%.
So, let's, here's how we would apply
Bayes' rule.
We want to know the positive predictive
value.
We want to know the probability that you
will get moderate to severe cellulite,
if you test positive on this test.
Well, we can just apply Bayes' rule here,
so
that's going to be equal to the posit,
probability of testing positive,
given that you actually are a woman who's
going to get cellulite,
times the marginal probability of getting
cellulite, that's the prevalence in
the population, over the marginal
probability of testing positive at all.
Alright.
So what's the probability that you're
going to test positive given that you are
positive?
Well, that's the sensitivity of the test.
We just saw that that was 84%.
What's the margin of probability of having
moderate to severe cellulite?
The company just told us that that's 65%
in the general population,
so that's where we're incorporating that
number.
What's the marginal probability of testing
positive?
Well, there are two ways you could test
positive.
You could be one of those of 65% of women,
who actually has moderate to severe
cellulite, or
is going to get it and, your chance of
testing positive is 84%, the sensitivity.
Or, you can be one of the 35% of women,
who is not destined to get moderate to
severe cellulite.
Your chance of testing positive on this
test is actually 74%.
That's 1 minus the specificity.
Remember the specificity was 26%.
That means the false positive rate is 74%.
So that's the marginal probability of
testing positive.
When you add that up, it comes out to be
.805 in our denominator.
So, we can put all these numbers together.
So .84, times 0.65, that's equal to
.546 we divide that by the denominator of
.805,
we get that the positive predictive value
is 67.8%.
All right, so the, the company calculated
that,
in their literature, now in their
marketing material, they rounded that up,
so they said, oh, your, the, the actual
probability that you're going to
get moderate to severe cellulite if you
test positive is 60, it's about 68%.
Well they said, they rounded that up to
approximately 70%.
They were trying to boost it, make it
look, just look a little bit better.
Okay.
Now notice that that's an application of
Bayes' Rule.
For those of you who are more comfortable
using the tree, which most students
are when they first start this material,
you could also do this on the tree.
So let me just quickly show you how to do
it on the tree.
So, and then I'm going to show you how to
do it using a 2 by 2 table.
I'm going to give you many ways to get the
right answer.
And remember, with probability there's
many ways to get the right answer.
Some are more efficient than others.
Some are, are better for when you're
learning.
So, the first thing is, your either one of
these women get destined to
get the cellulite or you're not.
That's 65% prevalence and 1 minus 65% is
35%, so
that's whether or not you truly have the
disease.
Then, you are either going to test
positive on this CelluliteDX test or not.
If you actually have the disease, the
sensitivity again is 84%,
so your chance of not testing positive is
16%.
If you don't have the disease, you still
have a 74% chance of testing positive, and
you have a 26% chance of not testing
positive.
We can multiply across the branches, so
the upper branch is .546, this one is
.104.
This one is .259, this one is .091.
I just got those by multiplying across the
branches.
Notice if I add all these up, it sums up
to exactly 1, so I've done it right.
So now, once I know that you've tested
positive, I,
then I know that you're either on this
branch, or your on this branch.
So once you know you tested positive,
you're on one of those branches, which of
those is actually having cellulite?
Only the top branch.
So the probability that you're actually
going to get the disease,
given that you tested positive in this
case,
will be .546 divided by .259, plus .546,
and that again, comes out to be 67.8%.
So you can solve it
this way if you're more comfortable still
with the tree, and Bayes' Rule.
And I'm going to show you even one more
way to solve it.
So alternatively we can use a little trick
with 2 by 2 tables, and
a lot of students find it easier to
calculate it in this way, so if you're
more comfortable with a 2 by 2 table, this
is yet another way to get this right.
So, to solve for positive predictive and
negative predictive value,
you could incorporate the true prevalence
by just doing a little 2 by 2 table and
assuming that you have a denominator of
100 people.
Why a hundred, why am I picking a hundred
here?
Well, it's easy to deal with percentages.
If you treat them as whole numbers, so if
we start with 100 people,
then all the percentages just become whole
numbers.
So, for example, rather than talking about
65%, or
35%, I can say if I have a hundred women
in the general population,
65 of them would have cellulite, and 35
would not have cellulite, right, so
I can set it out this way, and make it
super easy to do these calculations.
Then you can apply the sensitivity and
specificity to figure out how many of
them are going to test positive and test
negative.
So, for example, we start with the
prevalence of the disease and
then we know, out of the 65 women who have
the disease, 84% of them
are going to correctly test positive, so
we can fill in that cell with a 55.
Out of the 35 women who truly do not have
the disease,
only 26% of them, that's a specificity,
are going to test negative.
So we're going fill in that cell with a 9
there.
Then you can just subtract.
Now we have enough information to be able
to fill in rest of the cells.
So for example, 65 minus 55 is 10.
35 minus 9 will get us to 24, 26.
So we can fill in all of those cells.
So now we have enough information.
We have the correct prevalence of the
disease in a population to
calculate positive predictive value
directly from the 2 by 2 table.
And again, maybe students find it easier
to do it this way, because dealing with
whole numbers is always easier than
dealing with fractions and probabilities.
So what will the positive predictive value
be?
There are 81 women who will test positive,
out of a sample of 100 women.
Out of that, those 81,
55 of them will truly go on to get
moderate to severe cellulite.
So the positive predictive value here is
68%,
the same 68% we calculated in two other
ways.
What's the negative predictive value?
The negative predictive value, we would
calculate by recognizing that there
are 19 women in the general population who
will get a negative on this test.
Of those 19, only nine of them will go on
to not get cellulite.
Ten of them will actually go on to get
cellulite.
So, the negative predictive value here, is
47%.
So 47% of those who test negative, will
not get cellulite.
In other words,
now remember that the company, rounded
that up to 50% when they reported it.
So they said, 50% of those who test
negative will not get cellulite.
So they're doing a little rounding again,
in their favor to look it,
make it look more interesting.
In other words, though, another way to say
it, rather than putting it negative
predictive value, which is probably a
little bit more difficult for most people
to understand, the better way to say it
would be that 53% will get cellulite.
So in other words, if you test negative
for
this test, you still have a 53% chance of
going on to get cellulite.
So, just to summarize here, if you don't
take the test,
your chance of getting moderate to severe
cellulite is 65%, right,
because that's the prevalence, the risk of
the disease in the general population.
So, if you don't take the test, you have a
65% chance.
Let's say you take the test.
If you take the test, four out of five
women who take the test are actually
going to test positive, and if you take
the test and you find out you're positive,
your risk moves from 65%, just barely a
little bit to 68%.
So, most women are going to find out their
risk moved up just a tiny 3%.
One out of the five women will test
negative.
Because their,
this is just has to do with the prevalence
of the particular genetic variant.
It's pretty rare.
If you test negative, then your risk goes
down from 65%, down to 53%.
So it moves slightly more down 12% but
still is not that different than
just your risk to begin with your prior
probability, it's not changed that much.
So, our conclusion would be then, the test
is basically useless, and
barely moves your probability from just
what, what your prior probability,
your starting probability was and most of
it are going to get, test positive an, and
their prior probability basically doesn't
change at all.
So, it's not the most useful test in the
world but
it's a really fun example for illustrating
diagnostic testing and Bayes' Rule.
And just to conclude this module, again,
sensitivity and specificity don't depend
on the prevalence of the disease, but
positive predicative value and
negative predicative value do depend on
the prevalence.
So make sure that you're always
incorporating that correctly as we
did in the example today.
And finally, this genetic variant was
significantly associated with cellulite,
there was a significant association there.
You can see from the example today though,
that that doesn't mean just
because something is significantly
associated, that it, that doesn't mean
that it's going to make a useful screening
test, so I'd keep that in mind.
[BLANK_AUDIO]