>> Hi, welcome to unit three.
Today we're going to introduce you to SAS
procedures.
There's two main types of code in SAS.
We already showed you how to use data
steps,
which manage data one row at a time.
>> Now we'll show you to use proc steps,
also knows as procedures.
These make changes to the data set one
column at a time.
Procedures carry out all the forms of
statistical analysis that we'll be
covering in HRP 223.
Let's start by taking a look at a simple
procedure called Proc means.
>> Proc steps always begin with the word
Proc, which is short for procedures.
And then, it's followed by the name of the
specific procedure you're using.
In this case, we're using the means
procedure.
This is followed by specification of what
data set you want to work on.
Proc means, will take the numerical mean
of a column you specify in a data set
of your choice.
Here, we'll work with the same [UNKNOWN]
data set we created last time.
>> Var is used to specify which column, or
variable you want to work on.
Here, we specifically say, we want to
focus on the variable weight.
And calculate the column mean.
If you don't specify which variable to use
in the SAS code,
you will automatically get results for
all the variable that are relevant to the
type of analysis you are performing.
Just like in data steps, proc steps must
always end with a run statement.
Let's run this code and take a look at the
output.
>> As you can see, proc means, gives a few
bits of information by default.
You can see the sample size, N,
the mean, standard deviation, minimum and
maximum values.
In general, procedures and SAS have some
default output.
But you can specify exactly what
information you want to see.
And you can specify additional options for
doing more things with the data.
We're going to show that to you in the
next few modules while going through some
important procedures that you'll need to
use in your data analysis.
>> Before moving on, just a quick note on
syntax.
There are a lot of different commands, and
a ton of proxy to use in SAS.
You will soon learn that each command will
have its own syntax.
It can be a bit hard to remember the
syntax for
each proxy you use, especially the ones
you don't use that often.
Lucky for us, SAS is a really thorough
online documentation.
>> When you are not sure about the syntax,
or you do not know what statement to use,
just search SAS and the name of the proc
you are using.
Go to the link on support.sas.com.
On the left, you can see a list of all the
statements that are valid for
your proc of interest and on the right,
you'll see an explanation of the syntax
for each statement.
You'll find this documentation to be
really useful,
as you start to use more procedures in
your data analysis.