Question one is asking about the amount of
exercise that student with ID number 2
reported in the survey.
And the first thing were going to do is
find student number 2 and
that would be right here in the left hand
side.
So all of the values in this row, belong
to student number 2, okay.
So I'm just going to highlight that right
here, and
then, of course, the question's asking you
about exercise.
And so the exercise variable's right here.
And we see that the value for student 2 is
zero hours of exercise per week.
This questions asking about which one of
these variables are a,
is a continous variable and the answer of
course is age at first birth.
This is the only continous variable in the
list.
Favorite fruit, gender, and occupation are
all categorical variables.
Okay, these are nominal variables because
they're classifying responses into
different categories.
Decade of birth is an ordinal variable
because it is categorizing with an order.
That is there's a relationship between
each subsequent group.
And so, we call that a nominal excuse me,
an ordinal variable.
This next question is asking us about to
pick the categorical variable, and
specifically the nominal.
Variable as opposed to the ordinal
variable.
Okay, so a nominal variable does not have
an order inherent to it.
Whereas an ordinal variable does.
And so of course the answer here is
favorite fruit, okay?
So strawberries, bananas, oranges.
These don't have an order to them.
And so they can be considered, or
rather this favorite fruit category can be
considered a nominal variable.
Now if the question had asked you which
one was an ordinal variable?
You would pick decade of birth, because
decade of birth would categorize you
into different buckets but these buckets
would have a relationship.
They would be in a certain order so that
would be an ordinal variable.
BMI, age at first birth and
height, of course would be categorized as
continuous variables.
And that's due to the nature of the
responses for each of those choices.
This question shows us a histogram for
pulse rates.
And it's specifically asking us what
percentage of
subjects had pulses between 80 and 90%.
Or excuse me, 80 and 90 beats per minute.
And so we going to, we're going to look at
the histogram.
All right, and we're going to think about
the cumulative percentage between 80,
which is right here, and 90, which is
about here.
Okay its half way between 80 100 and so
we're going to ball part this.
Because these are all basically below 10
and
these look like they might be even below
5.
You can make an adequate guess and
say that the closest answer to this is e
10 percent.
It's definitely not 200%, 100%, 90% and
it's probably not 50%.
Just because 13.3 is up here and so if you
can imagine stacking this bar on top
of here and all these small bars on top
and even really reaching that 13.3%.
As a review, I'd like to just point out
that this is a left skewed distribution.
So a left skewed distribution means that
the mean is going to be
less than the median.
So the mean is going to fall somewhere
around here,
the median is probably going to be
somewhere around here.
This question shows us another histogram,
this histogram shows the percentage of
students.
In buckets of sleep hours per night.
So the statistical program,
bend the number of sleep hours per night
into these categories for us.
And so let's take a look at the question.
So it's asking us to pick the true
statement.
A is asking or
A is stating more than half of the
students slept seven hours per night.
Looking quickly at the diagram, we see
that so
more than seven hours would be everything
to the right of this line.
And that's not more than 50%, so we know a
is not true.
B states that more than half of the
students slept between 6.5 and
7.5 hours per night.
And so, that would, that category of
students is actually just this bar okay?
And that is above 50 and so b here is the
correct answer.
But lets go through the rest of the answer
choices just to make sure that they
are also force, c reads, at least one
student slept 10 or more hours per night.
There's no one in the 10 category so we
know that's false.
And D reads 25% of students slept six
hours or fewer per night.
Looking at six or fewer we see that this,
it would be this percentage plus this
percentage.
So, right here.
These two blocks together would need to
reach somewhere around here, and
sort of visually, by visual inspection, we
see that that's not true.
So this question gives us a list of
numbers, and asks us to
calculate the median value within this set
of numbers, this set of 20 numbers.
So this is one of those tedious problems
where you have to actually order
the numbers the right way in order to
calculate the median value.
So that's what I'm going to do first.
So, [COUGH] going to write this at the
bottom here.
I'm actually
going to stop
there.
So, let's think about this.
So, There are 20 numbers, and so the
median value is going to be between
number 10, the average of number 10, so,
like, number 10 and number 11.
So this is going to equal the median.
And I know that because there are 20
numbers here.
So I just need to figure out what the 10th
and
11th numbers to then calculate their
average.
So this is 1, this is 2, this 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, 8, 9, 10 and 11.
And so the average of course of negative
12 and
negative 14 is going to be negative 13.
So the median value in this set of numbers
Is negative 13.
So this question is asking us about left
skewed data.
And it's asking us to pick the true
statement.
So as a review, left skewed data would
look something like this.
Where the tail on the left-hand side is a
lot longer.
And what this is going to do to the
distribution is it's going to shift
the mean to the left, okay?
The mean is going to go left.
So the mean might be somewhere around
here.
The median Might be somewhere around here.
Just for completeness sake, the mode would
be the top of the histogram.
The distribution of the histogram, and so
which statement accurately captures this
relationship?
Well, that's going to be statement d.
Where the median is going to be greater
than the mean.
So one trick when remembering when trying
to remember left-skewed right-skewed and
stuff like that is to remember this exact
relationship.
If it's left-skewed the median is to the
left excuse me,
the mean is to the left of the median.
And if it's right-skewed the mean is to
the right of the median.
Okay, so you can think about it as
describing a relationship between the mean
and the median.
And then you'll be able to sort of
intuitively imagine the distribution in
your head to answer these questions.
This question is asking us to calculate
the standard deviation of
the following numbers that we have in our
data set.
And to round our final answer to the
nearest whole number.
And so the first step Is to remember what
the formula for the standard deviation is.
And so I'll start off by writing that out,
so that is SD, for
standard deviation equals the square root
of the sum on top, that's an i there.
Of X sub I, minus the mean squared, over N
minus 1.
Okay, so that looks complicated, but
basically we need to figure out two
things.
In order to calculate this formula, we
need to figure out what n is, and
what this x bar is.
X bar is the average.
So first things first.
So n is probaby easiest.
So n is just the number the number of
numbers.
I guess in our data set, so that's going
to be one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, so that's going to be ten.
Okay, so n is ten.
And then we calculate the average here.
So that's just going to be 4 plus 3 plus 0
plus dot, dot,
dot, all the way to negative 300, divided
by N or ten, same thing.
And that's going to work itself out to be
negative 34.5.
So here we have the average and we have N
and what we can do is
replace these in the formula and so I'm
going to write This in, so n is now ten.
And so it's x minus negative 34.5.
And that's the same thing as x of i plus
34.5.
So you might be wondering to yourself,
what is this x of i,
what is this summation doing here?
I think the easiest way to explain it is
to,
is to write out the first A few terms
here.
Okay, so what is this saying?
So it's saying, we'll take the first
number in your data set when i equals one.
So that's going to be four, and then add
34.5, square that.
Okay, and
because this is the summation, here
because we're summing in this expression.
What we're going to do is going to add,
and
that we're going to move on to the next
number in your dataset.
Which is going to be 3, okay, I you can
imagine i, e being equal to 2 now.
So accept 2 or 3 plus 34.5 squared, plus
again,
because of the summation, 0 plus 34.5
squared.
Okay, and we're going to do that all the
way
until negative 300 plus 34.5 squared,
okay?
So that takes care of the numerator.
And then on the bottom we're just going to
have 10 minus 1, which is 9.
And, if we do this all out, that is going
to equal 94.
And so, the answer to this question is a
94.
So in this question, we're asked to
calculate the standard deviation again,
and round our final answer to the nearest
whole number.
'Kay, so it's very similar.
It's the same thing as the last question,
so it's good practice for us.
So once again, the first step Is to write
out the formula for
the standard deviation, and that hasn't
changed since last time.
So, that's going to be the square root of
the sum of x
sub i minus the average, squared over n
minus 1.
And so once again, we need to know two
things.
We need to know n and we need to know the
average.
So, n here's going to be a I have a
feeling it's going to be 10 again, 6, 9,
10 yeah.
So n is 10, and I got that just by
counting the numbers here and then the
average is
going to be negative 8 plus negative 10
etcetera.
Until negative 30, divide by 10.
Okay, and the average this time is going
to equal negative 18.5.
So now that we have these two values once
again we can rewrite our formula by
substituting those va numbers in.
So again This is just going to be the same
thing as adding 18.5 here.
So, I'm going to write the first few terms
once again.
So this is going to be negative 8 plus
18.5 squared.
Plus negative 10 plus 18.5 squared all the
way to
the last number in our data set.
Let me just drag that over, all divided by
9, okay?
And the standard deviation in this case is
going to equal 7, so
the answer to this problem is e, 7.
This problem asks us to calculate the
interquartile range given the follow data
points, the first thing you should notice
is that the data is arranged.
For us is already sorted in descending
order which is great because it means we
don't have to do that.
That would otherwise be the first step.
So now, what are we going to do.
Well, our approach to these types of
problems is going to first, is going to be
to first find the median, okay, which
represents the 50th percentile.
And then let's say that's the edge of our
data set, and that's the edge of
our data set, (no period) And then, to
find the middle, okay?
So that's going to be the 75th percentile,
and then to move this way.
To find the middle, the median,
essentially, between here and
here, to find the 25th percentile.
Okay, great and of course we're doing that
because the interquartile range is defined
as the value of the 75th percentile minus
the value of the 25th percentile.
So lets take a look at the data.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
eight, nine, ten, okay, always ten.
So there's ten values here.
Which means the median is going to be the
average of negative four and
negative five.
So median is going to be negative 4.5.
But that's less important right now.
What's more important is to sort of
visualize Is this sort of
middle 50th percentile line here.
Right, and what we're going to do,
is we're going to find, we're going to
move left, starting here.
We're going to move we're going to move
right starting here, move left
starting here, find the middle value, the
median of this subset of numbers.
And that's going to be negative 14.
Doing the same thing here the median is
going to be zero within that subset, okay?
What that's going to allow us to do is to
say that, okay,
this is the 75th percentile, this is the
25th percentile,
the IQR is simply 0 minus negative 14 or
14.
So the answer to this question is c, 14.
This question asks us to select the
statistical measure that
does not describe the spread of the data.
Our choices are variance, interquartile
range, the Standard deviation, the range,
and the mean.
So of these choices the mean is the only
choice that does not
describe the spread of the data.
All the other choices, the the variance,
IQR, the standard deviation,
the range give some kind of information
about the distribution of the data and
how its spread out.
The mean is a summary statistic, so
it does not give us any information about
the spread.
This last question is asking us to choose
the statistical measure that
is not influenced by outliers.
Our choices are the variance, the
interquartile range,
the standard deviation, the range, and the
mean.
The only value here that is not influenced
by outliers is
the interquartile range, okay?
The variance, the standard deviation, the
range and the mean will all be affected.
Let's say if you change one of your
numbers,
one of the values in your data set from
something like 30 to 300.
You can imagine that all those statistical
measures are going to be affected in
some way.
Now the inner quartile range in this
situation is not going to be affected if
30 is, let's say, already above the 75th
percentile.
Let's say 30's in the 80th percentile in
your data.
And you change that 30 to 300, okay?
Well that's not going to affect the
calculation of the interquartile.
Because that's only 75,
the 75th quartile minus the 25th quartile
it doesn't change what the numbers are.
Okay, so another way to phrasing this,
another way to think about this is.
That the interquartile range is more
dependent on how the numbers in your
dataset are ranked.
And the other values the other statistical
measures presented
here are more dependent on the magnitude
of the values in your data set.