So if the size of the effect is greater
that's going to increase your
chances of getting a significant P-value,
that's therefore going to increase your
statistical power.
If the variability of the thing you're
looking at
is higher there's more variability.
More variability is going to make it
harder to find an effect,
harder to get a significant P-value.
So that's going to decrease your
statistical power.
Bigger sample sizes, of course, are going
to increase your statistical power.
Finally, of course, we can play with the
significance level.
A typical study might set the significance
level at 0.05 but
that's not the only way you can do it.
Sometimes a significance level might be
set at something lower, like 0.01.
Well, 0.01 is going to mean your type one
error rate is lower than 0.05,and there's
a direct trade-off between type one and
type two error.
If you require a more stringent p value
cutoff, like .01
rather than .05, if you want a more, a
stronger significance of a smaller
significance level, than that's going to
actually decrease your statistical power.
It's harder to find a p value of .01 than
it is to find a p value of .05.
So that's going to decrease your
statistical power.
Notice that all of those four elements we
could put them together,
we could put those together and make a
formula that tells us how much, how
big we need to design our studies in order
to have sufficient statistical power.
If you look at all the things that affect
power, the one that's really most under
control, the control of the investigator-
Is the sample size.
The investigator can't really change the
size of the effect, or
the standard deviation, the variability.
The investigator can, change the
significance level but
there may be particular reasons that we
have to set it to .01 or .05.
So, what's really under the control of the
investigator, in
terms of influencing the statistical power
of a given study, is the sample size.
So when we plan studies, we actually sit
down,
before the study starts, and determine how
big of
a smaple size do I need in order to have a
sufficiently powered study.
Those sample size formulas are directly
related to
putting those elements together.
So, power and sample size are directly
related to one another.
And those are affected by the effect size,
the standard deviation, and the
significance level.
We can put all those five elements
together into formulas that tell us
how big of an n, how big of a sample, do I
need for
a given level of power for my study.
I'm just going to put one formula up, one
sample size formula up.
On the screen here so we can talk about
it.
I'm not expecting you to, to want to
memorize or
even use this formula at this point.
If you want to know more about sample size
formulas,
like the sample size calculation, there's
an entire optional module you
can take to learn about all the details of
this formula.
But what I really want Everybody to get
out of here,
is just the relationships between those
five elements that I just talked about.
Those five elements relate, and
you can put them together to come up with
a sample size format.
So for example, this formula says that the
sample size that you need in
each group is directly related to
variability.
The power you want, the significance level
you want, and the effect size you want.
The variability is in the numerator.
So if the outcome is more highly variable,
then for
a given power, you're going to need a
greater sample size to achieve that power.
The n is going to be bigger because,
variability is in the numerator.
Z beta is how we abbreviate power.
If you want a bigger power,
if you want a power more than 80%, you're
going to need a bigger n.
So, again, power is in the numerator.
You're going to need a bigger n if you
want more power.
If you change your significance level to
be more stringent.
Say, again 0.05 down to 0.01.
If you want a higher level of statistical
significance, then that's in
the numerator too, so you're again,
going to need a bigger sample size.
However, if the effect size is bigger, if
it, if the effect size in the real world,
the true effect is bigger, that's in the
denominator.
So to find a bigger effect size, you
actually need a smaller sample size.
If the effect size is big, it's going to
take less people in your study to find it.
So we can plug in some numbers, some
assumptions into a formula like this.
And come out with the approximate sample
size that we need in our study to
have sufficient power.
Again if you want more details about the
exact derivation of
this sample size formula and formulas like
it you
can refer to the optional module on sample
size calculation.