This first question is asking about the
primary benefit of randomization, and
the answer here is c.
Randomization is beneficial because it
minimizes confounding.
Okay.
It doesn't improve patient
recruitment really.
In fact, it might detract from it,
because patients have to agree to be
randomized to either arm in the study.
It doesn't reduce costs really, and it
doesn't serve to prevent recall bias.
The primary point of randomization is to
ensure that
confounders are balanced between the
different arms of a study.
This second question is asking about a key
benefit of
cohort studies both prospective and
retrospective.
The key advantage in cohort studies is
that the risk factors are measured before
you know the outcome, okay, and that's in
contrast to case control studies.
You recall that in case control studies
one of the weaknesses is
recall bias that is a differential memory
of exposures based on,
what group you are in whether you are a
case or a control.
Cohort studies don't avoid confounding.
They usually last longer than randomized
trials.
Especially prospective ones prospective
cohort studies and
they may involve loss to followup because
of this reason.
Primarily they take so long to occur.
So really the answer here is that
risk factors are measured before the
outcome has occurred.
The absolute, absolute key benefit of a
case
control study is that they allow us to
study very rare diseases.
You can imagine that if you're designing a
cohort study for this answer, and
you know that it's a rare disease, you're
going to need a massive number of
people enrolled in your study to generate
a few outcomes, just because it's rare.
Right?
With a case control study you can
basically cherry-pick your cases.
You can select the diseases.
And then match those patients on specific
controls.
That you define in your study design and
so,
that's really the key distinguishing
benefit between case control studies and
cohort studies and really other, other
study designs.
So, in this question we are presented with
a situation where 1,000 women
are enrolled for half a year and ten women
in that cohort developed breast cancer.
The question is asking us what the
incidence rate for that breast cancer was.
So first, what we want to do is calculate
the appropriate years of follow up.
And so what that's going to be is we're
going to multiply 1.000 times 0.5, okay.
So that's going to be 500 years of
follow-up.
And then we have, over that time, we have
10 cases,
so that's 10 over 500 which is equal to 1.
Over 50 or 2 eventers per 100 woman years.
Okay, so the answer in this case is going
to be d.
So in this question, we're presented with
a similar situation 1000
women are followed for half a year, 10
develop breast cancer.
This question's asking for the cumulative
risk of breast cancer.
So what we're going to do here is make
this a fraction.
So you have 10 cases over 1,000 women.
So the cumulative risk in this cohort is
1%, it's b.
So what's important to note here is that
cumulative risk does not
take time into account which is why we can
perform this calculation like we did.
The correct answer in this case is c.
The prevalence is the sort of measure of
the [INAUDIBLE] frequency.
I guess that can be calculated from a
cross section of studies.
You can't calculate the incidence rate,
you can calculate the cumulative risk.
But you can calculate the prevalence from
cross sectional designs and
they're often actually used, for that
purpose.
In case control studies, you can not
calculate disease frequency,
because you don't know the greater picture
of the population.
Because we're only selecting a certain
number of cases out of
an unknown amount of cases.
We do not know the disease frequency.
The answer to this question is true.
When it's possible to calculate both the
rate difference and the risk difference
the rate difference is preferred because
it's a more precise measure.
This statement is false, it's a little bit
tricky.
So the number needed to treat or harm is
actually the reciprocal of
the difference in disease rates, not the
difference in disease risks.
This statement is true.
One cannot calculate risk difference, rate
differences, or
the number needed to treat, or harm from a
case control study, right?
And so the case, in a case control study,
the researcher picks the cases.
And so you do not know anything about the
frequency of cases.
Because the, your study isn't reflective
of the general population.
The answer to this question is c.
Rate ratios and risk ratios are not always
equal.
So the reason for this is that risk ratios
could differ if
the groups being compared were followed
for differing amounts of time.
This is rare but it does happen.
If disease rates are identical in two
groups the cumulative risks will
differ if one group is followed for
longer.
But again, that's sort of a rare situation
in reality when that happens.
This question asks what are the odds that
correspond to a risk of 60% so,
if you remembered what the definition of
an odds is,
it's simply the probability over one minus
the probability.
So, if the risk or the probability is 60%,
that's going to be 60% over one minus 40%,
and that is going to be equal to b, 3 over
2.
So this question presents us a situation
40% of
our treated group has a positive response
versus just 10% placebo group.
What is the risk ration and odds ratio?
The risk ratio is the more straight
forward one to calculate,
here it's giving us a probability of 40%
having a positive response to
the treat group versus a probability of
10% here, so that is going to be 4.
The odds ratio, right, if you remember the
odds is defined as p over 1 minus p.
So that's going to be let's say 40% over
60%, so
100% minus 40% divided by 10% over 90%,
that is going to give us 6.
So the answer here is b.
The next question is asking us,
which of the following is not a measure of
relative risk?
And the answer here is d, number needed to
treat.
Everything else is a ratio.
Okay, so everything else is a measure of
relative risk.
It's a relative risk against some
reference group.
And so, the answer here is d,
number needed to treat is not a measure of
any relative risk.
So this question's a bit tricky so let's
talk it through.
So, in a cross-sectional study about sleep
quality and duration and
hypertension, researchers found that about
25% of normal sleepers had hypertension.
They also found that insomniacs were
significantly more likely to
have hypertension than normal sleepers.
The odds ratio for this association was
5.12.
It's asking us to pick the correct
statement.
So the correct statement here is c,
insomniacs with short duration have a
5-fold higher odds of having hypertension,
which corresponds to a 2 and a half fold
higher risk.
And the calculation for that will be shown
one your screen.
So that's RR for relative risk equals
5.12.
That's the odds ratio times 1 minus 0.25.
ta, plus 0.25 times 5.12 times 5.12 right,
is the odds ratio.
0.25 represents the probability in the
reference group
that's given in the question stem when it
says that
researchers Found about 25% of normal
sleepers had hypertension.
So, using this formula, we can calculate
that the relative risk is about 2.5.
You can rule out option d, because of this
and you can rule out A and B.
Because odds ratios give relative changes
in odds and not risk.
So, in this situation, we're presented
with a situation in
which the rate of premenopausal breast
cancer is about 30
out of 100,000 women per year in those who
have never used oral contraceptives.
One study estimated that the relative risk
of breast cancer for
users versus non-users is 1, is
approximately 1.2.
What is the corresponding absolute rate
difference?
So, the first thing we want to do is
calculate the absolute rate in
oral contraceptive users.
Okay and the way I'm going to do that is
I'm going to take 30 out of 100,000.
And multiply that by 1.19, which is the
relative risk.
Okay.
So I'm taking the rate of
premenopausal breast cancer in those who
have never used oral contraceptives.
Multiplying that by the relative risk, to
get the risk for
women who use oral contraceptives.
So that's going to give me about
36 cases per 100,000 women years.
Okay.
So then the absolute rate difference is
going to be 36 minus 30, so
about 6 cases per 100,000 years, and that
corresponds to c.
So, in this question, we're presented with
the same scenario.
We have a a rate.
So, 30 out of 100,000 woman per year for
developing breast cancer and
those women who've never used oral
contraceptives.
And we're also given a relative risk like
before but
this time we're asked to calculate the
number needed to harm.
So in order to do that, we're going to use
a result from the previous question.
So if you remember all we did was multiply
1.19 with this rate to get the absolute
rate of premenopausal breast cancer and
those who have used oral contraceptives.
So that was worked out to be 36 cases per
1000 women, I'm sorry 100,000 women, and
then the absolute rate difference is 36
cases per 100,000 women minus 30 cases per
100,000 women.
So the absolute difference was worked
out to be 6 cases per 100,000 women.
[COUGH] And so,
the number needed to harm is simply the
reciprocal Of this relationship.
Okay.
So the reciprocal of this.
So the number needed to harm can be
calculated
by dividing 100,000 over 6, to give us
16.667 or 16,667.
16,667 rather, and so our answer here is
b.