In this next module,
I'm going to show you the distribution of
some common statistics.
A mean, an odds ratio, and a correlation
coefficient.
In order to illustrate all of these, I'm
going to use some example data.
Some made up hypothetical data.
These are actually computer generated
data.
I have the computer generate some data,
and
it's loosely based on a real example in
the literature.
About that, that study was looking at
middle age and
older European men, and it was looking at
Vitamin D levels and cognitive function.
So I loosely based my made up data on that
study.
But it's just nice to have some toy data
play with this week.
There's 2 statistics that we're going to
look at from my hypothetical data.
I chose a sample of 100, so my sample size
here is 100 in my hypothetical data.
We're going to look at the Vitamin D
levels in those 100 men.
And we're going to look at the correlation
between Vitamin D and
cognitive function in those 100 men.
And cognitive function was measured by a
particular test,
the Digit Symbol Substitution Test.
And for the purposes of generating this
made-up data,
I assumed that the true mean vitamin D in
all middle-aged and
older European men is somewhere around 62
nanomoles per liter, and
the true correlation coefficient between
vitamin D and IQ function.
The cognitive function was 0.15, which was
a very weak correlation.
So let me just illustrate for you this
hypothetical, made-up data.
So, in the sample, I have a sample of a
100 men, and
I've got their vitamin D levels.
And I've plotted those vitamin d levels
here in histogram.
So, notice that the vitamin D levels in
the sample follow a right
skew distribution.
That makes sense for
something like vitamin D because you can't
get lower than zero.
But, you know, vitamin D can get quite
high in a handful of people.
So you get this tail up to the right.
The mean vitamin D turned out to be 63
nanomoles per liter in my sample.
And the standard deviation was 33
nanomoles per liter.
Here's a graph showing the correlation
between the vitamin D levels and
this cognitive test, the DSST score higher
values on
that cognitive test mean that are
cognitive function.
You can see that there's a small, very
weak,
positive correlation between vitamin D
levels and cognitive score.
And I built this into my made up data, a
very small weak correlation here.
You can actually calculate a statistic
that quantifies that correlation.
It's called the correlation coefficient
and
it comes out here to be a value of 0.15.
Some of you may have heard of correlation
[INAUDIBLE] coefficients before.
If you haven't, a correlation coefficient
is this nice little measure because its
unit less.
Its a value that ranges from negative one
to positive one.
If you're at zero or
somewhere close to zero, that means those
two variables are uncorrelated.
You're measuring the correlation between
two variables.
So zero would mean uncorrelated.
Positive 1 would be perfect positive
correlation.
Negative 1 would mean perfect inverse
correlation, that is that if vitamin D
levels went up and cognitive function went
down, and anything in between positive one
and zero or negative one and zero is some
kind of in between amount of correlation.
So 0.15 is pretty close to zero so it's a
small, it's a very weak correlation.
But the correlation coefficient in the
sample of
a hundred came out to be 0.15 here.
So how would I figure out, what's the
distribution of the mean here?
So we're going to use the mean Vitamin D
as my example.
What's the distribution of the mean?
How can I figure that out?
Well, I'm first going to figure it out by
running a computer simulation.
So, here's how the computer simulation
works.
I'm going to tell the computer that
there's some
large population of men European men.
And I'm going to tell the computer the
distribution of vitamin D in
this large population.
And I'm going to tell the computer it's a
right skewed distribution.
So vitamin D follows a right skewed
distribution.
It has a standard deviation of 33.
And let's say that the true mean value in
the the population is 62 [INAUDIBLE]
nanomoles per liter.
It doesn't matter too much what I pick
there.
But lets say I'm going to pick the value
of 62.
So I tell the computer, this is the
population you're sampling from.
And then I have the computer sample a
random sample of
100 virtual men from this underlying
population.
Each of those men is going to have a
vitamin D level.
I take those vitamin D levels and I
average them to calculate the mean.
Vitamin D level for that sample of 100.
Then I'm going to repeat the experiment
over and over and over again.
Again this is the though experiment.
I'm going to select a different random
sample of 100 men, calculate their mean.
Then I'm going to do that again and
again and again, to get a sense of the
distribution of the means.
I've arbitrarily decided to do that 10,000
times.
Again, 10,000's a pretty large number but
not so large that it will hang my
computer.
Then, then we can explore the distribution
of those 10,000 means.
We can actually look at the distribution
of the statistic here and
the statistic here is a sample mean.
[SOUND] So here's the results of this
computer simulation.
What you are looking at is the histogram.
On the Y axis is the count.
Out of 10,000 times, how much did
different outcomes, different means occur.
On the X axis is the mean vitamin D level.
So this represents the mean out of 100
men, and in each sample of a hundred men.
So you can see that most often we got a
mean of about 62,
somewhere around 62, because remember the
true mean in the population is 62.
So that's not surprising.
What else can we say about this
distribution?
Well, you might have noticed, and
this might have surprised you, that it
turns out to be normal distribution.
The means follow a normal distribution.
This is a little surprising because
remember, Vitamin D,
the trait followed a right skewed
distribution.
The, that distribution, that underlying
distribution is right skewed.
But, when we take the means, the means
follow a normal distribution.
And we can prove this with a theorem
called the central limit theorem.
For those of you who are interested in
that,
there's an optional module on the central
limit theorem.
But it turns out that when you take
averages,
averages follow a normal distribution.
Conceptually, what's going here is
you can image your on this right skew
distribution.
There's going to be a very few number of
people who have very high values.
So you might get a man in a particular
sample who has a value of 200 for example.
Well if you average that 200 in with 99
other men,
that has the effect of bringing everything
towards the center.
So that 200 really gets diluted, because
you averaged it with 99 other men.
So it ends up when you take averages, it
ends
up bringing everything towards the middle
and it ends up forming a normal curve.
The mean of the means, I'm going to say
that again, the mean of the means,
that's the, this is the mean of the means
we're talking about here.
The mean of the means turned out to be 62
nanomoles per liter.
Well, that's just the true value, the true
mean, so that's not surprising.
The mean of the means is the true mean in
the population.
Well that makes sense because if that's
the true mean,
then most of our samples should hover
around 62, the true mean.
The standard deviation of the means turns
out to be 3.3 nanomoles per liter.
Now that's interesting, you remember that
the, the standard deviation of the trait
was 33 nanomoles per liter [SOUND] but the
standard deviation of the means which we
also called the standard error of the mean
turns out to be 3.3.
It's exactly 33 divided by 10.
Well, the sample size here was 100, so
what we're actually doing is,
we're dividing the standard deviation by
the square root of n, and
that's what gives us the 3.3.
This 3.3, I didn't get by a mathematical
theory though.
I just had the computer calculate the
standard deviation from these
10,000 observations.
And it turns out to be 3.3.
So, the distribution of mean vitamin D
that I got from this computer simulation.
I see that it's normally distributed.
The mean is equal to the true mean.
And the standard deviation, or
what we also call the standard error, is
3.3 nanomoles per liter.
I got this all out of the computer
simulation.
But the distribution of a sample mean,
in general, people have long ago worked
out with mathematical theory.
And it turns out that if you're talking
about sample means,
means that you calculate from data, they
follow,
actually they don't exactly follow a
normal distribution.
If you want to know more about why that
is,
watch the optional module on the Central
Limit Theorem.
It turns out they follow a T-distribution,
but
remember that a T-distribution is
essentially the same as a normal
distribution as long as you're talking
about n's sample sizes at least of 100.
So since we have a sample size of over
100, essentially it's,
it's on a normal distribution.
This means that if you're talking about
sample means and
you're talking about small samples,
actually small samples you have to worry
about it being on a T-distribution.
You'll have slightly fatter tails than the
normal.
So it's not exactly, means don't exactly
follow a normal distribution for
real data.
They usually follow a T but by the time
you're talking about a sample size of
greater than 100 where, where it's
interchangeable with the normal.
So I'm just going to call it a normal
distribution.
In general, sample means the mean of the
means is the true mean in the population.
Well, that make sense.
The standard error, somebody has worked
out the formula for standard error,
the standard error of a mean is the
standard deviation of the trait,
the variability of the trait like vitamin
D,
divided by the square root of n, the
number of people you're averaging over.
And let's remember,
we saw that that in fact works out with
exactly what we saw in the simulation
because the standard deviation here was 33
if I divide by the square root of 100.
I get exactly 3.3, exactly what came out
in the simulation as well.
So both the simulation and mathematical
theory are matching up.
So the standard error of a mean,
again, is the standard deviation of the
trait divided by the square root of n.
So you can see some things about how
standard error works just by
looking at the formula.
The formula gives us some insight here.
I don't, we're not worry about memorizing
the formula but
look at the formula in terms of what is it
telling us.
So standard error decreases as sample size
goes up because sample sizes in
the denominator.
So bigger sample size means less standard
error.
Well that makes sense.
As you sample more people you would expect
the uncertainty to go down,
the imprecision to go down.
The variability of the static from sample
to sample will go down if
you're sampling more people.
going to get closer to the true mean.
The standard error increases with greater
trait variability, that, that s,
that standard deviation of the sample is
in the numerator.
So if vitamin D were more variable,
that's going to cause more variation from
in the statistic.
Right?
It's going to cause more uncertainly.
So those are the two elements of standard
error.
And just to illustrate those,
I did another simulation where I increased
the sample sizes to 400.
So I did many, many, many samples of 400.
Notice to what happened to my normal
curve, it shrunk.
It, the standard deviation went down.
The standard deviation in this situation
came up to be 1.7.
My mathematical theory would predict that
it would be 1.7.
If Vitamin D was more variable, let's say
the standard deviation of Vitamin D in
the population was 40 rather than 33,
you can see that that causes this curve to
widen.
The standard error goes up here, it goes
up to four because if Vitamin D
is more variable we get more variations in
the means from sample to sample.
So standard error again depends on the the
variability of
the trait as well as the sample size.