Hi, welcome back.
In this module, we are going to show you
how to use proc univariate.
This procedure is useful for getting
descriptive statistics for
the columns in your data.
So here, we have the basic syntax for the
proc univariate.
>> Remember, you always start your code
with proc and
then the name of your procedure.
Then, you must specify the data set to
work on.
Obviously, it's the heart disease data set
I imported earlier.
In the next line of code,
you specify which variable you want to
perform your univariate analysis.
Remember, SAS procedures work on data one
column at a time.
So unless we specify something else,
SAS will run proc univariate on all of the
columns in our data set.
Let's take a look at the column for h.
Make sure to end your procedure with a run
statement.
[SOUND].
>> Now, let's run the code, and look at
the output.
As you can see,
SAS provides lots of information about the
distribution of your data.
Here, we have the sample size.
This is the number of non missing values
that proc univariate, was able to read for
the age variable.
Here, we have the Mean, Median, and Mode.
So that you have estimates for the central
tendency of your data.
proc univariate also reports, the standard
deviation.
Variants and range so you can estimate the
spread of your data.
Down here at the bottom is some
information on
the various quartiles of distribution for
age.
>> If you wanted to look at more than one
variable, we can specify that in the code.
Let's take a look at some more columns.
[SOUND].
If you scroll down through the output, you
can see the results for
each variable we listed in the code.
As you can see, we first get the output
for
the variable age, Next we get the output
for the variable CPK.
And finally we get the output for the
variable called follow up.
It will be nice if we could visualize this
data.
Let's go back into the code.
Here, we had a histogram statement.
Now, SAS will give us a histogram of our
data.
The age variable looks roughly normally
distributed.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
It looks like
these other variables aren't really that
normal.
Let's run a statistical test for
normality, to see if the age variable
actually falls in normal distribution.
As you can see, we have to specific a test
for normality and.
In the first line of code.
These kinds of options are pretty
[UNKNOWN] for this specific procedure.
So, I'll probably try the online test
documentation if I am not sure how
to enter the code.
[SOUND]
Here, the p value is greater than 0.05.
So, we can't reject the null hypothesis.
The age is normally distributed.
You'll learn about more about these Tests
of Normality in your HRP
bio-statistic courses.
But for now, just know that you can run
these tests using proc univariate.