Welcome to CSI Medical Errors or case
studies in medical errors.
My name is Dr. Steve Chen and I'm the
director of accreditation, quality and
safety at Stanford Hospital and Clinics.
I will be the presenter for the material
in this continuum medical education
program, reviewing medical error events
and lessons learned.
This program is sponsored by an education
grant provided by the Pfizer Corporation.
The objective of this three hour program
is to integrate national patient safety
goals, requirements in clinical practice
in areas of patient identification,
Universal Protocol, medication labeling,
and medication reconciliation.
Second objective is to develop practical
skills to improve team work and
communication among healthcare providers
and apply them to prevent medical errors
and at the time when medical events occur,
that is, immediate feedback.
The third objective is to evaluate root
causes and
contributing factors that lead to various
medical errors and the fourth objective is
to develop skills to apply to practice the
appropriate procedures or
steps to assure that such such events are
prevented in the future.
This course will accomplish these
objectives by
presenting four different real life case
scenarios and give you a sense of
the work that goes on behind the scenes
whenever a medical error occurs.
The goal of this course is to give you
information that you can use in
your clinical practice so that you will
minimize the chances of
having such an event happen to you and
your patients.
To start this course off,
I wanted to share a video clip from a
medical error experience.
In 1998, the institute of medicine
provided a report called,
To Err is Human, and in that report
estimated that there were
98,000 lives lost attributed to medical
error.
Without a doubt,
this is a significant healthcare issue
first publicized in this report, and
since then we have learned multiple things
associated with medical errors.
When a medical error occurs,
there are a number of other ramification
that rises as a result.
They all take one's energy or focus and
may include the following.
Disclosure to patient and or family.
Personal reputation.
Personal confidence.
Time, energy, and cost to be involved in
the follow up investigation.
Time, energy and cost to be involved in a
lawsuit.
Reporting to medical liability, licensing
and National Practitioners Data Bank.
Disclosure that will have to be done for
future faculty, hospital and
health plan application.
So, without a doubt, there are certainly
huge ramification associate whenever one
is involved in such a medical event.
The human cost, you know, when you
actually look at it, actually is enormous.
Healthcare costs have been rising for
several years.
Costs for technology, pharmaceutical,
infrastructure and
staff have been discussed at both
professional and government levels.
In the past decade, more focus has been
applied to the cost attributed to
medical errors and health care acquired
conditions.
Another factor that has not been
considered has been the human causes
associated with these events.
One would recognize the patient and
their family as having been effected by a
medical error, but
what about the second victim, which would
include the involved care providers?
Each of us clinicians go through a
training program that hopefully prepares
to deal with clinical challenges and less
than desirable outcomes.
In some cases, that may even mean dealing
with a patient's death.
The monetary side, for the second victim,
can vary significantly.
I'd been involved with such cases, such as
a patient's suicide,
where a licensed clinical social worker,
who had been working in her career for
only two years, quit the profession after
hearing what had happened to her patient.
She never returned to healthcare.
In the old days,
we used to say that a person did not have
the right stuff to do this work.
And deserved to be out of healthcare.
The reality is,
that very few of us are ever prepared to
deal with this significant patient event.
Courses like this, is here to inform you
that medical errors do occur and
may occur with such frequency that it's
inevitable sometime in your career,
a bad thing will happen to one of your
patients.
The concept of healthcare acquired
conditions or HAC are events that occur to
patients that are complications, that in
the past, have been tolerated.
Since third party and government pairs
were compensated,
the healthcare organization for additional
services provided to manage these events.
With healthcare reform, this is no longer
the case.
Hospitals that have patients develop
healthcare acquired conditions are no
longer reimbursed for those services or
days in the hospital.
Effective the day that these conditions
were identified.
The results are the following: longer
length of stay,
more patient dissatisfaction, more cost of
care,
more chances to develop additional
healthcare-acquired conditions,
more administrator costs, more external
oversight.
Organizations are not getting reimbursed.
And when you look at this particular slide
and see that a good number of these
events are not only attributed to actually
things that occur in the hospital.
There are also a huge number of items that
occur outside of the hospital.
So, at what point do we draw that line in
the sand in terms of
tolerating these events?
That if you followed the Chinese
philosopher, Lao Tzu,
if you do not change direction, you may
end up where you are heading, and
that certainly is the case for healthcare.