>> In the last module, we showed you what
a dataset looks like in SAS.
You might be wondering where that dataset
comes from.
>> That's what we'll show you today.
>> [SOUND] Your data set can come in many
different file types.
[SOUND] Often times you might get a
dataset as an Excel file,
which will have the file format .xls or
.xlsx.
Another common file type used with Excel
is a .csv file.
SAS has it's own file format for data sets
called .sas7b.
All of these file types and many more, can
be imported directly into SAS.
>> Many researchers like to use red cap to
collect their data.
We will not be discussing Red Cap and
HRP223, that being said if your data's an
online Red Cap database we can
provide you with a special program that
will let you import that into SaS as well.
>> Let's take another look at that data
set we showed you last time.
It's hard to tell what a lot of this
means, the columns have strange names and
it's hard to tell what these one's and
zero's mean.
What we need is a data dictionary.
This is basically an explanation of each
variable is, and
how the variables are encoded.
Here is what a data dictionary might look
like.
Now we can see that the variable Hospidays
represents the length of
the hospital stay measured in days.
CHF is a variable about heart failure
complications.
If his [INAUDIBLE] has complications, they
are entered as a one.
And if they didn't, they are entered as a
zero.
>> Whenever you get a data set, make sure
you also get a data dictionary, or
else you will not be able to interpret the
data.
Sometimes, people like to put a data
dictionary at the top of an Excel file.
If you can, try to open up your data set
in Excel and look at the data set and
case it as a dictionary.
We were just describing a data set in SAS
Enterprise Guide, but I want to take
step back and show you how to import your
data using the point and click method.
Even though I tend to write most of my own
code in SAS,
I still like to use the point and click
method to import data.
This method makes it easy to rename
variables, specify permanent folder, and
ensure that SAS is importing the variables
in the right format.
>> If you're using an Excel file, open it
in Excel first and
make sure that first row contains the
variable names.
Sometimes people include things like a
data dictionary, or
other comments which are not data or
variable names.
If there's any extra information, delete
it.
>> Since we're dealing with a new project
in SAS, let's open it up.
Our first step is going to be to
reestablish our permanent folder,
by pointing to the folder we created in
the previous module,
we can save the data set in a permanent
file.
First open up a new project, which we've
already done.
Paste in the code which we've also already
done,
and then point to the permanent folder.
Now, we're ready to import our Excel data
set.
>> Click on File and then Import Data.
Navigate to the file you want to import
and then click Open.
>> In the next page,
you can specify which library you wish to
import your data in to.
By default, you can save it in to the work
library.
If you'd like to save your data into a
different library,
such as a permanent library you've already
made, click Browse to find that library.
We're going to save our data into the
HRP223 library we just made.
Select a library and then click Save.
When you're done specifying your library,
click Next.
>> If you're importing data from an Excel
file with multiple worksheets,
you can select the right worksheet here on
the left.
Also, make sure to check the box that
says,
first row of range contains field names,
and click Next.
On the next page, please make sure to
check each variable and
verify that it is being imported in the
correct format.
>> If you have a new Mac variable, the
data type should give us this number.
If you have a date variable, the data type
should be able to send us date.
If you have a categorical variable, with
data entered as words or
characters, the data type should be listed
as string.
You can specify the data type, by
selecting the variable and
clicking Modify.
This step crucial because if you
mis-specify your data type.
But problems with your analysis.
So here we can see that the age variable
is specified by a string.
That's incorrect, so lets click Modify and
fix that.
Now, we'll correctly specify it as number.
>> While you're on this page, you can also
specify the name and
or label of each variable if you'd like to
rename it.
Variable names can not have any spaces,
and
are used in specifying the variables for
analysis.
On the other hand, variable labels can be
lengthy descriptions with or
without spaces.
These are used in graphics and, or tables.
>> Once you make sure that your variables
are correctly represented,
click Next and Finish.
>> Your data set has now been imported
into SAS Enterprise Guide.
>> Now, you can put it into the data set,
you can double check, if that everything
is in order.
The column names have icons next to them,
which indicate which data type they are
entered as.
This blue icon indicates that its a number
variable.
And this red icon, indicates that its the
string variable.
This one's incorrect.
Click Modify Task.
And go back to the field attribute, to
correctly specify your variable.
[SOUND].
[BLANK_AUDIO]
>> Now everything looks correct,
please always make sure to check the to
define the field attributes windows.
Incorrectly specifying a field attribute,
can make it impossible to run even the
simplest data analysis.
>> Once you input your data in SAS, you
can start running your data analysis.
SAS stores a copy of the data set and
whatever library you're working on,
and leaves your original data set file
intact.
That way you don't lose or
change the original data once you start
working on it.
>> One finally note, let's use point and
click to look at our data.
Notice that some cells just have a period
in place of a number,
this is SAS way of encoding missing data.
We'll return to this idea in future
modules.