Now, we know how to set up a simple macro.
We want to set up our macro so that
whenever we invoke it,
it will tweak the code each time.
Like we mainly did when we copy and pasted
the code.
We're going to continue from the example
in the last video.
We want to be able to change the input
Dataset that we start out with,
as well as the output Dataset that we save
everything into.
Whenever there's a variable in our code
that we wish to tweak,
every time we run the macro, we use a
placeholder variable like this.
[SOUND] Here, we made a placeholder
variable called inputDataset.
Now, whenever we run this macro, what ever
we type inside these parenthesis will get
inserted right here, where I have the
placeholder variable.
It is important to note that when you're
specifying the placeholder variable
inside of your code, it must always begin
with an ampersand and end with a period.
Let's run this macro and see what happens
when we invoke it.
[NOISE] Here I
invoked the macro twice.
The first time, I told it to use group1
for
the placeholder variable called
inputDataset.
So, behind the scenes, Sass ran this first
line of code.
Next, it ran this line of code.
But, when it reached this place order
variable, it filled in exactly what I
typed in within the parentheses when I
invoked the macro.
In the parentheses, I typed out group1, so
Sass filled that in, right here.
Basically, Sass ran a line of code that
said set, group1.
Then Sass ran the rest of the code exactly
the way it is.
What this did was create a new Dataset
called work.group1_BMI.
Filled in the data from group1 like I
specified.
And, then specified a new variable for
BMI.
Sass then repeated this process the second
time I invoked the code.
Except this time, when Sass reran this
entire chunk of code,
it changed the input Dataset to
work.group2.
It still saved everything in the output
Dataset called work.group1_ BMI.
But, it tweaked the input Dataset just
like we told it to.
>> Now, let's add in a second placeholder
variable, so
we can also tweak the output Dataset.
>> Whenever you have multiple placeholder
variables in your macro statement,
they must be separated by commas, just
like this.
>> [SOUND]
Now, whatever you
type right after the parenthesis will get
filled in for the input Dataset.
And, whatever you type following the
comma,
will get filled in for the output Dataset.
Let's run this macro and invoke it.
When you invoke the macro, make sure you
specify the placeholder variables in
the correct order, just like you made in
your original macro code.
First, we have the input Dataset, and then
the output Dataset.
So, now I've invoked the macro five times.
When Sass invokes the macro for the first
time,
it'll use group1 as the input Dataset, and
group1_BMI as the output Dataset.
And, the rest of the code will be the
same.
When it invokes the macro for the second
time,
it'll use group2 as the input Dataset and
group2_BMI as the output Dataset.
Each time I invoke the macro,
it tricks the code slightly to use the
variables that I specify.
This is just like we did when we copy and
pasted the clip by hand, except now Sass
is doing it automatically.
And, now we have five output Datasets,
just like we wanted