So for this question you're comparing two
unrelated independent groups; smokers
and non-smokers.
The outcome is a continuous variable,
cholesterol.
So that's going to lead us in our little
chart of statistical tests,
we've got continuous outcome, independent
groups,
that's going to lead us to a T-test since
we have two groups.
Now we don't know for sure that
cholesterol is normally distributed, but
we have a fairly large sample size here,
so
we're not going to worry too much about
that.
Then, we also don't know if we have
homogeneity of variances in
the two groups, but
if we're doing the t-test, we could choose
the un-pooled variants if that's the case.
In this case, we're comparing two
independent groups.
Smokers and non-smokers.
The outcome is continuous cholesterol.
So that's going to lead us to a two-sample
T-test.
However, in this case we clearly have
different variances between
the two groups.
The T-test has a way to deal with that.
Which is to just choose the un-pooled
variants.
If the variances aren't equal, it's not
really fair to pool them.
We'll just use the unpooled variance and
the standard error.
In this question the correct answer is c,
a parity test because we're
comparing a single group of smokers before
and after they quit smoking.
So we have a,
we have two correlated groups that's the
same people before and after.
We have a continuous outcome here which is
cholesterol,
which is why we would end up at the paired
T-test here.
We don't know for sure that the change in
cholesterol is a normal distributed
outcome, but because we have a fairly
large sample here we can assume that
the central limit theorem will kick in if
we're little off normality.
In this next question,
we're told that we have a normally
distributed continuous outcome.
So we know we're going to be on the row
for continuous outcomes here.
But we have to read the question carefully
because even though the data were
measured at three time points, the
question was asking just what do we
need to use in order to compare baseline
to the end of the study?
So we're only using two time points, so
that would put us on a paired T test.
It's the same people, so we have
correlated data.
It's only two time points, continuous
outcome.
So d, a paired T-test would be the correct
answer here.
In this question, we have a continuous
normally distributed outcome and
we're comparing groups over multiple, more
than two time points, so
we have a correlation, in that we have a
time series here.
We have a continuous outcome, and many
time periods, so
we're going to be using repeated measures
in ANOVA.
So a repeated measures in ANOVA is correct
here.
The assumptions of one way in ANOVA, are
that the outcome variable is
normally distributed, that we have
homogeneity of variances.
That is, that the variance of outcome is
the same in all groups.
And, we're assuming that the observations,
the groups are independent.
So, the correct answer here would be d,
all of the above.
This question is asking, if you run a
randomized control trial of.
For treatment regimens,
you compare blood pressures at the end of
the day using a one-way ANOVA, and
the p-value is point zero three, so you do
get a significant p-value.
What can you conclude from that?
So what you can conclude is actually c,
just that at least one of the treatment
regiments is different from the other.
ANOVA is a global test, so
it doesn't tell you actually where those
differences lie, it only tells you
that there's a difference in at least one
of those groups.
In this question we want to compare
vitamin D levels between three
independent groups, we're not sure if our
outcome variable level,
vitamin D levels is normally distributed.
What should we do?
Well that's a very simple one right?
If we don't know if it's normally
distributed it's actually easy to
run some tests for normality.
So we should do d test oppression for
normality.
In this question,
we have an outcome variable that we know
is not normally distributed.
We also have a small sample size.
We want to compare between multiple
groups.
We're going to have to use a
non-parametric test because of
the violation of normality here.
So the correct non-parametric test is a
Kruskal-Wallis test.
A non-parametric ANOVA because we have
three groups.
The term,
non-parametric refers to the fact that we
are not estimating any parameters.
So d is correct here.
We're just not estimating any parameters
we're only getting p values.
Non-parametric is often used in the case
when we have non
normally distributed data but its not
synonymous with that.
The non-parametric equivalent to the
paired t test is b the Wilcox and
Sine rate test which you can find on our
big statistical chart here.
In this situation we have.
Correlated data.
All the reviewers are paired so we have a
particular author suggested reviewer
an editor suggested reviewer that are
linked to a single paper.
The unit of observation here is the paper
and not the reviewer.
Each paper has two reviewers, those
reviewers are correlated or paired.
If you are looking at this [INAUDIBLE],
you notice that we have a two by two
table, you might have though oh,
difference in proportions test.
But because of the correlation,
we have correlated data instead we have to
use a McNemar's chi-square test.
Which is appropriate when we have
correlated data and a two-by-two table.
In this question, we have paired data.
Each paper is linked to two reviewers, an
author-suggested reviewer and
an editor-suggested reviewer.
And the question her is, whether or not
the author-suggested reviewers.
Tended to give more favourable reviews.
Because we have paired data,
some of the cells presented here actually
don't matter.
So we don't get any information when both
reviewers gave a favourable review.
That doesn't help us to distinguish
between author-suggested and
editor suggested reviewers.
Similarly, we don't get any,
any information when both give, give an
unfavourable review.
So where we get the information is when
there was discordance,
when they didn't agree.
And we can see there was a hundred cases
where they didn't agree.
It was much more likely that the author
suggested reviewer would give
a favourable review when there was a
disagreement.
This is going to be analysed by a Mcnemar
chi square test and
will come out to be significant to say the
author suggested reviewer does tend to
be more favourable when there's a
disagreement.
In this question, I have both a
categorical predictor and
a categorical outcome.
I've got smoking group and graduate
school, whether or
not you went, which is a binary.
Outcome because I've got two categorical
predictors and
I've got independent groups, the smokers,
ex smokers, and never smokers are not
related that's going to lead me on our
little chart to a Chi square test.
So the answer is e Chi square test.
Survival analysis is a set of statistical
techniques that we use when we
have time to event data.
So out of the choices here only c involves
time to event data.
This is where we have a cohort study we
follow women [INAUDIBLE] into find out
the time it took for them to develop
breast cancer or
not develop breast cancer.
So that only c involves a time to event
outcome.
This question involves interpreting a
Kaplan–Meier survival curve.
So clearly you can see from the curve
there's two groups here.
Both of those groups had some fractures.
They had some events so the curve is going
down, so a is not correct.
B is also incorrect, because it says that
the probability of fracturing in
the previous fracture group over two years
was more than 50%.
And you can see from this graphic, that we
never cross the 50% line.
C is actually the correct answer.
The probability of avoiding a fracture for
at least one year in
the previous fracture group, that's the
dotted line, was approximately 80%.
You can see that by just going to about a
year, this is time on the x axis so
a year is somewhere around here.
If you scroll up you can see that the
survival probability indeed was
somewhere around 80%.
And actually d is incorrect because the
survival curve is actually,
are statistically different in this
picture.
These data came from a twin study, so each
case is somebody with Parkinson's disease
and they have a twin who does not have
Parkinson's disease, so we have these case
control pairs that are correlated by the
fact that they're within a twin pair.
So we have correlated data here.
Our outcome here is binary, you have
Parkinson's disease or you don't.
Our exposure variable, our predictor
variable is whether or
not you've been exposed to various
chemicals.
So, we have essentially categorical data
for both the predictor and
the outcome, but we have this correlation,
so
that's going to tell us we're going to
have to do a MacNameir's test.
However, if you look carefully at a lot of
this cells.
Remember for a McNamar's test we only care
about the discordant pairs,
which would be these middle two columns.
If you look at all of these columns, a lot
of the columns involve sparse data.
So one or two people only in some of those
cells.
So not only do we have to do a McNamar's
test, but we have to do an exact test to
calculate those probabilities exactly,
rather than using a normal
approximation to the binomial which is
what a Chi-square normally would do.
So we're going to use a McNamar's exact
test here.
This question asks you specifically about
the probabilities for
PRC, it's asking you to calculate.
The p value for the p,e,r,c chemical
column it might be helpful here to
draw a two by two table if that helps you
to,to see the problem.
So we have your either.
We have cases, the case is either these
are pair data, so we have cases and
controls, so the cases have Parkinson's,
the control is their twin, and
we're analysing things at the level of
pairs, so we have in this case then,
what we're looking at here is you were
either exposed to p,e,r,c, or you weren't.
And some other cases both were exposed,
some of they were,
both were not exposed, others there was a
discordance.
So it turns out that the majority were not
exposed, so
we had 93 pairs where neither the case nor
the control is exposed.
There weren't any pairs where both case
and control were exposed.
However, we did have a couple of pairs
where there was discordance.
So there were five pairs where the case,
that is the person with Parkinson's
[INAUDIBLE] disease, was exposed to this
chemical But the control was not.
And we have one situation, one case where
the opposite was true,
the control was exposed to the chemical
but the case was not.
It turns out from McNamar's test the only
thing that's of use,
the only information that's informative
for us here is the discordant pair.
So we have six discordant pairs, and null
hypothesis here is
that the chemical is not related to
whether or not your case or a control.
So under the null hypothesis we've got six
discordant pairs,
if there was no relationship between the
chemical and
getting Parkinson's disease this would
follow a binomial distribution.
X would follow a binomial distribution and
the n here is six which is
just determined by how many discordant
pairs we ended up with.
The p would be point five under the null
hypothesis.
In other words just think intuitively if
there's no relationship here
between the chemical and Parkinson's
disease.
You'd expect [INAUDIBLE] the discordant
pairs to kind of be even about three
where it was the case that was exposed and
not the control and three where it was the
control that was exposed and not the case.
Well the question we're really asking here
is how far is a five one split?
From what we'd expect under the null which
is a three, three split.
So we're a binomial we're going to have to
because is small numbers we're going to
have to calculate that exact binomial
probability.
So we're literally going to go through and
calculate the exact binomial probabilities
here.
So what did we actually see?
We saw the case where we ended up with
five discordant pairs where it was
the case who had been exposed and not the
control.
The binomial probability would just apply
our binomial probability formula here
we've got six choose five.
P is point five.
So we do point five raised to the 5th.
And then one minus p is also point five.
So we do, point five raised to the first.
But, remember, p values, we have to
calculate the probability of what we saw,
and everything more extreme.
So we also have to calculate the
probability that we could have gotten all
six discordant pairs.
It was the case that was exposed.
So we do six, two, six point five raised
to the 6th.
We also have to consider, the other tail.
Remember, if we did out all the binomial
probabilities here,
they'd go from zero to six.
We could get something that, excuse my
crude drawing here.
But we get something where we have five
and six in one tail, but
we have to consider we want to do a
two-tailed hypothesis, and
consider we could have been at, just as
extreme in the other direction.
And as we could have ended up with only
zero or one discordant pairs where it
was the case that was exposed, so we have
to do a two tailed probability.
You can do that by,um calculating the
other tail which is the probability that x
equals one.
And the probability that x equals zero.
It turns out that those are exactly the
same as the ones that you see here, so
this one comes out to be point zero, one,
five, six, two,
five, this one comes out to be point zero,
nine, three, seven, five.
This one will also be zero point zero,
It's symmetric.
And this one will be zero point zero,one,
five, six, two, five.
When you add all of those up,
you get that the p-value here is point
two, one, eight, seven, five.
This is a situation where we have paired
data.
We have repeated measure It's the same
women measured before and
after they've smoked.
We have a continuous outcome which is
blood pressure and also heart rate.
And so we're going to be
using a paired T-test here because it's a
before an after with a continuous outcome.
The correct answer here is false.
You actually cannot calculate the paired
T-test from the data given in the table.
Why is that?
Well, we're given the mean before smoking,
and the mean after smoking, but
remember the paired T-test looks at the
differences for individual women.
And right now we don't know the difference
values for individual women.
We don't know how much each women
individually went up or down.
We would need that information in able to
be able to calculate the paired T-test.
In this case breast feeding although
usually a continous variable has
been divided up into categories.
So we're actually comparing groups here.
Our predictor variable is a categorical
variable.
If we want to look at overweight at 18.
That is also a categorical variable.
It's binary.
You either were overweight at 18, or you
weren't.
So we've got two categorical variables
here.
We've got, more than a two by two table.
So we will be doing a chi square test
here.
In this question, breast feeding is a
categorical variable; we're
comparing groups of men by whether or
not they were breast-fed over the
duration, how much they were breast-fed.
Our outcome variable is binary: you're
either obese or you're not obese.
We also do not have sparse data.
So we're going to be using a Chi-square
test.
And because we don't have sparse data,
we don't have to worry about the Fischer
exact test or doing an exact test here.
In this case, we're going to be comparing
different groups, so
we're comparing men in different groups of
duration of breast feeding so
that's a categorical predictor groups.
They're independent groups our outcome
variable now is BMI,
BMI is a continous variable.
We're going to assume that it's normally
distributed or
close enough where such large samples
sizes that we can run an ANOVA test here.
So this question says lets say we do our
Chi square test for obesity and
breast feeding, feeding group.
And we get a significant p value.
P is point zero three.
What does that mean?
Well, the Chi-squared test is a global
test, so
it actually doesn't tell us where the
differences lie, it just tells us that at
least one of those breastfeeding groups is
different than the others.
And if you actually look at the numbers
here, you know, it goes from 9.6% obese to
13.1% to 20.7%, it looks like it's going
up as you get more breastfeeding, and
then it goes down for the really long
breastfeeding group.
So, there's no particular pattern here.
So, all we can conclude is d, that the
percent of obese subjects differs in at
least one of those breast feeding
categories.
This asks you to calculate the mean change
in exercise duration.
And you can do it just off this graph.
It's nice that they were measured in only
units of zero point five,
nothing finer than that.
So, for example, this first person went up
three seconds,
the next person went up point five, this
one was zero point five, one point five,
zero, one point five, point five, point
five, one point zero, point five, zero and
point five.
You literally just have to pick those off,
up off of the graph.
Well if you add up all of those numbers,
I'm not going to write it
all out here just because it would take
awhile, but if you add up all of
those numbers from one to 13 you end up,
and then divide by 13 to
calculate the average here you end up with
point seven, seven.
To calculate the standard deviation of
change here,
we simply going to take each observation
and subtract it from the mean.
Well, you've already calculated the mean.
To b point seven, seven.
So for example, we take the first person,
subtract and mean square that, then we do
this for the next person.
The next person has a value of point five
subtract from the mean square.
That.
We're going to do that for all thirteen.
I won't write it out completely here.
You're then going to divide by n minus one
for
the standard deviation, your divide by n
minus one, so
that ends being 13 ,minus one or 12 here,
and then we square root that whole thing.
When you calculate that out you get a
value of point eight three.
To calculate the standard error of the
change here we would take the standard
deviation for change, which we calculated
already as point eight three.
And divide by the square root of n.
So point eight three divided by the square
root of 13 is point two, three.
That would be our standard error here.
To calculate the 95% confidence interval.
We're going to take the observed mean,
which we already calculated to be point
seven, seven.
We're going to add and subtract our t
value here for
a 99% confidence interval I gave you, as
three point zero five, five.
We're going to multiply that by our
standard error which we
calculated already to be point two, three.
When you add that all out you're going to
end up with a confidence interval of
point zero six, seven to one point four,
seven.
The answer to this question is true,
it is statistically significant at the
zero point zero one level.
How do we know that, well we just
calculated the 99% confidence interval.
That confidence interval does not include
the null value which is zero here.
This excludes zero therefore we can be
sure that the p
value is less than point zero one.
The answer to this question is.
False.
We did prove that there is a statistically
significant increase in
the exercise duration of these patients.
However, it's unclear if the camp is
responsible for this change.
They could have all gone up for other
reasons.
We don't have a control group here, so we
can't conclude causality here.
We just know that for some reason they
went up a significant amount.