Now we're ready to do some simple analysis
on the data.
Remember, you have two types of variables
in your dataset.
Continuous variables and categorical
variables.
>> Let's look at the distributions of our
continuous variables first.
We can do this using proc univariate.
As you can see from the code.
We start out with proc univariate and then
specify our data set.
Then using a var statement,
we can specify the variables that we
want to have in our univariate analysis.
We're going to analyze age, BMI, weight,
and height.
We then include a histogram statement, so
they get a histogram for each of these
variables.
As you can see from the output, we still
have age versus BMI by deceit status.
This is carried over from the previous
graphic.
That's why you usually want to include G
options, reset equals Alt before and
after each of your graphics.
Here's the output for the variable age.
You can see the mean, median, mode,
standard deviation, variance and range.
And a lot of other information, here at
the quantiles,
here's information about extreme values.
And down here, is a histogram as well as
information on missing values.
We have a similar output for the BMI
variable,
for the weight variable and for the height
variable.
>> We might also be interested in looking
at these distributions among the subset of
individuals who are diabetic and
individuals who are not diabetic.
We can do this by adding a by statement in
our code.
Under histogram, we write by is diabetic.
This will allow us to have an output that
is stratified by diabetes status.
Let's run this code and see what happens.
As you can see we now have an error
statement.
It says the data set, work BMI is not
sorted in ascending sequence.
>> Remember, if you want to use a by
statement,
you first have to sort your data set by
the variable that you want to stratify on.
So first, you have to sort our data set by
isdiabetic using proc sort.
Now, if we run it, it will stratify our
data correctly.
As you can see from the output, it will
first give us all the results for
the subset of non diabetics within our
data set.
Here's the information for
the age variable amongst those who are
non-diabetic.
Here's the information for
the BMI variable, amongst those who are
non-diabetic.
And same for weight and height.
And then it'll have all the information
for the people who are diabetic.
So here is the age information for
diabetics, BMI, weight and height, as
well.
>> Now let's take a look at our
categorical variables gender,
diabetes status, race and smoking.
We also have our new categorical variables
that we made by chopping up age and BMI.
For these categorical variables we can use
proc freq.
Let's take a look at our code.
By now you should be familiar with the
proc freq syntax.
In this case, we made sure to specify that
our data set was the BMI_quartiles.
Underneath, we have our table statement.
Here we list, all of our categorical
variables we want to look at.
Let's run the code and take a look at the
output.
>> Here we can see the one way frequency
tables, for each of these variables.
As you can see, we have 582 non-diabetics
and 413 diabetics.
It'll also tell us the percentage of ea,
each of these sub-groups.
Let's make a contingency tables, so
we can see the distribution of these
variables for diabetics and non-diabetics.
>> Remember, if you want to create
multiple contingency tables,
you can use asterisks and parentheses and
include all the values you want to cross
with is diabetic.
This code creates five separate
contingency tables.
Now that we have these contingency tables,
we can run a Chi-squared test to see if
there's an association between alkon
variable and the categorical predictors.
>> [SOUND] We can also add additional
options to
limit the output, so it's not as
cluttered.
In the output area we can see whether
these Chi-squared tests provided enough
evidence to reject a null hypothesis.
That these variables are independent.
For example, say we believe that there was
a relationship between smoking status
and Diabetes.
Down here we can see the contingency table
for Diabetes versus smoking status.
We can see here that the Chi-square value
has a p-value that's less than 0.001.
This means that the alpha equals 0.05
level, we can reject the null hypothesis.
In other words, there's sufficient
evidence to
show that there is an association between
smoking status and diabetic outcome.
>> Let's make some two-by-two contingency
tables and
have Saas calculate some risk ratios.
To do this, we'll create a new program.
Use proc frequency and specifier data set.
And use our table statement to cross,
Isdiabetics with females and
smoking staff.
>> In the options, we specify relrisk,
that tells us we wanted to calculate
relative risk measures.
In the output, we can see that it
calculated Odds Ratios and Risk Ratios.
This will tell us the strength of the
association between these variables.
As we can see there is an Odds Ratio of
0.8, for
the association between gender and
diabetic status.