>> Hello and welcome back to HRP223.
In this module we're going to show you
some of the basics of coding.
Considering that this is a ten week
course, it would really be impossible for
us to show you everything that you need to
know.
>> The truth is,
the best way to learn how to code is by
starting to write it yourself.
By struggling through it, looking at
suggestions online and asking SAS for
help, you'll develop your coding skills
over time.
In this module, we're going to go over the
basics.
And the by the time you're in HRP 262,
you'll be writing most of your code on
your own.
In this module, we're going to start
building your own small data set, but
we'll continue to use in future modules.
Lets look at some code.
At the beginning of this program, is the
code to create a library.
Just like we saw in an earlier module.
Remember, this must be done every time we
start a new project.
>> There are a few more things you need to
know about cutting SAS.
As you can see in SAS, every statement
must end in a semicolon.
If you leave out a semicolon, a program
will not run correctly.
A semicolon tells SAS that a certain
operation, statement, or even procedure is
finished and that it should move on to the
next one that you have written.
It's going to start thinking of the
semicolon as a period.
Just make sure to end your SAS statements
with a semicolon.
>> Another key feature of SaS code is the
word run, followed by a semicolon.
Run statements tell SAS to go over the
previous code they've written and
process it.
Without a run statement, SAS will not
necessarily produce an output.
Checking for
semicolons in run statements is typically
the best way to catch mistakes.
We'll talk more about the run statement
when we cover data steps.
>> Also, notice that there are different
colors for different bits of code.
All you need to know for now, is that red
is bad.
See, if Ram starts typing somethings in
SAS and
then it doesn't understand, it will be
colored red.
This is extremely useful for catching
typos and
mistakes, as you start writing your own
code.
>> It's always useful to write comments,
so
that you can explain what your code does.
Let's add a comment into our program.
One way to add a comment, is by starting a
line with foreslash asterisk and and
ending a line with an asterisk foreslash.
You can type anything you want inside a
comment, and it won't affect the code.
As long as it's within the asterisks.
>> As you can see, all comments are in
green.
>> Now, let's take a look at the next
chunk of code in this program.
The next two lines of code are part of
what's called, a data step.
There are two main types of code that
we'll see in SAS.
Data steps and PROC steps.
In the following example, we're going to
be using a data step.
Data steps deal with creating, cleaning,
and formatting data.
We'll tell you more about these in a bit.
Just know that whenever you end a Data
step or
a Proc step, you must have lines that say
run.
>> When we say data hrp223.people, we
create a new
data set called people in the hrp223
library that we pointed to earlier.
Notice how once again, we end with a
semicolon.
When SAS runs codes,
it processes the statement one line at a
time starting from the top.
At this point, the data set is empty.
As you can see there are no columns and no
rows.
In the next line, we have run.
This just ends the program.
>> We have now just written a code for the
program.
We still need to run the program to make
SAS do the steps we put in.
Click on this green arrow to run the
program.
[SOUND]
On the right side of the screen, we can
see the applet of this program.
Here it shows the new data set that we
just created.
As you can see, there is no columns and
there is no rows.
It is completely empty.
>> Let's see what happens when we delete a
semicolon somewhere in our original code.
Now, you can see that our program doesn't
actually run.
Instead of showing you the output data
set, SAS brings up what is called the log.
The program log records everything that
SAS does.
As you can see SAS actually tried to run
the program, and
everything was going fine until this line.
Here we run into an error, which resulted
from us leaving out a semicolon.
When your program doesn't run you'll see a
red X icon in the process flow.
Check the SAS log because sometimes,
it provides useful information about where
to find a bug and how to fix it.
Now let's go back and add our semicolon.
Now when we click Run.
Everything is fine.
>> So here we have our first step of code.
Let's add another line to our code.
This first line creates a new data set
called people in the hrp223 library.
The next line creates a new variable
called weight.
This means, we'll have a column called
weight in our data set now.
And because weight equals 188, this column
has one value, 188.
[SOUND]
As we can see we now have a column for
weight, and has one value.
Let's take it one step further and add a
new variable for gender.
In our code we will write gender equals m.
Note, that when you enter a value for a
number, you don't need quotation marks.
But if you enter a value that's a
character or
a string, you do need quotation marks.
When we run this, you'll that we have a
data set with two columns.
One for gender and one for weight.
[SOUND].
[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this chapter code, we create a new data
set called people in
the hrp223 library just like we did
before.
Next, we specify the columns in our data
set.
Input tells SAS that you're naming the
columns, and
anything that comes after it will be the
name of a new column.
So we have a column, called gender and a
column called weight.
Notice that there is a dollar sign that
comes after gender,
this specifies that gender is a variable
that allows characters as its values.
In other words, will not be able to do any
mathematical operations on this variable.
Like, addition subtraction multiplication
or division.
>> Now that we specified what columns to
have in our data set,
we need to fill these columns in with
data.
To do this, you write data lines and then
a semicolon.
Now, you can type out values to fill in
your columns.
Make sure to enter them in the same order
you created your variables.
First, we have gender.
Next, we have weight.
So, when we enter each rogue data, gender
comes first and then comes weight.
Make sure you have a space between each
value.
Put a semicolon at the end of all the data
lines, and
then include your run statement.
If you look at the data we have used to
fill out the columns,
one of the females has a period instead of
a value.
SAS uses periods to represent missing
values.
>> In your HRP classes,
they'll often import data sets with lots
of missing values.
It's important to know what these periods
represent,
when you come to analyze your data.
We'll discuss this in more detail later.