In this next module we're going to spend a
little bit more time talking about some of
the tools that you would use as part of
doing a root cause analysis.
We're going to focus on three of them in
particular that
I've personally found very helpful when
conducting root cause analysis.
The first one, we've spent some time with,
is talking about brainstorming.
The second one is flow charting or process
mapping.
And the third one is the use of the cause
and
effect diagram otherwise known as a
fishbone diagram.
As the slide shows there are different
other,
tools that you could certainly use as part
of a root cause analysis to figure out
exactly what's going on, in many of those
other situations it's a,
a factor of taking advantage of data to
analyze what's going on and
determine what may be root causes or a
contributing factor.
First one we're going to spend a little
bit of
time talking about is brain storming.
Some people know it as White Boarding.
Other call it Blue Sky.
See What Sticks.
Post It.
It's known by a variety of different
names.
But basically, the bottom line, is to
quickly generate as many ideas as
you can on a particular problem or a
particular subject.
The whole concept is to try to take
advantage of everybody that's in
the room to throw out as many different
ideas in a very short period of time.
basically, the more ideas you throw up,
the more likelihood that you may, be able
to capture, maybe, some,
some different ideas about what's going on
with that particular situation.
Part of brainstorming is really
identifying either a topic,
a problem, issue, and making sure that
there is some degree of
mutual understanding of the task and
objective.
So, for starters, when you're doing this,
you'll have folks participating in and
throwing out the ideas, and no idea is too
little, or too big, but
once you get through that process of
actually getting them up on the board,
then the next step is actually sorting
through them or prioritizing.
So that you can kind of focus in on what
may be the core issues that's going on.
The whole focus of this is really looking
at the number of ideas and
not necessarily the quality.
So I know it's really easy to throw those
ideas up, and to critique 'em, and
you know, criticize them saying that
they're not really practical, or that's
not what really happened, but in fact, the
real, the real intent is really to kind of
consider all of the variables that might
be involved in a particular situation.
One of the basic ground rules about
brainstorming is making sure that no
criticism is allowed.
and, you know, you, that can go both ways,
mostly negative, of course.
But, the other side of it is that no idea
thrown on the board should be ruled in as
the idea after you have been doing it for
a few minutes.
Most of the time you may take aside 10,
15 minutes worth of time to be able to
come up with some of
the different ideas that might have
contributed to a particular situation.
Process map, otherwise known as flow
charting.
Pictures are worth a thousand words.
So, a map that draws out a picture really
does permit a reader or reviewers to
actually visualize what the different
steps are or the different processes
are that's involved in anything that's
going on when it comes to patient care.
This picture really does permit the reader
to see the different inputs and
outputs, ramification of action as well as
linkages,
that may occur between other processes,
that either run in parallel or
are contributing to what you're
evaluating.
Or even looking at what might be happening
downstream.
So really, you know, the whole concept
behind process mapping is to kind of, kind
of, pictorially show, diagrammatically to
folks who are involved with
doing the root cause analysis, more of an
understanding of the step-by-step-by-step.
Now, along the same line,
some people may confuse this with actually
developing a timeline.
A timeline is more of the chronological
review of the sequence of events,
or sequencing of steps that might occur.
And it is actually something that you can
use in conjunction with
doing your process mapping to understand
what's going on.
One of the variables that often times is
missed when doing a root cause analysis
is, you know, people may understand the
step-by-step, but the timing of when those
steps occur can actually contribute to why
the event happened, or actually paint
a different picture of the dynamics that
was going on at the time of an event.
This next slide actually shows a very
simple flow chart it has to
do with something that many of us do every
morning, and
that's the issue of waking up.
So, you have a start, and the alarm rings.
Are you ready to get up?
Yes or no?
The diamonds are generally used as a
decision step in
terms of making a yes or no decision.
If you say no, you hit the snooze button
and go back to sleep and
then the alarm clock re-triggers again in
five minutes.
If you're ready to get up, you take that
next step in the process.
Roll out of bed, climb out of bed, crawl
out of bed, and then on with your day.
So this is a very simple process map.
You may be surprised or not surprised to
find that some of the steps involved in
evaluating things like root cause in the
course of doing a root cause analysis,
such as a medication error or a surgical
procedure event, or a communication gap.
You may find yourself drilling down and
finding that there may be tens if
not hundreds of little steps involved with
carrying out that particular function.
I know one couple studies of been
published about
evaluating the nursing process for
administrative medication.
From the point of them getting the order,
to pulling the medication out,
to preparing the medication, and
administering the medication had
something in the neighborhood of like 80
plus some odd steps.
So, you know, you, you wouldn't be
surprised that if
there are that many steps with all these
different decisions involved and
any time that there may be a disruption or
interruption of any one of those steps.
You probably are not going to be surprised
to find that a medication error or
medication event can occur.
The next tool we're going to talk about is
cause and
effect diagram, otherwise known as
Fishbone diagram, or Ishikawa diagram.
Once again visuals are very, very helpful
for
the participants to understand why a
particular event was to occur?
When you're using a fishbone diagram,
you use elements of your brain storing
process to kind of throw,
what are some of the factors that might
have contributed to leading the event.
Now when you're doing the brain storming
it's hard to take, just a brain storm idea
and show that there is a connection with
other aspects of a particular system or
process and that's where you use a
Fishbone diagram to
actually demonstrate the linkage between
those different ideas and
how it can contribute to the adverse
outcome.
This Fishbone diagram does connect the
individual cause-and-effect relationship
to reveal any of the system type causes
within a particular issue.
On its own you may not be able to see it.
But certainly when you see it in the
context of how it's related to
other things that are going on for the
[INAUDIBLE].
You can actually paint a very definitive
picture of system process issues that
needs to be addressed.
These Fishbone diagrams can be very, very
basic.
Just to let you know, you know, when
you're doing these things in a group you,
you'll be surprised how much you can
accomplish in, in 15, 20 minutes.
or, you know, you can take hours and
actually, you know, go down to extreme
details.
Depending on what the issues are, you
could really use the tool to drill down.
To figure out what is going on?
What are the cause and effect of any
particular, system process issue?
And then when you add variables into that,
you can really show how the linkages can
occur between these things.
Thereby helping you identify what you need
to do in terms of solutions.
Now, part of the Fishbone diagram is going
to include the head of the fish,
basically the problem, effect, or outcome.
In this case we're doing a root cause
analysis so
we actually had a adverse outcome or a
significant near miss.
There's your problem.
The horizontal branches on the Fishbone,
actually outlines your causes,
so, in this case were talking about
variety of different things that
actually led to that particular outcome,
each one of those diagonal lines,
are, could be considered major processes
or major systems.
And with them, then they identified the
different causes.
The sub-branches are really the reasons
why a particular cause was to occur.
So there's your reasons, you know, take
for
example staff there was an adverse
outcome.
It actually led to an unintended retain
foreign object and
because the staff wasn't trained on a
particular new piece of equipment.
They didn't know that the setup had
particular little parts that needed to
be done, that needed to be secured.
And as a result,
because they weren't secured properly, it
was left in the patient.
Really the reason for something like that
could be attributed to staff education.
It could be related to the lighting,
it could be related to the instructions
that came from the manufacturer.
It could be, you know, those were the
reasons that we're drilling down to
identify what the real root cause are.
So we can put the system process fix in,
into place.
Some other categories, and
these are the categories that we kind of
focus in on from a greater system process.
You may, you want to consider using the
methodology of machine,
material, measurement, management, method,
and manpower.
Each one of those major categories.
You know, if you use the direct missions
methodology,
we'll make reference to things like human
resources,
leadership medication management,
performance improvement.
You know, the, the, the categories kind of
drive really who's going to be
responsible or dealing with ownership some
time in some organization.
So, just be aware that you can use
different categories, as,
as part of the causes in evaluating when
you're doing a Fishbone diagram.
Now, here's another example of a completed
Fishbone diagram where you actually had
an event.
Doesn't really matter what kind of event.
So they elect to use the categories of
procedure, personnel,
reagent supplies, equipment, and
environment.
So, you look at those categories, and then
you drill down.
So, what are some of the causes.
If you look under procedure, the standard
operating procedure not clear.
Process is too complicated.
How many of us have, policy and procedures
in our organizations that actually,
nobody really has looked at in any great
detail, and
realize that the procedures are very
prescriptive, but not realistic.
And that's sometimes a, a, a real
challenge, because you would like to
follow the policy or the procedure, but if
they are not realistic or
they're complicated or they're fuzzy or
they're not clear or
just not communicated, you know, you can
be pretty much assured that
you're going to have variable outcome,
thereby leading to an adverse event.
So take a look at under the environment,
it's not uncommon for
us to have adverse events happening,
because the temperature is inappropriate.
The ambient noise is overwhelming us, one
of the big initiatives with
joint commission right now is looking at
clinical alarms, because we
know that a lot folks are, are distracted
by the fact that alarms are going off, or
they hear it all the time so they start to
ignore it.
space, space is always a huge issue in
health care.
It doesn't matter if you're a large
organization or a small organization.
You're a clinic with just you as the
provider and one assistant in the front
office to a big surgical OR where there's
basically you know,
30, 40 operating rooms that's being that's
actively having cases.
You know, if you don't have enough space
to provide care, you know,
that can lead to adverse outcomes.
So those are the three tools that you want
to be aware of that you might be
exposed to as part of your root constant
analysis work,
the brainstorming, process mapping, and
cause-and-effects diagram.