In this next module, we're going to dive
right in to the logistic regression model.
We've talked about, when you have binary
or categorical outcomes, that is,
when you're looking at proportions, we've
talked about some statistical tests when
you don't want to adjust for anything that
you can use.
So this is like the risk difference,
relative risk, the Chi-square test,
the McNemar's chi-square test, so we
talked about those, but what about when
you want to do a regression analysis when
you have a binary or categorical outcome?
In that case you're going to be using
logistic regression,
which we're going to talk about in this
module.
I want to just give you a little overview
of logistic regression so, to
remind you when we did linear regression,
the model looked like the following.
We were predicting the value of some
continuous.
Outcome variable, call it Y as a, a
function of X.
Here's a simple linear regression model.
We have the intercept alpha, and the beta
is our slope.
So that was the simple linear regression
model.
In the multi-variant regression model, we
can add some additional betas and
x's, additional predictors.
That makes it then a plane or
a higher dimension thing, but essentially
we're feeding lines, linear regression.
Logistic regression actually isn't that
different.
The right hand side of the equation is
identical in logistic regression, so
it's going to look something like this.
There's a linear combination of datas and,
and x's, risk factors.
It looks exactly the same.
And everything's going to be set up
exactly the same in terms of
defining the predictors of the, of the
model.
You can put binary predictors in.
You can put continuation.
You can put categorical.
You can do dummy coating.
All of that is the same as with linear
regression.
What's different in logistic equation is
the left hand side of the equation.
We are no longer modelling y-i.
The outcome variable directly.
Rather we're going to be modelling a
transformation of the outcome Variable.
In logistic, the case of logistic
regression,
we're going to be modeling the log odds of
the outcome.
And I know that sounds terrible, that's
called a logit function, and
I'll explain why in a minute.
We're going to be modeling this logit
function, the log odds of the outcome,
that's our outcome variable.
We're going to be modeling that as a line
though, as an alpha plus a.
Beta x, intercept, and the slope.
Because we've made this transformation,
the beta is just slightly more
complicated to interpret than the beta
from linear regression.
So for linear regression, the beta was
just the slope,
it's as x goes up by 1 unit, how much does
y go up?
So there was a direct interpretation.
It's just slightly more tricky to
interpret the betas from
logistic regression, but
actually it's not terrible because the
betas from logistic regression.
If you exponentiate them, what it gives
you out is the odds ratio, and
I refer to in the second week of the
course.
We talked a lot about odds ratios, and I
told you,
hey, logistic regression spits out odds
ratios, and this is where it comes from,
the betas, they are directly interpreted
as odds ratios, just by exponentiating.
And the reason there's an exponential
involved, is because our outcome variable
Involves a natural look so this is just
the overview of where we're going this.
Just keep in mind that the right hand side
of the equations the same as
with linear regression so we're still
fitting a line.
It's just we're fitting the outcome
variable there's
something trickier going on.
Let me start here with a simple example,
using that example data set, data set on
my Stanford student that I've been using
since the beginning of the course.
One of the questions I asked my Stanford
students is whether or
not the consider themselves to be book
smart or street smart.
this is a binary variable, book smart, the
variable is equal to one,
that means Means that they consider
themselves book smart.
If the variable is equal to zero, the way
I've coded it.
That means that they consider themselves
to be street smart.
So we can see that this is the book smart
group over here.
And this is the street smart book, group
over here.
And I, just as an aside, I've been asking
this question.
So lots of Standford students just for fun
over the years.
And it generally comes out about 80% of my
Standford students consider themselves to
be book smart and 20% consider themselves
to be street smart.
And that was indeed the case in this
little practice data set is
right around 80%.
I wondered if book-smart students did
more,
spent more time on homework, were more
studious, than street-smart students.
And so I wanted to look at the variable
homework in the number of hours per
week that they spent on homework.
That's another question that I'd asked
these students.
And we can look at that here.
And I've done this.
I've looked at this graphically here.
So I'm graphing, my predictor variable is
just a binary, a yes-no,
book smart or not.
In my outcome variable here is homework in
the number of hours per week and
now, surprisingly there are students who
consider themselves book smart as you can
see from this graphic here, actually, on
average, do slightly less homework than
the students who consider themselves
street smart for whatever reason.
So it went kind of in the opposite
direction from what I might have expected.
This analysis, this graphic that I'm
showing you here actually coincides with
a linear regression.
So the way I set up the problem now is
I've got a binary predictor variable and
a continuous outcome variable homework.
We could model this with a linear
regression.
Using what we talked about last week.
When we have a binary predictor it's a
very simple linear regression.
Right.
That line is just,
you connect the mean for the street smart
group with the mean for the book
smart group and if you connect two points
with a line, that, that defines a line.
And then so we end up with a very simple
line.
So we could answer this question.
Look at this question.
In this data set with a linear regression.
Or even a T test, which of course is a
special case of linear regression.
This is cross-sectional data however, so I
happen to pick, just for
the purposes of illustration, And for this
slide, to put book smart as the x
variable, as the predictor in homework as
the outcome variable.
But because this is cross-sectional data,
I could ask, I could flip that.
I could ask not whether or not you
classify yourself as
book smart predicts the amount of homework
you do, but I could ask it the other way.
Does the amount of homework you do or the
amount of time you spend on
homework predict whether or not you
consider yourself book smart?
So I'm just going to flip the x and y
variables.
So here's the graphic when I flip the x
and y variables.
So now my x, my predictor variable,
is continuous, the number of hours Spent
on homework per week.
And my outcome variable is this binary,
this yes-no.
0 is street smart, 1 is book smart.
We've got a new graphic, and we could try
to fit a line to these data.
But look what happens when I try to fit a
line to these data.
Notice that all of my, my outcomes are
either all 1 or all 0, so you just get
these two stripes, and it doesn't, it
doesn't seem optimal to try to fit a line.
I did fit a line to these data.
You can do it, you, this is a linear
regression line.
So I've fit the linear, the best fit line
to these data.
But you can see that if you look at this
picture it doesn't really look like that
line fits the data very well, right?
I mean we're doing linear regression last
week we had these scatter plots and
we were trying to find the line that was
kind of very close to all those dots.
Well, this line does, I mean you can fit
it, but
it doesn't look very close to all of those
dots.
It doesn't look like a very good fit.
So, a linear regression model is not
optimal here.
Well, what do we do?
Again, I told you we're still going to
want to fit lines Here.
So how can we still fit a line but do
something other than linear regression?
How could we, what could we do?
So, what we could do here, is to transform
the outcome variable.
Again, I still want to fit a line
ultimately, but
I don't want a zero one variable as my
outcome, because a zero one
variable just doesn't fit well to a line,
it has only two possible values.
So what could I do?
How could I transform that binary,
that zero one variable into something that
better fits a line?
Well here is one thing, this is where,
just a starting point,
because we're going to go further with
this.
But, let's just start with some, some
simple thing we can do.
So, recognize instead of modeling it as a
yes no A zero one.
What if we could somehow model it as a
probability.
A probability as you know, is a value that
ranges from zero to one, but
it can take on any value between zero and
one, so
we would do a little bit better, we would
put in all these values between.
Between zero and one back into play,
if somehow we could model this as we could
make the outcome variable
the probability of being book smart rather
than yes no you are book smart.
Just looking at the data here you can see,
well.
That's not immediate, obvious, immediately
obvious how you would do it.
In fact, we're going to do something
called the logit, which is a function of
the probability, and in fact what the
computer is going to do is do
a little algorithm involving some calculus
to calculate the probability of the logit.
But we can actually approximate it just
looking at the data, and
I think that this is the best way to
understand it.
So if I wanted to get a probability here,
rather than a 0-1 variable, imagine I did
the following.
What if I just,
to get a probability I'm going to have to
look at more than one person.
I'm going to have to look at a group of
people.
So what if I kind of arbitrarily looked at
you know, a group of people.
Let's just pick, say.
The, the ten people with the lowest amount
of homework time per week.
Notice that these little red dots here.
Actually, some of these dots represent
more than one person.
Because there were a lot of people who had
tied values.
They selected the same number of homework
and
they also called themselves book smart,
for example.
So that each of these dots might represent
more than on person.
So imagine that this, and
this what I've Putting this box here
represents ten people.
I could look at the ten people with the
lowest amount of homework time,
putting in the lowest amount of homework
time.
And I could count up how many of them
called themselves book smart, and
how many of them called themselves street
smart.
And I could calculate a proportion, a
percentage.
A probability.
So let's say, I'm just making this up, but
let's say when I calculate that.
Again, since some of these dots are
overlapping I can't do it exactly but,
from the graphic.
But let's say I count up and
I find that among those doing the least
Amount of homework.
Let's say that 90% of them, again I'm just
making this up.
Let's say 90% of that ten,
nine out of ten considered themselves book
smart rather than street smart.
Now I've got a probability rather than a
zero one.
And I could do this for the next group of
10, the next highest in homework.
Maybe in the next group, the probability
is,.
again, I'm just making this up, is 85
percent.
And I can't tell, because, again, these
dots are overlapping.
Maybe that comes out to be 85 percent.
But I could go along, and I could group,
people.
I have to group people in order to be able
to get a percentage of probability.
But I could come up with some.
Probabilities.
And of course, the probabilities I come up
with are going to depend exactly on how I
group them, but
just realize that the grouping is just for
the purposes of illustration.
When you actually do this with calculus,
you don't have to make any arbitrary
groupings.
Of course, we won't go through the
calculus here, but
the computer does that for you.
So if I could get that probability now, I
can make a graphic,
which is my predictor variable, is the
number of hours of homework per week,
the continuous variable.
Now my outcome variable is a probability,
a number that ranges between 0 and 1.
I have fewer dots on this graphic.
I'm going to just, for now, talk about the
graphic on the left side, this 10 groups.
I, notice I have fewer dots on that
graphic.
None of these dots are overlapping
anymore.
More, so actually I have, I had, my
previous graphic represented 48 people.
This graphic only represents 10
observations.
I divided those 48 people, up into roughly
even groups of, 10 groups of,
you know some are between.
Of about four or five per group.
And I got those percentages and I plotted
them here.
What you notice is that this is much more
amenable, this,
this scatter plot, to fitting a line.
Right now, we've got dots all around the
range, and
you can imagine actually fitting a
meaningful line to To those dots.
As I mentioned, this is just for
the purposes of graphing, just to show you
the concept.
And so, it's arbitrary how I group people.
So, of course, the graphics going to look
a little bit different,
depending on how I group people.
So just to show you that I also divide it
into five groups.
There's 48 people so this is roughly
groups of, you know, eight, nine or
ten and I calculated the proportion who
consider themselves book smart,
that probability in each of those five
groups, and I plotted it here.
By the way, when I'm each of these groups,
of course, has a range of homework values.
I'm using the mean homework time for
each group, that's what I'm putting in the
plot here.
So for example the lowest homework group
on this plot here,
they have a mean homework time of just,
you know 30 minutes to an hour and their,
the proportion that considered themselves
book smart was right around 78%.
So I'm using the mean just for graphical
purposes.
But the picture looks a little different
depending on How you group it, but
you can get the idea.
Now we've put back all the numbers between
zero and one into play,
it makes much more sense to fit a line,
but this is still limited, okay, so
this is not, we're going to go further
than that with this.
Because a probability is a number that's
bounded between zero and.
1, so it's still a bounded quantity.
You can't go lower than 0, you can't go
higher than 1.
The problem with that is imagine when we
fit a line, when you fit a line,
theoretically, that line can go anywhere
from negative in,
the y value can go anywhere from negative
infinity to positive infinity.
So, with this it's still not perfect.
So what we're going to do is instead of
directly Having the probability be
the outcome variable, we're going to make
a little transformation.
So probability is bounded from zero to
one.
If I divide the probability however, by
one minus the probability,
that of course is what we learned earlier
is the odds.
So divide the probability by the
probability of something not happening.
The probability divided by one minus the
probability.
That's what we learned in week 2 of the
course is an odds.
Why would I want to do that?
Well, a probability can't be bigger than
one.
But an odds can go from any, anywhere from
zero to positive infinity.
The odds has no right hand bound.
So now we've put in all the positive Real
numbers back into play.
We're still missing the negatives.
How can we get the negatives back in?
So here's where the natural log comes in.
So if I then take the natural log of the
odds.
It turns out that when you take a natural
log,
any value that was below one now becomes a
negative number.
So this, the natural log of the odds,
actually ranges from negative.
It can theoretically range from negative
infinity to positive infinity.
So now we've put all the numbers back into
play.
So now this is the optimal for fitting a
line.
So the outcome variable for logistic
regression, and I've mentioned earlier,
is actually going to be the natural log of
the odds of the outcome.
A little complicated but, it's for
mathematical reasons that we,
we We choose that.
And just to illustrate, I took those, the
same groupings, ten groups and
five groups, where I had calculate the
percent, the probability of
being book-smart in each of those groups,
and I transformed that into a logit.
so that's, I took the percentage, divided
by 1 minus the percentage, and
then I took the natural log Of that
number.
This gives me some numbers 0.5, 1.0, 1.5,
2.0.
the, the logit has no inherent meaning to
me.
But that's okay because when we
eventually will translate it back into
something meaningful.
But now this outcome variable is a number
that can theoretically go
anywhere from negative infinity to
positive infinity.
Makes a very fit, nicer fitting line.
I'm graphing here the logit for each of
these groups against again the mean
homework time in each of those groups.
And you could fit a line to that.
And that's what we're doing in logistic
regression.
That's the line that we're fitting.
So, we're going to estimate an alpha and a
beta, an intercept and a slope for
that particular line.
As I mentioned, the groupings here are
completely arbitrary.
When you actually do this in a computer,
there's calculus going on.
And so, you're going to get the best alpha
and the best beta.
When I do this graphically, it's a little
bit of an approximation.
You can see that the line is slightly
different when I
group it into ten groups than when I group
it into five groups.
These slides are slightly different.
But we can actually kind of look at these
graphics and
just kind of visually approximate the
equation of that line.
So, I'm going to do that now.
This is not as good as doing the calculus
in the computer.
But it is, it will give us a little bit of
an approximation and
I think it's also good for illustrating
what's actually going on here.
So what is the equation of this line?
There's two lines here.
And we can kind of say, the, the real line
is going to be somewhere around these two.
So first of all, what's the intercept
value?
So if I just look at the graphic, my
intercept for
this line over on the left side is, I
guess, about 1.6.
You know, I'm just approximating here.
And the intercept over for
the line on the right hand side of the
page is, maybe about 1.8.
So, let's just kind of call it that the,
the equation for this line, again,
if we're kind of saying there's one line
here that we're trying to approximate,
maybe it's around 1.7.
I'm just making it somewhere in that
ballpark.
Maybe around 1.7 is the intercept.
How would I get the slopes of these lines,
just visually here,
how could I approximate the slopes of
these lines?
So what's a slope?
It's rise over run.
So I could say, well, how much have I gone
up in the y variable and
how much have I gone up in the x variable.
So I can just kind of look at this as a
triangle here.
And say, well what's the, how far did I
go.
On, on the x axis I went from about 0 to
40.
So the x changes about 40 here, for this
triangle.
On the y end of things,
you know if you kind of approximate, it's
maybe going from about .3, maybe to 1.6.
I'm going to just call it 1.3 so,
sorry, the, you, the, we go up 1.3 in the
log odds.
So the slope here is going to be rise over
one, so 1.3 divided by 40 or
approximately .03 so the slope here is
about .03.
For this line we can use the same kind of
logic.
[SOUND] So, for the X we went over about
35 here.
That's about zero to about 35.
On the Y end, we've gone up a little bit
bigger, maybe about 1.8,
from one to about 1.8.
The slope then would be 1.8 divided by 35,
which is about 0.05.
So, you know, this somewhere I'm going to
approximate somewhere between 0.03
and 0.05.
Let's call it 0.04 and of course this is
negative.
I should, emphasize here that this is a
downward slope.
We've gone down 1.3 or down 1.8 and Y, so
both of these slopes are negative, so
on average, this looks to be somewhere
around negative 0.04.
This is just my graphical.
Approximation.
But that's what we're doing on logistic
regression.
That's the line we're fitting.
Now I'm actually going to put the data in
the computer and
let the computer use the beautiful
calculus to estimate this perfectly to
get the actual best intercept and best
data slope that fits these data.
And I'll show you that our approximation
wasn't bad.
Here's what the computer comes out with
when it
does what's called maximum likelihood
estimation.
This involves calculus it gives us some
maximum likelihood estimates.
I'm not going to go into the details of
maximum likelihood estimation, that's for
another course.
But this is just the way that using some
calculus that we're getting the best
alpha and the best beta here.
The best fit line.
So when I do this on a computer, the
intercept comes out to be just over 2.
So just slightly different than what we
got in our approximation Summation.
The slope came out to be right around
negative .04, negative .039.
So, and where did I get those in the
output?
Here's the estimate for the intercept,
that's the alpha estimate.
Here's the estimate for the beta, that's
the estimate for the slope.
Along with the alpha and the beta, we also
get a P value to.
Tell us whether that alpha or beta is
statistically different than zero.
A beta of zero would mean no association,
same as it did with linear regression.
So the intercept is clearly significantly
different than zero.
again, that's not all that meaningful
here,
because we wouldn't expect the intercept
to be zero however the p-value for
homework is not statistically significant.
So as you might have guessed just looking
at
the picture there isn't a strong
association here.
So it's not statistically different than
zero.
Probably meaning it doesn't look like
there's a lot of evidence that homework
And whether or not you consider yourself
book smart are related.
But here's the final model, the log odds
of being book smart, or considering
yourself book smart is equal to the
intercept 2.12 minus the slope .039.
And we would of course multiply that beta
times the amount of homework.
So this is a continuous predictor.
So we would be multiplying them out of
homework for
a particular person times that slope.
What's this logistic regression equation
useful for?
So, just like when we talked about linear
regression,
there's many Couple different potential
functions here.
So one thing is we could use the logistic
regression equation model to try to do
some kind of prediction.
This is very useful in clinical
applications because often we want to
classify people as having a condition or
not having a condition.
Condition, that's a binary outcome, so
if we're doing that kind of prediction, we
would likely be using logistic regression.
So we can try to come up with a set of
predictors that predicts who's going to
have a disease or not have a disease.
So that's one of the functions of logistic
regression prediction.
A second function of logistic regression
which is probably, is used more often,
is just to try to say,
is a particular predictor, like homework,
related to the outcome?
In this court case, booksmart or street
smart.
Are those variables related.
Is a treatment related to an outcome?
And that's very useful in of itself and of
course we can say, is that predictor,
that treatment related to the outcome
after adjusting for potential confounders.
So, that's another very important use of
the logistic The regression model.
I'm going to start by talking just briefly
about the first of these aims,
which is the prediction end of things.
Again here's a logistic regression model.
We've modeled the outcome variable, is the
log odds of the outcome.
The, we're modeling that as a line.
Let me take that model that we just fit.
And how would we actually apply it to make
some predictions.
So, if you're somebody who does no
homework per week, 0 hours of homework per
week, you could plug in that val, [COUGH],
value for homework of 0 into the model.
You get that your predicted logint is
2.12.
As I mentioned most of us don't think in
logint so wait a minute,
we're going to do something with that
number to make it more interpretable, but
if you did ten hours per week of homework
you could plug in ten.
The predicted logint there is 1.73...
if you did 50 hours per week, the
predicted logit is .17.
So the more homework you sdo, the more the
logit goes down.
Well I don't want to deal with a logit
because I can't think in logit.
However, we can get this, notice the
There's a probability in there,
what we want to get out is the predicted
probability of the outcome.
The predicted probability of considering
yourself booksmart in this case.
I want, I use to like this predicted
probability.
Well, it's actually not that hard to do,
right?
We've got one equation and one unknown.
We can isolate that probability.
So how do we do it?
The first thing that we're going to want
to do is we're going to want to
exponentiate both sides.
So for example the zero hours per week,
that person would be predicted to have a
logit of 2.12.
I can then exponentiate both sides of
those- Of that equation.
So that would tell me that the odds for
somebody that does zero homework per week
is the exponential raised to 2.12.
That value is 8.33 if you actually
calculated it out.
So e raised to 2.2 is Is 8.33.
That's the odds for a person who does the
odds of being book smart for
a person who does zero hours per week of
homework.
Then we could exponentiate this 1.73, that
will give me the odds for
somebody who does 10 hours per week,
that's 5.64.
We could exponentiate the 0.17, that gives
me the odds for
somebody who does 50 hours per week.
That comes out to be 1.19.
So your odds of being book smart, again,
goes down as you do more homework per
week.
So the opposite of what you might expect.
But of course this is not statistically
significant.
Well, of course, I don't think in odds, so
I want to go one step further and
translate the odds into a probability.
Well, here are the odds.
The odds is just the probability divided
by one minus the probability.
So we can actually solve for p here.
So, to solve for p.
For example, for this first one.
I'm going to multiply both sides of my
equation by one minus p.
Then I'm going to get that P is equal to
8.33 minus 8.33 p.
I can add that negative, that 8.33 p.
I'm going to add 8.33 p to both sides of
the equation here.
Then I'm going to get 9.33.
P is equal to 8.33.
Now to isolate p I'm going to divide both
sides of the equation by 9.33.
.33.
A general formula here is you would do p
is equal to the, odds divided by 1 plus
the odds.
And when you do that, 8.33 divided by
9.33.
Notice that's always going to be a number
between zero and one.
So that's going to give you a probability
that comes out to be 89%.
So the predicted probability for somebody
who does zero hours per week of
homework is that they have an 89% chance
of being book-smart.
The less homework, more chance of being
book-smart.
When you do this for
ten hours per week, you get 85% is the
predicted probability of being book-smart.
For somebody who does 50 hours per week,
they're only, you know, 54% chance.
Their predictive probability of being book
smart is only 54%.
Again, none of this is statistically
significant, but just in terms of
the effect sizes here, these would be the
predicted probabilities.
So out of a logistic regression model you
can predict for a particular person their
probability given their characteristics of
having a particular outcome.
You can also say how good of a job does
the model do of predicting.
An outcome.
You measure this with something called the
area under the curve,
the area under the ROC curve.
And the area under the curve for logistic
regression is analyse to the R
squared that we got out of linear
regression.
It's a measure of model fit and how good
your predictive power is.
Remember that when we did linear
regression,
sometimes you could over-fit your model,
and get really good R-squares,
that actually didn't mean that you had
great predictive power.
It just meant that you had an over-fit
model.
Same principle applies here.
Sometimes a really good area under the
curve reflects over-fitting rather than
good predictive ability.
So just kind of keep that in mind.
I just want to briefly review the ROC
curve.
So let me give you the big picture first.
So this is an ROC curve.
This is the ROC curve for the model we
just fit.
Homework hours predicting book smart,
street smart.
This is actually a really bad ROC curve.
Because homework is not very predictive of
the outcome here.
It's not signifigantly related.
An ROC curve.
Here's the diagonal line.
If you look at the diagonal line here,
the diagonal line on the ROC curve means
no predictive ability.
So if your model falls right near this
line,
that means your model has no predictive
ability, really.
And that's essentially what's happening
here.
Here's our, our, ROC curve in blue.
It's Not doing much better than the, the
line.
This line represents chance.
That you're, you're just flipping a coin
to determine whether or
not somebody has the outcome or not.
So, we're not doing much better than
chance here.
An area under the curve of 50% means no
predictive ability.
The are, an area under the curve of 60%
is, which we have here.
You can see that here.
It's really not much better than that.
What is the ROC curve, though, and what
we're looking for on the ROC curve?
You know you have really good predictive
ability when you get
a curve that looks like this.
Where that is an area under the curve's
going to be close to 100 percent.
The ROC curve is,.
What it actually is, is you're graphing
sensitivity against 1 minus.
The specificity.
High values,
close to 100% is really good predictive
power assuming you're not over fitting.
Values closer to 50% are poor or no
predictive power.
So that's the general picture of the ROC
curve, and
this, my computer just you know, when I
did the logistic regression it
spit this curve out for me automatically
so I didn't have to do any work to get it.
But just to give you a little bit of
detail about where it comes from so
you sort of understand that,
let me show you how this ROC curve is
drawn using this particular example.
Again, logistic regression model gives me
out a predicted probability for
every person.
In this case, the predicted probability
for a given person only depends on
the number of hours of homework that they
reported doing every week.
So if you did zero hours of homework,
you were predicted in 89% predicted
probability.
If you did 50 hours of homework, you had a
54% predicted probability and so on.
What we can do, is we can calculate the
predicted probability, and
again the computer is doing this for me.
We can calculate the predicted probability
for every person in the data set, and
some of these will be ties, because there
are some people who have the same.
Same homework time and thus the same
predicted probability.
So, I'm just showing here some of the
predicted probabilities from my
dataset I'm not showing all.
I'm showing I've lined up the predicted
probabilities from the lowest in
the dataset to the highest and
I'm not showing the ones in between I'm
just showing the lowest and the highest.
Just to illustrate.
What you then to is,
again, though our c curve is based on
sensitivity and specificity.
But we have a continuous predictor here.
So it's not that you know, I have a test
and you either pass the test or
you fail the test.
To get sensitivity and specificity from a
continuous predictor,
we're going to have a range of
sensitivities, and specificities.
The ROC curve is set up by doing the
following.
You take the person with the lowest
predicted probability in your data set,
you make that lowest predicted probability
the cut-off, for
being classified in this case as books.
Smart, so you say everybody who has a
predicted probability of .52 or
higher is going to be called book smart.
Well, since everybody on your data set has
a predicted probability of .52 or
higher, everybody in your data set's
going to be classified as book smart.
So we can actually make a little two by
two table here if our test is -- if
your predicted probability is greater than
.52, greater than or
equal to .52, you're going to be
classified as book smart.
That's a, that is as a positive test.
Then all 48,
there's 48 people here, all 48 are
going to be classified as book smart.
You're classified as street smart if
you're below .52 On
this particular cut-off.
That means nobody will be classified as
street-smart to start here.
And this is their -- we can actually then
compare that to the true value for
book smart or street smart.
So in my data set, out of 48, there were
40 book-smart people And
8 street smart people.
If we count them all as book smart
according to our test,
then we are going to have perfect
sensitivity and zero specificity.
So we've captured everybody who is book
smart if you make the test
predict a probability 0.52 or higher.
We're going to capture everybody who's
book smart, but
we're going to capture nobody who was
street smart.
We're going to miss classify all of them,
so our specificity's going to be 0.
We represent that on the ROC curve right
here.
So this is 100% sensitivity.
And 0% specificity because remember we're
graphing 1 minus 0.
1 minus the specificity, so 1 minus 0
gives us a 1.0 value here.
So we end up here on the curve.
Then we do this again.
Now we move up our cut-off for classifying
people as book smart or
street smart to the next predictive
probability level, which is 0.54.
So now we say, everybody who is 0.54 or
higher,
on their predictive probability, we're
going to call you book smart And in fact,
when we do this, that is going to capture
most everybody has point five four or
higher, but not everybody, so that's our
positive test.
Our negative test, now there are a few who
are below point five four.
They're going to be counted as having a
negative.
On this test.
So we end up with classifying 46 people as
book smart according to our test, but
two we're classifying as street smart
according to our test.
We can actually look at the true value,
who was actually book smart, and
who was street smart.
Remember we had 40 in our set who
considered themselves book smart.
And in fact, we ended up with 38 out of
the 40 who
were book smart were correctly classified
as book smart, and two were misclassified.
The two had predicted probabilities less
than 0.54 were actually out of
the book smart group.
And we misclassified eight, the eight
street smart people as book smart again.
So, our specificity remains at a 0.
Our sensitivity is now 38 out of 40, or
95%.
So we're not, we no longer have a perfect
sensitivity.
That's going to move us down on the chart,
here, to a sensitivity of 95% and
we're continuing to have a specificity of
0.
And we go on and do this for all the
observe, all the predicted probabilities
in our data set, and that's what defines
this curve here, and again, if we have no
predictive ability, you're going to end up
right along that line as we do here.
So that's the ROC curve that tells us how
good we're, how predictive our model is.
The other thing that's often more useful
or
more commonly used from the logistic
regression model is just the same.
What's the relationship between the
predictor, and the outcome, in this case,
homework and book smarts, and as I
mentioned earlier, the,
the beta coefficient from logistic
regression, what happens is if you x/g.
Exponentiate that beta coefficient from
logistic regression.
When you exponentiate that that gives you
an odds ratio.
So we can take this beta for homework here
and we can exponentiate it.
And so we can raise that to point,
negative 0.0389.
When you do that you come out with a value
of 0.96.
So that's the odds ratio here.
Here.
I'll show you in a minute why you can
interpret the beta like this.
But, what this means is we have quantified
the relationship between homework time and
your odds of being book smart.
And you would read this odds ratio of .96
to say that there is
a four percent decrease in your odds of
being book smart for
every one hour more that you spend on
homework per week.
So if I just exponentiate that beta, the
units here are, is,
you know, are one hour of homework per
week.
Notice now we've got an odds ratio for a
continuous predictor.
You can get that in a logistic
regressions, and now we're talking about
an increase in odds for a one unit
increase in the continuous predictor.
Everything up to now,
when we've done odds ratios, we've been
talking about a binary predictor.
You're either in this group or not.
But now we can get odds ratios for
continuous predictors.
Well, how does that translate?
How does that beta become an odds ratio?
Exactly how does that work?
So let me show you that now.
How do we get from beta to odds ratios?
Well, what is an odds ratio?
If I want to know the odds ratio for being
book smart, for the exposure here,
which is more homework time compared to
less homework time What is the odds ratio?
And odds ratio is a ratio of two odds.
So my odds ratio here would be the odds of
being booksmart.
For somebody who does more homework,
compared with the odds of
being book smart for somebody who spends
less time on homework.
And if we're just going with the units
that I've used here.
The difference between the numerator and
the denominator, I could make it in one
hour.
Difference in homework time, so what's my
odds ratio for
a one-hour change, a one-hour increase n
homework time,
how doe that affect my odds of being
book-smart?
Well, now I can just fill in, I fit a
model that tells me that predicted odds of
being book-smart for a given homework
level.
So I can just plug in that model.
So what's the odds of being book-smart for
somebody who does, say,
one hour of homework compared with
somebody who does zero hours of homework?
The odds, which I can put in the
numerator, so
I fit the model that says the log odds is
alpha plus beta homework times
the amount of homework, if I exponentiate
that, remember, I get the odds.
So the odds of being book-smart for
somebody who does on hour of homework, I
can put that in the numerator.
I can compare that to the odds of being
book smart for
somebody who does no homework.
So now I've made a ratio of two odds, the
odds for somebody who does one hour of
homework divided by the odds for somebody
who does no homework.
And then we can simplify this a little
bit.
What you'll notice right away is, you have
to know a little bit about how
exponential works to know how I leapt from
here to here, but if you have e raised to
alpha plus beta, that's the same as e
raised to alpha times e raised to beta.
Well, notice there, they both have the
same intercept, so
those intercepts are going to cancel.
That's the nice thing here.
Those cancel, and if we simplify this, it
just turns out that we're left with this e
beta times one in the numerator, divided
by e raised the zero in the denominator,
that's just e raised to beta homework.
And so that's the odds ratio.
You take the beta for homework, you
exponentiate it, you get the odds ratio.
And the actual value here, for beta was
negative 0.039.
Again, if I exponentiate that, I get an
odds ratio of 0.96.
Six.
So the odds ratio 0.96 means that for
every one hour increase in homework per
week,
your odds of believing yourself book smart
decreases by 4%.
And of course, it wasn't significant here.
I want to just extend this logic to show,
how not only can we get odds ratio out of
logistic regression.
We can get multivariate adjusted odds
ratios.
So just as we made the leap from linear
regression Simple linear regression of
multivariate linear regression.
We can do the same thing with logistic
regression.
It's very easy to add additional
predictors to the right side of
the equation.
We can have a bunch of predictors just
like this.
That's our multivariate linear logistic
equation.
And here's some examples.
Imagine that we did a study where we were
looking at lung cancer.
And let's say for the first logistic
regression model we fit, we put in as
predictors a binary predictor for smoking
and a binary predictor for drinking.
So we looked at smoking, yes or no, and
drinking, yes or no.
Those are two binary variables.
So that's one model we could fit.
That's a simpler model so I'm going to
start there.
The beta for smoking would then represent
the the effect of
smoking adjusted for drinking.
The beta for drinking represent the effect
of drinking adjusted for smoking.
We can make it slightly more complicated
by also adding an additional Small
variable additional predictor in the
model, let's add also age.
We could then get the effective smoking
adjusted for both drinking and age.
The effect of drinking adjusted for both
smoking and age.
And the effect of age, adjusted for both
smoking and drinking.
Let me show you now exactly what I mean.
By adjusted for.
When I keep using that term adjusted for,
what does that really mean?
That means that if I fix everything else
in the model,
it's the isolated effect of smoking or the
isolated effect of drinking.
So let me show you that mathematically
now.
I think it's helpful.
I'm going to start with the binary
predictor,
the model with the two binary predictors
because it's simpler.
Again, what's an odds ratio?
It's the odds of a disease, say, lung
cancer, for
an exposed group compared with the odds of
a disease for an unexposed group.
If I have just a binary predictor, say,
exposed and
unexposed drinker, a non drinker, smoker,
a non smoker.
That's what an odds ratio is.
My logistic regression model models the
odds of disease for given people.
So I can put in the numerator the odds of
disease for, say, a drinker, and I can put
in the denominator the odds of disease,
lung cancer here, for a non-drinker.
And that's what I've done here, so
my model, my first model had alcohol and
smoking, two binary predictors in it.
So if I want to know the odds ratio for
drinking, adjusted for
smoking, I can just say, let me compare in
the numerator the odds for a drinker and
in the denominator the odds for a
non-drinker, so they're, I put in a 1 for
drinking and 0, in the numerator, and a 0
for drinking in the denominator.
Now I'm comparing the odds of lung cancer
for
a drinker compared with the odds of lung
cancer for a non-drinker.
Now, I've also got smoking in the model,
so
I have to put in something for smoking,
but what if I hold it fixed?
So what if I say I'm only comparing a
drinking smoker to a non-drinking smoker
to a non-drinking smoker, so I put in a
one for smoking for both the numerator and
the The denominator, I hold smoking fixed.
And actually, it wouldn't matter if I
chose to
compare a drinking non-smoker to a
drinking non-smoker.
I just have to hold smoking fixed for both
the numerator and the denominator.
I have to make it the same.
If I make it the same, what you can show
is that the intercepts cancel, and
now, as long as I hold smoking fixed, The
smoking betas cancel.
What am I left with?
Well, if I simplify this,
I just have e raised to beta alcohol, e
raised to 0 in the denominator is 1.
So I can show that the odds ratio for
drinking, if I hold smoking fixed is
just all I do is take the beta for alcohol
and exponentiate it.
That gives me the odds ratio for lung
cancer compared to a non drinker.
And again, where I've held smoking
constant.
Notice that this well be the odds ratio
for drinking.
If i compare 2 small pairs or if I compare
2 non smokers.
So, I'm assuming the effect of drinking is
the same in smokers and nonsmokers.
I can use the same logic to show you this
works for a continuous predictor, as well.
So, here's a continuous predictor.
For a continuous predictor, I'm going to
be comparing the odds of disease for
somebody with a higher level of the
continuous predictor compared to
somebody with the lower level.
For example, imagine that I've got my
second model here that's got alcohol,
smoking, and age in the model.
Age is a continuous predictor.
If I want to compare in the numerator an
older person.
The odds of lung cancer for an older
person.
Compared with the odds of smoking for a
younger person in the denominator.
This will give you the odds ratio for an
increase in age.
How much does age affect my odds of lung
cancer.
I'm again going to hold all the other
variables in the model here.
Alcohol and smoking.
I'm going to hold those fixed.
So say I have two drinking smokers.
And I'm comparing a drinking smoker who's
29 years old to a drinking smoker who's
only 19 years old.
That's a 10 unit jump in age.
And you'll see, it wouldn't really matter
if I had put in 40 and 30, or
50 and 40, any 10 unit jump in age is
going to give me the same answer, here.
You'll notice that lots of things per er,
cancelled out, that's the great thing
here.
So we've fix all the other variables, they
all cancel out.
So we're left with, that the beta for age.
In this case, if we and if you solve it
here, 20, beta, e raised to beta 20
times 29 minus e raised to beta 19, that's
the same as e raised to beta h times 10.
So what this tells us is that if I
multiply the beta for h times 10, and
then exponentiate, I will get the odds
ratio for a 10-unit jump in age.
So this would give me, for a 10-unit
increase in age, a decade in age,
What's the increase in my odds of getting
lung cancer?
If I wanted to do it for a one unit
increase in age I would just take the beta
for age and exponentiate it directly.
That would give me the odds ratio for a
one unit increase in age.
It doesn't really matter what you pick for
the units of age, but
you want to pick something sort of
meaningful.
A one unit or ten unit increase is
probably reasonable.
That gives you the odd ratio for that unit
jump.
You can see for
a continuous predictor, the magnitude of
the odds ratio would depend on the units.
It's not going to, what units you choose
will not effect the p value, but
it will effect how big or small that odds
ratio looks.
Just keep that in mind.
You always have to give the units in your
table so
people know how to interpret that.
This is the odds ratio for age adjusted
for smoking and
alcohol which means that we've held
smoking and alcohol fixed.
So that is if we're looking at two people
who have the The same level of smoking and
alcohol and the only difference between
them is a ten unit difference in age.
This would be the effect of that age.
So, just to summarize the practical
interpretation here is
that you take the beta, the slope from a
logistic regression, for
any of your exposures, your predictors,
and you exponentiate it.
You get the odds ratio for that exposure.
And you will interpret that as that's if
the increase in the odds of your outcome,
for every 1 unit increase in the exposure
adjusted for controlling for
other varia-, all the other variables, all
the other predictors in the model.
And we'll practice looking at, an example
of how to use this in the next module.
Just to tell you, most computer packages,
when you run a logistic regression,
you don't actually have to even do the
exponentiation.
Most computer packages will automatically
give you the odds ratio.
So again, out of a logistic regression we
get these multi variate adjusted odds
ratios.