The correct answer for this question is d,
only, the standard error of the mean.
This is because when we have 246 patients,
we, that is quite a lot of patients.
The central limit theorem would have
started kicking in already.
So we would have the mean, the median, and
the standard deviation for
the sample to be closer to the mean, the
median, and the standard deviation for
the total population.
We wouldn't expect those parameters to
change very much if we had it,
added a hundred people.
But the the standard error of the mean,
which decreases directly with
the number of Samples that we have in a
sample size would definitely go down if we
added a hundred people to the number of
patients that we have.
In this case, because we have a very small
sample size of only 13, we need to opt for
a T-distribution as opposed to the normal
distribution.
A d-distribution has one less degrees of
freedom that a number of
the population of the sample.
In this case because we have 13 people-,
children in the sample the degrees of
freedom turn out to be 12.
The formula for
the standard error is given by standard
deviation divided by the square root.
Of the number of observations in the
sample.
And if we substitute the values that we
have, this comes out to 0.23.
This tells us that a is the right answer.
For this question, we know that the mean
is .66.
How do we notice this, is because we have
20 patients out of 30
who improve based on the exercise test,
test.
We also know that a standard error is
given by the formula P
times 1 minus p by a n in this case P is
0.66.
1 minus p is 0.33 and n is 30.
So we have a standard error of 0.086.
The confidence interval is now given by
the mean which is 0.66.
Plus or minus a z score that is pointing
to a 95 percent confidence interval which
is 1.96 multiplied by the value of the
standard error that it is calculated,
this turns out to be 50 to 84 percent.
Let's use the formula that we have for
the [UNKNOWN] calculator using the value
that we have in the two by two table.
This comes out to be 10 by 40 divided by 5
by 55, which is an odds ratio of 2.75.
B wants us to take the natural log...
Off the oz ratio that we found,
which is .75, which is 1.01.
You know that the formula for the standard
error of the log of
the odd ratio is given by by 10 this one
by 40, this one by 5, this one by 55.
This turns out to be .586.
The 95% confidence in material is now
given in new by plus or minus one point.
9 6, times the standard error.
In this case it's 1.01, plus,
minus 1.96 times .586.
Which is an old issue of 1.44 To 2.16.
This question wants us to exponentiate the
values we found in d.
So we have the confidence interval in
terms of odds ratio as opposed to log of
odds ratio.
So that would be an exponential of minus
1.4, which would be the lower bound.
Exponential of 2.16 which is an
exponential of the upper bound and
in terms of the odd ratio we get the
confidence interval to be .87 to 8.66.
The answer to 'F' is false.
The confidence intervals of the laws of an
odd ratio as symmetric as we
just found but when we exponentiate the
symmetry is lost.
And the confidence interval of the actual
odds ratio is not symmetric.
The answer to G is true.
The 95% confidence interval for the oz
ratio crosses one, so
we cannot reject the null hypothesis.
And thus we know that b is greater 0.05.
Part A of this question wants us to
roughly estimate
the two sided p value associated with this
distribution.
If we down the number of observations we
have to the left of negative 25 and to
the right of 25, we'll see they're about
25 observation out of a thousand that have
these values, on which are on the left or
the right data correspondingly.
This translates to a two sided B value of
.025 In
this question we know that the mean is
zero, and
x is 27, and that the standard deviation
is 12.3.
This means that the z-score is 2.2.
This corresponds to a probability Value of
.014 now because we are looking a two
sided 'p' values and not one sided 'p'
values we can multiply this by '2' and so
the final probability comes out to .028.
The next question asks us how would the
histogram would change if I
ran the simulation of a 10,000 times
rather than 1000 times.
And the correct answer is 1.
That it will simply be smoother because as
we have more and
more observations the center limit harem
will start kicking in, and
we will have a more and more normal
looking distribution.
When we have ten times more values, this
distribution will look ten times smoother.
The correct answer to 'D' is two.
The sample size of the hypothetical trial
is larger,
which is the reason that the 'p' value is
lower.
This question gives us the percentage of
US adults Who had five or
more drinks in one day at least once in a
given year.
And we have trends for, let's see, we have
trends for seven years.
We have the mean value as well as the 95%
confidence intervals given.
The question wants us to find for which
years we could reset the null
hypothesis that more than 20% of US adults
had five or more drinks in one day.
At a 0.25 significance level.
The answer is 2000 and 2003 only.
Because these are the only two confidence
intervals which don't cross 20.
And these are the only two confidence
intervals for
which we can safely reject the null
hypothesis.