In the fourth scenario,
we're dealing with an elderly patient
presenting to the emergency department.
This actually could be an emergency
department, it could be a clinic.
With a history of alcoholism, acute
pancreatitis.
Atrial fibrillation, degenerate joint
disease of spine and
both lower extremities, history of deep
venous thrombosis,
intermittent homelessness and multiple
previous hospitalization.
Upon past medical history, medications the
patient said
that they were taking warfarin, mini-dose
aspirin,
ibuprofen, naproxsyn sodium, and loves
garlic.
It turns out that all five of those
medications were prescribed by
different doctors.
So, based on this kind of history,
what do you think the patient actually
presented the emergency department with?
And, you guessed it.
It was a gastrointestinal bleed.
Pretty severe.
Patient actually was being provided care
in the same care
system by several different specialties
and clinics and doctors.
And it's interesting they were using the
same comprehensive electronic medical
system that crossed the entire continuum,
both the emergency department, inpatient,
outpatient.
And, it was interesting that when the
doctors that were involved in the case
were actually interviewed, they actually
never reviewed, or reconciled, or
assessed the medication that's being
prescribed by the other providers.
So, factors that were identified in this
particular event.
You probably guessed it.
The need to review medication prior to
adding, deleting or changing medications.
The need to do a pause or a timeout to
make sure we're dealing with,
knowing what the medications the patient's
on,
that we're ordering, prescribing the right
thing for the patient.
There's always could be factors of
fatigue,
distraction, production pressures.
Variation in work processes, staff
training, communication, teamwork, and
certainly, the culture,
especially if you have multiple
individuals taking care of this patient.
In this particular scenario,
lessons learned included National Patient
Safety Goal has a requirement that says,
gathering of medication information upon
entry into a healthcare setting.
This information should be used whenever
there is an addition, deletion, or
modification in the patient's medication
regimen.
Certainly use the electronic medical
record to assist with information
gathering or confirmation and the second
part of the national patient safety goal.
There's another element there that also
requires that the patient and
or care providers are educated about the
medication that they are taking.
We suspect that if the patient was aware
that
these different medication can affect the
patient's ability to coagulate.
It's real possible that they could have
prevented the event from occurring.
And, not sure if I mentioned, but in this
particular case,
the patient did survive, the visit to the
emergency department.
And subsequent of that, made their point
to let their,
his doctor know regarding medications that
he's taken to have it double checked to
make sure it's not going to effect his
potential bleeding status.