The final concept I want to go over with
regards to the standard normal curve is
that, sometimes, you aren't given the Z, a
lot of these problems are setup so
that you, you're given the Z and then you
have to find the probability.
But sometimes the problems go in the other
direction,
that is you're given the probability and
you have to work back to the z-score.
So if you're doing it in the inverse like
this, that's called a probit function.
So a probit function just means you're
given the area and
you have to find the z-score.
So let me just give you an example and
make it very clear.
So what if you wanted to know, for
this math SAT score, you wanted to know
what SAT score do I have to
get in order to be in the ninetieth
percentile of math SAT scores?
And again, assuming that we're on we have
a mean of 500 and
a standard deviation of 50.
So, how are we going to solve this
problem?
So we need to know what's the z-score that
goes with the ninetieth percentile.
Ninetieth percentile is just an area.
We want to know what's the Z-value that
corresponds to an area of ninetieth,
of 90%.
So, the ninetieth percentile for math SAT
scores is going to be somewhere over here.
That means that 90% of people are lower.
So that means our area to the left is 90%.
So we're going to go to the z chart.
We're going to find the area of 90% and
work backward to the z-score.
So if I go to my z chart and
I just have this, I literally have to scan
around with my eyes until I find 0.90.
And you'll notice that it comes 0.88,
8997, you also get 0.9015.
0.8997 is the closest to 0.90, so I'm just
going to pick that one.
So, that corresponds to what z-score, if
you scroll over, it's a 1.28.
So that corresponds to a z-score of a
1.28.
So, in order to have 90% area and to the
left, you need a z-score of 1.28.
So to be in the ninetieth percentile for
SAT scores, you need to be 1.28 standard
deviation above the average.
So what is 1.28 standard deviations above
the average if I want to
actually get the number, the number for
the SAT score that I'm going to need?
Well, how would I solve that?
Well, what is in this case, a standard
deviation is is a value of 50.
So first of all, I would multiply the
z-score times the standard deviation.
So, I want to be 1.28 standard deviations
above the mean,
that means I want to be 1.28 times 50
above the mean.
The mean here of course is 500, so I'm
just adding to the mean.
When I calculate the amount, I get that I
need to have a,
an SAT score of at least 564 if I want to
be in the ninetieth percentile.