[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next module,
I'm going to introduce you to the concept
of covariance and
we'll talk about linear correlations.
First of all, I want to review from last
week.
We talked about the fact that ttests,
ANOVA, linear correlation, and
linear regression all belong to the same
family of models.
They're actually mathematically doing.
All those tests are doing exactly the same
thing.
You could draw that mathematically they
are identical.
We talked about the assumptions that all
of those linear models have.
One of the assumptions was that the
outcome variable is normally distributed.
Of course, it turns out that these models
are quite robust against this
assumptions as I showed you last week.
We have something called the central limit
theorem which tells us that the means,
remember ttests, ANOVA, linear regression
or all looking at means,
tells us the means will be normally
distributed if your sample size is large
enough even when the underlying trait that
your looking at is highly skewed.
Eventually the central limit theorem kicks
in.
You can't guarantee exactly where that's
going to kick in.
So if you're dealing with small samples,
under a 100,
you have to worry about the normality
assumption.
Usually as long as our sample size is
above 100.
Most times unless you have an extremely
skewed distribution,
that central limit there will, will apply.
But for small symbols we're going to worry
about this and I'll show
you some ways to evaluate the, this normal
assumption for linear regression.
We also have an assumption called the
homogeneity of variances.
For the ttest and ANOVA,
that assumption said that in different
groups, in the different groups we
were comparing the variances across the
different groups had to be the same.
This week we're going to talk about linear
correlation and linear regression.
The assumption is the same except we might
be
talking about now a continuous predictor.
Instead of comparing groups our predictor
variable might also be continuous.
So how this assumption works for
continuous predictors is it says that the
variances for
the outcome variable have to be equal at
all levels of the predictor variable.
Again, models are quite robust against
this assumption.
That means if you have slight differences
in the variances at different levels of
the predictor variable, it's not going to,
be a big problem.
We need to worry about this when there are
really big violations of
homogeneity of variances.
I'm going to show how to do something
called residual analysis today,
to, to check this assumption for linear
regression.
Just keep these two assumptions in the
back of your mind.
[SOUND] I'm going to start here by talking
about Pearson's correlation coefficient,
which is again directly related to linear
regression.
So we've got a continuous outcome and
we've got observations that
are independent and we want to compare a
continuous to that continuous outcome.
So we have now both a continuous predictor
and
a continuous outcome variable, we're going
to use Pearson's correlation coefficient.
Just to give you an example, in the first
week of the course,
I showed you some data from that I
collected from my Stanford classes I
had a simple little data set of 50
observations, 50 students and
I had asked them things about coffee
drinking and their political bent.
I'm showing you here some data relating to
variables.
In the first week of the course, I showed
you how to look at one variable at a time.
Today we're going to be trying to relate
variables.
You see how variables go together.
Here I'm showing you on the x axis is the
variable political bent.
I asked the students to rate themselves
from zero to 100.
Zero being the most conservative, 100
being the most liberal.
I also asked the students to rate their
feelings about President Obama,
whether it's favorable or whether he, they
favor him or not.
So zero was an unfavorable rating, a 100
was the highest and most favorable rating.
Not surprisingly, as you would expect,
as people's political bent went up towards
100, towards the more liberal end.
Their ratings of President Obama also went
up towards a 100.
You can see that relationship displayed
here.
There's a definitely a strong relationship
between your political leanings and
how you feel about President Obama; again,
not surprisingly.
[INAUDIBLE].
How would we statistically evaluate this
relationship?
Now notice that the graphic is a great way
to evaluate this relationship.
We already know a ton just from plotting
it.
So all this stuff I'm going to be talking
about today,
where it's going to be very important to
plot your variables, as you'll see.
But what if we wanted to add one more
piece of information?
An actual statistic, and a p-value to this
graphic.
What statistic could we use?
Our statistical question here is,
is the political bent of a person related
to how they rate President Obama.
So what's the outcome variable here.
Because I graphed the ratings of Obama as
the y variable,
we're assuming that's the outcome
variable.
So, the outcome here is the ratings of
Obama on that scale from 0 to 100.
It's a continuous variable.
We of course, have to ask the question, is
it normally distributed?
Well, let me show you the distribution.
So here's the distribution for ratings of
Obama here's the histogram.
It turns out that it's not exactly a
perfect normal curve, right?
You can see there's a tiny bit of a left
heel here.
Those are the republicans, right in the,
in the class, but it's pretty close.
We have 50 people, 50 observations in this
data set.
By the time you get 50 people, if you
start with a distribution that's
reasonably normal, even if it's a little
bit off like this.
There's pretty good guarantee that the
central limit there is going to kick in.
By the time I get to 50 people, when I
start with something that's just a little
off from normal here, the means are
probably going to be normally distributed.
So for my purposes, for this linear
correlation evaluation,
I'm going to call this close enough to a
normal distribution.
If I only had, maybe, ten people in the
sample, I might not think that
this was close enough, and I might worry
about the normal assumption.
But this is not that far off of a normal,
and for
50 people, I'm going to say close enough.
Are the observations correlated?
No, I just have 50 independent students,
remember, in this data set.
Are we comparing groups here?
No in this case, the independent variable,
last week, we did all these statistical
tests where we compared groups.
But this week I'm talking about the
situations where the independent variable
may not be groups.
May not be categorical, it may be a
continuous variable as it is here.
So if you've got a continuous predictor,
and a continuous outcome variable,
your outcome is normally distributed or
close enough.
And you have independence, then that leads
us to Pearson's correlation coefficient.
I've actually talked about the correlation
coefficient already,
in week five of the course, I actually
mentioned it last week as well.
So as I mentioned, the [INAUDIBLE] the
correlation coefficient is
a value that ranges from negative one to
positive one.
Positive one is perfect positive
correlation.
Here we can see that r,
we represent the correlation coefficient,
we abbreviate that as r.
So we can see that r, the correlation
coefficient is 0.78.
So that's pretty high.
As you can see from the graphc, there is a
strong correlation here.
The p value is less than 0.0001.
The null hypothesis here is that r is
zero.
Because an r of zero would mean no
correlation.
So all that p-value tells us here is that
we can be pretty confident that these two
variables are really correlated.
That there is some correlation here.
I'm going to now walk you through where
the correlation coefficient comes from.
I haven't told you that yet in the course,
so
now I'm going to tell you where it comes
from.
So to understand the correlation
coefficient we have to actually go
back and introduce a new concept called
covariance.
So let me start by talking about
covariance and
then you'll see how covariance leads into
the correlation coefficient.
So here I'm going to start with the
formula for covariance.
The formula is actually instructive here.
Covariance is evaluating the relationship
between 2 variables.
But if you look carefully at this
covariance formula you
might recognize that it looks awfully
similar to the formula for
variance that I gave you in the first week
of the course.
Then of course the,
the title covariance will give you a clue
that it's related to variance.
I'm just going to walk you through what
this formula means,
what it actually produces.
What we're talking about here is when
you've measured two variables on everyone
in your dataset.
So xi and yi would represent, say, you
measured height and weight on people.
X1 and y1 would be the height and
the weight of the first person in your
dataset.
So you've got pairs of heights and
weights that are related because they are,
they belong to the same person.
What are we doing with covariance?
We are trying to estimate, we are trying
to decide whether or
not two variables are, are related to one
another.
Do they vary together?
So imagine you've got, imagine x is height
and y is weight.
And x bar therefore is the mean height in
your sample and
y bar is the mean weight in your sample.
Imagine you've got a person who's really
tall.
So there, that xi imagine that xi is
somebody who's, say a foot above average.
So if you do XI minus X bar for
somebody who's really tall your going to
get a positive deviation from the mean.
If somebody's really tall because height
and weight tend to go together.
Some, if somebody is extremely tall there,
they are also likely to be heavier on
average.
So it's very likely that if you're very
tall,
you're also going to weigh more than
average.
That means the, the deviation for
weighty yi minus y bar is likely to also
be positive.
Will always be but if height and weight
tend to go together positively.
It's, will tend to be that you're going to
end up when you're going to end up with
positive for the deviation for height, you
will also end up with a positive for
the deviation for weight.
So when you multiply together two
positives, of course, you get a positive.
Now let's say you were person who was
short.
So if you're, then your deviation for
height would tend to be negative.
But because you're shorter, you'd probably
also tend to weigh less, so
it would be likely that your deviation for
weight would also be negative.
When you multiply together two negatives,
you get a positive.
So if two things are positively related to
each other, like height and weight.
Your [INAUDIBLE] the covariance will be
something positive.
Now, let's take the case where we have two
things that are inversely related.
Two variables that are inversely related.
So, say if you party a lot in college,
perhaps the GPA will be lower.
Right?
So if you're partying too much,
you're not studying as much, maybe that
will lower your GPA.
Those things might be inversely related.
So let's just say you're somebody who
likes to party a lot,
you're going to have your xi minus x bar,
your deviation for
partying, you're going to be above average
on partying.
So you're going to get a positive for xi
minus x bar.
But, because you're above average on
partying,
maybe you're below average on GPA.
So for you deviation for GPA, maybe you're
going to get a negative.
So, what's a positive time-, times a
negative?
Well, that's going to be a negative.
And similarly, if you don't party as much,
maybe your, your deviation for
partying is negative.
Maybe that means your GPA is going to be
higher.
A negative times a positive is, again, a
negative.
So, two variables that are inversely
related will have negative covariance.
Finally, let's talk about two variables
that are not related at all.
So, let's say, height and your GPA in
college.
Probably not related, so let's say if
you're height is above average.
If your height's above average, well it's
kind of 50-50, whether or
not your GPA is going to be above average,
so maybe you have, it's random, right?
So you have a maybe 50% chance that you're
going to be multiplying that
that positive times a negative here.
So you're 50% chance that you're going to
below average on GPA,
then there's a 50% chance that you're
going to be above average on GPA.
So it's kind, so it's kind of a watch.
Half the time,
when you multiply these deviations
together, it's going to be negative.
And half the time it's going to be
positive.
You add up all the negatives and
positives, you're going to end up with a
coefficient covariance of 0.
So, two variables that are not related
will get a covariance of 0.
So, that's the idea with covariance.
I just want to point out again,
this formula's very similar to the formula
for variance.
Remember the formula for variance looks
like this.
It was xi minus x bar, the deviation for
x, squared.
So, you can think of a variance as just a
covariance between a variable with itself.
So, there's a direct similarity here.
And this formula is not too had to
understand.
Just to summarize, again, if x and
y are independent variables, then the
covariance will be 0.
If x and y are positively correlated, then
the covariance will be above 0,
will be positive.
If x and y are inversely correlated, then
the covariance will be negative.
Now, notice that sounds awfully similar to
what I told you earlier
about the correlation coefficient.
And indeed, there's a direct relationship
between covariance and
the correlation coefficient.
For covariance, the problem with
covariance as a measure is that it
completely depends on the units.
So think about what the units of
covariance are going to be.
If you're talking about the covariance
between height and weights.
Say, your units will be something like
kilograms times meters.
Well that's a little bit arbitrary, that
means a covariance for
height and weight is going to be different
depending on whether you measure it in
kilograms times meters as opposed to when
you measure it in pounds times inches.
So the covariance that magnitude is
completely,
completely dependent on units which makes
it hard to understand covariance and
interpret it directly, or to compare it
across different situations.
So wouldn't it be nice if we had a measure
that got rid of the units,
that standardized covariance?
And that's what a correlation coefficient
is.
If you divide the covariance by the
standard deviation of x and
the standard deviation of y, you, you are
essentially dividing out the unit.
So again, if your covariance was in
kilograms meters, well the standard
deviation of height is going to be the
meters and
the standard deviation of, of weight is
going to be the kilogram, so
you'll divide out the kilograms and the
meters.
You'll end up with a unitless quantity.
So it turns out if you divide the
covariance by the standard deviation of
x and the standard deviation of y, you
divide out the units and
you always end up with a value that will
range between negative 1 and positive 1.
And this is the Pearson's correlation
coefficient,
that measure that we've talked about
earlier in the course.
It's simply a standardized covariance.
We could have just dealt directly with
the covariance if there weren't this unit
issue.
But by standardizing you are making
something, a correlation coefficient that
has no units and something that always
ranges between negative 1 and positive 1.
It's comparable, you can compare it across
many,
many different situations, which is really
nice.
[SOUND] Again, the Pearson's correlation
coefficient is just
the standardized covariance of and I'm
presenting the formula once again here.
Again, you're probably not going to have
to calculate this by hand, but
if you ever wanted to calculate this by
hand.
This looks messy, but
all this is, is the numerator is
covariance, which I just showed you.
And of course you've,
you''ve already calculated in this course
before, the standard deviation.
A standard deviation of a single variable,
so the standard deviation of x and
the standard deviation of y.
So if you had to calculate this by hand if
you understand this conceptually you
should be able to calculate this by hand.
Of course it's very tedious to do this by
and
you would of course do this on a computer.
But I think the formula here is,
helps you to understand the concept of
covariance and correlation.
So correlation, the one thing to keep in
mind that people forget is that the
correlation is
actually measuring the strength of the
linear relationship between two variables.
I'm going to show you in a minute that if
the relationship is
something other than linear,
the correlation might, might not be picked
up by the correlation coefficient.
The correlation coefficient ranges again
between negative 1 and positive 1.
0 means no correlation, means your
variables are independent.
Negative 1 means perfect inverse
correlation,
positive 1 means perfect positive
correlation.
So here's a picture that's showing you
perfect positive correlation,
that means that all of the dots lie on a
single line.
That would be the pictorial representation
of an r of positive 1.
If you have inverse, perfect inverse
correlation.
All the dots lie on the same line.
But your, your slope is negative.
You're going down.
So that's the picture for that.
I'm just going to draw you a few pictures
here to illustrate correlation.
So greater scatter around the line
generally means weaker correlation.
So let me just show you some pictures of
what different correlations look like.
So here's a situation, imagine a situation
where basically if you know x, you pretty
much can nail y, you're everything all of
the dots are essentially on the same line.
That would be an example, as I just showed
you, of r of positive 1.
If, however, there's a little bit of
scatter around the line, that is,
if you know x, you can, you can get pretty
close to y, but it's not perfect, they're
not all perfectly on the same line, but
you're still pretty tight around the line.
That's going to be a strong correlation,
maybe something of the magnitude of
somewhere around 0.8.
So that's little bit of scatter, not
perfect correlation, but
still very strong.
However, if you have a lot of scatter
around the line [SOUND].
We have a big scatter here.
You know, here is the best fit line, the
line that kind of best fits
those points and there's just a lot of
scatter around that.
Well that's going to be much weaker
correlation because now if you know x
there's still a lot of variation in what
your outcome variable is going to be.
There is some correlation here but knowing
x doesn't tell you so much about y.
There's a lot of variability.
And this might be something in the range
of say, 0.3.
That's kind of a weak correlation.
And of course, you know, if you are
talking about a,
something that has a negative
relationship, an inverse relationship,
the slope is going to be in the other
direction.
This might be, say something like an r of
negative 0.6.
It's negative because the slope is
downward.
There's an inverse relationship there.
So that's just to give you a sense of what
different r's different correlations will
look like.
As I mentioned, the correlation
coefficient measures linear correlation.
Sometimes x and y are related,
that is there they're non-independent but
they don't have a linear relationship.
So here's a nice simple example.
Imagine that x and y have a beautiful
quadratic relationship like this, right?
This is a beautiful relationship so
clearly there's a direct relationship here
between x and y.
It's just that it's a quadratic
relationship.
If I were to try to fit a line to these
points, guess what?
The line is basically going to go right
through the points,
essentially having a slope of 0.
My r, my correlation coefficient here is
going to come out to 0.
I might, if I just calculated the
correlation coefficient in
the computer without plotting my data.
I might look at that r and say, oh x and y
aren't related, but that's wrong.
x and y are very strongly related in this
case,
it's just that they don't have a linear
relationship.
They have a quadratic relationship.
So always keep that in mind that the
correlation coefficient is only going
to capture linear relationships.
That's why it's so important to always
plot your data,
to evaluate [INAUDIBLE] are x and y
linearly related?
Because sometimes they're not.
Finally, if you don't have, if you have
two variables that are not correlated at
all the picture is going to look something
like this.
It's just completely random, x and y have
nothing to do with one another.
If you draw a line that best fits those
points,
of course it's going to be flat, the slope
is going to be zero,
and the correlation is going to be zero as
we said.
Back to my example data from my Stanford
class.
As I mentioned the correlation coefficient
between your political bent and
[UNKNOWN] ratings of [INAUDIBLE] President
Obama not surprisingly was high.
It was strong correlation, 0.78.
You can see that there's some scatter
around the line but
it's a pretty strong relationship highly
statistically significant.
I then went and looked at how does your
political bent relate to,
not your ratings of Obama, but
your ratings of the healthcare reform that
just happened in America.
Some people call it Obamacare.
I asked the students to rate how they felt
about that new healthcare law,
the new healthcare reform on a scale of
from 0-100.
Now you'd expect since the healthcare
reform was largely supported by Obama and
the democrats in the US.
You'd expect that your political bent
would predict your
feelings about the health care law.
But you can see that that's true to some
extent but
is not as strong as a relationship as we
saw in the last slide,
it's a much weaker relationship, there's a
lot of scatter here.
You'll notice that it's not it's certainly
not a perfect relationship because, for
example, I've got somebody over here who's
pretty Republican, and
they're really, they really like that
healthcare law.
And here's another Republican who's pretty
favorable towards that healthcare law.
On the other hand, I've got this really,
really liberal person over here who
doesn't like the healthcare law so much.
So you can see there's a lot of
variability.
It tends to go up.
Your feelings about the health care law
tend to go up as you tend to
get more liberal.
But it's definitely a wide range here and
the correlation coefficient of 0.3
reflects that this is a weak correlation.
It does come out to be statistically
significant,
which indicates that it's probably a real
association,
it's just that it's not [INAUDIBLE] not
totally tight, it's not very strong.
I want to just show you, I showed you this
graphic on the previous slide,
that had, I had put a line there, I had
already put the best fit line in.
The reason I want to show you the graphic
without the line is,
notice that when the graphic has the line
superimposed, when I've already asked
the computer to draw that line on, it can
be very misleading to the eye.
If I had shown you this picture first, you
might look at that and
wonder if there really was any correlation
at all there.
Your eye can pick up that there's maybe a
little bit of positive correlation, but
this graphic much better represents kind
of that it's, it's fairly random,
there's a little bit of a trend in
association here, but it's pretty random.
When you draw that line on, it's, it can
totally draw your eye to the light and
you can be misled to think that the
correlation is stronger than it
actually is.
So, just be careful about that, always
look at the picture without the light on.
On top as well, to make sure you're not
getting misled.
One final association that I wanted to
look at was whether or
not your political bent had anything to do
with your optimism.
You might think that since a Democrat's
running the country, maybe the Democrats
would be more optimistic or you know,
something like that.
It turns out that there's no relationship
between your political bent and
your optimism.
At least, not in my class.
So here I'm showing the, the correlation
and again,
the best fit line you can see that it's
pretty much random.
How optimistic you are doesn't really have
anything to do with your political bent.
The correlation coefficient here comes out
to be 0.09, which is pretty close to 0.
The p-value is 0.57.
Again, the null hypothesis here is that
the correlation is zero.
We clearly don't have any evidence to
reject that null hypothesis.
It looks like very well could be that the
correlation coefficient here is
right around zero.
Again that line is probably fooling you
right now.
It's drawing your eye and making you think
oh,
maybe there is a little bit of positive
correlation.
In fact let me take the line off, and you
can see that it's completely random.
Really there's no correlation here.
That line is misleading your eye a bit.