compare those [UNKNOWN].
Here's an example.
There was a study done on marathon runners
who is a cross sectional study.
Marathon runners tend to spend a lot of
time in the sun, so
they develop a lot of skin lesions from
sun exposure.
They develop something called nevi which
can be a precursors to melanoma, so
they're worrisome and the researchers
wanted to know whether or
not more sun would increase your nevi
that's expected.
They were curious whether or not if you're
a marathon who trains more intensely,
who trains faster who trains harder for
the same amount of sun exposure if you are
more likely to develop nevi.
The thought being that, somehow that
intense training is maybe going to wear
down your immunity is going to make you
more, at more risk for skin cancer.
And so, here is the results looking just
at training velocity.
They grouped people according to their
training velocity a slow group a medium
group, and a fast group, that last group
on the right is the fastest group.
Then they counted up their nevi.
Here are the box spots for the nevi
counts.
Our outcome variable here is nevi counts,
it's clearly not normally distributed
right.
We have very much right skewed data.
We would not expect nevi counts to be
normally distributed.
So how would we test whether or not those
3 groups are different?
Well clearly, since we have very skewed
data here,
we're not going to want apply a nova, our
sample size is.
Is reasonably small here.
It's 150 marathon runners, so there's,
roughly something like 50 in each group.
That's small enough with such skewed data
that we're going to not want to
rely on ANOVA.
We're going to want to use a
non-parametric test.
So how did I get to that, we want the
Kruskal-Wallis test.
I want to know whether the nevi counts
differ according to
training velocity group, slow, medium, or
fast.
My outcome variable is nevi count.
It is a continuous variable.
It's actually a discrete variable but you
know, it's it's a numerical variable.
Is it normally distributed?
No, it's definitely not normally
distributed and
it's also, we're also dealing with a
relatively small sample size.
The observations are not correlated; I
have three independent groups.
I have groups being compared, it's not two
groups being compared,
it's three groups being compared.
So that leads me to want to do the
non-parametric ANOVA,
which is called the Kruskal-Wallis test.
[SOUND] When the non-parametric ANOVA is
run again,
it's basically the same logistics as the
Wilcoxon rank-sum test.
I'm not going to go into it in any great
detail.
It involves ranking and adding up the
ranks within those groups.
It turns out that there is a significant
difference in
nevi count across the three groups.
Now remember, all an ANOVA tells you, it's
a global test, so
it tells you that at least one of those
groups differs.
It doesn't tell you which groups differ.
The authors went on further.
They wanted to know exactly where those
differences lay, however.
So they went on further and
applied the Wilcoxon rank sum test to do
the pairwise comparisons here.
But they adjusted for multiple
comparisons.
They adjusted for the fact that they were
then doing three tests.
And it turns out that they could show that
the lowest velocity, the slowest group,
differed [INAUDIBLE] significantly from
the fasted group, in terms of Nevi counts.