Let's dive into some actual real-case
scenario.
A very busy procedure day.
Cases were late in getting started for a
number of reasons.
Proceduralist was anxious to get this next
case started on time.
Because they had a whole clinic schedule
to deal with.
The patient was minimally sedated and
was a little groggy in responding to
questions from the nurse.
The nurse normally uses the consent from
the clinic, but in this case there were
issues with trying to locate the forms in
electronic medical record.
The proceduralist was pretty sure of the
procedure location.
You could picture this scenario where the
doctor walks up to the patient and
says, hey, we're going to work on your
knee, right?
And, the patient responds by saying,
right.
And, in the doctor's mind in that moment
they heard right.
Patient confirmed right.
And so the thought was, hey we're going to
go ahead and
work on the right knee when in reality it
was, it was actually the other extremity.
The outcome?
The patient was brought into the procedure
room.
The right side of the patient was prepped
and draped.
The proceduralist started to do the
procedure and
realized that the pathology was on the
opposite side.
The correct side was then anesthetized,
prepped, and
draped, where the rest of the procedure
proceeded uneventfully.
Now, in this scenario.
Which probably happens based on our
earlier statistics,
as many as 40 times a week across the
country.
Had multiple issues or multiple factors
that led to this particular outcome.
What were some of the potential factors?
Starts off with a concept regarding
marking of procedure site.
It's an element within the Joint
Commission's universal protocol.
The need to do a time out.
Talking to the doctor, the doctor said the
patient said right,
I thought it was right.
You know, we had to move, so there you go.
Was fatigue and distraction at issue.
We all have heard of the studies where
folks that are sleep deprived
the response to reacting or you know,
doing different activities is
equivalent to having a couple cocktails in
the system.
distraction, is that a factor where the
focus is on trying to
get the case started?
Get the procedure done so we can hustle
off to the clinic.
That could be certainly a form of
production pressure, where there's
a need to turn over the room quickly, move
the patient in, get the procedure started.
You can get the procedure going so we can
move on to the next case.
Other factors.
Were there lighting, noise, distraction?
Those things environmentally could
contribute to having a adverse event.
Staff training.
Did they have the right people?
competent, qualified, trained to know
exactly what needs to be done.
Communication, was it crystal clear?
Were we all on the same page?
Were we effectively being a good team,
working in a single mindset.
You know, be able to know what our focus
is.
And, to help each other out in the event
that something not quite right
could've been called out and could be
dealt with.
And the problem corrected before actually
any harm should occur to a patient.
And then ultimately, it's the culture.
As physicians, you have a huge role in
terms of
establishing that culture of the team.
So, what were some of the lessons learned?
Procedures on wrong patient or wrong
location are truly preventable.
Studies have shown that at least one
person on a procedure team was aware of
this, but due to the culture within the
procedure team, afraid to raise the issue.
I know many of us were trained in the
hierarchical structure of
a treatment team, you know, especially as
a medical student,
resident, first-year resident, intern,
fellow, attending.
That, you know, it's not uncommon that the
person that has the most detail could be
one of the more inexperienced team.
And just the sheer fact that they may be
aware of it,
they could have been in a position of
calling some, calling it out, and
this would've avoided a lot of hassle, for
a lot of different people.
This could be due to a number of issues,
including previous bad experience,
unfamiliarity with team members, different
communication styles or methods.
And let's not forget, you know, English as
a second language or
English not being a primary language.
And especially since we are operating in a
very culturally
ethnically diverse population in many,
many healthcare organization.
A lot of it could be communication gaps or
communication issues totally unintended,
so be aware of those factors.
What you say and do can significantly
influence how your team responds.
Some prevention suggestions to prevent
this kind of event from recurring,
a quick huddle to brief what is about to
be done.
We're not talking about the ten minute, 15
minute type of thing.
We're talking about, like, take like, the
10 seconds to
confirm according to whatever your policy
procedure is for your area, or core
documents to make sure that you actually
don't do something on the wrong location.
Take responsibility for the marking of the
procedure site.
In many organizations across the country,
they leave it to the senior most physician
senior most surgeon.
That is that if you have a chief resident
that's in the room, or a fellow or
the attending take the responsibility of
confirming and
marking the procedure site according to
your policy and procedure.
Participate in the procedural pause or
time out.
As I mentioned earlier this is not a five
minute deal.
This is actually a quick five second, hey
we're working on Miss,
you know, Maggie Smith.
We're going to be working on the right
bunion of her right foot.
Are we all in agreement?
And that pause could be the,
once final checkpoint before you actually
make that incision to start the procedure.
That checkpoint could be enough to
actually prevent a misadventure.
Be aware of production pressure, fatigue
and communication style.
And these are some of the steps that you
could actually implement as part of
your practice to prevent a bad thing from
happening.