In this next module, I'm going to talk
about the problem of residual confounding.
And this is a problem that applies to any
regression model.
So not just Cox regression but
also logistic regression, linear
regression any of the other types of
regression that we're actually not talking
about in this course.
So, it's a general problem for regression.
It comes up when you have observational
studies and
you try to adjust for confounding.
People sometimes will look at a paper and
they say, oh well, they adjusted for
smoking, they adjusted for alcohol, check,
check, check.
great, all the confounders are taken care
of completely,
we don't have to worry about them.
But in fact, statistical jar, adjustment
is not a panacea.
You often will have some left over or what
we call Residual confounding.
And this comes about, simply because,
imagine when we measure variables,
when we measure the predictor and the
confounder and the outcomes.
We're measuring all of those variables
with error.
So, when we go in and
mathematically adjust for these different
confounders, we can only adjust to
the extent that we've measured these
variables correctly without error.
And of course, there's always going to be
some error there.
Just think about the way we might adjust
for smoking.
You put in the model, smoker, non-smoker
and you say,
oh, I've adjusted for confounding by
smoking.
But, of course, among the group of
smokers,
there may be a wide variety of, in terms
of how much people smoke.
So, there may be some additional
confounding due to the fact that smokers
contains a lot of different types of
smokers.
And even in that nonsmoking group, you may
have some ex smokers.
So, there's all sorts of noise there,
that's going to prevent you
from being able to perfectly statistically
adjust away all confounding.
So again, residual confounding is just
this idea that you can not completely wipe
out confounding, simply by adjusting for
the variables and multiple regressions.
Always keep in mind there is going to be
some leftover confounding.
And I love to use this example to
illustrate residual confounding.
This was a 2009 study that looked at meat
eating and mortality.
And it's actually really a credit to the
authors that I use this example so
much, because they happen to be, you know,
full disclosure.
Put a lot of information in their paper
that allows you
to actually really see the residual
confounding well.
I've actually shown you the table from
table one
from this study a couple of times now.
So, I'm just going to briefly review what
you're seeing here.
I love this table, because it's just such
a good example,
a good illustration of how it is that risk
factors cluster.
And, and why confounding is such a problem
for observational studies.
So, what you're looking at here, is they
divided the study subjects,
these are just the men from the study,
into quintiles of red meat eating.
So, Q1 is the lowest quintile, Q5 is the
highest quintile of red meat eating.
And if you look at all of the lifestyle
factors that can affect your,
your risk of death and cancer,
they just seem to all get worse as you go
across those different quintiles.
So, for example, BMI goes up as you go
from Q1 up to Q5.
Smoking goes up, as you go across the
quintiles of red meat eating.
Education goes down.
Physical activity goes down.
Healthy eating goes down.
This is just to say that people who eat a
red,
a lot of red meat have lots of other
unhealthy habits in their life.
So, when you try to isolate what is the
effect of red meat only on death,
death and death from different causes,
it's actually really hard to do it.
It's hard to isolate that one risk from
all of these other things that go
along with being a red meat eater.
That's the authors did attempt to isolate
the effect of red meat.
And they did it with a multivariate
regression, with a Cox regression in fact,
because the outcome here was time to
death.
Time to death by different causes.
I'm not going to show you the the table
that shows the hazard ratio.
This is [UNKNOWN] good practice at looking
at hazard ratios.
And I'm going to walk you through this
table, because this is rather big.
So, first of all again, what's the
predictor here?
The predictor is the quintiles of red meat
eating.
So Q1 is the lowest quintile, and we're
going up to Q2 second, third, fourth.
And Q5 is the, those are the highest red
meat eaters.
They first look at the outcome of just
death overall.
And they treated these quintiles as a
categorical predictor.
So, there's actually, they're dummy coded,
so
we're going to get a separate estimate for
each of these quintiles, a separate hazard
ratio.
If you look at the basic model,
the reference group is the lowest red meat
eaters.
If you look at the basic model,
what you can see is that death seems to go
up as you go across the quintiles.
Now, this is not adjusted for anything,
but you see, it's really nicely going up.
Probably not so
surprising given that all those bad habits
went up as you went across the quintiles.
The P-value for trend here is
statistically significant.
And this P-value for trend is something
you're going to see in the literature, so
I want to briefly say how they got that
P-value.
So, this is a single P-value that's trying
to get at whether or
not there's an increase as you go across
the quintiles,
an increase in the rate of death.
So, all they do to get this P-value for
trend is that in the they run across
regression model.
And what they put in the model is a single
beta.
And the x variable here is a variable
that's a numeric variable: one, two,
three, four, five.
So, they take those quintiles,
and they code them as an ordinal variable:
one, two, three, four, five.
And then they put that set of numbers as a
predictor in the model.
They're putting in only a single beta,
meaning they are not treating it as, as,
as separate dummy variable.
So, they're allowing just a single, what's
the increase in risk as you
go from one to two, two to three, three to
four and four to five.
And the idea is that, that the key value
for
that beta comes out to be statistically
significant as it does here,
that there's some increase as you go
across the ordered category.
That's the idea of a P value [UNKNOWN].
We are seeing that here.
What's interesting is that the next line
shows you the adjusted models.
So you'll see that the risk, especially in
the quartile four, quart,
quarter, in quintile four and quintile
five the when you adjust it,
it doesn't attenuate the hazard ratios to
some extent.
Now, there is some increased risk
[UNKNOWN] where 1.21 and 1.31 here, but
there's some attenuation.
So that's suggesting that when you adjust
for
confounders, you are attenuating the risk,
so there is some confounding going on.
What gets even more interesting is when
you look at the cause,
specific mortality rates.
So here, next thing that we're looking at
here is cancer mortality, so
they're only looking at deaths from
cancer.
So again, quintalize the reference group.
As you go across the different quintiles
of red meat eating indeed,
your hazard ratio for cancer is going up,
and the p value for trend is significant.
So, I'm just going to focus now on
quintile 5,
because those are the really risky ones,
the ones eating the most red meat.
So the hazard ratio here is 1.44.
And this is the unadjusted model.
So, that's saying that there's a 44%
increase in the mortality rate for
those in quintile 5 compared with those in
quintile 1.
It is statistically signficant.
Now, when they adjust for all those things
like BMI,
smoking, all the bad things that red meat
eaters do, you can see that there's
a great attenuation of the risk,
[INAUDIBLE] goes from 1.44 down to 1.22.
Now, it remains statistically significant.
It remains elevated, right?
The confidence interval here does not
cross one.
So it looks like,
oh well, we adjusted for all those
confounders, and we still found something.
So there's, there's still an increased
risk.
And you kind of check off the box, we
adjusted for smoking, we adjusted for BMI.
So, and something still remains.
So, therefore, red meat eating is the
cause.
Well, okay.
Let's keep going, though.
Okay.
So
now, we get down this to cardiovascular
mortality, same idea.
You start at 1.44, it's statistically
significant.
You adjust for things,
it goes down to 1.27, still statistically
significant; still elevated.
Alright, but here is the real interesting
one.
You go to the next set of lines here.
Mortality from injuries and sudden deaths.
Okay, so what, what is this category here?
This is people who died from essentially
car accidents, gun fights,
these kinds of things.
And you know, random injuries and sudden
death.
It's very hard to make a causal story of
how red meat eating could
cause you to have a higher risk of
injuries or sudden deaths, right.
There's no reason that eating red meat
should cause you to have a car accident.
Okay, so we're not expecting, this is
almost like a control outcome here.
We're not expecting any association here
between red meat eating and
mortality from injuries and sudden death.
But let's look at the results, so you look
across at the results.
So, first let's start with the unadjusted,
the unadjusted hazard ratio.
Wait a minute.
It is elevated 1.24 and statistically
significant.
And you adjust and
it actually doesn't change much, 1.26 and
statistically significant.
So wait a minute.
What's happening here?
We have the, how do you interpret this
1.26.
There's a 26% increase in the rate of
deaths from injuries and sudden
death in the heaviest red meat eaters
compared with the lowest red meat eaters.
This can not be causal, right?
This has to be due to confounding.
People who eat a lot of red meat have
riskier behaviors, they are risk takers.
Therefore, there is an increase in, in in
the risk of death from these causes, but
it's certainly not due to the red meat
eating.
It's got to be due to confounding.
Well, guess what [LAUGH], the magnitude of
the hazard ratio here,
1.26 is the basically the same as the
hazard ratio we got from cancer mortality,
which was 1.22 and from cardiovascular
disease which was 1.27.
That implies to me that the 1.22 and the
1.27 for cancer and
cardiovascular disease are also likely to
be due simply to residual confounding.
We can't adjust away all the effects of
smoking and
BMI, and all of those things that cluster
with red meat eating.
So, I think this is just a really great
example of residual confounding,
cause you can see the residual confounding
in that mortality from injuries and
sudden deaths category.
The one good thing about residual
confounding is,
it's usually pretty contained.
That is that, you worry about residual
confounding when you
have very moderate and small elevations in
risk.
So the relative risks would usually that
if they're just due
to residual confounding, spurious effect
due to
residual confounding are usually going to
be in the range of 0.6 to 1.6.
And people have tried to model this and
kind of say well, how, how much effect,
how bad can the residual confounding be?
Well, there's really no relationship.
You might get relative risks all the way
down to 0.6.
Or maybe all the way up to 1.6, just
purely by residual confounding.
But it's hard to get much bigger than
that, if you know, if you've adjusted for
the things, and your, you,
you've, you have some error, it, it can
make errors in that kind of range.
But your not going get, we're not worried
about getting the relative risk of
like two or three just do to residual
confounding usually.
Now, what we notice here is of course that
in this case what were our hazard ratios,
they were like 1.22, 1.27, so they were
totally within that range.
So, when you're talking about these kind
of moderate size relative risks,
that's where you start to think hm,
they're kind of moderate size could this
be due to residual confounding?
And one last thing to keep in mind is that
usually we think about confounding,
sort of creating these spurious
associations, but
confounding can also obscure
relationships.
And similarly, residual confounding can
also obscure relationships.
So, sometimes you may fail to find an
effect because of residual confounding.
And those examples are harder to detect
because you,
you know you just don't see anything.
But keep in the back of your mind that
residual confounding can
also obscure relationships leading
researchers to miss associations.