Welcome back,
in this module we're going to show you how
to use the ranks procedure.
This is a fairly simple procedure that
allows you to compute the ranks
of the values of the numeric variables in
your data set.
As you learn more about Statistics, Proc
ranks will become an essential tool for
non-parametric analysis.
Also ranks were used when generating,
quartile, decile, percentile or
any other group you might be interested in
studying.
I'm going to start with the new data set
as you can see I've a column for
gender, weight and age.
[SOUND]
Let's look at some code.
If you look at the code,
you can see that we start with Proc rank
and then we specify our data set.
We use out equals to name a new SAS data
set that will contain the ranks data.
Var which is short for variable instructs
SAS to rank the variable called age.
Let's press Run and see what happens.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You see how the original values for
the age variable are replaced with ranks
for the non-missing data?
[SOUND]
Here's the data point with the first rank.
That means it had the lowest value for
age.
But what if we want to see the ranks
without replacing the original values?
[SOUND].
>> Let's modify the code to include the
original age values as well as
a variable with the age ranks.
In this modified code, we've included a
ranks statement.
This code actually names the variable used
to store the ranks for
the non missing data.
To clarify, we now have told SAS to create
a new variable called rank underscore age,
that records the ranks of the age
variable.
Let's run this and compare the two
outputs.
Notice how our original output had the
ranks listed under the variable name, age.
It was labeled, Value of age Were Replaced
by Ranks.
After including the rank statements,
we now have an output that includes the
actual age value and the ranks
listed under the name ranks underscore age
with the label ranks for variable age.
>> Notice how SAS ranks the data.
The lowest values get the lowest ranks and
the higher values get the higher ranks.
This is ascending order.
SAS will rank the data in ascending order
by default.
If you want to change the order of the
ranks,
you can do that by including the
descending option at the end of your
first line of code.
With descending order, the highest value
would get the lowest rank and
the lowest value would get the highest
rank.
As you can see, the subject with the age
of 18,
which is the highest value, got the lowest
rank.
Number 1.
And the subject that had age 13,
which is the lowest age got the highest
rank.
>> So, what else can you do with proc
ranks?
Like we mentioned in an earlier module,
it's sometimes necessary to convert a
continuous variable into a categorical
variable by splitting it up into separate
bins.
You can use prop ranks to help set up
these bins.
Let's first return to our people today set
and use the following code.
Notice how I've included the words groups
and
an equal sign at the end of our first line
of code.
When you write groups equals a hundred,
you could create percentiles.
Groups equals ten deciles and in our case,
groups equal four for quartiles.
Let's run this and look at the output.
Now, I can see that there is a new column
for age quartiles.
The quartiles were based on the overall
distribution and
each individual record gets a value for
the specific quartile and falls inside