The correct model here is B,
the exposure seconds is equal to 49 minus
0.6 times the years since 1930.
The reason I'm doing it as years since
1930 is because on my graphic I'm
not given, my y-axis here doesn't go at X
equals zero, it goes at x equals 1937.
So it's just easier for
me to estimate the equation of that line,
using years since 1937 as my x variable.
You can see I'm very close to 50 here so
I'm guessing that that intercept is at
about 49, so that's my intercept.
How do I get the slope here?
Well slope is rise over one, run, so
we're going to just calculate the change
in y over the change in x.
So the change in y in this graph we're
going from about just kind of
estimating 49 maybe down to about 10 here.
So I'm going to say that's roughly about
39 we're going down so it's negative.
X changes from 1937 to 2000 so that's a 63
unit change in X so that's going to give
us a slope of about negative 0.6 so that's
where I got the slope here.
Just kind of eyeballing this graphic here.
Which Pearson's coefficient looks the most
reasonable?
So actually, it's D, negative 0.3.
You can see that's there an awful lot of
scatter around this line.
This is really not a high correlation at
all.
So the correct answer is negative 0.3,
it's negative certainly, because there our
line is going down.
But a negative 0.5 is actually too big
here.
So negative 0.3 is the correct answer.
There is a little bit of correlation.
So it's not 0.01 here.
But it's, it's very weak.
So it's point, negative 0.3.
The correct answer to this is, is B.
Actually, linear regression is probably
not totally appropriate here.
We have a fairly small sample size, and
we're violating probably two of the
assumptions of linear regression.
So you can see that we have a lot of
zeroes in terms of the alcohol
exposure time in the movies.
If you have a lot of zeros like that, if
we were to put this in
a histogram you're going to get this kind
of huge zeros and
then it's probably going to be a right
skewed distribution.
It's definitely not going to be normal and
we've got a fairly small sample size here.
Also we're violating homogeneity of
variances.
You see that there was actually a lot of
variance in,
in the movies alcohol exposure early, in
early years and
then it was kind of lessened between and
then there seems to be more at the end.
That may just reflect, you know, how many
movies are captured at each time point,
but it does look like there's some
difference in in the variances there.
The correct linear regression equation
here is C.
It's going to be a dummy coded re,
regression equation because we
have a categorical predictor so our
alchemist logs here are P.
We're going to have some intercept which
will represent the mean in
the reference group.
And then we're going to have a beta for
the infrequent drinkers, and a beta for
the occasional or regular drinkers.
And what is it mean to dummy code?
So again, when we dummy code what we're
doing is we're saying we've got
a categorical predictor where you want to
represent that with two binary variables.
So here's my drinking category that I've
got my occasional regular drinkers.
I've got my infrequent drinkers.
And then I'm making the never drinkers the
reference group.
That's somewhat arbitrary.
But that was the only correct answer I
gave you.
So you had to use that one as the
reference group.
Then I'm making two new variables.
A binary variable.
Which is you're an infrequent drinker or
you're not.
And a binary variable which says you're an
occasional or regular drinker, or
you're not.
So that means the occasional or regular
drinkers will be a one on that variable,
and the other two will be zeroes.
The, infrequent drinkers will get a one on
the infrequent variable, and
the other two will get zeros.
And the never group by default, they're
the ones that get a zero for
the infrequent variable and a zero for
that occasional, regular category.
So they actually, their mean will be
captured in the intercept.
The correct answer here is negative 1.35.
Where did I get that from?
So I'm going to go to the graphic for the
occasional regular drinkers.
And I'm looking for the slope for
the people without depression, that's the
solid line.
Well that lines goes from about a positive
0.1 down to a negative,
about negative 1.25.
So what's the slope?
Well, the change in y here, it goes down
1.35.
X goes from never a drinker to occasional
drinker, remember this is quoted as
a 01 variable so the change in x is just
going to be one.
So, our slope is negative 1.35.
It's just the difference in the means
between the reference group,
the never drinker group and the occasional
regular drinker group.
For this question, notice, I didn't ask, I
didn't specify which graph for
you to look at.
That's because the intercept represents
the mean for the never drinkers and
you can see the never drinkers on both
graphics.
The never drinkers have a mean of 0.1.
So the intercept here is going to be
positive 0.1 or the, depth A here.
So one of the main conclusions from this
picture that we an draw is B.
The alcohol drinking seems to be
associated with a smaller decrease in
inflammation in the depressed group, than
in the nondepressed group.
The nondepressed people seem to get a
better benefit from alcohol.
There's actually an interaction going on
here and
that's what this graphic illustrates.
So, the correct model here is D.
This is a, Model, linear regression model
that has just a categorical predictor in
the model that's been dummy coded, so
if you find the 4.4 in our little table
here, the outcome is visual reception.
We're talking about the unadjusted beta,
so
the only thing that's in the model is the
categorical variable.
It's a three-level categorical variable.
You are either exclusively formula fed,
partially breast fed, or exclusively, or
almost exclusively breast fed.
So there's three categories.
So, our visual reception scores are
outcome.
That's going to be equal to some intercept
plus the beta for
the exclusive breast feeders plus the beta
for the partial breast feeders.
And, I'm assuming, that the, and it tells
us in the table that the reference group
is the formula fed group so, that's why,
they, those are captured in the intercept.
The correct answer here is B.
the, again, we're talking about this value
of 4.4.
It's saying that, on average, it's a, a
yes/no variable here.
You're either exclusively breast fed, and
that's being compared to the reference
group of exclusively formula fed.
So, on average, the exclusively breast fed
babies score 4.4 points higher in
visual reception, compared with the
formula fed babies.
That's what the the value of that beta
coefficient means, the beta coefficient,
the 95 percent confidence interval here
goes from 0.7 to 8.2,
it does not cross the null value of zero,
therefore we know that this is
a statistically significant result, so
again the correct answer is B.
So the correct answer here is A.
Much of the apparent relationship between
exclusive breastfeeding and
infant cognitive function was actually due
to confounding by other variables.
And you can see that here in all of these
different, models and
all these different outcomes.
You can see, for example, for the visual
reception score goes from 4.4 down to
2.4 when adjusted for these potential
confounders.
So there's a big drop in the data and
that's true across all of
the different datas That are measuring
cognitive function here.
Not just the visual reception score.
The correct answer here is A.
Breast milk DHA was treated as a
continuous variable.
So these beta coefficients represent the
change in cognitive score for
every 1% increase in DHA.
There's actually a clue here in the table,
because if you read carefully you can see
it says continuous, and if you read the
fine print it tells you that it's,
the units here are per a 1% increase in
fatty acid concentration.