>> Welcome back.
In this module, we're going to show you
some extra tricks for managing data sets.
First, I'll show you an alternative to if,
then, now statements.
Most of the time, if then now statements
are enough to get the job done.
Sometimes, it's important to make sure you
cover all possible cases with your if
then now statements.
You can do this by using a select end
statement.
Let's look at an example.
So, instead of using if statements,
we have when statements to specify the
conditions which must be in parenthesis.
There's no need to use a then statement.
If the condition in the when statement is
met,
SAS will perform the action that follows
the close parenthesis.
Here we have a block of three when
statements to specify conditions and
actions, just like we did with the if then
else statements before.
It's important to note that, whenever you
want to use a block or when statements.
You must begin the block with a select
statement, and
end the block with an end statement.
Just like with if then else statements, we
create a new variable called weight group,
which depends on the value of weight and
gender.
The difference, is that if one of these
when statements is not satisfied.
The program will not run.
You will get an error and a notification
in the log.
This is useful for catching conditions you
did not consider.
Let's look at what happens when I try to
run the code.
We get an error and a notification in the
log.
Looks like we forgot to consider men with
weight over 200.
And we haven't really specified what to do
if weight is missing, or
subject is a woman.
Here, I fixed the code.
Men with weight over 200 are now placed
into weight group four.
And males, females, or anyone with a
missing value for
weight are now given a missing value for
the weight variable.
Now the code will work, and
we can be sure every case in our data set
was covered by our conditions.
>> I'll now show you an easy way to filter
your data sets.
Sometimes you want to run a data analysis
on a subset of your data.
It can be helpful to create a separate
data set that just has the specific group
that you want to focus on.
Here's how you would do it.
I start with naming the new temporary data
set that I want to create.
In this case, I will call it female.
I then use set to fill in all the data
from the hrp223people3 data set,
by including where gender equals f.
I'm asking SAS to only fill in data where
gender is F.
In other words, we will only include women
in this new data set.
I just want to reiterate that you should
always remember to use quotation marks,
when specifying a character value in SAS.
In the code above in the example in the
previous modules,
we made sure to put the M and F values for
gender in quotation marks.
When you're using aware statements, you
can either use parenthesis and
logical operations, just like we did with
if then statements before.
You will soon learn that if you're using
the label statement,
you can use apostrophe's to label columns.
At first, it will be hard to keep track of
all these quotation marks,parenthesis,
apostrophe's.
But just remember, you can always check
the syntax and
the SAS documentation online.
I also want to take a few minutes to talk
about the label statement,
the label statement can give a column a
more scriptive title.
Which will be displayed instead of the
variable name.
>> Let's take a look at the code, as you
can see I start with data and
name my new data set people_label,
and then include set to fill in the data
from the original people data set.
The statement label weight allows you to
create a label,
that is associated with the weight
variable.
Make sure to include an apostrophe so
whenever you use a label statement.
If you use quotation marks,
SAS will still run your code but your
label will look a little different.
So when you see this, SAS has now created
a new data set with
all the same observations and variables as
before.
In this new data set, there's now a label
associated with the weight variable.
So whenever you make any graphics, or
analysis, or
just look at the data set, instead of
displaying the variable name for
weight, it'll display this label instead.