Let's go back to some data I presented
earlier about the prevalence of depression
and artery blockage in a large cohort of
elderly men and women in Rotterdam.
We can use these data to calculate some
odds ratios.
But before we do the odds ratio, I'm first
going to calculate for you,
the risk ratio.
This study had divided people into 3
levels of
coronary calcification low medium and
high.
It also looked at the prevalence of
depressive disorders within each of those
groups so you can see that as you win up
in the corner in calcification levels that
your going up slightly in the prevalence
of depressive disorders.
To calculate the risk ratios here we have
to pick 1 of the groups to be
the reference group.
So I'm going to pick the, the lowest
coronary calcification group that
also has the lowest prevalence of
depressive disorders.
So it sort of makes sense to make that the
reference group.
To calculate the risk ratio for the median
group compared to the low group then I'm
going to divide the 2.3% by the .9% I get
a risk ratio 2.56 to
calculate a risk ratio for the high group
compared to the reference group I'm
going to divide the 3 by the .9 and get a
risk ratio of 3.33.
How do I interpret these that 2.56 you
would interpret that those with moderate
blockage in the median group of coronary
calcification have a 156% increased
prevalence of depressive disorder compared
to those with the least blockage.
The 3.33 would, you would interpret that
as those with the most severe
blockage have a 233% increase in the
prevalence of depressive disorder,
compared with those with the least
blockage.
Okay, so those are the risk ratios, and
you might think it would be just natural
to report the risk ratios here.
I mean this is a cross sectional study,
it's not a case control study.
The, the risk ratios are valid.
Why would you report anything else?
However, if you look at the paper from the
study,
you'll notice that when it came to
reporting measures of relative risk,
the authors actually reported odds ratios
not risk ratios.
So what's going on here is that the
authors wanted to adjust for confounders.
So they used logistic regression.
And as I said, logistic regression gives
you odds ratios.
And if you read very carefully in the
little footnote here,
you'll notice it says.
Odds ratios were calculated with logistic
regression.
And they even tell you all the confounders
they adjusted for.
This was obviously an observational study.
There are lots of potential confounders
that we want to adjust for.
So they adjusted for
things like age, sex, cholesterol,
cognitive score lots of things.
So that's why they're reporting odds ratio
because they
did this multivaried adjustment.
Logistic regression, logistic regression
gives you odds ratios.
I'm now going to walk you through how to
calculate odds ratio's.
Using a, of course, the unadjusted
percentages.
We're going to use the unadjusted numbers
so
we're going to get slightly different oz
ratios then the authors got when they
used this multivariated adjustment
because, of course,
when things are adjusted they're going to
there going to shift slightly.
But we're going to get, actually you'll
see we get pretty similar numbers.
The first step, before we can calculate an
odds ratio,
we have to calculate an odds for each
group.
So for the low coronary calcification,
calcification group.
The, the risk, the prevalence of
depressive symptoms was .9%.
Therefore, the odds is the, the risk.
The percentage.
Divided by the, the risk of having
depressive symptoms divided by the risk of
not having depressive symptom.
So the risk of having depressive symptoms
is 0.9%,
the risk of not having it therefore was 1
minus 0.9% or 99.1%.
So that's the odds of depressive symptoms
for that group.
For the medium coronary calcification
group we would divide the risk,
2.3% By 1 minus that, 97.7 percent.
That's the odds for the medium group.
The odds for the high, coronary
calcification,
the severe blockage group, is 3 divided by
1 minus 3 percent, which is 97 percent.
So those are how to calculate the odds.
The odds ratio is then calculated by
making a ratio of odds.
And notice, there's lots of fractions
running around here.
So it's, gotta keep track of everything.
[INAUDIBLE].
We're now going to make the odds ratio by
taking the odds in each group and dividing
by the odds in the reference group.
I'm again going to make the reference
group that zero to 100,
that low coronary calcification group.
So to calculate the odds of depressive the
odds ratio.
For depressive systems.
In the medium group compared with the
reference group.
I would take the odds in that group, which
was 2.3 percent divided by 97.7 percent.
That's the odds for the medium group.
I'm going to divide it by the odds for
the reference group, which was .9 percent
divided by 99.1 percent.
When I calculate that out, I get a value
of 2.59, again, slightly different than we
got for the, that the author got for the
adjusted odds ratio but pretty close.
For the high group, the odds ratio would
be the odd
in the high coronary calcification group,
that's 3% divided by 97%,
divided by the odd in the reference group,
which again, 0.9% divided by 99.1%.
'Cuz, see, you're dividing, a fraction by
a fraction.
So, a lot of fractions going on here.
So when you actually calculate that out,
you get a value of 3.41.
So the odds ratio of 2.59 would be incr-,
interpreted as 159%
increase in the odds, not the risk, the
odds of depressive disorder for the 3.41.
That's interpreted as a 241% increase in
the odds of depressive disorder.
And notice that it's an increase in odds
and not an increase in risk and
that distinction is actually not important
if you have rare outcomes.
But, as we're going to see in the next
module, that distinction of
odds here is very important when you have
common outcomes because the odds ratio is
going to be very different than the risk
ratio in those cases.
So again, notice we have, in this case, we
have a rare outcome.
Depressive disorder was very rare here.
So the odds ratio and the risk ratio.
The unadjusted odds ratio, and the
unadjusted risk ratio are very similar.
We calculated the unadjusted risk ratio to
be 2.56 earlier.
For the odds ratio, it was 2.59.
They're almost the same.
For the high group, the more severe
coronary blockage.
It was 3.33 was the risk ratio.
3.41 was the odds ratio.
Notice, the odds ratio is always bigger.
But the difference here is so small, that
when you have a rare event.
It turns out that you can interpret the
odds ratio as you would a risk ratio.
And that's usually the case when we're
talking about a case control study.
Because we usually do case control studies
because of the outcome we're
interested in is rare.
However, when the outcome is common,
as is often the case in cross-sectional
studies or cohort studies,
the odds ratio and the risk ratio are not
similar; they can be extremely different.
And if you interpret the odds ratios
wrong,
that can be very misleading, as we're
going to see in the next module.
I just want to reiterate.
You might be wondering, why the heck do we
ever calculate this confusing odds ratio.
So again, there's two reasons.
You need the odds ratio because, it's the
only valid measure of relative risk for
a case-control study.
And because sometimes authors want to run
logistic regression.
And logistic regression gives you out odds
ratios and so that's what end up,
people end up reporting.
So that's the two main reasons we're going
to end up seeing odds ratios.
There's something wrong within odds ratio,
is simply that you have to be very
careful in your interpretation so that you
don't end up misleading your reader.
Finally, I want to challenge you to
practice calculating an odds
ratio on the Vioxx data.
So, take the data you see on the screen
here.
In a moment I'm going to ask you to pause
the video.
Try to calculate the odds ratio on your
own, and then restart the video and
I'll walk you through the calculation of
the odds ratio.
Show here.
Alright, so hopefully you had no trouble
calculating the odds ratio here.
So to calculate the odds ratio, we're
going to calculate the odds for
the Vioxx group, that's going to be the
numerator, that's 0.42%.
And the, the cha, that's the chance of
getting a heart attack,
the chance of not getting a heart attack
is therefore 1 minus that.
Which is 99.58%.
That's the numerator.
In the denominator, the odds for the
Naproxen group is 0.1% divided by 99.9%.
When you calculate that all out, you get
an odds ratio of 4.21.
Now remember, that our rate ratio and our
risk ratio here Or 4.2.
And so, the odds ratio is almost identical
here to the risk ratio.
Well, why is that the case?
Because the heart attacks here was such a
right rare event.
By which I mean a very rare event.
When you have rare events again, odds
ratios and risk ratios are similar.
And you can see that.