Now we're going to show you how to use if,
then,
now statements to create new variables.
Sometimes when you're trying to manage
missing data,
you can use a technique called imputation.
You'll learn more about imputation in your
other HRP courses, but for
now, just know that imputation fills in
missing data with a reasonable guess.
In this case, we will fill in the missing
values for weight with the mean value for
weight, but we will add in an extra layer
to our imputation strategy.
Since men and women have different
distributions of weight,
we will fill in our missing values
depending on our gender.
So let's take a look at some code.
Beforehand, we calculated the mean weight
for
men in our dataset, which turned out to be
154.
We also calculated the mean weight for
women in our dataset which turned out to
be 140.
So here we specified how we want to fill
in those values into our dataset.
We have multiple conditions for
these if than statements, enclosed in
these parentheses.
The first condition is if weight is
missing and if gender is male.
For these records, we create a new
variable called imputed weight which will
receive the value of 154, like we
calculated before.
The next condition is if weight is missing
and if gender is female, for
these records, we'll create a new variable
called ImputedWeight and
it receive a value of 140.
And then finally, if the last condition
specifies if weight is not missing,
then new variable will just be equal to
the original value of weight.
As a side note in SAS the shorthand NE is
equivalent to not equal.
Another way to code not equal,
is by using a less than symbol followed by
a greater than symbol.
Like this.
[SOUND] In the example above, you could
alternatively write IF
weight less than greater than dot then
ImputedWeight equals weight.
As we discussed earlier, periods are used
for missing data.
Now, if we run the code and look at our
output,
we can see that we have a new variable in
our dataset called ImputedWeight.
If weight is not missing,
computed weight is just equal to the
[SOUND] original weight.
If weight is missing and gender is male
then the imputed weight is equal to 154.
In this case, we didn't have any missing
values for weight for any males.
If weight is missing and gender is female,
then the imputed weight is equal to 140,
as we can see in these rows.
>> Now we're going to walk you through
another way you can use if then L
statements.
Within the if then L statements, you can
also flag items that are likely incorrect,
or just interesting to keep track of.
Earlier in this module, we used if then L
statements that we
believed were way too extreme for our data
set.
Say instead that we
want to flag all observations that have
unrealistic weight values.
This way, we would not be removing or
changing any values in our dataset.
It is always important to think carefully
about the realistic range of
values that your variable could have.
When it comes to weight, it is impossible
for a person to have a negative
measurement, furthermore, it is impossible
for a person to have a weight of zero.
Like we discussed earlier,
we also find it unlikely that anyone in
our dataset has a weight greater than 500.
Here we have a code for
flag all observations with unrealistic
weight values.
If you look at the code you will see that
we put flag equals zero right after our
data line what this does is create a new
data set where all
rows have a variable flag of zero by
default.
We can then add our conditions and
actions without including an else in front
of the multiple conditions.
All rows would automatically get a flag
value of 0 unless it
needs the condition to be specified.
In which case, SAS will change our flag
value to one.
Take a look at the code.
If a row has a weight value greater than
500,
then SAS will change the zero to a one for
the flag variable.
If a row has a weight that is less than or
equal to zero, then SAS will change the
zero to a one for the flag variable.
Now is a good time for me to point out how
SAS deals with missing data.
Like we mentioned earlier, missing data is
represented with the period.
But behind the scenes, SAS treats missing
data as negative infinity.
This means that a missing value is
considered less than any non missing value
including negative numbers.
So, if you specified if weight is less
than or equal to
zero then flag equals one SAS will flag
all rows with weight less than or
equal to zero and also all rows with a
missing value for weight.
This is because a missing value is
considered less than zero.
Here I've run the code so that we can look
at the output.
Do you notice how the individual with the
weight of 9,800
is now a flag value of one?
The male with the negative weight also has
a flag value of one.
Furthermore, all rows with missing values
have flagged values for one.
>> We will now go over a more complicated
example.
With a ten week class, such as HRP223,
we're unable to
cover every aspect of coding related to if
then, else statements.
The best way to master this data set is to
try working with it yourself.
After this module, you'll have a few quiz
questions using the people dataset.
We'll have you read the people variables
in this task, and
write your own if, then code.
Let's look at a final, more complicated
example.
We're interested in creating a weight
group category for male patients.
Let's take a look at a final complicated
example.
We're interested in creating weight group
categories for male patients.
Weight is a continuous variable, but
sometimes it can be useful to treat it as
a categorical variable like this.
Now we have four different bins for our
continuous variable.
We can use these categories in our data
analysis later on.
You'll learn more about the reasons for
turning continuous variables into
categorical variables as you
continue studying epidemiology and
clinical research.
Let's take a look at our code.
On the left here is the data that we're
importing,
notice how we're using logical operations
in our code.
You can include and and or
statements in parentheses to specify the
conditions following the if statement.
In our first line of code, we're asking
SAS to check each row for two conditions,
if the row has an N for gender and the
weight value is less than or equal to 100.
And the row gets a value of one in the new
weight group variable.
If a row does not meet both of these
conditions,
SAS will move on to the next else if line
if code.
Here's SAS will test if a row has a M for
the gender column and the weight value
between 100 and 150.
If the row meets both of these conditions
a new weight group
column gets evaluated too otherwise SAS
will continue to check if a row has M for
gender or any of these other ranges for
the weight variable.
And finally our last else if statement has
three conditionals.
If the subject is a female or they're
missing an entry for
gender or they have a missing weight
value,
then SAS would give them a missing value
for the weight group variable.
Let's quickly take a look at our outcome.
Perfect.
We now have a dataset that creates
categories for
our continuous weight variable, but only
for the males.