[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this next scenario, we have an
emergency situation.
Blood was needed for a patient.
The patient was bleeding out profusely and
the medical team was yelling out for
more blood.
When the multiple units of blood arrived,
one of the doctors started screaming at
the staff about getting the blood hung
immediately.
There was a shift change and the oncoming
nurse, who is,
just come on duty was given a unit of
blood and proceeded to hang the blood.
It was not until after the code situation
stabilized that the unit realized that
the blood was provided was actually meant
for another patient.
So you may be able to picture a busy,
frantic situation.
Staff jumping in to help try to manage the
patient.
There's probably a fair amount of chaos
and pandemonium.
People are kind of hustling around,
screaming and yelling.
So what was identified in this particular
event as being the factors that led to
wrong blood being hung in this particular
patient?
Well, failure of use of two person
identification process, and
when it comes to high-risk medication and
blood product transfusion, there's a need
to have two separate individuals
independently doing an identification
verification process to make sure they got
the right product for the right patient.
And I know some of you would say, well,
this is the middle of a crisis situation.
Well, you might've been able to save the
patient at that moment by
keeping their blood volume up, but
then subsequently that develop another
problem because a patient has a hemoatic,
hemolytic reaction because they have
received the wrong blood.
So, you know,
granted the question is always a balance
between safety and treatment.
And, you know, there's kind of a fine line
that probably in most organizations' case,
they do it right, like 99.9% of the time,
but
that 0.1% time's enough to create a lot of
issues in
an organization where you have entities
like the federal government, the state,
the Joint Commission, the plaintiff
attorneys, etcetera living with you.
Another factor that was identified in this
particular event, fatigue issue.
Certainly distraction, production pressure
environmental issues,
space, lighting, noise variation of work
processes.
Those are things that, you know, in a
frantic, chaotic situation, especially if
you have shift change, you have people
trying to leave, people are coming on
duty, you know, and they could create
hand-off issues, communication issues.
Staff training.
I know that most organizations, depending
on the kind of care service and
treatment they provide, would actually
have exercises or
drills to practice those once in a while
type of events.
But, nevertheless, you know, every event
has its unique variables and,
you know, the factors that lead to a bad
outcome could be slightly different.
Communication was certainly a factor.
Teamwork was a factor and certainly
culture.
Some of us know that in a frantic
situation, you know,
we're trying to get some response from
staff, do the right thing.
You know, sometimes the yelling and
screaming actually aggravates and
confuse the situation more, rather than
getting the job done.
So but hindsight after this particular
event, the review process you'd say,
well, it's 20-20, it's crystal clear, we
know exactly what we did wrong.
And why we did it wrong, but in the moment
when these things occur,
which we've all been evolved with in terms
of medical emergency,
things are seen differently in the lens of
the different participant.
And ultimately, you know, you, you really
prefer that it do not cause harm or
does not cause harm to your patients.
Some of the lessons learned from this
particular event,
Joint Commission's National Patient Safety
Goal require that two individual perform
a two patient identification check prior
to administering blood.
It doesn't distinguish between emergency,
urgent, or routine.
you, we all know in the case of a
emergency bleed out situation, you know,
fluid blood volume is super critical.
But even so, you still need to make sure
the double checks are put in place and
that they're followed through.
Another thing,
the frantic nature of the case disrupted
communication between the team members.
There were certainly issues regarding the
hand-off, and the oncoming nurse, you
know, in this situation clearly thought
all the double checks were done and
all they were asked to do was to hang the
blood, not realizing that the double check
process hadn't been already done by the
team at the patient's bedside.
Another factor in term of lessons learned
is tight space limited the ability of
the team members to maneuver to perform
the double check.
They, in this particular situation, you
know, they had a wristband on the patient.
The armband is used as an identifier
because certainly, you know,
folks can't ask the patient.
The patient was non-responsive in terms of
their identification, so
they rely on the wristband and
unfortunately because of the really,
really tight space in this particular
clinical setting staff was wasn't able to
get to the wristband to do a verification.
So some of the prevention strategy and
this is really based on the culture
of safety, is that there needs to be an
understanding to push back when necessary.
Staff probably would have benefited from
having someone pull the doctor aside that
was yelling at the staff to hang the blood
because I think, in the most cases, folks,
when they know what they're assigned task
are, they're going to go out and do it.
They don't need anybody else yelling and
screaming at them to do it faster.
They just need to be able to do it.
So there needs to be a culture of safety
with the team, to be able to push back
when necessary, to make sure that, the
right thing is done for the patient.
Communication hand-off practices,
especially in the emergent situation.
I know many times, many of you folks, are
involved with code situation, and drills,
and exercise, and actually have real
drills real events, and real emergency.
That one of the big learnings from these
things is the debrief after the event,
to figure out, did we do it exactly the
way our system and processes had intended.
Or are there things that we need to do to
expedite things?
change things?
In this particular situation, there was a
need to do a repeat back instruction for
confirmation about the patient that we're
working with.
And if we had that in place, the staff
would have, you know,
made aware that in fact that the blood
product that was available to the patient,
that the doctor was asking them to hang
emergently,
would have been confirmed to be not the
right patient.
And then there's another concept that
we'll mention that there's a fair
amount of research and literature on.
Has to do with team situational awareness.
We all know when the adrenaline gets going
you're going to hear what you want to
hear, or you're going to hear what you
think you need to hear, and that you know,
that when you communicate things,
everybody may not be on the same page.
This concept of situational awareness
plays out in,
certainly in the aviation biz, business,
commercial airline industry,
when somebody in the front of the
airplane, ideally the co-pilot, you know,
would say, hey, you know, to the pilot,
lights on, looks like gas low.
And if the pilot is focused on trying to
control the airplane because something
mechanically had failed, they may not hear
anything that the the co-pilot says, and
that has to do with the concept of
situation awareness.
So in the moment, in the situation, the
adrenaline is going,
there's multiple things being processed by
the individual.
You may not be aware or cognizant of
what's going on.
And you only may be aware of only your
particular slice.
And that's life.
What you feel may most important may not
be the most important thing for
the rest of the team.
[BLANK_AUDIO]