So now, I'm going to review the
Kaplan-Meier statistics.
So the Kaplan-Meier curve is
a non-parametric estimate of the survival
function.
All that means is that we're not trying to
say, oh,
this survival function follows an
exponential distribution.
Or a specific distribution, a specific
shape.
We're just defining the survival function.
Whenever events occur, we define the
survival function.
So, it's an empirical estimate of the
It's just what is the probability of
surviving past certain times in
the sample taking into account censoring.
If there was no censoring.
If people didn't drop out of the study at
different times.
In fact, this would be a very easy thing
to estimate.
But the, the trick to Kaplan-Meier is that
it's accommodating that censoring.
And the Kaplan-Meier curves, we're going
to draw some Kaplan-Meier curves.
Those can be compared statistically to get
a P value with a log-rank and
a log-rank test is just a type of
chi-square test.
So, let me just show you how this works
very briefly with a simple example.
You have five subjects who start a study.
And let's say that the first event that
happens in
the study is that subject E dies four
months into the study.
We're going to define the survival curve
here right at four months,
whenever events occur.
So, we're going to go to our curve.
Our curve starts at 100%, but at four
months Subject E dies.
So, we drop our curve.
The survival probability now goes down to
80%.
4 out of 5 survived that event time.
4 out of 5 survive past four months, so
our survival probability here is 80%, we
drop the curve down to 80%.
Let's say the next thing that happens is
that subject A drops out after six months.
They are censored at six months.
We don't know if they went on to die in
the last six months of the study.
But, we know that they were alive through
the first six months of the study.
We're not going to change the curve
because we
don't know that anybody died there.
But we're going to indicate that on the
curve with a little mark.
Then, the the next thing that happens is
that subjects see dies at seven
months at those sites.
So, that's another event we're going to
change the curve.
We're going to drop the survival curve the
probabilities down seven months.
Notice that I'm indicating at six months,
where subject A dropped out of the study
with a little bar here.
This indicates the censoring that somebody
was dropped out of the study.
We drop our curve down at seven months
when subject C died.
Now, the way that these censoring gets
incorporated here.
Is that right before seven months at that
time point,
there were actually only three people at
risk of dying.
You're not going to count subject A in the
denominator here because they
were censored.
So, we'll weigh that subject A is getting
incorporated here the way that we're,
how they in fact that they were censored.
Is that our denominator now is just 3
rather than 4.
So, we say that 2 out of 3 survived this
second interval from four to seven months.
The survival probability for this second
interval was 2 3rd, 2 out of 3.
And then, on say subject B and D,
survive all the way to the end of the
study period and the study ends.
So, we just draw the curve over we don't
have anything else happen.
Now the Kaplan-Meier curve gives us a
cumulative probability of survival.
So we have, we drop the curve down here
at, to 80%.
80% of the people were surviving.
Where did I drop the curve?
I didn't tell you yet where I dropped the
curve down here.
So what, where, what percent, what was my
chance of survival?
Where did I drop the curve down here?
I mean, to do that, we have to multiply
together the probability of
surviving the first interval, which was 4
5th.
You have to survive the first interval and
the second interval to get the cumulative
probability.
The probability of surviving the second
interval remember was 2 out of 3.
So, to get the cumulative probability of
surviving the past seven months,
we multiply 4 5th times 2 3rd, that's s
survival probability of 53%.
So, this curve is now at 53%.
So, our curve here is defined at just 2
times points when events occurred.
There was an 80% probability of surviving
past four months,
and a 53% probability of surviving past
seven months.
And through to the end of the study,
we just multiply those intervals together
assuming we have independence here to
get the total probability of surviving the
whole time.
Notice that this Kaplan-Meier estimate of
survival takes into account censoring.
The 53% that we've estimated the
probability of surviving
past the year is kind of a compromise
between two other possibilities.
We started the study with five people.
We know that two people died.
So, if you were not accounting for
censoring you could just say well there
was 3 out of 5 people who survived the
study.
So, maybe a rough guess at the survival
probability would be 60%.
On the other hand, you might look at it
with the sort of glass half empty.
And you might say, well you know,
actually I only know that two survived in
past the year.
I don't know what happened to the third
one.
So, I'm going to say that the survival
probability is only 40%.
And maybe it's a little higher than 40%,
but I might make a guess of 40%.
So, my bounds here is, I could either
estimate.
If I wasn't accounting for censoring, I
could either estimate the probability of
survival for a year to be 40%, because I
only say two survive the year.
Or I could estimate it to be 60% because I
only saw two die.
It's going to be somewhere in between
there.
So, notice that the 53% from the
Kaplan-Meier estimate is
a good compromise between those two.
Let me do go through a real example of
doing a Kaplan-Meier curve.
This is, we're going to just look at a
single curve for one group of women.
I'm going to make a happy route here.
Come here rather than death, we're going
to talk about time to conception for
people who are trying to get pregnant or
having trouble.
The failure therefore is a good thing, the
event is a good thing.
So there were 38 women who were treated
with infertility with a certain treatment.
And we are trying to track their time to
pregnancy.
All the women were followed for
up to two years to describe time to
conception and the event is conception.
So, we're starting with 100% of women not
being pregnant, [COUGH] and
women survive until they conceive.
As to the event here is conception is a,
is a positive outcome.
So, here's all the data.
It's a nice data set because it just
writes out all, we can see all the data.
These are the women who had the event.
These are the women who did not have the
event and this is the timing of it.
So, here's the Kaplan-Meier curve that
corresponds to these data.
And everywhere you see a little star,
that's just where a woman was censored.
She dropped out of the study before she
became pregnant.
So, we start at a 100% and it drops down
from there.
Remember, we want the curve to drop here.
We want, when the woman are trying to get
pregnant,
the survival function is a step wise
function with nine event times.
There's nine unique steps on this curve
that defines the survival probabilities.
Again, we only find the survival
probabilities where we actually see event.
So, let me just show you walk through how
this is calculated.
Again, a computer will do this for you but
its nice to have some concept of what's
going on.
So, the first thing the first month and
women can only get pregnant once a month,
right?
So, the first month, the first cycle,
there were six women who conceived.
So, they all had events in the first
cycle.
So, we can represent them on the curve six
women conceived in
the first menstrual cycle.
Therefore, 32 out of 38 survived
pregnancy-free past the first month.
So, we drop the curve down here.
A the survival probability of not getting
pregnant is 84%, so
we dropped the curve down to 84%.
That's the survival probability of making
it past one moth without getting pregnant.
Second thing that happens is in the second
month, we had five women who conceived.
Now, there is one woman who was censored
after two months.
I'll just, I'm going to call her 2.1 so we
don't get confused.
So, there were,
I had written down that a woman conc, that
was censored at two months.
That means she made it through two months,
we know she didn't get pregnant the second
month.
So, her censoring is going to happen after
the second month.
How do I represent this on the curve?
Well, I'm going to drop down the curve.
Five women conceived in the second month.
What was the risk set?
How many women were at risk of conceiving
in the second month?
There were 32 women.
We started with 38, six got pregnant in
the first month, 32 are left.
Therefore, 27 out of 32.
About 84% again survived the second month
pregnancy free.
To get the cumulative probability of
survival,
we have to we have to multiply together
the probability of
surviving the first month times the
probability of surviving the second month.
We multiply those two probabilities
together.
I get a total probability, a cumulative
probability of surviving pregnancy free,
free, past the second month of 71%.
So, I dropped the curve down to 71%.
Next thing, in the third month, we have
three women who conceived.
One woman is censored in between the
second and the third month.
So, we have to she is not going to be
included in the risk set.
She was not at risk of getting pregnant in
the third month because she
was dropped out.
So, there were only 26 women who were at
risk of getting pregnant in month three.
Out of those, three got pregnant, 23 did
not.
So the survival probability is 23 out of
26 or 88.5%.
Again, we have to multiply that with the
other ones to get
the total probability of surviving past
three months pregnancy for eight week.
Drop our curve down now to 62.8% in the
fourth month.
We had one person who had censored at 1
3rd,
so the at the fourth month, our risk set
was down to 22 women.
3 get pregnant, 19 did no get pregnant.
We're going to do the same thing.
Now, our probability of is down to 54%,
and we can keep going with this.
You get the idea.
[COUGH] At six months, there risk set of
18 women.
So, 88.8% survived this next interval
pregnancy free.
We're going to drop the curve now down to
42.9%.
That's your probability of surviving past
six months, pregnancy free in this study.
And I got bored here and
decided to just scroll ahead when you get
down to 13 months.
The probability now is down to 22%, and
I just want to point out what happens at
the end of a Kaplan-Meier curve.
So, at 13 months, the probability was 22%
that dropped rapidly down to 15%.
So, there was kind of a big drop off here
at 16 months.
But that drop just represents that there
were three women left in the study.
And one got pregnant, and you get a big
drop in the curve just from three women.
So, as you get to the end of Kaplan-Meier
curves,
you're often down to a very small number
of women.
We have to be little bit careful about
interpreting the end of
the Kaplan-Meier curve things getting
legally.
So, two women did not conceive.
The tail of that curve here represents
that there
are just two women who remain
pregnancy-free for the rest of the study.
And it's not a represental lock, it's only
two women.
So again, at the end of the study that the
last of them are going to 16 months.
And then, they are at that point,
there was only 3 women left, 2 didn't get
pregnant, 1 did.
So this is, you can imagine our estimates
are getting very wiggly.
There's a lot of uncertainty when you get
down to such small numbers.
So, just keep that in mind with the end of
Kaplan-Meier curves.
Finally we can also compare Kaplan-Meier
curves between two or more groups.
And here's an example of two groups.
Researchers randomized 44 patients with
hepatitis to receive either a steroid or
no treatment.
And then, they compared the survival
curve.
And here's the raw data.
In this case, I've got two groups.
So, I'm indicating censoring with a little
red star.
So somebody who has a little red star
means that they were
censored at that time.
People who don't have the star had the
event at that time.
I'm not going to go through the drawing of
these two curves, but
it would be the same way that I just
showed you.
And here's the resulting Kaplan-Meier
curve.
So, the red is the control group, they're
dying off faster.
The outcome here is death, and the steroid
group is doing a lot better.
Are those two curves statistically
different?
That's one question we're going to want to
answer when we're comparing groups.
It's a little misleading to the eye.
Because if you look at these two curves,
you might think, oh well,
the two curves are converging at the end,
right?
The two curves seem to join back together
at the end.
There seems to be a big divergence, and
then they seem to, to come back in.
But remember at the end of a Kaplan-Meier
curve, there's a lot of,
there's very few people left.
And so, there's a lot of uncertainty if
you were to drag,
draw confidence in amongst those estimates
would be very wide.
So, at this little jump here,
this drop, this big drop you're seeing in
the steroid curve at the end.
That just represents there were only three
people left.
And one of them died and two of them
remained.
So, the survival probability,
you're multiplying the curve by 2 3rd
which is a big fraction.
You're, you're really dropping the curve
quite a bit here,
just due to one person dying.
Also, there's only just six people left in
the placebo control group.
That just happened to survive the rest of
the study.
So, that represents that long curve at the
end just represents six people.
So, you have to be a little careful about
over-interpreting the ends of
Kaplan-Meier curves.
They can get pretty wiggly with such small
numbers.
So, I ran a log-rank test on these data in
a, a computer package.
Actually, doing the log-rank test by hand
is pretty tedious.
But a log-rank test compares those two
curves.
It compares them across all the time
points at once.
It's a chi-square test.
It's a chi-square test with one degree of
freedom.
Again, I'm not going to go into the exact
details of the test.
But it's a chi-square test with one degree
of freedom.
It did come out to be statistically
significant here.
Saying that the overall those time points
there is
a significant difference between the two
groups.