Welcome back.
In this module we're going to talk about
Proc Sort.
This procedure is useful for sorting your
data set.
Let's use the people two data set we
created in the last module.
Proc Sort can be used to sort the people
data set.
Say we want to organize our data set so
that we have females first and then males.
Let's look at some code.
We start with Proc, which by now you know,
stands for procedure.
Our next command is sort, followed by the
data set we want to sort.
Here we've included out equals
people_sort_gender,
to name the output data set.
The next line of code says, by gender.
Which means that were sorting our data set
by the gender variable.
Since this is a character variable it will
be sorted in alphabetical order.
Let's press run.
Here's our output,
as you can see the new data set is sorted
by gender.
[SOUND]
>> Now suppose were interested in sorting
the data by ages in descending order.
To accomplish this, I once again write
Proc Sort,
specify our people2 data set and name a
new data set called people_sort_ages.
In the next line, I write by descending
age.
This tells SAS to sort my original data by
descending age values.
Let me run this.
You can now see that the data are ordered
by age.
From the highest to the lowest.
So far, the examples we have used, have
been pretty straightforward.
But what if we want to sort on more than
one variable at a time.
Say we wanted to sort by gender and then
by weight within the gender levels.
Let's take a look at the code for this.
For our by statement, we first wrote
gender, and then specified weight.
So within males and females, the data
should be sorted by weight.
Here we'll run it, within males and
females, we now have the data sorted by
weight.
The key to multiple level sorting is drive
by and
then the variables you want sorted in the
order you want them sorted.
In our case, we wanted gender first and
then wait in ascending order.
>> Now I'll cover something a little bit
more complicated.
Let's start by rebuilding our people data
set.
In this data set, I've duplicated one of
the records.
As you can see here.
I want to demonstrate a function of Proc
Sort that lets you remove duplicates.
SAS can do this if we
include the NODUPLICATES option in the
Proc Sort's statement.
Let's take a look at the output.
As we can see, we no longer have that
duplicated record in our data set.
Oh, this is a great feature.
It only works when duplicate observations
are right next to each other.
What do you do when duplicate observations
are not next to each other?
In this case,
I sorted the data set by all the variables
by adding underscore all underscore.
This code forces the duplicate
observations to fall
right next to each other.
And then we run this code,
it'll remove all the duplicates, no matter
where they're on the data set.