Many procedures can use something called a
buy statement.
This allows you to run a procedure on all
the subsets of the data,
specified by some categorical variable.
For example, if you have a variable for
gender, which can either have a variable
of m for male, or f for female, we can
specify by gender, to run a procedure
on a subset restricted to males and then
again on the subset restricted to females.
>> Now suppose you want to calculate the
mean weight for men and for women.
We already showed you how to do this using
the where statements in proc means.
But if you do it this way, you have to
repeat all your code for
each subset you're interested in.
If you're looking at a variable with more
than two levels,
it could extremely cumbersome to repeat
your code multiple times.
Instead, if you specify by gender as we
show you here,
you automatically run your procedure on
all the levels of the gender variable.
>> But there's one catch before we're
ready.
If you tried to run this code, you'll find
that it doesn't work.
Before you can use a by statement, you
need to sort your data set.
We need to sort it by the gender variable
first.
In this code, I first sort by gender, and
then use a proc means with a by statement.
Now, it will give us the output for
females, and for males all at once.
>> So just to summarize, Proc sort can be
used to sort your data in ascending or
descending order, and you can use it to
remove duplicates as well.
>> If you want to use a by statement to
run a procedure on multiple subsets of
the data, you need to use proc sort to
sort the data on your variable of
interest first.