When we do statistics on binomials,
what we actually usually do are statistics
on proportions.
So I just want to point that out now.
We don't usually talk about, oh, I got 60
I found 60 smokers in my 200 cases.
We don't usually talk about the number 60,
we talk that about the proportion that
that's 30% of my sample.
So our statistics are all going to be on
the proportions rather than the counts.
So you'll just notice when we do
statistics on proportions,
it'll look a lot like the binomial.
But everything will differ by a factor of
n.
So, a statistic on a proportion, when I,
I represent that as a p-hat, that means a
sample proportion.
If I want to know, what's the mean and
standard deviation of a sample proportion,
those fall right out of the binomial.
The mean and variance for a binomial.
So the mean is just p.
That's, np for binomial, divide by n.
Because a proportion divides by n, that's
the mean for a, proportion is p.
And similarly, the standard deviation for
the binomial is the square root of n times
p times 1 minus p.
If you divide that quantity by n, it turns
out to be this lower quantity.
And we're going to see this particular
formula a lot because that's the standard
error of a proportion.
So again, that formula is going to come
up, but
it falls right out of the binomial.
And, when we're doing statistics on
proportions,
we're actually usually calculating
z-scores.
We're actually pretending we're on a
normal as long as the original binomial,
the n times p, is greater than 5.
So most of those statistics on proportions
have that assumption embedded in
them that n times p is greater than 5.
If it turns out that you have a situation
where you have n times p is very, is much,
is less than 5, that often occurs if you
have a very small sample.
You need to instead go back to calculating
the exact binomial probabilities.
And those tests are, they are, just what
they sound like.
They are, they are named things like the
exact binomial test.
So we'll see some of those in the case
where you might have small numbers and
it's not appropriate to approximate with a
normal.