Alright, now, we're going to jump to the
continuous case.
As I said, the continuous case is a little
bit more tricky.
It's a little bit more math involved in
this.
We're just going to touch upon the
continuous case this week.
But, if you have any continuous
mathematical function, if that
function integrates to 1, that just means
that the area under that curve is 1.
Then, it is by default a probability
function.
The probabilities associated with a
continuous probability function are just,
again, areas under the curve.
Just integrals.
And, probabilities are going to be given
for a range of values rather than
any particular value, so in the discrete
case, we talked about the probability that
exactly 1 occurs, or the probability that
exactly 9 occurs.
With a continuous case there are no
particular,
there's an infinite number of possible
particular values, so
we're always talking about the
probabilities of ranges of values.
Like, what's the probability that it will
fall between 1 and 2?
So let me just give you an example to make
this clear.
So, a very simple but
important probability function is the
exponential distribution.
And let me just write up what that
function is.
So, the exponential distribution is e
raised to negative x.
We call that the exponential distribution
in probability.
And that function is just a mathematical
function,
where the area under the curve is one.
And we can kind of just draw a picture of
that function to see that.
You can't have negative values.
So it starts at one and it kind of goes
down towards the x-axis like that.
Now, if I just told you that the area
under that curve is 1,
you'd probably say that sounds reasonable,
right?
If you were to calculate the area under
the curve here, it starts at 1 and
it goes down towards the x value, it seems
reasonable that that area might be 1.
So if you want to just believe me, that's,
that's fine.
I can also show you the interval for those
who are interested.
Again, this is optional,
but we could take the integral over all
possible values of this function.
So you can have any value from the x, can
be anything from 0 to infinity.
If we take the integral of e raised to
negative x.
And we, we integrated over the, from 0 to
infinity.
We get a value of 1.
Again, that, that integral is just there
for those of you who want it, but
that just proves that the area under the
curve is 1,
therefore, it's a probability function.
So here is the same function, just drawn
out.
We call this the e raised to the negative
x,
we call that function a probability
density function.
It's analogous to a probability mass
function, that little table where I
wrote out if x is this, the probability of
x is that, for for the discrete case.
But really, the probability density
function it gives us this curve, but
we can't really talk about the probability
of any particular value off of this curve,
because there's an infinite number of
possible distance, different values here.
So we can't really assign probabilities to
any particular value,
we can only assign probabilities to a
range of values.
So we're always talking about a range of
values.
because if you say, what's the probability
of getting a value of 1?
Well, do you mean 1 or do you mean 1.0, do
you mean 1.023?
Right?
So you're always really talking about
a range of values.
So, in, that means that, when again, when
we're talking about a range of values,
we're actually a, talking about a
cumulative distribution function rather
than a probability mass function.
But don't worry about that terminology.
All that means is, instead of looking at
the original function,
we're looking at the area under the curve.
And again areas under the curve happen to
be calculated with integrals, but
you can kind of look at this picture I'm
showing here.
So like if I asked,
what's the probability on an exponential
function of being between 1 and 2?
Well, you could kind of just draw in that
area and you could almost estimate it just
from looking at the picture, that that's
around, you know, a quarter of the area.
Or, you could do out the actual integral,
which I'm showing on the bottom for
those of you who want to see the integral
done out.
We could do the integral from 1 to 2 and
we find out that precisely the area under
the curve here is 23%.
And here's an example of how this might be
used in medicine.
So let's say that we found out, we did a
study and
found out that survival times after lung
transplant roughly follow
an exponential distribution, an
exponential function .
So people are dying after a lung
transplant at a certain rate.
If it follows an exponential function,
then we can use that information or
approximately follows an exponential
function to get,
to calculate the probabilities of survival
in different time periods.
So for example, the probability that a
patient will die in the second year after
surgery, somewhere between the year one
they will survive up through year one but
die before year two, that that is they
will die between years one and two.
If we get the end of the curve it's 23%,
so
their probability of dying in that
interval is 23%.
So it has very useful applications, the
exponential function in survival analysis.
We'll talk about that in the very last
week of the course.
Another example of a useful,
continuous probability function is the
uniform distribution.
It's a very simple, nice little function.
So it's easy to, to understand, so
it's easy for illustrating some of, some
of these concepts.
So the uniform distribution is just a
distribution where you can,
x can only take on values between zero and
one, and they all have equal probability.
Hence, it's uniform.
And you can see,
it just makes that function, literally
just makes a little box, a little square.
And the area under the, the curve here,
the area in that box has to be 1, right?
The, the width is 1, the length is 1, so 1
times 1 is 1.
You can also prove that the area under the
curve is one by doing
an interval here should you choose, of
course, we don't really need that because
everybody knows that the area under of
that box is just one.
So the very simple little distribution and
it's easy even without knowing any
calculus to calculate areas under the
curve here.
So for example if I said,
what's the probability that x is between a
quarter and a half?
Well, that's going to be 1 4th or
if I said, what's the probability that x
is between 0 and 1 ?
Well, that's going to be 50%.
And this has real practical implications
in medical research.
So, for example, when you're doing a
randomized trial, and
you're randomizing patients.
Say you're, you're randomizing half the
patients to treatment and
half the patients to control.
The typical way that you would do that is
to use a random number generator in
a computer.
And, one of the random number generators
available to
you works by randomly generating a number
between 0 and
1 with equal probabilities of all the
numbers in between.
In other words, it's based on a uniform
distribution.
Every subject has an equal probability of
getting it, any number between 0 and 1.
So you can arbitrarily say if the subject
ends up with a number below 0.5,
we're going to call them control.
If the subject ends up with a number above
0.5, we're going to call them treatment.
That will randomly assign people to
treatment and
control with 50-50 probability.
And I had a case a couple of years back
where a student of mine had done some
a research project where she had randomly
assigned people to a treatment group and
a control group.
And then actually literally flipped a coin
you know, an actual
point to decide where people were going,
which group they were going to end up in.
And the reviewer one of the reviewers of
her paper came back and
said, well, they were, they didn't like
the fact that it was done manually,
that that a person had actually flipped
coins.
Because that allowed the probability,
the problem that you could introduce error
or bias.
And so, it's better to have your computer
virtually flip coins.
And, and this is what I just described is
exactly the computer flipping
a coin virtually.
So it's very useful for things like
randomizing patients.
Now, all probability distributions have
two features to them that
are very important, they have a mean and a
variance.
And this mean and variance are just like
the mean and
variance that we talked about in the first
week of the course.
So in the next couple of modules, I'm
going to tell you how to calculate
the mean and variance for a probability
distribution rather than for data.
And we've already seen some mean and
variance of probability distributions.
We saw the normal curve before.
The normal curve has a mean, and it has a
standard deviation.
So, we've seen these before.
Now, I'm going to show you how to
calculate them.