In this module, we're going to tell you
about PROC GPLOT,
which can be used to create scatter plots
and line plots.
>> PROC GPLOT gives you a lot of control
over the scatter plots and line plots.
Let's start with a basic scatter plot.
>> By now you should be used to the syntax
for
the first line of your procedure in SAS.
We start out with PROC GPLOT, and then
specify our data set.
In the next line, we have a plot
statement.
Which tells SAS that we want to make a
graph.
We type age asterisk weight, to specify
the variables in this plot.
The order is important here.
By defaults, the first variable will be on
the vertical axis, and
the second variable will be on the
horizontal axis.
>> As you can see,
we have a simple scatter plot that graphs
age versus weight.
Now suppose we want to add a title to this
plot.
After the first line of code specifying
PROC GPLOT and the data set of interest we
will write, title and age verses weight
within apostrophes.
Remember, always include apostrophes
around your titles.
>> As you can see,
by default, SAS will put the variable
names next to the x and y axis.
It's good to have a descriptive axis label
though.
We'll show you how to do that.
>> [NOISE] These label statements
are very similar to a title.
You start with label, specify the variable
you want,
and then make sure to put the labels
within apostrophes.
>> This way you can specify the units of
your axis.
>> SAS automatically determines the range
for
the x and y axis as well as the spacing of
the little tick marks.
Let's manually set the size of the axis.
To accomplish this, we need to return to
our code.
Underneath our, our label for age and
years.
We put axis1 order equals parenthesis 100
to 180 by 5.
And the next line we define axis2 with
order equals 20 to 100 by 5.
Notice how we specify the range of values
and the jumps between each value.
>> Next, we have to specify which axis is
going to be axis1 and
which one's going to be axis2.
To do this,
we go into the PLOT statement, and include
a forward slash to add some extra options.
We write vaxis which stands for vertical
axis, equals axis2.
And haxis which stands for horizontal
axis, equals axis1.
As you can see, we've now manually set the
range for our x and y axis.
Say you want to specify the height of your
axis labels.
You can do this in code as well.
After each axis statement, we would write,
label equals parenthesis h equals 3.
[SOUND]
Here we have h, which is short for height,
which controls the size of that label.
If you want a bigger label, you can use a
larger number here,
and if you want a smaller label, well, you
would use a smaller number.
We can also control the symbols that SAS
uses for the data points.
We only have one type of symbol here,
which SAS will refer to as symbol1.
So if you write a symbol1 statement, you
can change the settings.
Let's say we want a red triangle with a
smaller height.
We can specify this with v equals
triangle, for the shape.
C equals red, for the color.
And height equals 0.5 for the size.
There are many options for shapes and
colors that you can use, and you can find
these on the online documentation.
>> What if we want to add a line to our
graph?
In the same line where we specified our
symbol attributes,
we can add i equals sm70s.
And line equals one.
In SAS, i stands for interpolation line,
and sm stands for smoothing.
The 70 tells SAS how smooth you want your
interpolation line to be.
The larger the value, the smoother the
line.
The lower the value, the closer your graph
will follow the noise in your data set.
The s at the end of sm70s stands for sort.
In order for SAS to make an interpolation
line,
it first has to sort the data behind the
scenes.
If you leave off this s at the end, your
line will look really weird.
By adding line equals 1,
you're just selecting the type of line we
want SAS to draw.
Once again the online documentation will
show you a bunch of different options.
>> [SOUND]
What if we want to show different
subgroups of the data?
It might be nice to compare this plot for
men versus women.
[SOUND] We can do this in the plot
statement by adding in, equals gender.
When you do this, gender must be a
categorical variable.
SAS will now distinguish between males and
females, and it will add a legend to the
plot.
Now that we have two different subgroups
in the data,
we can also use two different symbols.
I added in a line for symbol2 in the code.
And I made it a blue square instead of a
red triangle.
As you can see, we now have different
symbols for men and
women, as well as a legend that will tell
us which one is which.
>> At this point, you can see we've added
a ton of options to our plot.
Most of your plots won't be this
complicated.
But if you want to add more options,
you can just look at this online SAS
documentation.