In this question you are presented with a
hundred blood donors
with the following distribution of blood
types.
The question is asking for the probability
that a random donor will have blood type
'AB' because the question doesn't specify
whether these donors are RH positive or
RH negative.
We can conclude that there are going to be
4 donors out of 100.
Were going to have blood type AB, or in
other words 4 percent.
So the answer here is A.
This question is asking us for
the probability of getting 3 sixes if we
roll 3 dice.
The probability of rolling one six with
one die is simply one out of six,
and so with three die, that probability id
going to be one out of 216.
So, the answer here Is going to be b.
This question is asking us for
the probability of getting a sum of eight,
if we roll two dice.
Okay, so this is a little bit more
involved but
basically the thought process behind this
is to think about all the different ways,
in which you can get a sum of 8 and
because the numbers only range from 1 to
6, we have limited possibilities.
So, you can have 2 plus 6, or 6 plus 2.
You can have, 3 and 5 or 5 and 3 and
lastly you can have 4 or 4, okay?
So, that's out of a total of 36
possibilities, right?
So there are 6 total possibilities in each
die; you square that to get 36.
so, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5; 5 possibilities out of
a total 36 possibilities.
And so we see that the answer is c.
So this question is asking us about the
probability Of
drawing a three card sequence exactly.
And this is from a standard 52-card deck.
It actually doesn't matter what three
cards they are for this question.
What you have to realize is that there's
only one way to get
that particular three card sequence.
And we have to calculate the number of
total possible three-card sequences.
So, because there's only one possibility,
1 goes in the numerator.
And the total number of three-card
sequences.
Well when you, before you pull your first
card, you have 52 cards available.
Okay, so it's 1 out of 52, essentially.
Then after you pull your first card, there
are only 51 cards left.
After you pull your second card, there are
only 50 cards, 50 cards left.
And so, your calculation becomes 1 over
the product of 52 times 51 times 50, and
so we see that the answer here is letter
D.
So, this question is asking us
about how many different 5-card
combinations are possible.
If you draw five cards from a standard
deck.
And the question specifically clarifies
that you do not care about order.
So in this situation, you can directly
apply the choosing function, okay.
The choosing function, the formula for
that is n factorial.
Over n minus r factorial times r
factorial.
Okay, so n factorial, the n here,
represents the total number of cards in
the deck.
So that's 52.
And you're pulling 5 cards from that deck.
So it's going to be 52 minus 5, or 47
factorial down here; times 5 factorial.
So n is 52 here; and you're choosing 5 out
of 52, so r is 5, okay?
So we see that the answer Is in fact
solution D.
This question reads: what's the
probability of
getting four fives in a row when you roll
a die four times?
Okay, so the thought process is that
there's only one way.
To get four fives.
So that's going to be in the numerator.
In the denominator you want to have the
total number of outcomes.
And because each die has six faces, you
have six choices each time.
Of course you're going to roll that that,
roll that die four times.
So it's going to be one over six raised to
the fourth.
4, or 1 over 1296; so we see that the
answer is c.
One other way of thinking about this,
right, is to,
is to take each die individually.
So if you roll a dice four times, you want
four 5s in a row.
There's only one five on each face, so
every time you only have a one in
six chance of rolling a five, and you're
going to do that over four times.
Again, this going to give you the same
answer, but
it's just another way of thinking about
the problem.
So this question reads: a randomized
crossover trial Involves four
interventions.
Each participant will get each of the four
interventions in random order.
How many possible orderings of
interventions are there?
So this is simply 4 factorial.
So 4 factorial is going to equal 24 and we
see that the answer.
Is B.
Now the reason this is 4 factorial might
not be immediately obvious at first,
but basically the question is asking for
the possible orderings of 4 different
interventions.
So basically imagine you have intervention
A, intervention B, intervention C,
and intervention D.
Right?
So it's asking us
How many ways can you order these four
letters.
So when you first your intervention here,
or your letter, you have four choices.
So I'm going to put 4 here.
Then after you pick your first one Whether
it's D or not,
you have three choices left.
So you're going to pick, I'm going to put
three here.
And so you can see if I follwoed that
logic,
I'm going to result in this expression 4
times 3 times 2 times 1,
which is simply the same thing as four
factorial.
So this question reads when you draw three
cards from a standard 52
card deck What's the chance that you will
get a three-of-a-kind?
Okay.
So, this is a little confusing at first,
but let's break the problem down into
pieces.
So, the first thing I'm going to do is to
think about what I
want to be in the fraction.
Okay?
So, In the top i-, in the numerator rather
I want to
have the different number of
three-of-a-kind hands, okay.
So, all, all sort of the, the winning
hands are getting three-of-a-kind.
And then the denominator I want the total
possibility of
three-card combinations, okay?
So the denominator is going to be 52
choose 3; that's saying,
I choose 3 cards from a 52-card deck.
And that's going to be all the possible
three-card combinations, OK?
And so that's going to equal 22,100.
Now let's think about the numerator depth.
So, for each type of card, of which there
are 13 types,
right, there's 4 choose 3, so 4 ways that
you can get a three-of-a-kind.
So there are 4 times 13 or 52 different
three-of-a-kind hands.
So then the fraction becomes 52 over 22100
Or answer choice C.
Okay, so this question reads: a certain
lottery works by
picking five lucky numbers from 1 to 47
and one MEGA number from 1 to 27.
You only win if you match all 6 numbers.
Okay, so basically, You have a condition
for the first 3 numbers, and
then a new condition for the last number.
So that's one way of thinking about it.
So how many possible combinations are
there for
the first part of picking 5 numbers?
So that's going to be simply 47 Choose
five, which is equivalent to one and
a half million.
About, basically.
Okay so there are one and a half million
possible five number combinations for
the lucky numbers.
Then each of these right,
each of these five each of these
combinations, each of these five
numbers can be combines with one of 27
different numbers from that mega number.
So the total number of ways to win is 27
times this number, 47 Choose 5, okay.
And that works out to be
about 41,416,353.
So, how many ways are there to win?
Only one.
So, this is your answer.
And that corresponds to answer A.
So, this problem introduces the at least.
Type problem, and just as a review, for at
least type problems, the key is to
realize that the probability of at least,
of the event happening at least once,
is equal to 1 minus the probability of it
not happening at all, not at all.
Okay.
So, the question reads if a couple has
five children,
what's the probability that they have at
least one boy?
Again, and so you're clued in to this fact
that it's an at-least type problem,
because of the wording in the question.
What's the probability that they have at
least one boy?
So this probability is represented by the
probability of having,
of doing 1 minus the probability of no
boys at all, right?
So, that's equal to doing 1 minus and, you
know it's 0.5 1 minus 0.5 raised to the 5.
so, and it's raised to the 5 because the
couple has five children.
So you do 1 minus 0.5 raised to the 5th
and
that works out to be 0.969 or about 96.9%.
So answer choice d is the correct answer.
In this next problem we're given a
situation where the probability
of some situation B is 0.75, and a
probability of some situation A is 0.2.
And then we're given this joint
probability of A & B as 0.1.
And we're being asked if A and B are
independent connect or not so, if 'A' and
'B' are independent then the probability
of A happening times the probability of
'B' happening is equal to this joint
probability.
Okay, so we can check whether they are
independent or
not by multiplying Point seven five times
point two,
which works out to be point one five,
which is not equal to point one.
So we say that they are not independent.
The correct answer in this case is A.
This question reads.
Suppose that 15% of the population is
exposed to some dangerous chemical Z.
So, if you're not exposed to Z,
you have a lifetime risk of some bad thing
happening of .0001.
And if you are exposed to Z Your lifetime
risk increases fourfold to .0004.
So, what percent of the population will
develop this really bad thing, and
this problem is pancreatic cancer.
And so, the way of doing this is to just
calculate, and use the law of
total probability, which is just a fancy
way of saying Weight the percentages.
So, if 15% are exposed and their risk,
right is .0004, you want to add that to
the 85% of the population.
Where their total risk is 0.0001, right?
And just add these two to get the overall
risk in the overall population, and
this works out to be .000145.
So the correct answer here is answer
choice d.
This next question presents us with a
similar situation.
So 15% of the population is exposed, which
means 85% are not.
Those that are exposed have an elevated
risk of .0004 of
developing pancreatic cancer.
Those who are not exposed have a, a
fourfold lower risk of .0001.
The question is specifically asking if
someone develops pancreatic cancer,
what is the chance that he or she was
exposed to Z?
So, this is probably easiest illustrated
through A diagram so
there are two branches here.
You can either be exposed to chemical Z or
not exposed.
So, your probability to exposure is 15%
and probability of non-exposure is 85%.
If you're exposed, right.
So, if you're exposed, the probability of
developing disease is 0.0004.
If you're not exposed, the probability of
developing disease is .0001.
And I'm just going to subtract to fill out
this branch and
this branch and basically just going to
subtract by 1.
So this branch is going to be 1 minus.
Point 04 and this branch is going to be 1
-
0.0001 because that's the probability
that's left over.
So, another way of thinking about that is
that,
these probabilities have to sum to 100 at
every juncture.
So, if I multiply this out I get 0.00006
here.
And if I multiply this out, on the bottom
I get .000085.
[COUGH]. Okay? And these are what we're
interested in
because ultimately what we want to do
right remember is to calculate.
The probability that a person was exposed
to chemical Z given that he or
she develops pancreatic cancer.
And the fact that she this person he or
she develops pancreatic cancer is
represented by these 2 probabilities.
Okay.
So, the probability of disease given
exposure,
which is this over the probability of
disease when you're not
exposed plus the probability of disease
When you're exposed, right.
So that's going to be the sum of both of
these numbers.
So this is the expression that we are
interested in.
And this is equal to 41.
0.4%.
So if you have pancreatic cancer,
there's a 41.4% chance that you were
exposed to this bad chemical.
So in this question we're given a
fictitious probability of
event B which is point seven five.
We're given a fictitious probability for
event A, which is point 2.
Then we are also given a probability for A
and B.
This joint probability of point 1.
Okay, and the question's asking what is
the probability of A given B.
Well, the probability of A given B,
there's a formula for this.
You can do the probability of A and B over
probability of B.
Think about it, as dividing out.
This probability of B.
And so that of course is equal to 0.1
divided by 0.75 and
that is equal to 0.133, and so the answer
in this case is answer A.
In this question, we're given a, a few
clues.
And we're being asked to select the
correct statement about sensitivity,
specificity and positive and negative
predictive values.
So, let's read the question first.
So, in a group of patients presented at
the emergency room with ankle pain 30% of
them have a fracture.
60% of patients with a fracture are older
than 55 and
30% of patients without a fracture are,
are older than 55.
So what this kind of information
immediately lends itself to is
making contingency table or a 2 by 2.
Because we're dealing in percentages we
could just.
Make up a baseline number of patients at a
100; this is going to make things easier.
So we're told that 30% of patients
presenting with ankle pain have
a fracture.
So you make this row Fracture, and this
row No fracture.
30% of 100 is 30, which makes this row 70.
Now the columns are going to be Age let's
just make this greater than 55,
and we can make this less than or equal to
55.
Okay, so next part.
60% of patients with a fracture Are older
than 55.
So of, of the three patients that
comprised these two cells,
sixty percent lie in the top right cell,
okay?
So .6 times 30 is going to equal the
number in this cell,
which is going to be 18.
That automatically makes this one 12.
Then the next clue, 30 percent of patients
without a.
Fracture are older than 65.
So 30% of 70 is going to be the number in
this cell, and that's going to be 21.
Which is going to make this cell 49 just
by subtraction.
Then when I add vertically, to fill out
this 2 by 2.
So once we have this 2 by 2 setup we're
basically basically done with
the question.
So, looking at this 2 by 2 you can
calculate the negative predictive value.
Now your predictive value of course is,
the number of true negatives, over testing
negative.
Okay so basically of all the people who
tested negative how many were
actually negative, that's what this is
getting to.
So that's going to be 49 over 61 [SOUND],
which corresponds to answer d in our
question.