What about the distribution of a
correlation coefficient?
So, the correlation coefficient,
again ranges from a value of negative one
to positive one.
0 means that two variables are
uncorrelated.
+1 is perfect positive correlation.
-1 is perfect inverse correlation.
Everything in between is some level of
correlation.
And we have the picture here shows that we
have a very weak correlation between
vitamin D and cognitive scores.
So what' s the distribution of
a correlation coefficient another measure
we can calculate from our data.
Let me do another computer simulation.
So in this computer simulation I said that
the true correlation between vitamin D and
cognitive function in the entire
population of older.
European men is 0.15.
If that's true then I can sample from that
population,
sample both vitamin D levels and cognitive
scores.
I select a random sample of a 100 virtual
men.
They all have a cognitive score and
a vitamin D level based on this underlying
correlation.
I calculate the correlation coefficient in
the sample.
And then I do this, again and
again and again, and let's say I do it
15,000 times this time.
You're getting the idea of a computer
simulation now, and
then we can explore the distribution of
those 15,000 correlation coefficients.
So, here it is, here's the results.
So, notice, I found a normal curve again.
Well, this is great.
Lots of statistics follow normal curves,
so
it turns out the normal curve is very
important for this reason.
So here are some things.
It's normally distributed, hooray.
The mean turns out to be exactly the true
correlation,
0.15, because most of my samples come out
somewhere around 0.15.
I asked the computer to calculate the
standard deviation of
these 15,000 observations, what we would
also call a standard error here.
It came out to be, in my simulation, 0.10.
So, that's for
my computer simulation, the distribution
of the correlation coefficient.
It turns out that the shape of the
distribution for
a correlation coefficient, as with the
mean,
is a normal distribution as long as we're
talking about sample sizes above 100.
It is on a T-distribution though for
smaller samples.
So if you have smaller samples, there's
some additional uncertainty and
you actually are at a T-distribution,
which looks a little bit different.
So for smaller samples,
you have to worry about being on a T
rather than an, a normal.
But for larger as in this example it's
essentially under normal.
The, the mean of the distribution of a
correlation coefficient is the true is
the true correlation coefficient, not
surprisingly.
The standard error, somebody's worked out
with mathematical theory,
it tuns out to be approximately the square
root of 1 minus r squared and
r is the true correlation coefficient in
the whole population.
And divided by the square root of N.
Notice it has a lot of similarity to the
standard error of the mean.
They both have square root of N in their
denominator.
So bigger samples means smaller standard
errors once again.
Turns out that many statistics follow
either normal distributions, or for
small samples, T distributions, so this is
great.
You saw two examples already.
It popped up to be a normal distribution.
Even when we didn't start on a normal
distribution.
It turns out lots of statistics follow
normal distributions or T distributions.
So statistics that follow T distributions
for
small samples and normal distributions for
large samples, include means,
as well as difference in means, and
correlation coefficients.
Things we just saw.
Things that follow normal distributions
whether or not you have a small or
a large n, that is, it's always on a
normal distribution Include proportions,
risks, differences in proportions,
and a statistic that has to do with the
odds ratio.
And since we spent a lot of time on the
odds ratio in week two,
I thought I'd just introduce this now.
It's not quite the odds ratio that follows
the normal distribution,
it's the natural log of the odds ratio
that follows the normal distribution.
So let me just end with this last-
Statistic the odds ratio.
What's the distribution of an odds ratio?
Let's do another computer simulation.
You can see how much I love computer
simulations.
So, let's do a simulation for
an odds ratio to figure out the
distribution of an odds ratio.
So, I'm going to say I'm going to be doing
case control studies.
It would be a reason to calculate odds
ratios, as I'm doing a case control study.
I'm going to tell the computer,
imagine I've got this large infinite Large
population of cases and controls.
And, 20% of cases are smokers, and 20% of
controls are smokers.
I want to know that I would be doing a
case control study here to gauge
the relationship between smoking and,
being a case.
And let's say that there actually is no
relationship,
the odds ratio here happens to be one.
Because there, there's equal amount of
smoking in both groups.
That's my underlying population, and then
I'm going to, to my simulation.
So, I'm going to repeat over and
over again, case control studies with 100
people.
50 cases and 50 controls.
Every case and every control has a 20
percent chance of being a smoker.
In other words, it follows the binomial.
So that's how I can do this in a computer.
I can tell the computer that we're on a
binomial.
So I randomly select.
50 cases and 50 controls.
For that one sample, I calculated an odds
ratio.
I store that in a data set and then I do
this again and again and again.
Like I'm doing repeated, repeated case
control samples.
Repeated case control studies with
different samples of the same size.
Do it, repeat it say 1,000 times.
And then I'm going to observe the
distribution of the odds ratio.
So here we go.
Here's what it comes out to look like.
Wait a minute.
Oh no!
It's not on a normal curve.
Oh dear, everything else came out on a
normal curve.
The odds ratio doesn't naturally follow a
It doesn't follow a bell curve.
So notice that the distribution of the
odds ratio has a rights skue.
The true odds ratio was 1.0 here, so we
are centered around 1.0.
But we have this right skew, why would
that be?
Well the odds ratio is a little different
that the other statistics we've
talked about so far.
The odds ratio is a ratio; ratios can not
have values below zero.
So we have this right hand boundary, we
can't go below zero.
So we kind of end up clustering and going
right up into zero but
we can't go over it.
On the other hand, an odds ratio can be as
big as you please.
We've some big odds ratios in this class.
So the odds ratio can go way out,
it can get, it has no bound on the
right-hand side.
So you can end up with, even when the true
odds ratio is one.
You can end up in, in a given sample, and
when you have small samples like this.
You can end up with some pretty big odds
ratios.
Notice that one in 1000 times, even though
the true odds ratio here is one,
that means there's no association here.
Just by chance, one in 1000 times we got
an odds ratio way, way out here at 6.8.
So it can happen just by chance, but its a
Right-skewed Distribution.
So that's a problem because we want
everything to end up on a normal or a T.
So, what can we do to force this to go on
a normal curve?
Actually, there's a little transformation
we can make that will turn the odds ratio,
the distribution of the odds ratio into a
normal curve.
What we can do, is just simply take the
natural log of the odds ratio.
Here is the histogram when I take the
Yay, we're back on a normal curve.
So what happens is, that when you take the
natural log.
Any value for the odds ratio that's
between zero and one.
That's a decimal.
When you take the natural log of a
decimal, you end up with negative values.
So you bring back the negative values back
into play.
And now you end up on a beautiful normal
curve.
It's centered around zero because the
natural log of one which was
the true value here.
The natural log of one is zero.
So, that this curve ends up centered
around zero.
So, we're back on a normal curve.
So, even when we don't start on a normal
curve naturally we can force statistics to
be on a normal curve.
And when we do statistical inference on
odds ratios we actually are always working
with the natural log of the odds ratio for
this reason.
Now somebody worked out from mathematical
theory the standard error of
the natural log of the odds ratio.
So this is the standard error for
the natural log of the odds ratio for this
curve here.
And it turns out to be the square root of
1 over a plus 1 over b.
Plus 1 over C, plus 1 over D.
Don't worry about that formula, but just
realize A is exposed cases,
B is exposed controls, C is unexposed
cases, and d is unexposed controls.
In other words these are the sample sizes.
These are just the sample sizes of
particular groups but
those are the sample sizes.
And notice that the smallest of those
group is contributing the most to
the standard error because it's.
Reciprocals we're looking at here.
So that's the standard era of the odds
ratio.
The, the natural log of the odds ratio.
Notice that like the other standard eras
sample size is very important.
And sample size is in the denominator.
So let me just summarize this.
The distribution of a statistic.
The shape of the distribution of many
statistics is
either a normal distribution or a key
distribution and
if its not we might force it to be on a
normal distribution.
The mean of the distribution of a
statistic turns out
to always be the true value of the
statistic in the larger population.
The standard error differs depending on
what type of
statistic you have there are many
different types of standard errors.
But it's always inversely related to
sample size.
We saw three examples in this module.
The standard error of the mean.
The standard error of the correlation
coefficient.
And the standard error of an odds ratio.
All of those had sample size in the
denominator.
So with the bigger the sample size the
lower the standard error.
But notice there's many different standard
errors.
Let me just repeat that, there's many
different stand, standard errors.
A lot of people think that this one,
because this is the one they most commonly
see, the standard error of the mean is the
only way to calculate standard error.
Well no, that's the standard error of the
mean,
every other statistic has its own formula
for standard error.
But notice they're all related to sample
size.