In this next module, I'm going to talk
about an important,
discrete probability distribution called
the binomial distribution.
It has widespread applications in
statistics .
So the binomial probability comes up in
lots of different scenarios.
It's a particular situation where you have
a fixed number of trials and
we'll call that n trials.
So like 15 tosses of a coin or
20 patients or 1000 people surveyed, but
there's a fixed number.
You're also dealing with a binary outcome.
So in each of those trials there are only
two possible outcomes.
Such as heads or tails, or disease or no
disease.
And we're going to call the probability of
one of those outcomes p,
and the probability of the other outcome 1
minus p.
The other thing that has to be true for
the binomial probability distribution to
apply is each trial, each coin toss, or
patient, or person surveyed, has to have
the same probability.
Of getting a success or failure as
everybody else.
So there's a -- every single trial had the
exact same probabilities, like when you
toss a coin, every time you toss a coin
you have a .5 chance of getting a heads.
So that's the scenario we're talking about
when we're talking about
the binomial distribution.
Now some of you may have encountered the
binomial probability distribution before,
and you may have been given a formula and
told how to plug into this formula to
calculate binomial probabilities.
Well, I hate to just give you a formula
without any reasoning behind it.
So what I want to do now is kind of walk
you through the logic,
build up to that formula, so that you have
some sense of where it comes from.
So that hopefully if you ever forgot the
formula you could just derive it yourself.
So we're going to start with a simple
example to build towards figuring out
the binomial probability formula.
Take the example of five coin tosses.
If I ask you, in five coin tosses,
what's the probability that you flip
exactly three heads in five coin tosses.
Calculate that probability.
Well, this is an example of a binomial
distribution.
We have 5 coin tosses.
So our n, in this case, is 5.
Each coin toss is an independent trial.
Each coin toss has the some probability of
success of a heads, .5.
And the same probability of a failure, a
tails.
So this is a binomial distribution.
But how would you calculate that
probability using some of
the tools that we learned last week?
What's the probability that you flip
exactly three heads?
And I want to know the probability of
exactly three heads.
So, not two, not one, not four.
But exactly three.
So how could we solve this?
So let's just kind of walk through how we
could solve this.
How we could approach this problem.
So, first of all you could just think
about okay,
here's one way to get exactly 3 heads.
You might flip a heads, and
another heads, and another heads, and then
a tails and a tails.
That's one way to get exactly three heads.
Well, what's the probability of that
particular outcome?
We can calculate that, right?
What's the probability that you get a
heads on the first toss,
a heads on the second toss, a heads on the
third, and then two tails?
Well, it's going to be 0.5 times 0.5 times
0.5,
those are the probabilities of getting
three heads in a row.
And then you have to get two tails in a
row, so that's another 0.5 times 0.5.
So it ends up being 0.5 raised to the
fifth.
That's the probability of getting exactly
3 heads in that particular arrangement,
where we're considering order.
3 heads first, and then 2 tails.
Now's the probability of that exact
arrangement.
All right, well, what if we think about
another possible arrangement?
Another way we can get 3 heads in 5 coin
tosses.
There's another way we could get it.
We could get tails, and then 3 heads, and
then a tails.
Well what's the probability of that exact
arrangement?
Well it's going to be again, the
probability of tails,
times the probability of heads, times the
probability of heads,
probability of tails.
Again, it's going to be 0.05 times 5
raised the the 5th.
In fact, if you write out any exact
arrangement where you've got two tails and
three heads in a particular order, the
probability of any particular order is
going to be 0.5 raised to the third times
0.5 raised to the second.
In other words, the probability of a heads
raised to the third, because we're
getting three heads, times the probability
of a tails, raised to the second.
Well that solves the probability of any
particular exact arrangement and
then all we have to answer is how many
possible arrangements are there.
How many possible ways can we arrange 3
heads in a string of 5 letters,
3 each is in a string of 5 letters.
So.
Overall the probability of 3 heads and
tails is 1 half raised to the fifth.
For every unique arrangement how many
unique arrangements are there?
Well one way to solve this would actually
just be to write them out in this case.
There's not that many in this case so we
could write them out systemically.
So I actually went through and did that.
So one way to get 3 heads is tails, heads,
heads, heads, tails.
Another way is heads, heads.
Heads tails tails another way's tails
tails heads heads heads and
I just I systematically sat there and
wrote them all out each one of
those exact arrangements has the
probability 1 half raised to the 3rd
times 1 half raised to the second or the
probability of heads raised to the 3rd.
And the probability of tails raised to the
second.
Now, wouldn't it be nice, though, if there
were a neat and tidy way to come up
with the number of arrangements, other
than just writing them out systematically.
In fact, it turns out there is.
You can view this problem as a
combinations problem, a choosing problem.
And we can apply the choosing function
here.
So the way you need to think about it, is,
you think.
Okay, I've got 5 [UNKNOWN], 5 tosses and I
have to give any 3 of them to heads.
By default the other 2 will be tails.
So I have to choose
spots out of 5 to give to heads, the other
2 spots will be tails.
So it's actually a 5 choose 3.
There are 5 choose 3 ways to arrange 3
heads in 5 trials.
So we can just apply the choosing
function, the combinations function here.
If you apply that here, it comes out to
give us a value of 10,
exactly the number that I dealt when I
wrote them out systematically.
So that turns out the probability of
getting exactly three heads turns out to
be 10 times one half 3 to to the 5th or
31.25%.
We can actually calculate all possible
outcomes when you toss a coin five times.
What are all possible outcomes?
Well you can get 0 heads, 1 head, 2, 3, 4
or 5 and
we can calculate the probability of all of
those.
And that's what I've done here using the
same logic in that
probability distribution looks like this,
although those areas, if you add them up,
will add up to 1.
Now, let's extent the problem just a
little bit.
Let's extend the problem to the ase where
it's a little bit less simple because we
now have uneven probability, so
probability of a success and
failure are no longer equal.
So here's a particular example.
As voters exit the polls, you ask a very
small but representative random sample of
six voters if they voted for a particular
proporsition.
Let's say that the true percentage of
voters who voted for that proposition is
55.1%, so the probability that any random
person has voted for it is 55.1%.
What's the probability that in your sample
of six exactly two voted for
the proposition and four did not?
So let's use the same logic to solve for
this probability.
Well, we can write out all the possible
outcomes.
We could get two yes votes.
The first two people we talk to could say
that they voted yes on the proposition,
and the next four could say no.
That's one way to get exactly two yes
votes.
The probability of a yes is now .551, the
probability of a no is .449, 1 minus .551.
We have to get 2 yeses in a row and then 4
nos in a row, so
that's .551 raised to the 2, 2nd times
.449 raised to the 4th.
Well, what's another way to get exactly 2
yeses?
Well I could get no and then yes, yes.
And then no, no, no.
And again, that's, you're going to see
that,
that comes out to just 0.551 raised to the
second, 0.449 raised to the fourth.
No matter what particular outcome I write
out,
they all have the exact same probability.
How many possible outcomes are there?
How many possible ways is there to arrange
two yes votes in six trials?
Well, that's a six choose two problem
again.
There are six choose two ways to arrange
two yes votes among the six voters.
So six choose two, if we calculated it
out, turns out to be 15.
And how did I get that, again, to apply
the choosing function?
Six choose two.
Is just equal to 6 factorial divided by 2
factorial divided by 6
minus 2 factorial or 4 factorial.
If you do that out that's going to be 6
times 5 times 4 factorial.
I'm writing it this way because I know I
can cancel the 4 factorial in
the denominator.
2 factorial's just 2.
So these cancel.
That turns out to be 30 divided by 2 or
15.
So there are 15 ways To get exactly two
yes votes and four no, no votes.
There's cer, there's 15 arrangements and
the probability of each arrangement we've,
we've calculated here so we're just
going to multiply that probability by 15.
Now you might start to notice a general
pattern emerging here, right?
We have a choosing function in the front.
And then we've got the probability of
success,
raised to the number of successes, and
the probability of failures, raised to the
number of failures.
So this is now going to generalize into
our general formula for
calculating binomial probabilities.
This, by the way comes out to be 18.5%, if
you calculated it all out.
If you want the final answer.
So here's our general binomial formula.
If you've got a binomial distribution that
is n trial, independent trials,
each trial has a probability of success p
and a probability of failure 1 minus p,
then the probability of getting exactly X
successes, like exactly Three heads or
exactly two yes voters is the following: n
choose X,
the probability of success raised to the
number of successes, raised to X, times
times probability of failure raised to n
minus X, that is, the number of failures.
So again, n is the number of trials.
That defines that binomial distribution.
X is the particular probability that
you're trying to calculate.
What is the probability of getting exactly
x successes out of those n trials?
1 minus p is the probability of failure.
p is the probability of success.
So if you can reason through and
understand where this formula comes from,
I think it makes sense.
And then you can, once you know where this
formula comes from then you can apply this
formula to calculate probabilities
whenever you have a binomial distribution.
And you'll get good at these if you
practice a lot of them.
Let's do some practice problems.