These data came from a twin study, so each
case is somebody with
Parkinson's disease and they have a twin
who does not have Parkinson's disease.
So we have these case control pairs that
are correlated by the fact that
they're within a twin pair.
So we have correlated data here.
Our outcome here is binary.
You have Parkinson's disease or you don't.
Our exposure variable, our predictor is
whether or
not you've been various chemicals.
So we have essentially categorical data
for both the predictor and the outcome but
we have this correlation.
So that's going to tell us that we're
going to have to do a McNemar's test.
However, if you look carefully at a lot of
these cells.
Remember for a McNemar's test, we only
care about the discordant pairs
which would be these two middle two
columns.
If you look at all of these columns, a lot
of the columns involve sparse data.
So one or two people only in some of those
cells.
So not only do we have to do a McNemar's
test, but
we actually have to do an exact test to
calculate those probabilities exactly.
Rather than using a normal approximation
to the binomial,
which is what a Ky square normally would
do.
So we're going to use a McNemar's exact
test here.
[SOUND].
This question asks you
specifically about the probabilities for
PRC.
It's asking you to calculate the p value
for the PERC chemical [INAUDIBLE].
It might be helpful here to draw a 2 by 2
table if that helps you to,
to see the problem.
So we have your either we have cases.
The case is either, these are pair data,
so we have cases and controls.
So, the cases have Parkinson's.
The control is their twin and we're
analyzing things at the level of pair.
So, we have, in this case, then,
what we're looking at here is you were
either exposed to PERC or you weren't.
And some of the cases, both were exposed.
Some of them weren't, both were not
exposed others, there was a discordant.
So it turns out that the majority were not
exposed.
So we had 93 pairs where neither the case
nor the control was exposed.
There weren't any new pairs where both
case and control were exposed, however,
we did have a couple of pairs where there
was discordance.
So there were five pairs where the case
that is the person with Parkinson's di,
disease was exposed to this chemical.
But the control was not and
we have one situation, one case where the
opposite was true.
The control was exposed to the chemical
but the case was not.
It turns our for McNemar's test the only
thing that's of use
the only information that's informative
for us here is the discordant pair.
So we have six discordant pairs.
And the null hypothesis here is that the
chemical is not related to whether or
not you're a case or a control.
So, under the null hypothesis we've got
six discordant pairs.
If there was no relationship between the
chemical and
getting Parkinson's disease, this would
follow a binomial distribution.
X would follow a binomial distribution,
and the n here is 6
which is just determined by how many
discordant pairs we ended up with.
The p would .5 under the null hypothesis.
In other words just think intuitively,
if there's not relationship here between
the chemical and Parkinson's disease.
You'd expect there, did, the discord
appears to, kind of,
be even about three where it was the case
that it was exposed and not the control.
And three where it was the control that
was exposed and not the case.
The question we're really asking here is,
how far off is a 51
split from what we'd expect under the
normal, which is like a 3 3 split.
So we're on a binomial, we're going to
have to because of small numbers,
we're going to have to calculate that
exact binomial probability.
So we're literally going to go through and
calculate the exact binomial probabilities
here.
So what did we actually see?
We saw the case where we ended up with
five discordant pairs where it was
the case who had been exposed and not the
control.
The binomial probability, we'll just apply
our binomial probability formula here,
we've got six choose five P is 0.5 so we
do 0.5 raised to the fifth, and
then one minus P is also 0.5, so we do,
0.5 raised to the first.
But, remember, P values we have to
calculate the probability of what we
saw and everything more extreme.
So we also have to calculate the
probability that we
could have gotten all 6 discordant pairs,
it was the case that was exposed, so
we do 626.5 raised to the 6th.
We also have to consider, the other tail,
remember if we did out all the binomial
probabilities here, they go from 0 to 6.
We could we'd get something that excuse my
crude drawing here.
But we get something where we have five
and six and one tail, but
we have to consider we would run into a
two tailed hypothesis and
consider we could've been just as extreme
in the other direction.
And as we could have ended up with only 0
or
1 discordant pairs where it was the case
that was exposed.
So we have to do a two tailed probability.
You can do that by, calculating the other
tail which is the probability that x
equals 1 and the probability that x equals
0.
It turns out that those are exactly the
same as the ones that you see here.
So this one comes out to be .015625.
This one comes out to be .09375.
This one will also be 0.09375 and this one
will 0.019625 when you
add all of those up, You get the P value
here is 0.21875.
These is a situation where we have carried
the data, we have repeated measures.
It's the same women measured before and
after they smoked.
We have a continuous outcome which is
blood pressure and also heart rate, and,
so we are going to be using a paired t
test here because it's a before and
after with a continuous outcome.
The correct answer here is false.
You actually cannot calculate the paired t
test here,
from the data given in the table.
Why is that?
Well, we're given the mean before smoking
and the mean after smoking, but
remember, the paired T test looks at the
differences for individual women.
And right now, we don't know the
difference values for individual women.
We don't know, how much each woman
individually went up or down.
We would need that information in able to
be able to calculate the paired T test.
In this question, breast feeding is a
categorical variable.
We're comparing groups of men by whether
they or not they were breastfed or
the duration of how they were how much
they were breastfed.
Our outcome variable is binary.
Your either obese or you're not obese.
We also do not have sparse data, so we're
going to be using a [UNKNOWN] square test.
And because we don't have sparse data we
don't have to worry about
the fisher's exact test, we're doing an
exact test here.
In this case we're going to be comparing
different groups.
We're comparing men in different groups of
duration of breast feeding, so
that's a categorical predictor, groups,
they are independent groups.
Our outcome variable now is BMI, BMI is a
continuous variable.
We're going to assume that it's normally
distributed or
close enough with such large sample sizes
that we can run an anova test here.
So this questions says, let's say we do
our ki square test for obesity and
breast feeding group, and we get a
significant P value, P is .03.
What does that mean?
Well the ki squared test is a global test,
what it actually doesn't tell us where the
differences lie.
It just tells us that at least one of
those breast feeding groups is
different than the others.
And if you actually look at the numbers
here, you know,
it goes from 9.6% obese to 13.1% to 20.7%.
It looks like it's going up as you get
more breastfeeding, and
then it goes down for the really long
breast feeding group.
So there's no particular pattern here, so
all we can conclude is D, that the percent
of obese subjects differs in at least one
of those breast feeding categories.
This asks you to calculate the mean change
in exercise duration.
And you can do it just off the graph.
It's nice that they were measured in only
in units of .5, nothing finer than that.
So for example, this first person went up
three seconds.
The next person went up .5, this one was
zero, .5,
1.5, zero, 1.5, .5, .5, 1.0, .5, zero, and
.5.
You literally just have to pick those up,
up off of the graph.
Well if you add up all of those numbers,
I'm not going to write in all those all
out here,
just because it would take a while.
But if you add up all of those numbers
from 1 to 13,
you end up and then divide by 13, to
calculate the average here.
You end up with .77.
To calculate the standard deviation of
change here,
we're simply going to take each
observation and subtract it from the mean.
Well, you've already calculated the mean
to be 0.77.
So, for example, we take the first person,
subtract the mean square of that,
then we do this for the next person.
The next person has a value of 0.5,
subtract from the mean square of that.
We're going to do that for all 13.
I won't write it out completely here.
You're then going to divide by n-1.
For the standard deviation, you'll always
divide by n-1, so
that ends up being 13-1 or 12 here.
And then we would square-root that whole
thing.
When you calculate that out, you get a
value of 0.83.
To calculate the standard error of the
change here, we would take this.
Standard deviation for change which we
calculated already as 0.83 and
divided by the square root of N.
So, 0.83 divided by the square root of 13
is 0.23.
That would be our standard error here.
To calculate the 95% confidence interval,
we're going to take the observed mean,
which we already calculated to to be 0.77.
We're going to add and subtract our t
value here, for
a 99% confidence interval I gave you, is
3.055.
We're going to multiply that by our
standard error,
which we calculated already to be 0.23.
When you add that all out,
you're going to end up with a confidence
interval of 0.067 to 1.47.
The answer to this question is true.
It is statistically significant at the
0.01 level.
How do we know that?
Well we just calculated the 99% confidence
interval.
That confidence interval does not include
the null value which is 0 here.
This excludes 0, therefore we can be sure
that the p value is less than .01.
The answer to this question is false.
We did prove that there is a statically
significant increase in
the exercise duration of these patients.
However, it's unclear if the camp is
responsible for
this change, they could have all gone up
for other reasons.
We don't have a control group here so we
can't conclude causality here.
We just know that for some reason they
went up a significant amount.