In the case of a discrete probability
distribution, the formula for
the expected value is [SOUND] x times P of
x.
So, we can just make a new column here
which is x times P of x.
We get 0.1, 0.4, 1.2, 0.4, and 1.
And if we add all these numbers together,
we get the mean as 3.1.
In the previous question, we found that
the mean for
this distribution was 3.1.
We will be applying the standard formula
for
the standard distrubtion here which is.
I'm just going to write out the first
couple of
expressions to help you understand how
this is calculated.
So for x of 0 we have 0 minus 3.1 times
the probablity of x of 0 which is 0.
Plus for x of 1, 1 minus 3.1 and
the probability of getting of x of one
which is 0.1 and so on.
We have corresponding terms for 2,3,4 and
5 and
if we do the math the answer comes out to
be 1.22 We are given a normal
distribution with a mean of 1 gram per
centimeter squared and
a standard deviation of 0.1 gram per
centimeter squared.
And the question wants us to find.
The area total left of .85 gram per
centimeter square.
Now this corresponds to a z value of which
is [SOUND] and if we look
out the probability Cause it's pointing to
z value of minus 1.5.
You see that a probability is 0.0668.
One thing to note here is that we should
be referring to the one tail z values and
not the 2 tail z values because we only
want to
find the probability That this we have
values which are less than .85.
We don't want to find the probability that
we have values greater than one
standard deviation about the mean.
In the previous question, we found the
area of the curve to the left.
Of .81, .85.
This question wants us to find the area to
the right of 1.15.
We could argue that because the normal
distribution is symmetric,
the area that we found in the previous
question would be exactly the area that we
would find in this question as well.
But let us just go through the numbers.
To confirm that that is the case.
In this case, the z value is [SOUND] and
if we look up the probability
distribution, [SOUND]
we'll see that the p value corresponding
to this Is 0.0668.
Which is exactly the same value that we
found in the previous question as well.
This question is a straight-forward
application of
the binomial equation again.
We have n equals 5.
We are given that b is 0.513.
And we want to find the probability Of x
being 4.
And this, recalling the expression that
we had for the binomial distribution.
And if we do the math here,
we'll find that the answer is 16.9%.
So there is a 16.9% chance that out of the
next 5 births exactly 4 are boys.
Question 6 has approximately normal
distribution with a mean of 80 and
a standard deviation of 10.
We need to find.
The value of x such that we have 25
percent of
the normal distribution area to the right
of x.
So the first step here would be to find
the z square corresponding to 25% in
the right tail and we can look this up in
our z table and
we'll see that the z squared that we would
be looking for is 0.674.
Now, it's a simple job of plugging this
into the formula for z,
we know that z is x minus mu by standard
deviation.
We can flip this around make x the subject
of the formula and
say that x is z times standard deviation
plus mu.
Which comes out to be 86.74.
That's to ensure an A in this class.
We need to get a score of at least 86.74.
This question has a doctor who performs 8
operations a day the probability of
success of any one operation is 95%.
We want to find the probability that a
doctor has exactly two failed operations
on a particular day directly applying the
binomial formula to this question.
We have 0.95 raised to 6 because we have
six successful operations and
0.25 raised to the 2 corresponding to the
two failed relations.
And we see that the probability is 5.1%.
This question has the same doctor as the
previous question.
He still performs eight operations in a
day.
The probability of success of any one
operation is still 95%.
Now we want to calculate the probability
that a doctor has two or
more failed operations on a given day.
There are two ways of solving this
question.
We could either find the probability that
the doctor has two or three.
Or 4 or 5 or 6 7 or 8 fill operations on a
given day.
Or we could just find the probability that
the doctor has no fill operations or
1 fill operations on a day, add them up,
subtract them from 1,
that should give us the same answer that
we're looking for.
And because the second method actually has
us adding up only two terms of
the binomial distribution, it's actually
much simpler to calculate than.
The fourth method here.
So, that is the one we'll be using.
The probability of having no field
operations
on a given day is, the probability of
having one operations on a given day is,
[NOISE] And if we just add these two
terms, and
subtract them out from 1, the answer we
get is 5.7%.
We can model this game using the
following.
We have two outcomes for this game.
Either we win the game, or we lose the
game.
If we win the game, we get the payoff of
$1 million, and
if we lose the game, we get a payoff of
zero.
But either way, we have to pay $50 to play
the game, so
the total payoff in case we win is $1
million minus 50 and
the pay off, if we lose is negative $50.
Let's say the probability associated with
winning is b and
the probability associated with losing is
one minus b.
Let's find out.
What the value of p is.
The probability of winning is the
probability of
getting either three or four sixes.
Now, we can model each of these two
expressions using the binomial equation.
In this case, the binomial is the fact
that we have four die.
N is 4, and the probability of getting a 6
on any one die is
one sixth because this is an unbiased die,
so we,
the probability of getting three 6s as by
6 to the third and 5 by 6th.
Probably you are getting four 6s.
This gives us the total probability of
varying as 0.0162.
Now we can use the value of P that we
found, which was 0.0162,
To find the expected value of this game.
You know that point b is 0.0162.
1 minus b is 0.0.
Okay it's actually 0.9838.
The expected value of this Is,
can be found using the expression that we
have for the expected value of
a discrete distribution which is summation
of x times p of x.
Again the [UNKNOWN] is $1 million.
Minus the 50 that we paid to play.
And the probability of us winning 0.0162.
And the payoff if we lose is a negative
$50.
And the probability of us losing, which is
0.9838.
And if we do the math, we'll see that the
probability, the expected value for
the game comes to about $16,000.
Which tells us that the, the expected
value is positive.
Question 10 has a binomial distribution
but
we are told that we can use a normal
approximation.
Before we go on to the normal
approximation, though,
let's just find quickly the expected
value.
And the standard deviation for the
binomial distribution.
The expected value is n times p,
n in our case is 200, and p is 0.5, which
gives us an expected value of 100.
The standard deviation is n times p time 1
minus p, which comes out to 7.07.
Let's now go to the normality
approximation.
We have a mean of 100 and a standard
deviation of 7.07.
We want to find the probability that A
number chosen from
the distribution turns out to be greater
than 112,
which is just equivalent to finding the
area to the right of 112.
Let's just find a z-score corresponding to
112 before we go on.
We know that the value of Z is given by x
minus m by standard deviation.
This comes out
to 1.7.
And that's the probability of choosing a
number from this distribution and
finding And that number to be greater than
112, [INAUDIBLE] of
having a probability of Z being 1.7 or
more, which comes out to 4.45%.
In this question, we are considering a
variable called Wake-up time, and
we have 24 observations for this variable.
We have the histogram, the normal
probability plot and
the results of a formal test of normality,
and
we need to decide whether this variable is
normally distributed.
Now, the histogram is approximately
normal,
even though it isn't exactly normal.
The normal probability plot is more or
less a straight line, and the value
of p that we get from the formal test of
normality is 0.25, which is quite high.
All three point to the fact that we can
treat this variable as
approximately normal, even though we know
that it isn't exactly normal.