In this next module,
we're going to look at another measure of
association called the relative risks.
Instead of subtracting the risks in the
different groups,
what if we instead divided them to make a
ratio, that's called a relative risk.
There are several measures of relative
risk and
relative risks appear very frequently in
the medical literature.
If you take two incidents rates and divide
them, that's called a rate ratio.
You'll also see something in the
literature called a hazard ratio.
A hazard ratio is also a ratio of
incidence rates.
It's just a ratio of what we call
instantaneous incidence rates or
hazard rates.
Hazard ratios actually come from a
regression technique that we're
going to talk about much later in the
course.
But for now,
you can just interpret them exactly the
same way you would interpret a rate ratio.
If you divide two cumulative risks, or two
prevalences, we call that a risk ratio.
Now some people might call the ratio of
two prevalences a prevalence ratio,
to distinguish it, but I tend to lump them
together and call them
all a risk ratio because cumulative risks
and prevalences are both just proportions.
Another measure of relative risk I'm going
to talk about a great deal this week is
something called an odds ratio.
An odds ratio is a ratio of two odds and
I'm going to have to tell you what
an odds is in a minute because you may not
really understand what an odds is already.
But the odds ratio comes up a lot in the
medical literature for two reasons.
The odds ratio is the only value measure
of relative risk for case control studies.
That's one reason.
The other reason that odds ratios come up
a lot, is that a lot
of researchers want to do a regression
technique called logistic regression.
It's a multivariate regression technique
that's used when you
have a binary outcome, and you want to
adjust for confounders.
It turns out that logistic regression
gives you out odds ratios.
So even if you're doing a covert study, or
a cross sectional study,
if you use logistic regression, you're
going to get out odds ratios.
So, odds ratios are all over the
literature.
But as we're going to see in this module
and the next module,
they're a little bit of a funny measure
and sometimes they're tricky to interpret.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So how do we interpret relative risk?
So the rate ratio and the hazard ratio,
you can interpret as the percent increase
or decrease in the rate of the outcome.
The risk ratio is the percent increase or
decrease in the risk or
prevalence of the outcome.
The odds ratio is the percent increase or
decrease in the odds of the outcome, and
again I'll fill you in on what an odds is
in a minute.
If you have a relative risk that's equal
to 1.0,
that means that the risks in the two
groups are equal,
because, say if the risk is 20% in one
group and
20% in the other group, if you divide 20%
by 20% you're going to get 1.0.
So that represents where there's no
difference between the groups,
we call that the null value.
If you have a relative risk that's less
than one,
that indicates a protective effect.
Whatever was in the numerator is
protecting you from the outcome.
If you have a relative risk that's greater
than one, that indicates a harmful effect,
an increased risk.
Let's calculate the rate ratio first
starting with
the GI event data from the Vioxx study
we've been talking about.
Incident rates were 2.1 and 4.5 again.
All we have to do here to make a rate
ratio is to
divide the two incidents rates.
And notice because we're dividing two
rates, the units here,
the 100 person-years actually cancels out.
And the rate ratio doesn't have any units,
it's unitless.
We come out with a rate ratio of 0.46.
The interpretation is that Vioxx reduces
the rate of GI events by 54%.
I got that 54% simply by subtracting 1
minus 0.46.
So that's a 40, 54% reduction in the rate
of GI events.
If I want to calculate the risk ratio for
this same data, I'm just
going to divide the risk in the Vioxx
group by the risk in the Naproxen group.
Interestingly I get exactly the same a
number here, 0.46.
So in this case the rate ratio and the
risk ratio are identical because,
remember, the person-years of follow up
was exactly the same in both groups.
So, if you're following people for the
same amount of time and the risk ratio and
the weight ration would come out to be the
same.
However, if there was a differential
follow up
between the groups then this wouldn't be
the case.
Because if one group was followed for
longer than the other group,
that would increase the risk in the group
that was followed longer, and
it would change the risk ratio compared
with the, the rate ratio.
Now I want to read to you what they put in
the pay, in the paper's abstract.
During a median follow-up of 9 months,
2.1 confirmed GI events per 100
patient-years occurred with the rofecoxib,
that is the Vioxx group, as compared with
4.5 per 100 patient years with naproxen.
Now they're going to give the relative
risk.
The relative risk is 0.5 so they rounded
up from 0.46 to, to 0.5.
95% confidence interval, 0.3 to 0.6 and
it's highly statistically significant.
I want to spend just a minute here to walk
you through what that
confidence interval means.
We're going to spend a lot of time on
confidence intervals in an upcoming week
of the course.
But I want to just give you sort of a
conceptual understanding of
what that confidence interval means here.
So the relative risk that we calculated in
the study,
what we call the point estimate.
What we calculated in the study was
exactly 0.46 rounded up to .5.
So that indicates a halving of risk.
But that's just what we saw in the study.
And of course,
whenever we do a study, we know that
there's going to be some uncertainty.
In other words the true effect of Vioxx on
GI events might not be exactly 0.5.
We understand that when we do a study,
there's uncertainty.
We have to put a margin of error around
our estimate.
That margin of error is what we call the
95% confidence interval.
So the 95% confidence interval here is 0.3
to 0.6.
That gives us a plausible range of values
for the true effect.
The real effect of Vioxx on on GI events
we believe is
somewhere between 0.3 and 0.6.
Another way to interpret it is we say we
can be 95% confident that
the true effect of Vioxx verus naproxen is
between a 40% and
70% reduction in the rate of GI events.
Where did that 40% and 70% come from?
The upper limit of the confidence interval
is a relative risk of 0.6.
That's a 40% reduction in risk.
The lower limit in the confidence interval
is a relative risk of 0.3.
That's a 70% reduction in risk.
Now let's move to the heart attack data
from the study.
What's the rate ratio going to be here.
The rate ratio will be the rate in the
Vioxx group divided by the rate in
the Naproxen group.
When you do that division it comes out to
be 4.2, if the risk ratio is
actually identical, as I said before,
because the groups should follow for
equal amounts of time.
The risk ration and the rate ratio are the
same.
How do we interpret these results?
We would interpret this that Vioxx
increases the rate or
risk of heart attacks by fourfold, or you
would say by 320%.
But let's see what the authors actually
put in the abstract here.
So, here's the abstract from the paper.
The incidence of myocardial infarction,
heart attack,
was lower among patients in the naproxen
group than among those in the Vioxx group.
0.1% versus 0.4%.
We already saw that number in the last
module.
Relative risk 0.2, 95% confidence
interval, 0.1 to 0.7.
So notice that when the authors reported
the data on GI events,
they put the naproxen in the denominator.
They put the naproxen as the reference
group,
but when they report the data on heart
attacks, they're flipping things around.
They're making Vioxx the reference group.
They're putting Vioxx in the denominator.
And you can probably think of the reason
that they might have wanted to do that.
So there are actually two funny things
going on here,
as I alluded to in the last module.
So firstly, they reported risks rather
than rates.
For the primary outcome GI events,
remember they
actually reported the incidence rates,
they reported the risks here,
likely because the risk difference here
looks smaller than the rate difference.
Secondly, they flipped the relative risk.
They divided the risk in the Naproxen
group by the risk in
the Vioxx group rather than the other way
around.
So remember the risk in the Vioxx group
was 0.42.
The risk in the Naproxen group is 0.1.
If you divide 0.1 by 0.42 you get a
relative risk of 0.24 and
they rounded down in the abstract to 0.2.
They rounded to one decimal place.
So they twisted the message here, right.
They twisted the message to make it look
like naproxen is protective rather than
that Vioxx is harmful.
And technically, they haven't done
anything wrong mathematically.
The numbers are correct.
But flipping the relative risk of course
completely shifts the take home message,
and people missed it.
Not one person wrote a letter to the
editor of the New England Journal,
after this article was published,
questioning the author's logic here.
People bought into the story that the
authors were trying to sell,
that Naproxen is this miracle heart
protective drug.
Instead of that Vioxx is a dangerous drug.
Here's the, what they wrote in the paper's
conclusion.
I showed you this in the teaser earlier.
Thus, our results are consistent with the
theory that Naproxen has
a coronary protective effect.
And highlight the fact that rofecoxib
Vioxx does not provide this
type of protection.
The finding that naproxen therapy was
associated with a lower rate of
myocardial infarction needs further
confirmation in larger studies.
Of course, naproxen is the reference
group, the control group in this study.
So every comparison really outta be Vioxx
versus naproxen,
not naproxen versus Vioxx.
But they totally put the focus on naproxen
to take the focus away from Vioxx and
it worked.
In fact it turns out that naproxen has a
very small,
if any cardio protective affect.
So here was clear evidence sitting in the
literature in 2000 that Vioxx raises
the risk of cardiovascular events.
Some people think that if if people had
actually looked at this study more
carefully and kind of questioned the
reasoning of the authors here,
that Vioxx might have actually been pulled
off the shelves sooner than 2004.
The data were sitting here showing us that
there's this
cardio harmful effect of nap, of Vioxx.
And there's actually a lot of backstory
here that I'm not telling you.
There was actually some data omitted from
the New England Journal of Med,
of Medicine paper.
If you're interested in all of this,
you can Google it, you can find out more
about this story.
People made a big deal about the fact that
some of the heart,
actually three heart attacks that probably
should have been included in
that New England Journal paper that
weren't.
But in fact,
that data that was already available in
the paper really told the whole story.
It's just that the authors had managed to
spin that story and people bought it.
So the bigger lesson here, is that it's
very important when
you're reading a medical paper to always
look at the data yourself.
And then interpret the data yourself.
Because you allow the authors to lead you
through their interpretation of the data,
you can easily get sucked into the story
they want to tell you.
And that's what happened here.