The answer to this question is true.
You can only make a type II error, which
is a false negative error,
when the null hypothesis is false.
The correct answer is B.
Statistical power is the probability of
getting a statistically significant result
when the null hypothesis is false.
Statistical power is the probability of
detecting a real effect, or
rejecting a null hypothesis when you
should.
Out of the options that we have for this
question, the only element that does not
increase statistical power is increasing
the significance level from 0.05 to 0.01.
It is harder to achieve a significance
level of 0.01 does a statistical power
will actually go down if we reduce the
statistical significance from 0.05
to 0.01.
This question has a sample size of a
100,000 children.
Now because the sample size is so very
high, we cannot safely say that we
have actually found a correlation between
blood sugar and IQ.
Even though the p value is very small.
P values tend to become smaller as we
increase the sample size.
So we should, we should find out the
actual size of the effect before we
make any strong statements of the
correlation between blood sugar and IQ.
In this case we had researchers who ran 50
statistical tests.
And we would expect to get at least two or
three tests which have p values less than
.05 just by chance.
That's the fact that we have these two
significant p
values isn't a very strong statement.
It's just likely a reflection of chance
rather than a finding of true effect.
In this question we have researchers who
found that women who take,
who took a particular drug, x, had a
significant increase in bone density.
But women who took a drug y did not have a
The correct answer here is B.
The fact that the p value is significant
in one group but
not the other does not tell us whether the
two groups differ significantly.
It also does not guarantee that the effect
is bigger in the drug x group because p
values depend on the effect size, the
variability, and the sample size as well.
The question here,
has researchers who attempted to determine
whether babies who are exposed to x-ray,
while in the womb have an increase risk of
certain childhood cancers.
We see that the odds ratios comes out to
be 2.44.
The confidence interval is 0.95 to 6.33
and
the p value is actually greater than 0.05.
Failure to find statistically significant
result may reflect a lack of
statistical power than the lack of an
effect.
Thus we should pay more attention to the
effect size and
confidence interval rather than to the p
value.
Both myeloid leukemia and inutero X-rays
are rare events,
thus the statistical power for this
association was likely to be very low.
The correct answer just turns out to be B.
Out of the five options given in this
question, the only two for
which we have correlated observations are
c and e.
In c, we are,
comparing the pre-treatment with the post
treatment values of certain patients.
And these are obviously correlated because
we're looking at the same patient before
and after treatment.
And E has a group of cases where we were
looking at sibling controls and
these are again, these again would tend to
be correlated because the siblings would
share some genetic information.