[BLANK_AUDIO].
The background on the subject of medical
error is based on
the 1998 Institute of Medicine's report,
To Err is Human,
which really started the initial patient
safety move here in the United States.
In 2002, the Joint Commission formerly
known as the Joint Commission on
Accreditation of Healthcare Organization
or
JCAHO, established it's National Patient
Safety Goals or NPSGs.
Implemented in 2003, National Patient
Safety Goals were required,
to help accredited organizations address
specific areas of concern in
regards to patient safety.
The joint commission has a term called
Sentinel Event.
It's definition is, an unexpected
occurrence involving death or
serious physical or psychological injury,
or the risk thereof.
Serious injury, especially including loss
of limb or function.
The phrase, or the risk thereof, includes
any process variation for which
a recurrence would carry a significant
change of serious adverse outcome.
Such events are called sentinel because
they signal the need for
immediate investigation and response.
The term sentinel event and error are not
synonymous.
Not all sentinel events occur because of
an error and
not all errors result in being called a
sentinel event.
The source of this information is from
the Joint Commission's Comprehensive
Accreditation Manual,ah, 2013.
Now, what are some of
the events that are considered Joint
Commission Reviewable Sentinel Events?
As I mentioned earlier, the event that
results in an unanticipated death or major
permanent loss of function, not related to
the natural course of the patient's
illness or underlying condition, or the
event is one of the following.
If the outcome was not death or permanent
loss of function not related to
the natural course of the patient's
illness or underlying condition.
These may include invasive procedure,
including surgery, on the wrong patient,
the wrong site, or the wrong procedure.
Unintended retention of foreign object in
a patient after surgery or
other invasive procedures.
[SOUND] Prolonged fluoroscopy with
cumulative doses of greater than 1500
rads to a single field or any delivery of
radiotherapy to the wrong body,
region, or greater than 25% above the
planned radiotherapy dose.
Hemolytic transfusion reaction involving
administration of blood or
blood products, having major blood group
incompatibilities.
That is, ABO or Rh or other blood group
types.
Abduction of any patient receiving care,
treatment, or services.
Sexual abuse, assault, including rape.
The National Quality Forum has developed a
Serious Reportable Event
definition in Healthcare.
In 2002, to facilitate uniform and
comparable public reporting to
enable systematic learnings across
healthcare organizations and systems and
to drive systematic national improvement
in patient safety based on what is
learned about, both from the events and
how to prevent their recurrence.
Many organizations recognize these events
as never events,
such that they should not occur while a
patient is receiving healthcare.
The following is a list of the National
Quality Forum Serious Reportable Events.
They include surgical invasive procedures,
intra operative and post operative death.
Product or device events.
Patient protection events, care management
events,
environmental events and radiologic
events.
Also on the list are potential criminal
The Joint Commission has been collecting
data submitted by
accreditor organizations since the early
2000.
Since those years, Joint Commission has
taken data from these submissions to
establish work groups to develop
recommendations that can
help organizations learn and prevent these
events from occurring.
Through the sentinel event alert
publications,
healthcare organizations, whether
accredited by Joint Commission or
not, have been able to implement solutions
that would assist in
making sure that these events do not occur
within their organization.
This activity has also led to the
development and implementation of
National Patient Safety Goals that are
accreditation standards that
healthcare organization must comply with,
in order to maintain their accreditation.
The NPSGs are program specific.
Which means our specific national patient
safety goals for
hospital, as there are specific for
ambulatory accredited organizations.
The information on this slide,
most frequent sentinel event reported to
joint commission between January and
July 2013, as you look at the top 10
that's been reported to Joint Commission.
You'll see that there are certain
commonalities and certain frequency of
events and considering that these are
voluntarily reported to Joint Commission,
you could just imagine that any one of
these events probably occur in
much greater frequency in healthcare
organizations across the United States.
Now, I'm going to take a few minutes here
to highlight some of
the hospital specific national patient
safety goals.
Regardless of where you practice, if you
are working in
a joint commission accredited hospital,
these standards will be enforced no matter
whether it's a United States academic
medical center, a community hospital,
Department of Defense, county, for profit,
or VA facility.
So, let's take a minute to review what the
current requirements are.
Number one, failure to utilize two patient
identifier, and
two independent person verification for
blood administration.
The need to perform medication
reconciliation.
You need to respond appropriately to
clinical alarms.
You need to perform hand hygiene.
And you need to perform proper universal
protocol from marking of procedure site
and timeout, to prevent wrong patient,
wrong side, wrong procedure events.
Joint Commission expects that an
organization responds to a sentinel event.
At a minimum, the items listed on this
slide are completed.
Your hospital may have additional
requirements that must be fulfilled due
to state laws, hospital policy, and
procedure.
So, starting off with the physician or
attendant,
should be notified that an event occurred,
but there's an expectation that
internally administration is informed of
this particular event.
At some point there needs to be a
notification or
information provided to the patient and or
their care designee.
There may be a need to notify certain
regulatory agencies, there is a need to
conduct a root cause analysis that it is
comprehensive and thorough.
And then, ultimately, a need to implement
corrective actions to
ensure that these things do not occur
again.
[BLANK_AUDIO]