Hello and welcome to HRB 223, Introduction
to Data Management and Analysis for SAS.
My name is Joshua Wallack.
>> And I'm Ron Somderash.
We're going to teach you the basics of how
to use SAS Enterprise Guide,
with weekly modules, quizzes and
homework assignment, we're going to
explore SAS Enterprise Guide together.
>> SAS is a really important data analysis
tool for medical researchers and
clinical epidemiology.
Just.
With SAS Enterprise guide,
you can use code or point and click to
analyze your complex data sets.
Unlike code, where you actually have to
type out your commands, the point and
click interface works simply by pointing
and clicking your mouse.
>> Although the point and
click method is a great way to analyze
your data without having to write your
own code, it does have a lot of
limitations.
With that in mind, we're going to focus on
teaching you how to read, write, and
use your own code.
>> Since this course will focus on coding,
our lectures will generally be based in
SAS Enterprise Guide.
During the in-class meetings, there will
be lab sessions.
These are a great place for
you to ask about the homework assignments
or quiz questions.
We'll also be able to help you out with
any technical issues that may arise.
Enjoy the modules and we'll see you in
class.