In this next module, I'm going to walk
through a real example just to
practice how to interpret the results of
logistic regression.
So I'm going to use a real example from
the medical literature.
This was a case control study that was
done,
the physicians who graduated from medical
school at UCSF.
What they were looking for, the outcome
they were interested in was being
disciplined by the Medical Board of
California.
So if a physician gets disciplined by the
medical board,
that's a pretty bad thing, so those are
the cases.
They identified 68 physicians who have a
disciplinary action between 1990 and
2000, who had graduated from UCSF.
Those are the cases in our outcome
variable here is that
disiplining from the Medical Board of
California.
It's a case control study so the
researchers found those people who
had been disciplined, you know it's fairly
rare.
So they zoned in on them by picking those
in particular.
Then they found controls, the controls
were graduates,
196 controls, who were matched by medical
school graduation year.
So they were the same graduating class,
and specialty choice.
So each, for each case, the, they went out
and
found a couple of controls who came from
the same graduating class.
And were from the same specialty choice.
The aim of the study, I'm just quoting
from the paper here, was, to determine
if medical students who demonstrate
unprofessional behavior in medical school.
Are more likely to have subsequent state
board disciplinary action.
So they were going back into the records
of these graduates and trying to
determine if there were things that could
predict subsequent disciplinary action.
By the medical board in particular.
They wanted to see if there was some
unprofessional behavior in medical school
that could flag those who were at risk of
this outcome.
It's a binary outcome, you're either
disciplined or you weren't.
What kind of analysis are we going to
analyze?
We are going to use to analyze these data.
If you look at our little chart here,
we've got a binary outcome.
We were disciplined by the Medical Board
of California or not.
It's a case control study so the outcome
is case or control.
We want to do some kind of regression
analysis because it's
an observational study , we want to be
able to control for confounder.
That might lead you to think, oh, I should
pick logistic regression.
And in fact, the authors of this study did
indeed use just
a plain old logistic regression analysis.
I want to just point out here though, if
you look closely at this study,
the observations are not independent, they
are correlated.
This was a matched case control study.
Each case was matched to a couple of
control.
So actually we should be using here the
logistic regression for
correlated data which is something called
conditional logistic regression.
That counts for the correlation.
So that's actually the proper statisical
technique that should've been used here.
It would still give odds ratios, and in
this case,
I'm not sure it would have made a huge
difference to the results of this study.
But it's correlated data, so
that would have actually been the
appropriate statistical test to use.
What's the consequence here that the
authors used
logistic regression instead of conditional
logistic regression.
We have a situation where were are
comparing within groups.
Remember when we were talking about
correlated data, I told you that if you
ignore the correlation when you're doing a
within group comparison.
That your peer leaders are going to be too
high.
That means you might miss in effect by not
analyzing the data correctly.
So here what you should do is compare each
case to their matched control.
cases, those case control groups are more
similar to
each other than to other people in the
study.
If you account for that correlation, you
actually would've gotten
probably here a little bit better P values
than what the authors got.
So their analysis could be described as a
little conservative.
Anything that came out significant, we're
pretty sure that's real.
But it could have been that those P values
could have come out more significant in
some of the things that didn't come out
significant.
In the correct analysis might have, so
this is a conservative analysis by
ignoring that correlation.
I just want to point that out to
remind you the importance of thinking
about correlation.
In any case, the author's used a regular
old logistic regression, and
again, these results might be a little
conservative.
We might have missed something here as a
result.
But we can look at the odds ratios, that
logistic regression model, and
just, I want to walk you through how you'd
interpret this table.
So this is Table 5,
from the paper, this is the results of the
logistics regression analysis.
Notice that they're not presenting any
betas, they're just simply going right for
the odds ratios.
They're not presenting any intercepts, we
don't need all of that for
this particular example.
We only care about the odds ratios.
So, just they're just presenting directly
the odds ratios,
the confidence intervals for those odds
ratios, and the P values.
I know want to walk you through what each
of these odds ratios means,
how do we interpret it?
So the first predictor you'll notice here
is male gender.
So the Odds Ratio here is 1.51.
Now this is a fairly rare outcome.
So we can interpret the odds ratios like
risk ratios and
there's not going to be much distortion in
the effect here.
So the odds ratio is 1.51 for males.
It's not statistically significant so
we're not sure that it's any different
than one.
We would say that there's a 50 percent
increase in the odds of the disciplinary
action for men versus women, but it's not
statistically significant.
So this model includes all the things that
you see in the table.
So once you adjust for all of these other
factors the effect of male,
of being male is not statistically
signifigant.
The next variable is, Undergraduate GPA.
This is a continuous predictor, it ranges
from 0 to 4.0.
So the way that, you interpret this odds
ratio.
First of all, we notice that
undergraduate, GPA is protective.
So as your GPA goes up a whole unit, so
this is for
a 1 unit increase in GPA, that's pretty
big.
That's like going from 3 to 4, 2 to 3.
A one unit jump in your GPA, will decrease
your odds of
disciplinary action by 43%, but it's also
not statistically significant.
So once you've accounted for all the other
things, all the other variables that
you see in this table the effect of
undergraduate GPA is not significant.
It doesn't appear to be an independent
predictor.
Although it trends in the direction of
being protective here.
Interestingly the MCAT score, so the way
they measure MCAT score here.
It's this is comparing those who are in
the lowest quartile of MCAT score to
those who are in the higher 3 quartiles,
so this is a binary variable here.
If you're in the lowest quartile compared
to the others, your odds ratio was 1.01.
So after counting for
all these other things in the table,
there's really no effective MCAT score.
Interestingly enough, MCAT score was not
an independent predictor at all here.
The P value you can see is, you know,
very, very high.
If you another binary variable, if you did
not pass, if you failed,
in other words if you failed, any of your
courses in medical school.
Your odds ratio was 1.30, so
a 30% increase in your odds of
disciplinary action, although again,
that's clearly not statistically
significant, so that's very close to 1.
Not an independent predictor, but in the
direction of increasing your risk.
Finally, if you had, displayed
unprofessional behavior in medical school.
Severe enough to meet, this, their
criteria here that they,
you had displayed this unprofessional
behavior in medical school.
Which they think might be a flag for later
disciplinary action.
This is the only significant predictor
after adjusting for
everything else in the model.
So that doubled your odds of getting
disciplinary action.
And in this case, because the outcome is
fairly rare, if you said it
doubled your risk of having disciplinary
action, that would actually be very close.
So that was the only independent predictor
after adjusting for
everything else in the model.