[BLANK_AUDIO]
This next module we're going to spend a
little bit of time talking about some of
the identified root cause analysis that's
been reported to The Joint Commission.
Joint Commission has been collecting
sentinel event data since its
late 1990s early 2000s, and what they
found that out of all the reports
614 of the cases had human factors or
fatigue or distraction involved.
We could just imagine, you know, with
people working long hours double shift.
Things can occur where folks aren't
focused on what the issue or
task is at hand and as resl, as result
leads to an adverse outcome.
leadership.
The lack of performance improvement
infrastructure.
A lack of policy contributes to, why bad
things happen.
And that usually applies to a structure
and a lot of your policies actually
outline step by step procedures in terms
of how things needs to be done.
And as a result when they're not done
properly, it leads to an adverse outcome.
And you know, the whole intent about
policy and procedure is to create
the infrastructure or the methodology upon
what the expected practice is going to be.
Performance improvement infrastructure
that's missing actually alludes to
the fact that there is now a system place
to be able to escalate these issues.
To be able to identify what needs to be
addressed, and
then have a systematic way of addressing
those issues.
Communication, we often time rely on
communication,
not only between team members, but other
discipline.
But we all know that patients also are a
party in this and
especially if you're providing information
to them and
they're not following the instruction or a
patient gave you information that you
weren't aware of that was critical to
their disease process.
And as a result, it does, you know, these
things do lead,
potentially can lead to an adverse outcome
assessment.
Working up the patient, taking into
account all of the information from
diagnostic tests, lab tests, procedures,
consultations, etc.
Those are all factors been identified as,
contributing causes for
a sentinel event to occur.
Information management it's not uncommon
that we don't use the identifiers,
that's on the patient, on the wrist band
or,
we actually did a procedure without
checking against their ID, or
we're engaging them to tell us, you know,
their full name and date of birth.
All of these are things that actually can
lead to a sentinel event.
Physical environment we spoke about this
earlier,
how the environment may not be conducive
to.
Being able to focus on the patient when
the code alarms, when they're going off.
And you get fatigued from hearing them
going on and on and on.
Don't realize that the one alarm for
your patient is a true sign, symptom of a
patient having a problem.
Then it could be set with space.
There's inadequate space to be able to
check the patients armband,
because, you know, everyone's at the head
of the table where the armband is, and
trying to take care of the patient.
That's why some facility actually, you
know,
require they having an armband at the
wrist as well as a band at the ankle.
So that way the staff can actually go up
and
check without disrupting the care that's
being provided continuity care.
We often time know that when patient move
from one city to another.
That [UNKNOWN] carried through the
handoff.
The information communication from one
team to
another team can lead to an adverse
outcome.
Operative setting including things like
blood use and patient monitoring.
We notice that events occur in procedures
that are not necessarily always in an OR.
I mean, there are procedures that are done
at the bedside, the ICU, the ED.
The diagnostic area and as a result when,
system process procedures aren't
being followed, those things can lead to
an adverse outcome.
Medication just about every patient we,
treat.
You know, if all of a sudden use some
medication, and
as a result, when the medication, isn't
properly prepared,
administered, documented, controlled,
stored, labeled.
All these things are factors that can
actually cause an adverse outcome.
And then planning for
the care that we're providing our patient
in terms of making sure that we
understand based on our assessment what's
going on with the patient.
That the plan is communicated properly to
the entire team.
Everyone's on the same page.
Everyone is of a single mindset and
to be able to carry our the fraction to
take care of the patient.
So those are the core you know, care
planning, medication use operative,
all these things are, have been identified
as root causes that have been reported to
joint commission over the last several
years as
factors that have been involved in causing
certain events to occur in a patient.
Now, what are some of the common
challenges that are facing clinicians,
and I'm sure you can relate to each one of
these.
Certainly there are production pressures.
To be able to see more patients, do more
procedures.
You know, you're trying to get a lot done
in a little bit of time.
When you speed things up, things happen.
Certainly, you are more productive, but
the question is, are you more effective.
Multi-tasking, distraction, well,
because of production pressure, it's not
uncommon for us to.
To be distracted, trying to accomplish all
those different tasks,
the multi-tasking when you're trying to do
more than one thing at the same time.
Yeah, you can do one or two things really
good but can you do three or four things?
It's not uncommon for us to have reports
that the wrong patient got the medication
order in place, because what had happened
is that the physician had three or
four computer screens up, open, on their
different patients.
And their one chart they're trying to put
an order in,
another chart they're trying to put a note
in, a third chart they just got a page,
and, and someone's asking questions about
another patient, so
that's classic situation where it, you
know, inadvertently.
You know, with the new technology of
electronic medical records,
a bad thing potentially could happen for a
patient.
Complexities, it's also with old and new
technologies.
Many of us are in hybrid states, you know,
everything from robotic surgery, robotic
pharmacy, to the latest imaging gizmo.
And you know, sometimes, you don't know
how to use a tool.
Develop familiarity to understand how the
tool works.
The ramification of an error is pretty
great or pretty significant.
One event that we had evaluated was a
pretty
common procedure using a particular.
Device and it was interesting that the
team that was involved was setting up
the procedure, both the doctors and the
nurses weren't quite familiar with it.
And as a result, it took a lot longer to
do a relatively routine procedure.
And in the process of taking a lot longer,
they inadvertently had gone
through the area where they were working
through into another area.
The patient didn't have any serious
long-term outcome.
They told the patient what had happened,
but nevertheless, you know, because of
those new, old technology, things happen
and, and can lead to an adverse outcome.
Certainly communication is a factor that
has affected most of us as clinicians.
That were, were have expectations we
thought we
communicated the information properly and,
in, in, in effect we did not.
And as a result misunderstandings or
assumptions were made.
And that leading to an adverse outcome.
Teamwork, we rely so much on teamwork.
We stress teamwork but actually, do we
know our role on the team?
Do we participate as a team?
Very, very common challenge.
Many hospitals are struggling with the
issue of things like who's really in
charge of the patient.
As submitting doctor, are you responsible
for the patient?
If you have a hospice program, who's in
charge?
If you have a intensivist program?
You have a patient in the ICU, is the
intensive in charge?
Is the surgeons in charge?
Is the hospital that's in charge, is the
committee, committee and
doctors, these kind of things regarding
teamwork, adds confusion and
when you have confusion you're set up for
potential for an adverse event.
Then finally we talked about culture and
culture is really the dynamics of how a
team actually works,
communicate, cooperate able to erase
issues and concerns when they do
come up without fear of getting
reprimanded or verbally abused et cetera.
The key thing behind culture is that as
clinicians,
as physicians on a team you really do set
a foundation of how a team functions.
If you ask for folks to be collaborative
and you're patient and
willing to listen to all the viewpoints
before making decisions, I think your team
is going to be more working with you than
passive aggressive not working with you.
Or not raising issues when they should, or
flat out, you know, argumentative behavior
or disruptive behavior is
another factor that we find affects the
culture of a lot of teams.
These six items are common things that
faces clinicians.
It may not be now for you, you know, in
your particular practice, but
somewhere down the road as dynamics change
change because of competition, health care
reform, management change, process
changes, procedure changes, you know.
Don't be surprised if these things are
going to pop up.
Now, some things we want you to beware of
when doing an, a root cause analysis,
are things are little danger zones or
little things you want to be aware of
that can pop up that can affect the
outcome of your root cause analysis.
Starting off with a tendency to jump to
conclusion.
Most of us, in health care, are really
geared at fixing things as they pop.
I mean, that's a knee-jerk response.
That's inherent, must be something in our
DNA, that causes us,
when some problem arises, or
a situation arises for us to jump in, and
based on what we know address the issue.
Probably need to be a little bit more
deliberate.
Give the information that you're gathering
a chance to kind of mature, verify,
validate before you automatically come up
with your conclusions.
You know, one of the things about jumping
to conclusion is also at
the same time people like to fix the
problem.
So, coming up with the solutions before
the root causes or
contributing factors are identified is
another danger zone.
It's something we want you to be aware of.
So, just because you heard it, you figured
that's it, fix it, and move on.
Doesn't necessarily actually address the
problem.
And you'll know it because you'll end up
having the problem.
Problem recur itself again down the road.
Not having the right people in the room
it's either they're involved with
the event, management that's directly
overseeing the area where the event occur,
senior leadership.
Having, not having the right people in the
room can really effect the outcome of
your cause analysis.
Because when you don't have the right
people in the room,
you don't have the right information.
You don't have the right accountability.
And it certainly, you know, when it comes
to actually, following up and
address the issue by not having the right
people in the room,
you may not actually fix the problem.
So you need to make sure that your process
is, is set up in s-such a way that you
have the folks directly involved to
evaluate, understand what's going on.
That led to the problem and
then having the right people in the room
to be able to address and fix the problem.
In some organizations like the VA,
you have a team of folks that actually do
the root cause analysis evaluation.
Pre, present the root cause as the
contributing factor to the solution.
They present that to the executive team at
the VA hospital and
the executive team then designates folks
to go out and fix the problem.
That's their methodology.
Other places actually have all the people
involved with the event,
as well as the leadership team together,
so that they can.
They could hear first hand what the
problem is, so
they can decide on what the solution's are
going to be.
Another danger is actually
under-resourcing, and
that's really issue of time.
in, in this situation, every time these
events occur,
this is not going to be a ten minute
huddle, and
we're going to figure out what the
problems are and fix it.
It usually involves significant amount of
energy and
time, to being able to drill down, figure
out what's happening.
To, to be able to set aside the right
amount of time to be able to drill down,
does require resources and a commitment.
In some organization, when somebody is
involved or designated.
To be involved in root cause analysis that
becomes their primary focus and
their primary job, even though they may be
the chief biomedical person, or
the HR person or the chief nurse or the
chief of staff.
You know, the key thing is is that you you
know need to allocate the amount,
adequate amount of time and energy.
Today we're going to do this right.
Fail to follow up or follow thru.
Can't tell you how many times, people go
thru this whole exercise, and
you know, roll out the solution, and
nobody follows up.
Up to see that the implementation or the
changes were actually put in place.
You can be assured that you'll probably
have the event occur again some time in
the near future, if you don't have follow
up or follow through.
All right, so, we gave you some heads up
in terms of
what some of the challenges are, some
things to be aware of.
When doing a root cause analysis, now
comin' down to the 12 easy steps to
doing the root cause analysis from my
standpoint.
So, what you want to do is quickly, after
an event occur, gather the evidence.
Maintain a chain of custody.
It could be digital photos.
It could be video clip, it could be the
actual materials.
It was thing like an equipment failure, or
medication, administration issue.
Gather a list of witnesses, and this could
be staff, patient, doctor,
resident, fellow, caregivers, anybody that
was in the area who might have heard or
seen whatever is was.
Was that was going on that you're trying
to verify or validate.
What was the event?
Getting a statement.
This either could be a handwritten
statement, an interview.
It could be assistant managers in the
clinic, a unit, department.
It could be the management.
It could be your Patient Safety person,
Risk Management.
It could be from the doctor.
But get all the, get a statement from
folks as soon as possible after the event,
so you can kind of recreate what the
actual event was or
understand what the issues were.
You need to have a process to verify or
validate those statements, and many times
when you you know,
hear the story you may have to go back and
ask the witnesses the question again.
What did you actually hear what'd you see,
because what you said was this.
And when we cleared other folks they had a
different story.
So you know, you need to verify, validate
the statement.
Take that information and to the best of
your ability recreate the event.
Recreating the event actually kind of
paints a picture to
everyone who's evaluating an event.
What was going on?
What was the dynamics of the team?
What was the communication?
What was the environment like?
Was the lighting good?
Was the, was the there was a lot of
ambient noise was it chaotic,
was it stressful, were there other
extenuating pressures or
factors contributing the event, it's
really easy to
assume that a nurse made a midair well
what happen what else was going on.
Develop a timeline.
And be aware, that the timeline may be one
thing for the doctor, one thing for
the nurse, one thing for the technician,
one thing for the medical assistant.
You know, if you develop a timeline, then
you probably want to think about
having this time, minute by minute,
segment by segment, hour by hour,.
Depending on what it is, in terms of the
increment of time, and
then who was doing what at what particular
time.
It's actually starting the process when
you're taking that timeline is
actually starting the process, developing
a little flow map, or process mapping.
Take advantage of your RCA tool.
We talked about brain storming.
We talked about the process mapping.
We talked about the fischform diagram.
You know, take advantage of those tools to
be able to drew down what's going on.
We talked about this earlier.
Identify your stakeholders and other
vested parties.
Certainly those directly involved in the
event have a vested interest in
knowing what's going to happen as a result
of this event.
And, and also don't forget your C suite
folks and
even in some cases your board of directors
or your governing body.
It has a stake in this in terms to
understand what happened,
because inevitably at that level, you're
going to be query by the media,
best friends, donors, other folks.
And then what's going to be done as a
result to this prevent it from happening.
The ninth step, identify the root causes
and contributing factors.
Develop your solutions, implement those
solutions.
The only way you can implement is having
the right people in the room with
the right authority and accountability to
make it happen.
And then you want to monitor the action to
make sure that those fixes,
solutions are put in placed so that event
doesn't occur again.
So there you go.
We gave you the 12 easy steps for doing a
root cause analysis.