The correct answer for this is D.
On a T-distribution we are not guaranteed
that 95% of the area will fall within 2
standard deviations of the mean, even
though this is a fact for
the normal distribution.
This isn't proof for a T-distribution.
Especially for when we have a small number
of observations.
The answer is true,
because the researchers measured what
really the entire population we
can safely say that this is a true value
and there is no sample statistic involved.
The correct answer is b.
The standard is a measure of variability
of the sample statistic.
A is incorrect because the formula given
in a is valid only for
the standard area for mean.
But we could have standard errors of a lot
of other statistics as well.
For example, we could have standard errors
for mo-modes and medians, and
the formula for that would not be the
formula given in it.
Meanwhile, we know that the formula for
the Standard Error in a mean is
the standard deviation divided by the
square root of the number of observations.
In this case our standard deviation is 10.
We have 400 observations, we see that the
standard data comes out to be 0.5.
The correct answer for this question is B.
The size of the smallest group, and
we can illustrate that using a very simple
example.
Let's say we have a case where a was 1, b
was 10, c was 100 and d was 1,000.
We can see that of all expressions in the
formula come out to be one by
one plus .1 plus .01 plus .001.
And we can see that the first expression
is the one that are going to impact
the standard error the most.
The correct answer here is d.
Different statistics have different
forcumlas for standard errors.
We know that the formula for standard
error of the mean.
It is given by the standard deviation
divided by the square root of
the number of observations, but this is
only the formula for
the standard error of the mean.
We have very different formulas for the
standard errors or
the mean, the modes, the median for
example.
The answer to this question is d, all of
the above.
The confidence interval gives us
information about the effect size,
the precision and the statistical
significance.
The correct answer is a, changing from a
99 to a 95% confidence level.
Because [INAUDIBLE] lower level of
Confidence decreases the rate of of
the confidence interval.
A 95% confidence interval of a mean will
include the true
population mean 95% of the time.
This is true by the definition of the
confidence interval.
If we sample both women and men together
we would have a higher standard deviation
of heights because we would expect the men
to be Taller than the women,
is the only sample of women we would
expect the heights to be closer together,
because of which the standard deviation
would be lower.
The first confidence interval would be
narrow,
narrower because it involved a larger
sample size.
We know that the formula for the margin of
error is,
one by the square root of the number of
observations,
which comes out to 4%.
In this case, we know that the mean is
55%.
In the previous question, we calculated
that when we have 625 observations,
the margin of error is 4%.
So if we want to find the lower and upper
bound for
a 95% interval, this would be 55% plus or
minus 4%.
The lower bound would be 55% minus 4%,
which is 51.
And the upper bound would be 55% plus 4%,
which is 59%.
The correct answer is b.
Because the smallest standard error will
result in a smaller p value.
The correct answer here is d.
There is not enough evidence to reject the
null hypothesis.
A is incorrect because we have failed to
prove that the treatments differ but
this is not equivalent to proving the
treatments are the same.
B is incorrect because we were not given
enough information about whether the drug
in the placebo improved the insomnia
symptoms.
C is incorrect because the high value,
P value shows us that we cannot reject the
null hypothesis [SOUND].
In this question the correct answer is C.
There is only 2% chance that the observed
difference in cure rates could have
arisen if the drug had no effect.
This is by the definition of the B value.