In this next case study,
we're going to actually spend a little bit
of time talking about a situation where,.
A pre-operative or procedure room set up.
Patient was already brought into the room,
and was on the table.
The anesthesiologist was chatting with the
patient, having a great conversation.
The anesthesiologist went ahead to hook up
the patient to the EKG monitor,
get the pulse oximeter clip on the
patients finger.
Got the temperature.
The monitor on the patients forehead.
And basically just having a great
conversation with
the patient who's there to have.
A surgical procedure.
The plan was to have a general anesthesia
and so the patient, anesthesiologist just
prior to the patient being brought into
the room was having all the meds drawn up.
Loaded in the syringes recapped.
You know, basically at their work table
area,
by the head of the table all good to go.
The patient was right there and he went
ahead and
gave the pre operative antibiotic.
Which was a hospital initiative,
designed to reduce the chances of
post-operative, surgical site infection.
The anesthesiologist continued to have
this conversation with the, patient.
But after a few minute, noticed the
patient was no longer.
Responding to any of his verbal command.
The patient basically was lying still, not
moving.
The pulse oximeter started to go off.
The the alarm started to ring a little
bit.
Basically it indicated for whatever reason
the patient wasn't really oxygenating.
Anesthesiologist was starting to think,
you know this patient must be having some
sort of reaction to the antibiotic he'd
just given, and started administering some
medication to respond to the suspected
allergic reaction.
The anesthesiologist got really concerned
because the patient wasn't responding to
any of those medication and basically was
not ventilating.
The anesthesiologist started a process to
manually ventilate the patient and
then over a 20 minute well, 15,
20 minutes worth of time, the patient
started to breathe on her own.
In this situation, if you were the quality
officer or
patient office what do you think was
actually going on in this situation?
It was interesting that after we had a
chance to review the event,
and actually spoke to the patient
afterwards.
It was interesting, the patient described
this helplessness feeling,
where the patient was not able to move a
single muscle.
Almost as if they were kind of, paralysed
or, or frozen.
The, patient indicated that couldn't move
their mouth, their eyes couldn't focus.
But the interesting thing in this patient,
was that the patient was able to hear
everything that was going on in the room.
At the time when this event occurred.
It was a little discerning because you
heard a lot of commotion and
a lot of language that could have been
considered a little on the.
Hostile or foul side, but the fact of the
matter is that she couldn't respond to any
of the questions the doctor was asking and
couldn't tell them about you know,
how much actual pain she was enduring
because they were, you know,
they were poking her and try to ventilate
her.
Even though she was unable to do that
herself.
Well, the end result of this was that, you
know,
what was uncovered was that the patient
probably endured a.
Paralytic medication reaction.
Patient actually didn't get the antibiotic
is probably what ended up happening.
When the review was done it was found that
the anesthesiologist and
the team that's involved with, you know,
setting up that room,.
Never label the syringes.
They drop several medications, you know,
and those of you in anesthesia, you know,
you've got your muscle relaxants,
your paralytics, you've got your
sedatives, you know, your narcotics.
You know, and, and so, and plus in this
situation, he had the antibiotic.
If they're given out a sequence, or at a
timing when you are not ready for
it, it creates, workflow variations and
potential heart patients harm.
In this situation, he would, the factor
that was
identified that clearly that the labeling
of syringes wasn't done.
And so, because of some other activity
that was going in the room.
The anesthesiologist was a bit distracted
with some of the commotion that was
going on, and as a result the distraction
led to them grabbing the wrong syringe and
administering the wrong medication at the
wrong time.
As we spoke before,
some of the other factors that also played
in this case were issues of fatigue.
This was a procedure that was later in the
day.
Anesthesiologist and the anesthesia tech,
actually had, been working
started actually a little earlier that
morning because of some other, activities,
and case load that was going on, so there
was a bit of fatigue that was involved.
The usual production pressure, was a, it's
another factor.
The environment.
The issue, what was kind of interesting
was that the lighting was.
Turned down.
And it was a bit noisy.
There was a preference on the part of the
surgical team to
have certain music playing, as they're in
the process of setting it up and
that added to a little bit more
distraction.
And when the lighting's down a little bit,
they don't all see clearly what it
is that they're actually grabbing, you
know, from their anesthesia work area.
So, you know, all these things, you know,
we talked about team training, team
communication, teamwork, and
culture are all factors that contributed
to this particular event to occur.
You know, what's,
what was interesting about this was that,
the thought that a paralytic reaction.
To the medication that was administered
really wasn't, you know,
considered until that interview of the
patient who basically said, you know,
this is what happened and this what I
felt.
You know, I was.
Quite aware of everything that's going on
because you know,
my ears was hearing and my brain was
working.
But I could not move a muscle.
Or you know, move my mouth to save my
life, to tell you what was going on.
So be aware of these events.
Can occur, they do occur.
But there could be some steps we could put
in place,
to be able to prevent these kind of things
from happening, again in the future.
Some of the lessons learned from this
event, is that and
even the Joint Commission, had recognized
that this is a possibility, that the.
Wrong medication could be given to a
patient or
the medication is given at an
inappropriate time or at the wrong time.
So one of the National Patient Safety
Goals that Joint Commission requires of
hospitals and ambulatory surgery centers
requires that any secondary.
Container, such as a syringe, a basin,
a secondary container needs to be labeled
with its content.
Even if you were going to get some saline
irrigation with
some antibiotic mixed into it, you know,
it needs to be labeled with its content.
If the medication is not immediately used.
Used or administered into a patient.
What we talk, what we're talking about
immediate use, immediate administration.
We're actually talking about drawing the
medication up and actually, you know,
putting it into a port or directly
administering into a patient or
using that to immediately irrigate a.
A, a wound.
What, you know, it basically means not to
be drawn up and then put aside, you know,
for a few seconds, or a few minutes, or a
few hours before it's actually used.
So Joint Commission requires that if
you're going to be drawing something up or
pouring something out,
you know, into another container, unless
you're actually using it right away,
the thought process is, is that, that
container needs to be labeled.
Needs to be marked with what it's content
is.
Another factor is that distractions have
been shown to
be a significant factor in medication
errors in general.
Most of the work that's.
Come out of the research associated with
this,
actually comes out of mostly the nursing
literature because nurses for
the most part in healthcare setting are
the primary profession.
That's actually involved in the
administering medication of patients.
They have learned that many times being
distracted momentarily for
that split second is enough to cause a
mediation error.
And so some of the initiatives that
organizations have
implemented including Stanford, you know,
are things like the little red lights
that's on the mobile computer.
That.
When the little red flashing light is on
it means the person that's in, who's
handling the cart is
involved with a medication administration
and that they should not be interrupted or
someone come up to them and ask a
question.
Because that actually is distracting, and
when you have distraction that could lead
to medication error.
In other health systems, and you might.
See this, you know, when you work at other
hospitals or
if you're on a rotation in another
facility.
They have a zone marked off you know,
on the floor where it's basically yellow
tape or red tape.
And if they're in that zone, they're
standing in that area, basically means do
not distract me because they are involved
with medication administration process.
Another example of that would be.
And this is seen in the Keiser system as
well as other health system.
Keiser was one organization that was
involved with developing the concept of
the sash.
Where, if they're involved with a
medication administration they're wearing
this yellow fluorescent sash they are,
that's a sign.
To everybody that they are not to be
interrupted because they are involved with
the medication administration process.
For the physicians, you know, when you're
at the bed side, the table,
the chair side, procedures suites, the
emergency department,
really is like gather, you know, all your
material that you need.
So that you have it readily accessible so
not, someone's not running in and
out trying to gather materials or supplies
or medication.
And then if you draw something up, and
then if you draw it up in a syringe and
you end up putting it down, you know,
you're going to need to look at
getting some labels, even though you're
going to pick it up in a minute.
And go ahead and administer that
medication.
The Joint Commission's expectation is not
only if you put it down it
needs to be labeled even if it's only that
one single medication and
it's the only medication that you use.
It really does need to be labeled with the
content.
An example of this might be something like
a plastic or
dermatology clinic where, you may be
having all these.
Syringes drawn up for the day.
Loaded with, you know, lidocaine with 1 to
100000, epinephrine.
You know, it, it's, even if you load up
four or
five syringes and that's the only
medication you have in your clinic,
the expectation is that from the Joint
Commission.
If they find it they're going to expect it
to be labelled with its content.
So I know that there's manufacturers that
have pre-made labels that.
You can actually purchase.
It comes in a roll and you peel them off
and every time you draw up
a syringe you label it after you draw it
up with what it's contents are.
So that everybody is on the same page and
they know what's in those syringes and
that there's no questions.
So, what are some of the prevention
strategies so
that you don't end up having an issue
associated with
a wrong medication being administered to
one of your patients.
And we talked about this earlier is that
unless the medication is drawn and
immediately used, the syringe needs to be
labeled with key information.
This labeling should be legible and
visible.
My suggestion is those pre printed labels.
It's just, there's companies out there
that manufacture these pre printed labels.
They're color coded, and they come in a
roll.
And they're for the most part legible.
I've seen people use, ball point pen.
I've seen markers.
And what ends up happening, if they are
not, resistant to,
being wet, they end up smearing.
You have no idea, what you, you know,
what's in there and as a result, it'd be a
set up for a problem.
Another prevention strategy, if there's
any doubt about the medication.
Or the container considering doing the
preparation over.
The issue is, is that, you know, you're
relying on the team members to be
helping you out and giving you exact what
you need.
You know, it's always worth doing that
double check.
But if nobody is sure about what it is
that's in that syringe and,
you have time to be able to reprepare that
particular medication,
you may want to consider tossing it and
starting all over.
Many of us know that whenever there's an
emergency or.
Urgency situation, it always contributes
to process variation because those create,
or, products that will create production
pressure.
because what you're trying to do is, you
know,
urgently, quickly get things taken care
of, get the medication in the patient.
But we all know that if the wrong thing's
put in and you're already dealing with
an emergency situation that can definitely
expedite the bad outcome.
So be aware that those emergency and
urgency are production pressure that
causes the need for speed.
And when you got the need for speed and
start short cutting things, that's when
bad things happen.
The last prevention strategy that we can
suggest.
Is doing a double check of the label
containers,
a safety strategy that could prevent a bad
outcome.
In some situations, some hospitals
actually tell,
you know, because they're considered high
alert or high risk medication, when
you do a double check, you should have a
double check also independently done.
With another licensed individual and the
concept there is that if one person,
you know, is not looking at it, you know,
carefully, maybe the second person to
validate or confirm.
But that basically means both individual
has to be focused.
Paying attention, independently doing
their own double check so
that by doing this independent double
check it will actually add
the more likelihood that, you know, you've
got the right med for
that patient that you're actually taking
care of.
So the double check is that, really that
pause that you want to take a moment of.
It's like, am I looking at the right
medication for
my patient before I actually look at
administering it?
Now, one of the strategies some
organizations do use because the,
the, medication container, is bar coded.
You know, if the bar coding specifically
is for that medication and
the bar coding system is linked to that
order for
that patient, you know, you can actually
use bar coding as the second double.
In other words that you check the patient,
check the medication, the system checks
the medication against the medication
order, and that can function as
a double check if you have that system set
up in your particular area.