Welcome back.
In
this module we're going to introduce you
to SAS macros.
in SAS, macros are actually an advanced
and a little bit challenging topic.
In your HRP courses you won't really need
to make your own macros, but
you'll be given macros that you'll need to
be using.
>> Once you jump over the learning curve,
and
discover the power of macros, you'll be
tempted to write, and use your own.
In this module, we'll just run you through
the basics.
>> A macro is basically a way to repeat a
chunk of code.
Let's say you've written some code that
you need to use a bunch of times.
Instead of copying out that code each time
you need it,
and tweaking the variables each time, you
can write a macro instead.
Let's look at a quick example.
>> Suppose you have a number of separate
data sets, which each have a variable for
weight and a variable for height.
For each data set, we want to calculate a
new variable for BMI.
Which is equal to weight divided by height
squared.
Here's the code for how we could do that
using data steps.
>> So we could write out a separate data
step for each data set.
We could copy, and paste this code, and
change the file names by hand.
This can get pretty cumbersome.
Especially if you have to do this multiple
times.
Instead, let's use a macro.
In that sense, a macro is a function.
All you need to do is give it information,
and
it will use that information to run some
code.
In the next module, I'll show you how to
make a macro, but for
now I'll show you what it can do.
We made this macro called makeBMI,
that will automatically add a new variable
for BMI.
All we need to do is tell sass the
original data set,
which is group one which will be modified
and
a new data set group one underscore BMI,
or the output will be saved.
Now, when I run this sass will use the
makeBMI macro function I created earlier.
It'll read in the group1 data set, add in
the bmi variable, and then save everything
in a new data set called group one
underscore BMI all in the word library.
As you can see, this macro did exactly the
same thing as that little chunk of code I
showed you earlier.
Here.
But now if I want to do this for multiple
data sets,
I can just repeat the macro function
instead of repeating all of that code.
>> Once we run these, you'll see that Sass
added a new BMI variable for
each of these data sets.
Once we ran the macro.
And we didn't have to go in and tweak the
code at all.
In the next few modules,
we're going to show you the details of how
to make the macros and
how to use them correctly.