In this next module, we're going to talk
about the concept of interaction.
I mentioned it briefly in an earlier week
in this course, but
now w'ere going to really delve into the
concept and
I'm going to show you how to test for
interaction in a regression model.
First of all, what is interaction?
Interaction is when the effect size
differs significantly between
different subgroups.
In other words, the relationship between a
treatment and
an outcome might differ depending on say
whether you are a man or
a woman, or some other subgroup
characteristic.
For example, if you've got a blood
pressure treatment that
works significantly better in men than
women, that's interaction.
That would mean that the effect size for
the blood pressure treatment was
significantly bigger in men than in women.
Another term you'll sometimes hear used is
effect modification.
Effect modification and interaction mean
the same thing.
You could say that the effect of the blood
pressure treatment was modified by gender,
or you could say that the treatment and
gender interact, either one is fine.
How do we test for interaction in a
regression model?
So, the test for
interaction in a regression model, you can
add an interaction term to that model.
And I'll show you what that is in a
minute.
If that interaction term is statistically
significant, that indicates,
that's proof of interaction.
Let's use this little blood pressure
example.
If I want to test for interaction between
gender and this blood pressure treatment.
Blood pressure is a continuous outcome
variable, so
I'm going to be running a linear
regression here.
I'm going to include in my model a beta
for treatment, and a beta for gender.
And I'm also going to include a term for
the interaction between gender and
treatment.
And what that is, it's literally I'm
going to multiple the value for
gender times the value for treatment.
So, let me illustrate that by writing out
a little mock data set.
You've got some variable gender.
In this case, I've coded it that one is
male and zero is female.
I've got another variable that's
treatment.
One means you're on the drug, 0 means are
on placebo.
Then I've got ID numbers, let's call them
1, 2 and 3.
So, let's say the first person here was a
male and
they were on the placebo, they will get
the values 1 for gender 0 for treatment.
Then we've got a female who was on the
treatment, that would be 0,1.
And then let's say we have a male who's on
the treatment, that's a 1, 1.
If you multiply those values together,
that is what an interaction is.
It's gender times treatment.
because literally we're going to multiply
the values of
those two variables together.
So, ID number one get's a value of 1 times
a value of 0,
that's going to give them an interaction
term of zero.
The ID number two gender is 0, treatment
is 1, 0 times 1 is 0.
ID number three, 1 times 1 is 1.
Notice that if you've got two binary
predictors,
a 0,1 variable, and another 0,1 variable.
The only people who are going to get a 1
for
the interaction are the people who have a
1 on both of those binary variables.
So, in this case, only people who both are
male and
got the drug will get a value of 1.
Everybody else gets a value of 0 for that
Interaction.
That's the, the data, the variables that
were then including in the model.
If the beta for the interaction comes out
to be statistically significant,
this would indicate that there's a
significant interaction.
And the way you would interpret the beta's
from the model, the beta for
treatment in this case, because women is
the reference group, the beta for
treatment represents the treatment effect
in the women.
The beta, the treatment effect for the
men,
you get by adding the treatment effect,
the beta for
treatment plus the date for interaction.
So men, their treatment effect is beta
treatment plus beta interaction.
In other words, the interaction term
represents the difference in
the treatment effect between the men and
the women.
So, if that's significantly different,
that indicates a significant difference in
those effect sizes.
Just in, as a side note here, there is
also a beta gender here.
This term will just indicate whether or
not there was a main effect for gender.
That is whether or
not males have higher blood pressure than
females, unrelated to the treatment.
So, that's what a model within an
interaction term looks like.
Now, let's visit some real examples of how
to apply this in the medical literature.
We saw this smoking cessation trial in an
earlier week.
In this trial, we had women smokers who
were concerned about their weight.
They were afraid to quit, because they
were afraid of gaining weight.
These women were randomly assigned to one
of four groups, so they were randomly
assigned to either get weight focused
counseling or to get standard counseling.
And they were randomly assigned to get a
drug, an anti-smoking drug,
bupropion, or to get a placebo.
So that makes up four total groups.
The outcome here was smoking abstinence.
It was biochemically confirmed.
It's a binary outcome: you either were
abstinent or you weren't.
So that means we're going to be
using logistic regression to analyze the
the data.
Here's the result to that study.
It's a rather busy table, so I'm going to
zoom in on some things now.
First of all, we're looking at actually
three different outcomes here.
They measured the abstinence rates at 3
months, 6 months and
12 months into the study.
So, each of those rows represent a
different time point in this study.
If you just look at the placebo groups
within each of those counseling groups,
you'll see that the rates of abstinence
are pretty similar.
So, at 3 months, it was 18%, where where
in the placebo group.
In the weight focused counseling group,
we're abstinent versus 19%, in the placebo
group in the other counseling group.
Those rates look very similar, so what we
would say here is that there
doesn't appear to be a main effect for
counseling.
In the placebo groups,
those quitting rates in the two counseling
groups look pretty much the same.
What about an effect for drug?
So if we compare the placebo group to the
drug group within each of
those two counseling types, what do we
see?
It appears that the drug actually does
improve quitting rates in both groups.
So, if I look at the weight focused
counseling group, if you're in the placebo
group the quitting rate was 18% at 3
months versus in the drug group and
it was 41%.
At 6 months you also see a similar a
pretty big increase.
In the standard counseling group, the drug
also appears to have an effect.
The effect isn't quite as big, but
you do see almost a doubling of the
quitting rates if you add the drug.
So, for example, in the placebo group at
three months, the quitting rate was 19%.
That went to 33% in the drug group.
At 6 months, it went from 10% to 21%, so
there's a pretty big increase.
Basically, a doubling of quitting rates in
the drug group,
even within the standard counseling group.
Now, as we talked about in the earlier
module on this example,
the P-value is highly significant for the
weight focus counseling group,
the P value of comparing placebo and drug
within that group.
It didn't quite make statistical
significance within the standard
counseling group, but it's very close to
that.
What we would conclude is there just
appears to be a main effect for drug.
Overall, drug seems to be doing something.
Even though it didn't quite reach
statistical significance in
the standard counseling group.
We talked about not misinterpreting those
p values in an earlier module.
If you look at the,
what the authors' concluded in the media
coverage of this study.
Here's the basic conclusion that was
drawn.
Among weight concerned women smokers, drug
therapy increased cessation rates
when added to a specialized weight
concerns intervention,
the weight counseling, but not when added
to standard counseling.
The implication there is that there is an
interaction,
they're saying that the drugs works in one
group, but not the other.
They're implying that there is an
interaction between drug and
counseling type.
However, they haven't done any formal
analyses to test for an interaction here.
So, there is, they haven't specifically
talked about interaction but
that's really the implication here, and
they haven't formally tested that.
So, I actually took the data in their
paper and
re-entered in the logistic regression to
test for interaction to see whether or
not there really is an interaction.
And what would it mean if there was an
interaction?
So, just go back to this slide for a
minute.
An interaction would mean that the drug
affect, the difference between, you know,
going from here to here.
The difference between placebo and drug
was much bigger in
the weight-focused counseling group than
in the standard counseling group.
It does appear to be somewhat bigger.
The, the, change from placebo to drug
appears to be somewhat bigger in
the weight-focused counseling group, but
not a lot bigger than in the standard
counseling group.
We can formulate tasks whether that effect
size is bigger.
We can run a logistic regression within an
interaction term.
Here's the logistic regression model.
Our outcome is smoking abstinence.
I'm going to put in the model a main
effect for drug, a main effect for
counseling type and an interaction between
drug and counseling type.
And these are all binary variables.
When I run that model using the data that
was available in the paper,
I find a significant effect for a drug.
There's a significant mean effect for a
drug.
I find nothing for counseling.
In fact, the counseling, the beta for
counseling does not come out statistically
significant.
And the interaction between drug and
counseling type also does not come out to
be anywhere near statistically
significant.
Indicating that we can't say that there's
a difference in how that
drug works in those two groups.
And here, I'm just showing you the p
values for
interaction from those models I ran.
I ran three logistic regression models for
each of the time points.
And in none of the cases does the P-value
even approach statistical significance.
So, we have no evidence that the effect of
the drug differs by counseling type.
Our main conclusion, then.
Our correct take home message would be
that the drug improves quitting rates over
counseling alone, period.
There's a main effect for a drug, there's
no main effect for
counseling type and there's no interaction
between drug, and counseling type.
It's not statistically significant, at
least, that we don't have evidence that
the drug behaves differently in those two
groups, at least not from this study.
The second example I'm going to show you
is a cross-sectional study of
about 1700 men and women.
In this study, they actually did formally
test for
interaction and they did find a
significant interaction.
This study was looking at the relationship
between sleep duration and
sleep problems, and hypertension.
It's a cross-sectional study but
they treated hypertension as the outcome
variable.
Hypertension is binary, yes, no.
So, we're going to be using, they did use,
logistic regression.
Let me show you the main results of that
study.
This charts a little complicated, so I'm
kind of going to walk you through it.
And I want to actually also write out the
logistic regression model that
was used here.
I think it's, it's a little complicated,
but it's instructive.
So, first of all what are we looking at?
The outcome here is hypertension.
So, we're looking at odds ratios for
hypertension,
based on two predictor variables: sleep
difficulty and sleep duration.
If you read the fine print, I just want to
note here that there's other things in
the model between, besides those two
predictors.
This is all data were adjusted for age,
race, sex, BMI etcetera, etcetera.
So, there's a whole bunch of other
variables in the model, but
I'm not even going to bother to write out
in the model.
But they are,
those predictors are also included in the
model, just to adjust for confounding.
The predictors that the researchers cared
about here were
two predictors; sleep difficulty, which is
a 3 level categorical variable.
You are either a normal sleeper, that's a
reference group.
You have poor sleep, kind of not at the
level of insomnia, but some trouble.
And then you could have insomnia which is
really trouble sleeping.
They also looked at a three category
variable for sleep duration.
So, they categorized people as getting
more than six hours per night,
getting five to six hours per night, or
getting less than five hours per night.
The reference group is getting is, is the
highest sleeping group,
more than six hours per night.
The [UNKNOWN] regression model with those
two categorical variables as well as
the interactions.
So, let me write out that model.
Again, we're modeling the log odds of
hypertension,
it's going to have an intercept.
And because we've got a multilevel
categorical variable,
we're going to be dummy coding.
So, this is a good review of dummy coding,
which we talked about last week.
The reference group is normal sleepers.
To dummy code a three level categorical
variable I need two dummy coded variables.
So, normal sleepers will will not get it's
own beta, but I'll have a beta for
poor sleep and I'll have a beta for
insomnia.
If you have a 0, 0 for poor sleep and a 0
for
insomnia, you are by default in the normal
sleeping group.
For sleep duration, I'm going to put in,
the reference is greater than 6 hours, so
I'm going to put in a beta for
5 to 6 hours and I'm going to put in a
beta for less than 5 hours.
If you get a 0 on both of those binary
dummy coded variables,
that means by default you're in the
greater than 6 hours duration group.
That's how I dummy code those two
predictors.
But now, the researchers also put in an
interaction term between those
two predictors.
So, let me show you what that looks like
in the model.
And for interacting two three level
categorical variables,
we are going to end up with four
interaction terms in the model.
First of all we're going to have an
interaction between poor sleep, and
5 to 6 hours duration per night.
We're going to have an interaction between
poor sleep and
less than 5 hours per night.
We're going to have an interaction term
for insomnia,
times the 5 to 6 hour duration, and we're
going to have an interaction For
insomnia in the less than five hour
duration.
Plus remember this model also has all
those other betas for
the confounders that I'm not going to
bother to write out.
So it's a little complicated but
each of these interaction terms is either
a one if you are in that group so, for
example, the, the poor sleep times five to
six hours per week.
If you're in the poor sleep group and you
sleep 5 to 6 hours per night, you're
going to get a 1 for that interaction
term, everybody else is going to get a 0.
So this breaks down to a bunch of binary
variables.
From all of these betas, by fitting all
these betas,
you are able to get an oz ratio for
each of these different categories of
both, sleep duration and sleep difficulty.
That's what they generated here,
they generated those odd ratios right from
the logistic regression model.
If you look at the fine print, it says the
interaction between [INAUDIBLE].
Insomnia and objective sleep duration is
statistally significant.
So, 2 interaction terms came out
statistcally significant.
Those that interacted insomnia, not poor
sleep,
but insomia with the short sleep duration.
And you can also see the interaction just
by looking at
the odds ratio that were generated by the
model, here.
So if you look at the odds ratios again,
the reference group was normal sleepers
who are sleeping more than 6 hours per
night.
If you compare poor sleepers and
insomniacs where everybody's sleeping at
least 6 hours per night, long sleepers.
You'll notice that poor sleep and insomnia
didn't make much difference.
The odds ratios are 1.31, so you don't
really get much increase in your chances
of hypertension if you have bad sleep as
long as you're sleeping enough.
Every night.
If we move over however,
to the group whose sleeping much shorter,
five to six hours per night.
Then you'll notice that normal sleepers
and
poor sleep, there wasn't too much going
on.
But those who have insomnia and are also
sleeping five to six hours per night.
Have a 3.5 odds ratio there so
a drastic increase in the odds of
hypertension.
Finally if you look at the really short
sleepers The effect of insomnia is even
greater, so as you get up to the insomniac
group and you're having really poor sleep,
you get a increase, a much bigger
increase, in your odds of hypertension.
And notice that this odds ratio comes out
statistically significant and so
does this one.
So again there's Significant interaction
here.
The sleeping difficulty doesn't seem to
matter as long as you're
getting enough sleep but, if you are not
getting enough sleep,
then the sleeping difficulty seems to
really impact your risk of hypertension.
That's what, that's what the interaction,
that's the sort of verbal way to describe
the interaction here.
I want to point out and remind you Ratio.
That we are dealing with odds ratios,
here.
And as I told you, talked a lot about in
week 2 of this course,
odds ratios, you have to be careful about
interpreting them.
This was a cross sectional study.
The outcome was extremely common.
In the reference group.
About a quarter of people in the reference
group had hypertension.
So the outcome is very common.
So you have to be careful about
interpreting.
These odds ratios look really big.
3.5 and 5.1.
You would not want to say that this was a,
that this 3.5 represented a threefold
increase in the risk.
Of hypertension in this group.
And you would not want to say that this
five,
this [INAUDIBLE] ratio of 5 represented a
five-fold increase in
risk of hypertension.
Since the outcome is common these
[INAUDIBLE] ratios are distorted,
these are not the increases in risk.
They are the increases in odds.
If you use little formula I gave you in
week 2 of the course, you could actually
convert back and figure out the risk
ratios, the corresponding risk ratios.
It turns out that there's more like a
doubling in the risk of hypertension here,
not a five fold increase.
So I don't want you to forget when you're
doing logistic regression we're
getting odds ratios Be careful about the
interpretation when you
have a common outcome.
This final example actually comes from a
paper that I wrote
in graduate school and so excuse the poor
resolution of the graphic.
It's a little bit of an older paper.
But this involved a, an interaction term
that we found in a linear regression.
So just to show you how this works also
for linear regression.
We were looking at three outcomes.
This was looking at bone densities, so we
looked at the bone density in the spine,
and in the hip, and overall in the body.
Those were the outcomes.
Since our outcomes are continuous bone
density is continous,
we were doing linear regression not
logistic regression.
Women athelets, this is a study about
women athelets, women runners.
Women athletes sometimes if they have
disordered eating, and
irregularities in their menstrual cycle,
it can cause them to loose bone density,
that's what this paper was about.
So, we were looking at kind of two factors
here.
We were looking at an eating disorder
score called the EDI score,
this tells us about eating, disorder
eating behaviors.
So, higher scores says,
a woman is more likely to have some kind
of eating disorder.
We also looked at menstrual cycle, and so
we divided women into two groups.
Those are the normal menstrual cycle,
those eumenorrheic women, those are all
the bars in the back of this graphics.
And women with menstrual irregularities,
we call that the eligo and
amenorrheic group, and that, those are the
bars in the front.
So, we looked at those two menstrual
groups as well as this
disordered eating score, and we looked at
the interaction between those two things.
And we did find a statistically
significant interaction here.
And it's kind of nicely pictured in these
graphics.
So, what's happening here is that,
if you look at the women who already has
menstrual irregularities.
If you look at the effect of eating
disorder score, it doesn't seem that
they're bone density changes much at all
across different eating disorder scores.
Once you already have menstrual
irregularities,
it doesn't seem to be much additional
effect of eating disorder score.
So the bone density is pretty flat across
those different eating
disorder score groups.
If you look however at the women with
normal periods, the eumenorrheic group,
the bars in the back, you can see there's
a pretty dramatic effect for
eating disorder scores.
So, as your eating disorder scores
increases,
your bone density goes down quite a bit.
And that's in all three sites.
So, interestingly, there's an interaction
here, because the the effect
of the eating disorder score was different
between these two menstrual groups.
And that had some certain implications
that were of interest.
But, we got the significant interaction in
a linear regression by
including the interaction between EDI
score and in menstrual group.