In this next module, I'm going to talk
about the formal types of
errors that can occur with hypothesis
tests, and directly related to that,
the concept of statistical power.
Lets review from last week, the steps of a
hypothesis test.
First thing that you do is to define your
null hypothesis,
that's the strong man that you want to
shoot down.
Once you define the null hypothesis then
you can predict the range of values for
your statistics that you expect to see
when you do an experiment if the null
hypothesis is true.
Then you got to do your experiment.
You calculate that statistic If the
statistic is within the range of
values that your expecting based on the
null hypothesis your P
value the probability of your data will
end up just a being something high in
other words your experiment will sort of
match, match with the null hypothesis.
On the other hand, let's say you do the
experiment and
you get a value that's outside of what's
expected, based on the null hypothesis.
Then you're going to get a low p-value.
The probability of your data, or
something more extreme is going to be
small, given the null hypothesis.
If the p-value is small enough you're
going to reject the null hypothesis.
In other words your data and your null
hypothesis don't match.
And therefore you're not going to reject
your data, so
you're going to reject the null
hypothesis.
That's the steps you go through in a
hypothesis test.
And the underlying logic is something like
this.
Assuming, assume that the null hypothesis
is true.
If the null hypothesis is true,
then you expect to see a certain thing in
your study.
Lets say that you don't see that.
So if A then b, not b.
If you don't see that, then you're going
to reject your original assumption.
That's the logic of a hypothesis test.
But because we're doing statistics, we're
of course dealing always with uncertainty.
We have to grapple with uncertainty.
So now throw in a bit of uncertainty.
If A is true, then probably we're going to
see B.
If we don't see B then probably A isn't
true.
There's uncertainty thrown in.
So, at the end of the day we have to make
a binary decision.
We either reject the null or we don't.
That decision can have some errors
associated with it.
Let's say that there, that the null
hypothesis is true.
There really isn't an effect.
But we erroneously reject the null
hypothesis when we shouldn't,
that's a false positive.
We've made a false positive.
We call that a type 1 error sometimes also
called an alpha.
On the other hand let's say that the null
hypothesis is false and
there is actually an effect.
But we failed to reject the null
hypothesis.
That's a false negative error.
We call that a type 2 error it's also
known as beta.
Directly related to the type 2 error is
something called statistical power.
Statistical power is just the complement
of the type 2 error.
If the probabilty that is there really is
a effect.
If the null the hypothesis is false.
It's the probability that we're going to
find that effect in our study.
Notice that all of these have a sneakly
conditional.
You can only make a type 1 error is the
effect isn't real.
If the null hypothesis isn't true.
You can only make a type 2 error is the
effect is real.
If the null hypothesis is false.
Just kind of keep that in mind.
I think the easiest way to understand type
1 and type 2 error.
Used to put them in a little box, and
I'm going to do that in a moment, but
whenever I talk about type one and
type two error, it always reminds me of
something called Pascal's wager.
So, this is a little bit of an aside, but,
I was a philosophy major in college, and,
if you've ever taken a philosophy 101
class, you've probably had to read.
A bunch of proofs from philosophers
throughout history about either
the existence or non-existence of God,
plus there's a lot to think about and
talk about in the philosophy literature.
One of my favorite proofs of all the ones
I've had to read,
was something called Pascal's Wager.
And I really like it, because it's simple,
it's a simple logical, rational argument,
rather than these kind of long winded,
drawn out proofs that were hard to read.
Pascal's wager was just a rational
argument.
So Pascal says, there's some truth out
there, either God exists or
God doesn't exist.
One of those things is true and we can't
really ever know for sure.
You have to make a decision however so
it's kind of immaterial whether,
what the truth is since that's, you know,
a knowable but you have to make a decision
regardless.
Your decision on Earth is to either reject
God or you're going to accept God.
Now let's say, this is Pascal's argument:
let's say that God exists.
And you reject God then you've made a big
mistake right that
means your depending on the religion you
subscribed to your going to hell or
some bad very bad thing will will result
so that's a big mistake.
On the other hand.
If god exists and you accept god, then
your, you've got it right, and
there's some kind of big payoff.
Like, you're going to heaven or
whatever the again whatever the particular
religion you subscribe to says.
It's always a big, really great thing.
On the other hand, let's say that god
doesn't exist.
And you reject god.
Well, then you've got it right.
But the payoff maybe isn't so big, maybe
you get to live your life a little bit
differently, maybe the payout is not huge
there, however if God doesn't exist and
you accept God, then Pascal says that's
really kind of a minor mistake.
The cost to you of that mistake isn't so
high Because, you know,
maybe, you live your life a little bit
differently.
Maybe you go to church or
temple, maybe you, don't drink as much,
but he says that,
those costs are much more minor compared
to the other mistakes you could make.
And that's his sort of rational argument,
for whether or
not to believe in God .So I think it's
Just an interesting and fun example.
And, it always reminds me of type 1 and
type 2 error.
Because put type 1 and type 2 error in a
box.
So, the null hypothesis is either true or
it's false.
One of those things is true, and we can
never really know with complete certainty.
Let me just throw in an example in here,
so
let's say that your null hypothesis is
that the vaccine,
the HIV vaccine like we saw last week,
doesn't work; that's the null hypothesis.
So let's say that one possibility is
that's true and
the vaccine actually doesn't work, if the
null hypothesis is false that would
mean the vaccine actually does have a
biological effect.
Now you got into a study and then you have
to make a statistical decision.
You're either going to reject the null
hypothesis and
conclude that, in fact the vaccine does
work.
Or you're going to fail to reject the null
hypothesis.
If you fail to reject the null hypothesis,
you're not saying that the null hypothesis
is true, you're just saying that there's
insufficient evidence to reject it.
Notice that, that's a slightly different
thing.
So just kind of keep that in mind.
We're never proving the null hypothesis,
we're just failing to reject it.
So let's say that the null hypotheses is
true.
In fact the vaccine doesn't work.
But let's say that you look at the results
of the study and
say you see that P-value of .04 that made
it under a .05.
And you decide to reject the null
hypotheses, and
conclude that the vaccine is effective.
Then you've made a type one error a false
positive, and
we think of that error as being fairly
egregious.
Right because you might then, go out,
give people the vaccine, you might make
policy decisions,
you might change how you treat patients
based on rejecting a null hypothesis.
We tend to guard pretty stringently in the
medical literature, or
we're trying to, against Type I error.
On the other hand, let's say that the
vaccine in fact does work.
It has some real biological biological
effect, in other words,
that the null hypothesis is false.
But let's say you look at the results of
this study and
you know the P values are kind of
marginal.
You're not that convinced.
So you don't reject the null hypothesis.
Then you've made a Type II error.
A false negative error.
You have failed to find an effect that
actually exists.
Again, though, when you Fail to reject a
null hypothesis you're
just concluding that there's insufficient
evidence that the vaccine works.
Therefore, you might decide to keep on
studying it.
We tend to think of a type II therefore as
a little bit less egregious,
because we don't tend to change medical
treatment and change policy based on it.
The result of a type II error is usually
there's further study.
So in the medical literuture we tend to
set the type 1 error to be
more stringent than the type 2 error rate.
And of course there's going to be a trade
off between those 2 things.
So if you set the type 1 rate to be more
stringent you have to loosen the type
2 error and vice versa.
In the medical literature a typical a
study might have a type 1 error rate of
5% and a type 2 error of 20%.
Again, the type one error rate is directly
related to the significance level.
So this is the false positive rate.
The probability of finding an effect that
isn't real.
If you set the statistical significance
cut-off a p-level of less than .05.
So in order to be statistically
significant and reject the null.
You require a p-value of less than .05.
That means that you're permitting a false
positive rate of
5% if there's nothing going on in your
data if there are no
effects you're still expecting to see a
significant p-value one in twenty times.
That's the Type I error rate directly
related to the significance level.
The Type II error rate is
the probability of missing an effect to
get a false negative.
Now, we don't usually talk directly about
the Type II error in medical studies.
What we do instead is talk about something
that's the compliment of
the Type II error.
We talk about the statistical power.
So, statistical power is just the
probability of
finding an effect if it's there.
Is the probability of not making a type II
error.
That's usually what we talk about in, in
medical studies.
When we design studies a typical study
might be designed to have a power 80%, so
that means we're allowing a false negative
rate of type II error rate of about 20%.
Now that's sort of your typical study.
That means that we, when we go out to do
studies we're accepting that in
about 1 in 5 studies we're going to miss a
real effect,
when there are actually effects we're
going to miss about 1 in 5 of them.
Statistical power is such an important
concept in medicine/g,
I'm going to spend now a few more minutes
talking about it.
Again, statistical power is the
probability of finding and
effect if 1 is there.
It's akin, when we talk about diagnostic
testing,
we talked about something called
sensitivity.
Statistical power is just akin to
If there is an effect,
it's the probability that you're actually
going to find it.
Finding an effect means coming out with a
significant P value at the end of the day.
Statistical power is [UNKNOWN] if there's
an effect there, the chances, the chance
that you're going to end up with a
significant P value at the end of the day.
Your P value is going to be under 0.05, or
whatever you set the bar at.
So statistical power is directly related
to P-values because it's
the probability of getting a significant
P-value.
What factors affect P values?
because the same factors that affect
P-values are going to
affect statistical powers.
So let's just review from last week.
What affects the p-values?
Well there are three things that affect
the P-values.
Remember we were calculating either Z or T
scores.
When we do statistical tests.
And those were directly related to the
effect size divided by the standard error.
And the standard error is some com-,
composite of variability divided by sample
size.
It's not exactly variability divided by
sample size.
It's more complicated than that but in
essence the standard error has
a variability in the numerator and some
version of sample size in the denominator.
So, roughly our z or t square was always
proportional to the effect size divided by
the variability divided by the sample
size.
That actually puts the sample size
essentially in the numerator.
Bigger Z scores and bigger T scores mean
smaller P values in other words if you
have a bigger effect size that's going to
decrease the size of your P value because
its going to make you more likely to find
a stastically significant effect.
If your sample size is bigger,
you're also going to be more likely to
find a statistically significant effect.
However, if you have greater variability
in the, in the outcome or
trait you are looking at, the greater the
variability the smaller the z or
t value, therefore the less chance you'll
have of finding statistical significance.
So those are the three factors that factor
into the p-value.
Well since the statistical power is just
the chance that your going to find
a significant P value of course power is
directly related to
all those factors as well.