For this first problem on the first
homework assignment we're provided with
a table that we're going to spend a few
questions dissecting.
So, we really should first understand what
this table what kind of
information this table's giving us.
On the left hand side here, we have all
the different values in our data set.
So, you can think of the,
about this as a list of all the distinct
values in our data set.
Okay, and
these are associated with relative
frequencies on the right hand side.
So, what is this really saying?
This is saying that in our data set, we
have 11 showing up 10 different times.
So, that's going to be looking something
like 11, 11, 11, ten times.
And then we're going to have 12 nine
times.
That's going to be 12, 12, 12.
Now usually it's not all organized this
way from in, in, in ascending order.
But that's how it's presented here in this
table.
Sort of a, a, a summary of our data.
So, the first question is asking us to
calculate the mean.
Okay, and the way we're going to do that
[SOUND] is we're going to use a short cut.
So, we know we have 11 ten times.
So, rather than writing out 11 plus 11
plus 11 plus 11,
we're going to do ten times 11, okay?
We're going to do the same thing for each
of these outcomes.
So, we're going to do 9 times 12 plus 11
times 13, et cetera.
All the way until we get to 6 times 16,
okay?
And this is all divided by the total
number of data points in our data set,
which is 60.
So, this is all going to be divided by 60
and
that's going to work out to be 13.4, okay.
So, the answer to the first question which
asks us
about the mean of the sample data is 13.4.
In the next question we're asked about the
standard deviation, and
in order to calculate the standard
deviation what we're going to need to do
is remember what the formula for the
standard deviation was.
And so let me start out by first writing
that formula.
So let's see I'll do it over here.
The standard deviation notated as SD here
is equal to
the square root of the sum of this
expression.
The number in your data set minus the mean
in your data set squared over n minus 1.
Now we know that n is equal to 60.
Okay, we have 60 numbers in our data set
and
we also just calculated the mean to be
13.4.
So, we have these pieces these components
so let's plug them into our formula here.
So, let's see, so 60 and 13.4, okay.
And, so what I'm going to do is write out
the first few
expressions here in the numerator.
The whole thing is in the written
solutions provided to you on
the class website.
So, for those who want to see the whole
thing I would encourage you to look there.
So, what I'm going to do is
write out this expression,
okay.
And you might have noticed that I did
something wrong here, okay?
What did I do wrong?
Well, if you think about what our data set
really looks like, it has ten 11's, right?
I said that before.
So, we can't just have one expression that
has 11 minus the mean of our data set,
we need ten of those.
So, what we're going to do is multiple
this by ten and similarly we're going to
multiple this by 9 because there are 12
nines in our full data set.
So, yes so I'll multiply the last one by
six as well.
And doing out this calculation, we're
going to get 148 on the top divided by
59 in denominator and that's going to
leave us with 1.58.
So, the answer to the question is 1.58,
the standard deviation of our data is
1.58.
The next part of the question asks us
about the median value of our data.
Okay?
So,
the median if you remember, is the middle
number in our data set.
Okay?
So, the first step
whenever you're thinking about the median
or
the interquartile range, is to arrange the
numbers in your data set in order.
Okay?
And this can be in increasing or
decreasing but you need to have them in
order.
Fortunately for us it's already presented
in that way.
Okay?
This is in, ascending order here, and
we know that we have 60 data points in our
data set.
So, the middle value or
the median is going to be between the 30th
and the 31st values.
Okay?
So,
how do I know what value is the 30th and
what value is the 31st?
If I don't write them out and order them.
Well, I know the first ten numbers are
supposed to be 11, and
then I know the next nine are supposed to
be 12, right?
So, the 19th number is going to be 12.
So, then if I add 11 to that I know that
the 30th number is going to be 13.
Okay, then I'm going to get 14, the 31st
number is going to be 14.
In fact the next 14 numbers are going to
be 14 because of that right there.
So, what is the median?
The median is the average of these two, so
13 plus 14 divided by 2.
The median in this case is 13.5.
Right, moving on to the inner quartile
range.
So, again, the first step would be to
order our data.
Fortunately for us, it's already ordered.
Okay, we know that the median or the 50th
percentile, remember those are the same.
The 50th, the value at the 50th
percentile, lies between the 30th and
31st number, right.
From the problem before, we know that
that's the case.
So, that means that, the 25th percentile
and the 75th percentile, okay,
are going to reside between the 15th and
16th numbers.
And the 75th percentile's going to lie
between the 45th and
the 46th numbers, okay.
And what is that going to be?
This is going to be 12, because we know
that the first ten numbers are going to be
11, and the next nine are 12, so that
includes the 12th number.
And then we want to look at the 45th and
the 46th number, okay.
And that's going to be 15, right here.
It's actually easier if you work backwards
from 60, okay to do that calculation, but
that's going to be 15.
And the reason why we're interested in the
25th and 75th percentiles here,
is that the IQR is equal to the 75th
percentile minus the 25th percentile.
Okay?
So, that's going to be 15 minus 12,
giving us an IQR of 3.
So, this last part of the first question
asks us to correctly identify
the histogram that's associated with the
data in our table.
So, looking at the answer choices very
quickly, and
I think it's immediately obvious that B is
not the answer, okay.
So, B shows that the frequencies are equal
across all
the different respiratory rates.
And that's certainly not the case here,
all these numbers are not equal, okay.
So, we can quickly eliminate B.
If you look at C closely, there's actually
a bar at 17,
and we do not have a 17 an outcome that is
17 in our data set, okay?
If there was a 17 here, there'd be the
number zero there.
So, C does not make sense, leaving us with
answer choice A.
So, moving onto question two of the
homework, question two is
showing us a table that's similar to the
table shown in question one.
There're only two different outcomes here
with outcomes on the left and
frequency shown on the right, and it's a
100 in this case, okay.
So lets look at what the questions are
asking us to do.
The first part asks us to calculate the
mean of our sample.
Okay?
So, again let's think about how to
read this.
So, this is saying that in our data set,
zero occurs 53 times.
So there's going to be 53 zeros here.
And then there's going to be 47 ones
following that, for
a total of 100 values in our data set,
okay.
So, the mean is simply going to be the sum
of all those values divided by
the number of numbers in our data set.
And so that's going to be equal to 53
times zero.
Right, which seems silly to do because
this is
just equal to 0 plus 47 times 1 divided by
100, okay.
And so the mean is going to be equal to
.47.
The second part of this question asks us
to calculate the standard deviation of
this data set.
And so again, the first step is to
remember what the formula for
the standard deviation is.
So I'll write that out one more time.
It's the summation of the expression shown
here, okay.
And so n is the number of values in our
data set so that's going to be 100.
The mean we just calculate it to be 0.47,
okay.
So, let me clean this up a little bit and
rewrite that expression here.
All right, and the in contrast to previous
examples,
this is actually going to be a shorter
expression to write out,
because there are only two distinct values
in our data set.
And I'll show you what I mean in a second.
So, we have 0 minus .47 squared plus 1
minus 0.47 squared.
And that's it because we only have two
values, i equals 1 here and
i equals 2 here, and that is all I equals.
The issue is that zero shows up 53 times.
So, we really should be doing this
calculation 53 times.
So, what I'm going to do is add a 53 in
front of there,
basically multiplying it by 53, and
multiply this by 47 as well.
Now, remember when you were calculating
the mean,
you might have said, okay, 53 times 0, I
don't have to do that, that's just 0.
In this case you do have to do this
because 0 minus 0.47.
Okay, so it's, it's negative 0.47 squared,
so
that's going to give you a number and
affect your standard deviation estimate.
So, don't just ignore the zero this time.
Okay, that's a common mistake.
So, this is all going to be divided by 99.
And then if you do have this calculation
it simplifies to 24.91 over 99,
which okay, which simplifies to 0.502.
Alright, so the standard deviation here is
0.502.
So, what is the median value in this data
set?
Well, the median value in any data set is
the middle number, okay?
And the middle number here, we know, well,
so, we know that there's 100 numbers here.
So, we know that the middle number is
represented by the average of the 50th and
the 51st number, okay.
And remember to order your data in what,
either increasing or
decreasing order but you need to order
your data in order for this to make sense.
So thankfully here it's already ordered.
It wouldn't be too hard to do since there
are only two values anyway.
But so you could imagine that the first 53
numbers in
your data set are going to be zero, and
then the 54th number is going to be one.
Okay?
So if this is the 54th number, 53, 52, 51,
50 we see that the average of 0 and 0 is
just 0.
So the median here is 0.
Great, so this piggybacks on to the next
question which is asking for
the interquartile range.
For it, to calculate the interquartile
range, okay, we're going to need to know
the number at the 75th percentile minus
the number at the 25th percentile, okay.
So, we calculated the number at the 50th
percentile it would you could gather
that the number at the 75th percentile
would be the average of the 75th and
76th numbers in our data set.
And similarly the 25th, the number at the
25th percentile would be
the numbers between the 25th and the 26th
numbers.
And so we know that this is going to be
zero and that is this going
to be one because of this relation and I
will keep reiterating that.
But basically we're going to do 1 minus 0.
The interquartile range is the glamorous
number of 1.
For the third question on this homework,
we're provided with table 1,
which is an excerpt from a paper published
in JAMA recently.
So, the first part of this third questions
asks us what type of variable is
the variable age.?
Okay So there's some clues here.
So, age is reported with the median in the
interquartile range and
the units here are given as y.
So, age in years, this is a continuous
variable because it's giving us years and
it's reported with the median
interquartile range.
We know, or, or the author, we know that
the authors believe that age is not
normally distributed because they report
the median and the interquartile range.
That's a very standard practice if age was
normally distributed.
The mean and the standard deviation are
usually reported.
The next question asks us about the
variable below that, okay.
Age greater than or equal to 75 years.
This is going to be a binary variable.
It's either going to be yes, older than or
greater than or
equal to 75 or no, less than 75, okay.
So, this is a binary variable, probably
coded as 1, 0.
The third question asks us what
statistical measures are used to
describe the central tendency and
variability of the age variable.
So, I already pointed this out, earlier
when we were discussing this,
but, it's reported with the median in the
interquartile range as indicated here.
The statistics used to describe age
greater than or
equal to 75 years is n and percentages,
okay.
So, this is the percentages of this end,
essentially.
So, 562 represents 17% of this overall
cohort of 32,
about 33 hundred people and 592 represents
about 18% of
this overall cohort of again, about 3,300
people.
The next three questions ask us to, gather
some values from this table.
So, the first one is asking us what the
median weight of the placebo group is.
So, we're immediately our attention is
drawn to this column, okay.
And then we want to find the weight
variable.
We notice that it's given, the median is
reported, okay.
So, the median in this case is going to be
81, specifically, 81 kilograms.
What is the percent of participants in the
ranolazine, I'm not sure if
I'm pronouncing that right, in the, in the
drug group basically, okay.
So, you notice it says female sex here,
and
that's the percentage of the participants
who are female,
which means that about 66% of those
participants are male.
The next question asks us about the number
or
the percentage of participants rather in
the placebo group who have hypertension.
So, again, we're going to go and
find the hypertension row here, which is
in the co-morbidity section, and we see
that the percentage of the patients in the
placebo group with hypertension is 73.9%.
The next part of this question is asking
us to
calculate how many binary variables are
shown, okay.
So, the trick here is to look at how these
variables are reported.
If there's a fraction, if there's a
percentage reported for
a certain variable, you can assume that
it's binary, okay.
And that's because when there are two
levels,
if you know the percentage here this one's
going,
just going to be 100 just minus the
percentage given in the other category.
That's why there are no like second level
or third level values reported here.
So, to get back to the question, all the
variables with percentages reported,
our fractions here, are age grid equals
75, female sex, white race diabetes,
hypertension, hyperlipidemia, whether
you're a current smoker or not.
History of prior MI history of prior
coronary revascularization and
prior heart failure.
The last part of this first homework
question asks you to identify the box
plot that represents the distribution of
each in the placebo group.
So, we look at the placebo group.
Whoops, I just covered what I needed to
show you.
So, we look at the placebo group, and
we see that the median is 64 with an
interquartile range of 56 to 72.
Okay.
So, for a box plot, the,
the interquartile range, this is really
going to be really informative, so,
you're going to want to pick the box plot
that looks like a boxy part.
So, this, this represents the
interquartile range here,
I just overshot that.
So, the box here represents the
interquartile range.
So, you're going to want to pick the box
where it looks like it ray,
ranges from 56 to 72, and that's going to
be answer B.
So, you might have thought that C could
also be the answer because it
satisfies that criteria of the
interquartile range.
But, there's another piece of information
here,
which is captured in this variable, aged
greater than or equal to 75 years Okay.
So, 18% of our cohort is older than 75.
It's unlikely that the maximum age is 75
years exactly and
that's what's shown in box plot c, which
further sort of lends, which,
which further provides evidence for the
fact that B is the correct answer.