Well, of course say, I don't think an
odds, so
I want to go one step further and
translate the odds into a probability.
Well, here are the odds,
the odds is just a probability divided by
1 minus the probability.
So, we can actually solve for p here.
So, to solve for p, for example, for this
first one.
I'm going to multiply both sides of my
equation by 1 minus p.
Then, I'm going to get the p is equal to
8.33 minus 8.33p.
I can add that negative,
that 8.33p, I'm going to add 8.33p to both
sides of the equation here.
Then, I'm going to get 9.33p is equal to
8.33.
Now, to isolate p, I'm going to divide
both sides of the equation by 9.33.
A general formula here, is you would do p
is equal to the odds
divided by 1 plus the odds.
And when you do that 8.33 divided by 9.33.
Notice that's always going to be a number
between zero and one.
So, that's going to give you a
probability.
That comes out to be 89%.
So, the predictive probability for
somebody who does zero hours per week of
homework, is that they have an 89% chance
of being book smart.
Less homework, more chance of being book
smart.
When you do this for
10 hours per week, you get 85% is the
predicted probability of being book smart.
For somebody else 50 hours per week,
they're only, you know,
54% chance of their predicted probability
of being book smart is only 54%.
Again, none of this is statistically
significant.
But just in terms of the effect sizes
here.
These would be the predicted
probabilities.
So, out of a logistic regression model,
you can predict, for
a particular person, their probability,
given their characteristics, of having a
particular outcome.
You can also say just how good of a job
does
the model do of predicting an outcome?
You measure this with something called the
area under the curve,
the area under the ROC curve.
And the area under the curve, for logistic
regression,
is analogous to the r squared that we got
out of linear regression.
It's a measure of model fit and how good
your predictive power is.
Remember that when we did linear
regression,
sometimes you could over fit your model
and get really good r
squareds that actually didn't mean that
you had great predictive power.
It just meant that you have an over fit
model.
Same thing principle applies here.
Sometimes a really good area under the
curve reflects over fitting rather than
good predictive ability.
So, just kind of keep that in mind.
I just want to briefly review the ROC
curve.
So, let me give you the big picture first.
So, this is an ROC curve.
This is the ROC curve for
the model we just fit, homework hours
predicting book smart, street smart.
This is actually a really bad ROC curve,
because homework is not very predictive of
the outcome here.
It's not significantly related.
On ROC curve, here's the diagonal line.
If you look at the diagonal line here,
the diagonoal line on the ROC curve means
no predictive ability.
So, if your model falls right near this
line,
that means that your model has no
predictive ability really.
And that's essentially what's happening
here.
Here's our ROC curve in blue.
It's not doing much better than the, the
line.
This line represents chance that you're,
you're just flipping a coin to
determine whether or not somebody has the
outcome or not.
So, we're not doing much better than
chance here.
An area under the curve of 50% means no
predictive ability.
The area, an area under the curve of 60%
is, which is what we have here,
you can see that here, is really not much
better than that.
What is the ROC curve though?
What we're looking for on the ROC curve,
you know you have really good
predictive ability when you get a curve
that looks like this.
Where that is an area under the curve is
going to be close to 100%.
The ROC curve is what it actually is,
is you're graphing sensitivity against 1
minus the specificity.
High values close to 100% is really good
predictive power,
assuming you're not over fitting.
Values closer to 50% are poor or no
predictive power.
So, that's the general picture of ROC
curve.
And this, my computer just, you know,
when I did the logistic regression, it
spits this curve out for me automatically.
So, I didn't have to do any work to get
it.
But just to give you a little detail about
where it comes from.
So, you can sort of understand that.
Let me show you how this ROC curve is
drawn using this particular example.
Again, my logistic regression model gives
me out a predictive probability for
every person.
In this case, the predictive probability
for a given person, only depends on
the number of hours of homework that they
reported doing every week.
So, if you did zero hours of homework,
you were predicted an 89% predicted
probability.
If you did 50 hours of homework, you have
a 54% of predicted probability, and so on.
What we can do is we can calculate the
predicted probability.
And again, the computer's doing this for
me.
That we can calculate the predicted
probability for
every person in the data set.
And some of these will be ties because
there's some people that have
the same homework time and that's the same
predictive probability.
So, I'm just showing here some of the
predicted probabilities from my data set.
I'm not showing all, I'm showing I've
lined up
the predicted probabilities from the
lowest in the data set, to the highest.
And I'm not showing the ones in between.
I'm just showing the lowest and the
highest.
Just to illustrate.
What you then do is,
again, there are C curve is based on
sensitivity and specificity.
But we have a continuous predictor here.
So, it's that you know,
I have a test and you either pass the test
or you fail the test.
To get sensitivity and specificity from a
continuous predictor,
we're going to have a range of
sensitivities and specificities.
The ROC is set up by doing the following.
You take the person with the lowest
predicted probability in your data set.
You make that lowest predicted
probability.
The cut-off for being classified, in this
case, as book smart.
So, you say everybody who has a predicted
probability of,
of 0.52 or higher, is going to be called
book smart.
Well, since everybody in your data set has
a predictive probability of .52 or
higher, everybody in your data set is
going to be classified as book smart.
So, we can actually make a little two by
two table here.
If our test is, if your predictive
probability is greater than 0.52,
greater than or equal to 0.52, you're
going to be classified as book smart.
That's a, that is a positive test.
Then, all 48, there's 48 people here.
All 48 are going to be classified as book
smart.
You're classified as street smart if
you're
below 0.52 on this particular cut off.
That means nobody will be classified as
street smart to start here.
And this there, we can actually then
compare that to their true value for
book smart or streets smart.
So, in my data set, out of 48, there were
40 book smarts people, and
8 streets smart people.
If we count them all as book smart
according to our test,
then we are going to have perfect
sensitivity and 0 specificity.
So, we've, we've captured everybody who is
book smart.
If you make the test predict the
probability 0.52 or
higher, we're going to capture everybody
who's book smart, but
we're going to capture nobody who's street
smart.
We're going to misclassify all of them, so
our specificity's going to be 0.
We represent that on the ROC curve right
here.
So, this is 100% sensitivity, and
0 percent specificity, because remember
we're graphing 1 minus 0.
1 minus the specificity.
So, 1 minus 0 gives us a 1.0 value here.
So, we end up here on the curve.
Then, we do this again.
Now, we move up our cutoff for classifying
people as book smart or
street smart to the next predicted
probability level, which is 0.54.
So now we say, everybody who is 0.54 or
higher on their predicted probability,
we're going to call you book smart.
And, in fact, when we do this,
that is going to capture most everybody
has 0.54 or higher, but not everybody.
So, that's our positive test.
Our negative test, now, there are a few
who are below 0.54.
They're going to be counted as having a
negative on this test.
So, we end up with classifying 46 people
as book smart according to our test.
But two were classifying as street smart
according to our test.
We can actually look at the true value,
who was actually book smart and
who was street smart.
We had 40 in our set who considered
themselves book smart.
And in fact, we ended up with 38 out of
the 40 who
are book smart were correctly classified
as book smart, and two were misclassified.
The two who had predicted probabilities
less than 0.54 were actually out of
the book smart group.
And we misclassified 8, the 8 street smart
people as book smart again.
So our specificity remains at 0.
Our sensitivity is now 38 out of 40 or
95%.
So, we're not, we're no longer have
perfect sensitivity.
That's going to move us down to the chart
here to sensitivity of 95% and
we're continuing to have a specificity of
zero.
And we go on and do this for all the
observe, all the predicted
probabilities in our data set, and that's
what defines this curve here.
And again, if we have no predictive
ability,
you're going to end up right along that
line as we do here.
So, that's the ROC curve that tells us how
good we're, how predictive our model is.
The other thing that's often more useful
or
more commonly used from the logistic
regression model is just to
say what's the relationship between the
predictor and the outcome.
And this case homework and book smart.
And as I mentioned earlier the, the beta
coefficient from logistic regression,
what happens is is if you exponentiate
that beta coeffecient from
logistic regression, when you exponentiate
that, that gives you an odds ratio.
So, we can take this beta for homework
here and we can exponentiate it.
And so we can raise that to point,
negative 0.0389.
When you do that, you come out with a
value of 0.96, so
that's the odds ratio here.
I'll show you in a minute why you can
interpret the beta like this.
But what this means is we have quantified
the relationship between homework time and
your odds of being book smart.
And you would read this odds ratio of 0.96
to say that there is
a 4% decrease in your odds of being book
smart for
everyone one hour more that you spend on
homework per week.
So, if I just exponentiate that beta, the
units here are, is,
are, one hour of homework per week.
Notice now, we've done an odds ratio for a
continuous predictor.
You can get that in a logistic regression.
So now, we're talking about the increase
odds for
a one unit increase in the continous
predictor.
Everything up to now,
when we've done odds ratios is we've
talking about a binary predictor.
You're either in this group or your not.
But now, we can get odds ratios for
continuous predictors.
Well, how does that translate?
How does that beta become an odds ratio?
Exactly how does that work?
So, let me show you that now.
How do we get from beta to odds ratios?
Well, what is an odds ratio?
If I want to know the odds ratio for being
book smart for the exposure here, which
is more homework time compared to less
homework time, what is the odds ratio?
An odds ratio is a ratio of two odds.
So, my odds ratio here would be the odds
of being book smart for
somebody who does more homework compared
with the odds of being book smart for
somebody who spends less time on homework.
And if we're just going with the units
that I've used here,
the difference between the numerator and
the denominator, I could make it a
one-hour difference in homework time.
So, what's my odds ratio for
a one-hour change, a one-hour increase in
homework time?
How does that affect my odds of being book
book smart.
Well, now I can just fill in.
I fit a model that tells me that predicted
odds of being book smart for
a given homework level.
So, I can just plug in that model.
So, what's the odds of being book smart
for somebody who does a 1 hour of
homework, compared with somebody who does
zero hours of homework?
The odds, which I can put in the
numerator.
So, I fit the model that says the log odds
is alpha plus
beta homework times the amount of
homework.
If I exponentiate that, remember, I get
the odds.
So, the odds of being book smart, for
somebody who does one hour of homework, I
can put that in the numerator.
I can compare that to the odds of being
book smart for
somebody who does no homework.
So now, I've made a ratio of two odds.
The odds for somebody who does one hour of
homework, divided by the odds for
somebody who does no homework.
And then, we can simplify this a little
bit,
what you'll notice right away is you have
to know a little bit about how
exponentials work to know how I leap from
here to here.
But if you have e to raised to alpha plus
beta,
that's the same as e raised to alpha times
e raised to beta.
Well, notice there, they both have the
same intercepts.
So, those intercepts are going to cancel.
That's the nice thing here.
Those cancel.
And if we simplify this, it just turns out
that we are left with with e beta times 1.
And the numerator divided by e raised to
the 0.
And the denominator, that's just e raised
to beta homework.
And that's the odds ratio.
You take the beta for homework, you
exponentiate it, you get the odds
ratio in the, in the actual value here for
the beta was negative 0.039.
Again, if I exponentiate that, I get an
odds ratio of 0.96.
So, the odds ratio 0.96 means that for
every one-hour increase in
homework per week, your odds of believing
yourself book smart decreases by 4%.
Of course, and it wasn't significant here.
I want to just extend this logic to show
how not only can we get
odds ratios out of logistic regression, we
can get multivariate adjusted odds ratios.
So, just as we made the leap from linear
regression,
simple linear regressions to
multi-variable linear regression.
We can do the same thing for logistic
regression.
It's very easy to add additional
predictors to the right side of
the equation.
We can have a bunch of predictors just
like this.
That's our multi-variable logistic
regression equation.
And here's some examples.
Imagine that we did a study where we're
looking at lung cancer.
And let's say for the first logistic
regression model we fit, we put in as
predictors a binary predictor for smoking
and a binary predictor for drinking.
So, we looked at smoking, yes or no.
And drinking, yes or no.
Those are two binary variables.
So, that's one model we could fit.
And that's a simpler model, so I'm
going to start there.
The beta for
smoking would then represent the effect of
smoking adjusted for drinking.
The beta for drinking represents the
effect of drinking adjusted for smoking.
We can make it slightly more complicated
by also adding an additional variable,
additional predictor in the model.
Let's add also age.
We could then get the effect of smoking
adjusted for
both drinking and age, the effect of
drinking adjusted for both smoking and
age, and the effect of age adjusted for
both smoking and drinking.
Let me show you now, exactly what I mean
by adjusted for,
when I keep using that term adjusted for,
what does that really mean?
That means that if I fix everything else
in the model,
it's the isolated effect of smoking, or
the isolated effect of drinking.
So, let me show you that mathematically
now.
I think that's helpful.
I'm going to start with the binary
predictor,
the model with the two binary predictors,
because it's simpler.
Again, what's an odds ratio?
It's the odds of a disease, say lung
cancer, for
an exposed group, compared with the odds
of disease for an unexposed group.
If I have just a binary predictor of say,
exposed and unexposed drinker, and
non-drinker and smoker, and non-smoker,
that's what an odds ratio is.
My logistic regression model, models the
odds of disease for given people.
So, I can put in the numerator, the odds
of disease for, say, a drinker, and
I can put in the denominator, the odds of
disease, lung cancer here, for
a non-drinker.
And that's what I've done here.
So, my model, my first model had alcohol
and smoking.
Two binary predictors in it.
So, if I want to know the odds ratio for
drinking, adjusted for
smoking, I can just say, let me compare in
the numerator the odds for
a drinker, and in the denominator, the
odds for a non drinker.
So there, I put a 1 for drinking in the
numerator and a 0 for
drinking in the denominator.
Now, I'm comparing the odds for
lung cancer for a drinker, compared with
the odds of cancer for a non-drinker.
Now, I've also got smoking in the model.
So, I have to put in something for
smoking.
But what if I hold it fixed?
So, what if I say I'm only comparing a
drinking smoker to a non-drinking smoker?
So, I put in a 1 for smoking for both the
numerator and the denominator.
I hold smoking fixed.
It actually wouldn't matter if I chose to
compare a drinking non-smoker to
a drinking non-smoker.
I just have to hold smoking fixed for both
the numerator and the denominator.
I have it the same.
If I make it the same, what you can show
is again, the intercepts cancel.
And now, as long as I hold smoking fixed
the the smoking beta's cancel.
What I am left with?
Well, if I simplify this, I just have e
raised to beta alcohol, e raised to the 0.
And the denominator is 1.
So, I can show that the odds ratio for
drinking, if I hold smoking fix is just,
all I do is take the beta for alcohol and
exponentiate it.
That gives me the odds ratio for lung
cancer for
a drinker compared to a non-drinker.
And again, where I've held smoking
constant.
Notice that this will be the odd ratio for
drinking.
If I compare two smokers or if I compare
two non-smokers.
So, I'm assuming that the effect of
drinking is the same in
smokers and non-smokers.
I can use the same logic to show you that
this works for
a continuous predictor as well.
So, here's a continuous predictor.
For a continuous predictor, I'm going to
comparing again the odds of disease for
somebody with the higher level of the
continuous predictor,
compared to somebody with the lower level.
For example, imagine that I've got my
second model here that's got alcohol,
smoking and age in the model.
Age is a continuous predictor.
If I want to compare in the numerator, an
older person, the odds of lung cancer for
an older person, compared with the odds of
smoking for
a younger person in the denominator.
This will give me the odds ratio for
an increase in age, how much does age
effect my odds of lung cancer.
I'm again going to hold all the other
variables in the model here, alcohol and
smoking, I'm going to hold those fixes.
So say, I have two drinking smokers, and
I'm comparing a drinking smoker who's
29 years old to drinking smoker who's only
19 years old.
That's a ten unit jump in age, and
you'll see it wouldn't really matter if I
had put in 40 and 30, or 50 and 40.
Any ten unit jump in the age is going to
give me the same answer here.
You'll notice that lots of things cancel
out.
That's the great thing here.
So, we fix all the other variables, they
all cancel out.
So, we're left with that the beta for age.
In this case, if we and if you solve it
here.
Beta, e raised to beta times 29, minus e
raised to 19.
That's the same as e raised to beta age
times 10.
So, what this tells us is that if I
multiply the beta for age times 10, and
then exponentiate, I will get the odds
ratio for a 10 unit jump in age.
So, this would give me, for a 10 unit jump
in age, a decade increase in age,
what's the increase in my odds of getting
lung cancer?
If I wanted to do it for a one unit
increase in age,
I would just take the beta for age and
exponentiate it directly.
That would give the odds ratio for a one
unit increase in age.
It doesn't really matter what you pick for
the units of age, but
you want to pick something that's sort of
meaningful.
[INAUDIBLE].
A one unit or a ten unit increase is
probably reasonable.
That gives you the odds ratio for that
unit jump.
You can see that for
a continuous predictor, the magnitude of
the odds ratio will depend on the units.
It's not on what units you choose will not
affect the p value, but
it will affect how big or small that odds
ratio looks.
Just keep that in mind, you always have to
give the units in your table so
people know how to interpret that.
This is the odds ratio for age, adjusted
for smoking and alcohol.
Which means that we've held smoking and
alcohol fixed.
So, that is, if we're looking at 2 people
who have the same level of smoking and
alcohol, and the only difference between
them is a 10 unit difference in age,
this would the effect of that age.
So, just to summarize, the practical
interpretation here is if you
take the beta, the slope, from a logistic
regression for any of your exposures,
your predictors, and you exponentiate it,
you get the odds ratio for that exposure.
And you would interpret that as that's in
the increase in the odds of
your outcome for every one unit increase
in the exposure adjusted for
controlling for other variable, all the
other variables.
All the other predictors that are in the
model.
And we'll practice looking at an example
of how to use this in, in the next module.
Just to tell you, most computer packages
when you run a logistic regression.
You don't actually won't even have to do
the exponentiation.
Most computer packages automatically give
you the odds ratio.
So again, out of a logistic regression,
we get these multivariate adjusted odds
ratios.