Welcome back.
Now that we have cleaned and
repaired our data we are ready to look at
the data to find any basic patterns.
Let's take a look at a histogram for the
variable age.
I always like to start with goptions reset
equals all.
Just to make sure that the settings used
for
the previous graphs won't get carried
over.
For our histogram, we're going to use proc
sgplot.
This coach should be pretty familiar from
the section on graphing.
As you can see we have a histogram for the
variable age, with the title age in years.
Now looks like it's roughly normally
distributed.
>> It would be pretty cumbersome if we had
to repeat this code over and
over again for all the variables we
want to analyze.
So let's create a macro so we can make our
lives a little easier.
We'll start with the same code, just to
make sure there aren't any errors.
We can then add percent macro at the top,
and percent mend at the bottom.
Let's name this macro histogram, and put
the parentheses after the title, so
that we create a function.
Since we're interested in multiple
histograms for
all continuous variables in our dataset,
we actually need a macro that allows us to
change the title and change the variable
of interest.
In our code, let's find the title
statement.
Instead of age, let's replace this with
ampersand title period.
Remember how in our discussions on macros,
ampersand and
period allow us to create a placeholder.
We need to do the same thing for age
variable.
Let's replace age with ampersand variable
period.
For both of these placeholders,
we need to put them in the function after
the title of our macro.
So after histogram,
we put title, variable, now we're ready to
run our macro.
>> With the macro run and stored in Sass,
we're now ready to invoke the macro.
Here we invoke the macro three times.
Remember, you always start it with % and
then the name of the macro, which in this
case is histogram and in the parentheses,
you include the values for the placeholder
variables.
So you start out with a title and then the
variable of interest.
Don't forget, the title has to be included
in apostrophes.
So first we invoke the macro for
the weight variable, then for height, then
for BMI.
As you can see we now have a histogram for
weight, for height, and for
BMI, just like we wanted.
Now, let's take a look at some simple
scatter plots.
Like before I'll start with G options
reset equals all.
By now you should be pretty familiar with
using proc gplot to make a scatterplot.
We'll set the title of age versus weight.
We'll make our labels so that we can
include our units in the access labels.
Using a plot statement we specify the
variables that we want to have in
the scatter plot.
We want to have age by weight so we have
age asterisk weight underscore kg's.
Using a simple one statement,
we can specify how we want our symbols to
appear in the scatter plot.
This will give us red triangles with a
certain height as well
an interpolation line.
As you can see, we had a scatterplot of
age by weight where
the symbols are red triangles and there's
an interpolation line.
It gives us the labels we want, as well as
the title.
>> [SOUND] Let's create a similar plot for
age versus BMI.
As you can see the first part of our code
is the same,
our title now is age versus BMI, and we
use our labels to
specify BMI in kilograms over meters
squared and age in years.
For axis one we specify an order zero to
50 by five.
This will be our BMI range.
We specify plot as BMI*age, and we label
our vertical axis as Axis one.
Let's take a look at the output.
Here you see our BMI distribution based on
age.
>> Let's make a slight modification to
this graph, so
we can see the subsets based on genders.
[SOUND] We'll change our title, and
in the plot statement we'll add BMI*age
equals is female.
Now we'll get different symbols for males
and females.
When we add in the symbol two statement
with different settings,
we can have a different symbol for males
and females in our graph.
It looks like males have a higher BMI than
females, across all ages.
>> Just remember, this data is made up and
there be values that are unrealistic.
>> Looking to the something,
except show different sub sets for
diabetics and non-diabetics.
It looks like in our data set,
diabetics tend to have a higher BMI than
non-diabetics.
>> Now that we've explored our data, we're
ready to run our analysis.