This question wants us to find the
probability that we would get a score of
three or less if we would roll a die.
now, this is a die which is fair, so each
and every outcome is equally probable.
For us to roll a three or less we would
have to roll a 1, a 2 or a 3.
And we know that the probability of
getting any number on a die is 1/6 for
a fair die.
So to get a score of 3 or less we would
just add up the probabilities and
get the total probability to be 3/6, or
1/2.
So C is the right answer.
The answer to this question is true.
This is a discrete probability
distribution because there are only four
values that X can take.
The probability that a patient has at
least two major adverse events is
the probability that the patient has two
adverse events or three adverse events,
and if we add both of these probabilities
up, we get a total probability of 0.07.
This is the right answer.
To find the expected value of x,
we would need to find the value of the
summation of x times px.
So for x of 0 we have a 0 here.
For x is 1, we get.
0.13 for this, we get 0.1, and for 3 we
get 0.06.
And if we add all of these up,
we get the expected value of x to be 0.29.
The answer for this question is D, for
minus $10.
The expected rally for this lottery is
minus 10.
Which is the amount you paid to play the
lottery.
And, the amount you'd
get if you win.
Times the probability of you winning.
Plus the amount that you'd get.
If you lose making zero dollars and the
probabiliyt of you winning, of you losing.
And if we add all of this up we get the
expected value to be negative $9.
We already calculated the mean for x as
point 29 in the previous section.
The formula for standard deviation in this
case is, and
I will just write out a couple of terms to
illustrate what time,
what this expression will turn out to be.
For x of 0 we have, for x is 1 we have,
and we'll have two more terms for
x is 2 and 3.
If we calculate our default expression,
we find that the value of
standard deviation is .65, which is D.
This question asks us to find the
probability of getting exactly 1
head in 5 coin flips.
This is a straight forward application of
the binomial equation.
Here we have N is 5, we have X is 1 and we
know that B is .5.
Putting that in into the binomial equation
we
get .5 times 1, and 2.5 times 4.
And if you multiply this out, we'll find
that the probability is 15.625 percent.
This question is again an application of
the binomial equation.
We have n is 10.
We have 9 coin, 9 heads, so our x value is
9 again, and
the probability of getting a head, or a
tail, is 0.5.
Putting that into this equation here, we
get the following expression for
the probability, [SOUND] which is the same
expression as we have in d,
which is the right answer.
This question gives us a case where we
have 150 participants,
each of whom has a 50% chance of being
allocated to the treatment or
to the control bucket and we want to find
the probability distribution of x.
Now it's very easy to see that the answer
to this is 'd'.
This is the binomial distribution with 'n'
equals 50 and
'p' equals .5 We could approximate it as a
normal distribution.
With n equals 150 as well but the exact
answer for
this question would be the binomial.
This question is similar to the question
we had previously.
The only difference is that now we have a
p value of 0.66 as oppose to a p
value of 0.5.
This is also a binomial distribution, and
the answer is e.
We'll be using 2 equations that we derived
for the binomial distribution here.
The first equation is the formula for
the expected value of a binomial, which is
n times p.
We know that n here is 150, and p is one
half, so
the expected value comes out to be 75.
We also know that the expression for the
standard deviation is
n times p P times 1 minus P and the square
root of that.
And if we substitute the value back in, we
see that the standard deviation is 6.
So let me just draw this out.
If we approximate this binomial as a
normal,
this is the mean.
Here we have a 75, and we know that 1
strand of deviation is 6 of it.
So if we have numbers between 69 and 81,
we would say that they are within one
standard deviation of the, the mean.
As the number that we are expected to find
is 69 we know that this is exactly one
standard deviation away from the mean and
hence, we 'b' being the right answer.
This question again needs us to apply the
formulae that we
talked about earlier to find the expected
value of a binomial distribution and
the variance of a binomial distribution.
The expected value is N times P which
comes out to 25,
the variance is N times P times 1 minus P
which comes out to 23.75,
the standard deviation is the square root
of the variance And the value we get for
the standard deviation is 4.87.
This question is a Speak Forward
application of the formula for z.
As z's quote is given by x minus mu by the
standard deviation.
In this case our x value is 0.95, our mu
is 1 and the standard deviation is 0.1.
Locking the values in, begin the z score
to be minus 0.5.
The answer to this is fairly
straightforward, the,
the only statement, out of the 4 given
options, which is not 2, for
anomalous distribution, is the fact that
it is a discrete probability distribution.
Anomalous distribution, if you remember,
is a continuous distribution.
This formula needs us to find out the z
squared for
the value of X, would be 0, then the mean
is 0.
Plugging this in, we know that the formula
for
Z is X minus mean by standard deviation.
If both X and mean are 0, we get a Z score
of 0.
This formula requires us to remember this
fact about the normal distribution.
Between one standard deviation below the
mean and
one standard deviation above the mean.
The fraction of the normal distribution
area that is enclosed is 68%,
which means that the area that is enclosed
Under two extreme edges is 32%.
Which means each of the two tails has an
area of 16%.
Now, let's use that to solve this
equation.
Do you know that the z
value of one corresponds to one standard
deviation above the mean?
We want to find the area to the left to z
of 1.
We could just find the area to the right
of z of 1 and then subtract 1 from that.
And as we found out previously,
this area is 16% which tells us that this
area is 84%.
This question.
Answers to identify the type of
probability distribution demonstrated by
the x vaiable here.
And it's very clearly obvious that this
variable doesn't follow the normal
binomaial or the uniform distribution.
This is an imperical distribution that was
observed in an experiment and
it doesn't follow any of the standard
Distribution that we have studied so far.
We are given that we have a binomial
distribution with N of 100 and B of 0.2.
Using the formula the expected value of X.
Which is np.
You get the expected value to be 20.
The formula for standard deviation of x is
n times p times 1 minus p.
Plugging values in, we see that the
standard deviation is 4.
This question asks us to
approximate the binomial distribtion from
the previous question.
Question as in normal distribution.
We know that the expected value for this
distrubution is 20 and
that the standard deviation is 4.
These are the [INAUDIBLE] in the previous
question The probability of getting 20
successes or fewer.
If I just draw it out for a normal
distribution.
It's just all the probability to the left
of the mean, and because we know
that a normal distribution is symmetric,
we know that this probability is 50%.
The correct answer here is C, that the
mean and median are far apart.
In a normal distribution, we have the mean
to be same as the median.
This is because in a normal distribution,
we have equal number of points to the left
as to the right of the median.
And hence, the mean is the same as the
median.
If we have a distribution in which the
mean and the median are far.
Far apart, that is clearly not a normal
distribution.
[BLANK_AUDIO]