Now let's talk about contingency tables.
For this example, we'll be building our
own data set related to marital status.
It will be three variables.
One for gender, where females get a one
and males get a zero.
There will be another variable for race,
with one for white and zero for black.
The third variable is for marital status.
Those who are single get a zero, people
who are married get a one,
and those who are divorced get a two.
Now we have our new data set.
Let's start with a simple contingency
table.
There will be one row variable and one
column variable.
Let's take a look at some code.
Notice how I've included
gender*MaritalStat.
This is the way of specifying which two
variables you want to analyze.
By putting gender first, we are
establishing this as the row variable.
Marital stat will then automatically
become the column variable.
Let's run the code and take a look at the
output.
Here you see we've created our two by two
table for gender and marital status.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
As you can see from the table, you have
Frequency, Percent, Row Percent, and
Column Percent.
Let's take a look at the first cell in our
table.
These are the people in the gender equal
to zero and marital stat equal to zero.
In other words, this cell depicts makes
who are single.
The first number 13, is the number of
single men in our data set.
The second number, 34.21 is the percent of
single males in our total group.
The row percent is the third number.
So 72.22% means that out of the males,
around 72% were single.
Finally, 56.52 is the column percent.
This means that nearly 57% of all single
people in our data set were males.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
>> Staring at all of these numbers can be
pretty confusing.
It's easy to make a mistake and choose the
wrong number when you do your analysis.
Luckily, SAS lets you suppress certain
output values.
Here's the code for how you can do that.
By including nocol, nopercent, and norow,
we'll be left with just our frequencies.
Let's run this code.
As you can see, we have a much cleaner
table now with just the frequencies.
So now we know there are 13 single men,
five married men, and zero divorced men.
This couple use the dataset that we looked
at earlier,
with people who are treated and people who
are cured.
This code will set up a two by two
contingency table, and
only give us the frequencies that we want.
[SOUND]
This quadrant shows the number of subjects
who were treated and cured.
This one shows that unknown subjects were
treated and not cured.
This is the number of subjects who were
not treated, but were cured.
And these are the subjects who were not
treated and not cured.
In your HRP 225 course, you learn how to
calculate risk ratios and Oz ratios.
Now that we have a two by two table setup,
you can calculate a risk ratio to
estimate the association between getting
treatment and being cured.
In the next module we'll show you how you
can use Proc Freq to
have SAS solve this for you.