[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this next case study, we're going to
talk about a situation where
making sure you've got the right patient
is really, really going to be critical.
As you can imagine, you know, bleeding is
a factor of you know,
patients who are coming to get care.
In this situation,
it was an emergency case where a patient
was profusely bleeding.
Emergency blood was needed, and the
medical team was urgently requesting for
additional blood blood product to be
available so
they could be able to transfuse it into
the patient.
When the multiple units of blood arrived,
one of the doctors started screaming at
the staff about getting the blood hung
immediately.
At the time when this event was occuring,
there was actually a change in
the nursing staff, and one of the coming
on duty nurse was given a unit of
blood by another staff person who was
basically pulling out of the cooler.
That was at the or near the,
the area where the resuscitation effort
was going on.
The nurse grabbed the blood and proceeded
to hang the blood.
You know, that was part of a series of
bags that they were
transfusing into the patient.
Unfortunately at the with all the effort
of the medical team,
the response team everyone that
contributed to try to save the patient,
the patient had expired during the
resuscitation attempt.
In the process of cleaning up the room
afterwards, several more units of
blood showed up at the patient, or at the
outside of the room and
the staff looked at it and looked at the
patient name and realized that the patient
name on the units of blood was different
from the patient that had just expired.
At this point when they look back at the
paperwork and, you know, looked at
the patient they recognized that they
probably, towards the end of the case,
where they're transfusing the last couple
units of blood,
inadvertently had grabbed blood that was
intended for another patient.
And actually trans, try, or had transfused
that in the patient.
The review of the case from pathology
indicated that you know, the patient
did not expire from the transfusion, there
was no evidence of molysis, but
that the patient had expired from the
significant blood loss.
And other medical problems that actually
contributed the patient's demise and
that the transfusion actually was not a
factor.
But nevertheless, this really shouldn't
have been done.
You know, they, there are usually clear
cut processes of double checking and
verifying they have the right blood, the
right blood product, you know,
identify the right patient prior to
actually hanging the blood.
So what were some of the factors
identified in this particular event?
And that was certainly the failure to use
two unique patient identification process
by two different individuals to uniquely
confirm and validate that they're working
with the right patient, the right blood
product and with the right orders.
Similar to the earlier situation where we
talked about, you know, situations about,
you know, high risk medications having a
two person double check process.
Both the joint commissions and the
American Association of Blood Banks, AABB.
The College of American Pathologists, CAP,
you know, they all have
very specific procedural double-checks
when administering blood to patients.
And in this situation the staff assumed
that the person handing the blood had
done the double check and the person who
handed off
the blood thought that that person was
going to do the double check.
And in this situation actually nobody
checked and
as a result the wrong blood was hung on
the wrong patient.
As others cases that we talked about, you
know,
production pressure, certainly a huge
factor.
When that contributed to this event
occurring where, you know,
folks were trying to get blood into this
patient to save the patient's life.
And this urgency emergency situation
creates process variation.
And certainly, you know, as part of the
process variation,
the team communication or the lack of
communication in this situation led,
well is a factor in leading to this
particular outcome.
We've talked earlier about distraction
part of the distraction that was
occurring in this situation was the one of
the physician was yelling or
screaming at the nurse to, you know, get
the blood hung.
The nurse should've given the instruction
to, you know, the doctor and
says hang on a second, let me do a
double-check to make sure we
got the right product here before we
actually hang it in the patient.
And so as a result, you know, the
distraction of being yelled and
screamed at by the physician actually
aggravated the situation.
And the staff just in the process of
trying to respond to
the physician request, varied from their
normal workflow process.
Now what's interesting, the culture of
their particular team, for
the most part, you'd have to say 99% of
the time it's very, very, very good.
Folks are constantly communicating.
You know, making eye contact.
Reconfirming, and verifying information.
99% of the time, you know, you'd have to
say that, you know,
they're a top notch, well oiled machine.
Everybody on the same page and
functioning.
But in this situation,
a patient who was at one moment sort of a
questionable stability.
Went from, you know,
being kind of there in monitoring
situation into a crisis situation.
Basically taking out, all the cards off
the table and then thrown up
in the air and then, you know, you're
throwing in this crisis situation.
So it's interesting in that when do talk
about culture, we also sometimes think
about, well, the ongoing culture of a
team, you know, is certainly one part.
But, but does the culture of the team
change when there's a crisis or
an, emergent, urgent situation.
And that's where programs like simulation,
you know, when you're thrown into crisis
situation and, you know, gone through a
simulation to see how you would react and
then lessons you can learn, is actually
very,
very beneficial in trying to prevent, you
know, these things from happening.
You remember I said earlier nobody woke up
that morning of the day of
this event occurred thinking I am
intentionally going to go out and
hurt patients or kill patients.
Nobody on the team thought that, but
certainly because of
the factors that we've identified here
through the review of this event.
You know, we've got a lot of things that
we can work on to improve on, and
one of the key things of course is just
being aware of the situation and following
standard work or standard process of doing
things like a double check.
Being able to communicate verbally.
Being able to provide feedback.
Not being distracted.
Are all key things that we would like to
see implemented on an ongoing basis.
So, we have some lessons learned.
You know, the Joint Commission does
require two individuals perform a two
patient identification check prior to
administering blood.
The thought is that these individuals are
generally
individual are determined qualified,
licensed personnel that are trained to be
involved with the blood transfusion
process, and that they have a process to
be able to perform the double check before
they administer the blood.
Certainly lessons learned about the
frightening nature of the case,
disrupt of the communication between the
team members.
Remember we said earlier that, you know,
someone was yelling at the nurse.
The nurse just showed up to help out.
And most folks when they're in that crisis
situation will just jump in to
do whatever they need to do.
However, there was a bit of
miscommunication where the folks didn't
bother to do double checks to make sure
they got the right product in hand.
And in fact, transfused the wrong product
into the patient.
As we said earlier, you know, it did not,
you know,
it's identify that this action didn't kill
the patient, didn't harm the patient.
But what happened if the patient had
survived the event?
They might have been able to survive the
resuscitative effort, but they wouldn't
survive the sequel of actually getting the
wrong blood type administered to them.
Another factor that was identified, and
this is something we kind of mentioned
before in other cases,
when the environment is not conducive to
the normal standard operating process.
The space in this particular area is very
limited.
Especially when the patient started to
crash.
And so, when the patient started to crash,
more staff showed up to assist in the
resuscitative effort.
And in that process, actually, it screened
out or blocked out the ability for
some of the staff to do the double check
of the patient's wristband to
make sure they got the right patient.
So this was something that the team
certainly learned about you know,
having space available, or clearing space
to make more room available.
Especially when you have additional staff,
and
additional equipment showing up at the
patient's bedside.
And that there may be a need to develop a
secondary way of
actually identifying the patient.
In many organizations, you know,
they put a wristband around one of the
patient's arm.
They also put it around the patient's
ankle.
Just so they have a secondary double check
in the event that these kinds of
situations occur.
So those are all certain som, some lessons
learned from this particular event.
And you know, the department makes a point
of sharing this kind of
information with the staff as part of
their onboarding or
their orientation to let them know that,
you know,
when we have urgent emergent situation it
throws a kink into things, and
it can shift the dynamics in such a way
with that it can adversely harm patients.
So, you know, it's something you really do
need to be aware of.
Some of the prevention strategies, that
was learned from this particular event.
The culture of safety that we spoke about
earlier.
Folks need to be in a position to be able
to push back when necessary.
The, the fact is if the nurse, you know,
had double checked when they pulled the
blood out of the cooler.
If the nurse prior to hanging it had du,
done the double-check.
If the nurse or they would've tell the
doctor who was screaming at them in
their face, you know, hurry up put the
blood in.
And say, hold on a second, I got it, give
me a chance to do it right.
This would alleviate, the hours of
investigator work in meetings, and
interviews that occurred after this event
occurred.
You know, this is all under the concept of
lean methodology where as a result of
this event, there's a ton of what I would
describe as learnings from this event.
But at the same time, all the wasted
energy that went into the meetings,
the reviews, the chart reviews, the risk
management involvement,
the lawyers involved, you know, the
department chair, the resident.
You know, everyone who is involved in
reviewing the event and
in reality it's non productive, other than
coming up with solutions to be able to
fix these things to keep it from happening
again.
So, the ability to push back is easier
said than done.
I know many of you folks are thinking, its
like, oh my gosh, you know,
it's like of course it would be clear that
I would tell that person,
hang on a second, let me carry this task
out.
But, or, how would you react is, if you're
in that crisis situation, and
you're giving the instruction and the
staff said, hang on a second, you know,
let me double check to make sure it's
right.
Would you react in a way that's actually
conducive to a culture of safety?
Second bullet.
Communication of hand, handoff practices
especially in emergent situations.
Many organizations adopt things like S
BAR.
It's an acronym that stands for situation
background assessment and recommendation.
You know, this communication handoff, you
know,
is kind of like similar to the flight
controllers in, in,
the flight, you know, the control towers
at airports, where there's a specific
communication methodology between the
pilots and, and flight control.
And because of their specific
communication,
the intent of it is to make sure the
communication is crystal clear.
Both from the sender standpoint to the
receiver standpoint.
You know, do you have that same setup when
you're working with your team,
especially in crisis urgent emergent
situation in terms of how you're going to
communicate things so that people are on
the same page,
of the same mindset, of that same, single
mindset.
And so that everyone knows that they're
doing the right thing, for
that, you know, for that patient at that
particular situation.
Another thought was, was re, regarding
repeat back instruction for confirmation.
We kind of mentioned this earlier, with
the flight control tower.
To the pilots in an airplane.
You know, some of you are pilots and, and
know that the instruction back or
confirmation back, you know, you, you can
use that piece of information to verify or
validate to make sure that were on the
same page.
There's a reliance on that process that
everyone's on the same page and
that the reason why we do this is that we
don't want to have planes, you know,
landing where they're not supposed to land
or
hitting things that they're not supposed
to hit.
And the same can be said in the clinical
care setting, you know, whether it's the,
in emergency department like this
situation, or is on the floor.
It's not uncommon, you know, in, in less
urgent situation, such as making rounds
to the, through you know, seeing all your
patients or seeing patient at clinic,
is that instructions are constantly being
given both to staff and patient and
other providers.
But are you sure they receive the
information in
the way that you intended so that they can
carry it out?
You know, this is
oftentimes a challenge when we're dealing
with patients, you know?
We give them tons of information in terms
of what to do about their condition, or
the disease process.
And, then we're expecting them to be able
to read what we gave them.
Well, how do we actually know they
understand what's going on?
And you really are hoping they follow the
instructions, or
they understand what's going on.
But it isn't until follow 'em, follow them
up on a followup visit or,
you know, if you get called that they
ended up in the emergency department or
the urgent care center, you know, that you
find out that they didn't understand what
the instructions were that you had given
'em.
The last bullet, and this has a lot to do
with the fact that, you know,
the team being aware of what's going on,
you know.
And what we would describe as situational
awareness.
Many time when the adrenaline gets going,
and that the intensity level
increase you know, folks, you know, react
very differently in those situations.
And as a result, situational awareness is
that,
it's almost like just a concept of knowing
where everything is and
what everything, you know, what is going
on with that situation.
For some people the clock speeds up faster
where they can't keep up with it.
And other folks, it actually, the clock
seems to slow down, you know,
when these things happen.
I've found that when those of us who can
actually react, and
this comes through experience.
And sometimes it's our personality, and
sometimes it's, you know, its the way we
were trained.
But certainly, when the clock slows down
and you can analyze all the data that's
coming in and all the steps that are
happening, all the action that's going on.
You'll be in a better position to be able
to provide instruction or
to be able to carry out a task.
The same, the same thing can be said that
you know,
[LAUGH] there's across the country there's
a lot of legislation looking at
the ability of people as they're driving
to be able to be on the cell phone and
texting, and or texting at the same time.
Heck, I've been in enough places across
the country,
I think people just have a problem with
driving alone.
But then when you add cell phone
conversation, texting you know,
drink, drinking coffee or
soda while they're driving, while shaving
or putting on their makeup.
You know, it's not uncommon this
multitasking creates distraction which
takes away from situational awareness.
One of the advantages of simulation
training that, you know,
I would highly encourage people to go
through simulation training.
Especially if they provide video feedback
or
instructional feedback after the scenario,
you know, the simulation is ran through.
Becomes a real behavior modification or a
kind of a adjustment in
terms of how you react, how you respond,
or how you even present or dis, or, or
say things to people in these different
situations.
So situational awareness is really, really
key.
And it's not something you can just read a
book about and get it.
It's almost like you have to go through
these scenarios to be able to
experience it, to be able to see how you
would react in those particular situation.
And ultimately, you know, the goal which
we've talked about all along in
this program is trying to do the right
thing for your patients.