In this next module,
I'm going to talk about the statistics
that are used to describe where's
the center of your data?
So the main measures that we use for
central tendency,
that is where's the center of your data,
are the mean and the median.
Probably most of you are very familiar
with the mean.
So, a mean is just an average and
you've probably all calculated the
averages throughout your life.
So, this is not something that's very
hard, but I'm going to,
want you to think a little bit about the
mean in a different way.
I want you to also think about the mean as
a balancing point.
I'm going to show you that in a minute.
I also want to show you the mathematical
shorthand,
the mathematical symbols that we use to
represent the calculation of a mean.
I'll be using some of these symbols in
this class, so
it's helpful for you to be comfortable
with these.
So how do we calculate a mean?
It's very easy.
We add up all of the values and we divide
by the sample size.
Again, probably many of you have
calculated many of these in your life.
But how's that look in math shorthand?
So in math shorthand,
the way that I'm going to represent a mean
is I'm going to write X bar.
And that's important to remember because
I'll be using the X bar a lot,
just to save myself the time of having to
write out the word mean.
So there's a little bit of math shorthand
that I will be using in this class.
So x bar represents the sample mean.
When I take some data and I calculate an
average or
a mean, that I will represent as an X bar.
The way we calculate X bar, the mean is to
add up all of the observations and
divide by n, and that's represented by
these symbols here.
So here's my summation sign.
So what this summation sign is saying is
add up all of
the observations from 1 to n, because
again, I have n observations in my sample.
I'm representing each observation as Xi,
so that X1 would be the first observation,
X2 is the second, etcetera.
And this just says add up all of those
observations.
And then we divide by n, the total number
of observations, and
this is a longer, over here, is a longer
way to write that.
If these symbols are a little unfamiliar
to you,
like if you haven't seen a summation sign
before, you should take the math
tutorial that's offered before you take
the rest of this course.
because I will be throwing up some
summation signs every now and then.
So let me just give a quick example of how
to calculate a mean,
this should be easy for all of you.
So for example, let's say I had some
hypothetical data here,
I have some data on eight participants in
a study and I have their data, their ages.
So it ranged from 17 to 38.
If I wanted to figure out their average
age,
I would just add up those eight values and
divide by 8.
When I do that, I come out with a value of
23.25.
So again, I think that should be pretty
easy and familiar to most of you.
Now I'm going to show you some of the
example data on my Stanford students.
So for example, I asked them to report how
many hours a week they spent on homework.
And you can see the distribution of
homework the homework variable here in
a histogram.
Well, it turns out that the mean for
homework in my student sample was 11.4
hours per week.
So on average, students were doing about
11 hours of homework.
Now, as I mentioned, you can think of the
mean as a balancing point.
So imagine, this kind of harkens back to
high school physics a bit.
Imagine that that this graphic that you're
seeing here,
this histogram, is actually a lever.
And each of these little red bars
represents a mass.
So the, the smallest red bar is a small
bass, the mass,
the biggest red bar is a big mass.
So we just picture this as being sort of a
lever wth masses on it.
And here is the balancing part, here is
the fulcrum.
And the goal here is to balance this like
a see saw.
To balance it so it's perfectly balanced.
The mean is the point at which, you, if
you put the,
where you put the fulcrum that you will
balance these masses.
And if you remember back to Basic Physics,
if you've ever done anything with levers
and fulcrums.
You'll remember there was a principle that
said the further away a mass is from
the fulcrum, the more force it exerts,
right?
So there was a formula that said that
force was equal to mass times distance, so
the mass matters, but also how far away
from the center you are matters.
And so, there, the same principles applies
with means.
The farther something is away from the
mean,
the more influence, the more pull it has
on the mean.
So let me illustrate that now.
So take for example the variable alcoholic
drinks.
So, here's the histogram for alcoholic
I asked students to report how many drinks
they had in drinks per week.
And, I'm showing you the histogram here.
For my student sample, the mean was 2.3
drinks per week.
Pretty low.
And again, you can think of that as the
balancing point.
So, I'm going to have to put the fulcrum
at 2.3 in order to
balance this lever that has masses stacked
on it.
And, if you were to take the very highest
value and
change that and make it higher, that will
have a big effect on the balancing point.
So again, the further you are from the
balancing the more force you're having.
So for example, what if I were to take the
person who drank the most,
which was only eight drinks per week.
And I were, was to make that a much higher
value, like pretend that,
that person were actually was an
alcoholic.
So imagine that, that, the highest value
was no longer eight drinks per week, but
it was all the way up like at 40 drinks
per week.
So I had an alcoholic in, in the data set.
If I were to pull that one value which has
very little mass.
Remember, it's only 1 out of 50 people.
So it's a very small mass.
If I were to pull that one value, really
far from the mean.
In order to balance this lever now, so
again,
imagine that this is just like a long
board her.
You've got masses on it.
In order to balance this, this is having a
lot of force now because it's so far.
So to balance this, I'm actually going to
have to pull the fulcrum quite a bit
to the right in order to balance this
lever now.
So that one little mass, is a very tiny
amount of mass because it's so
far from the mean.
It has a huge influence on the mean.
So the mean, if I plot my new data in
histogram where the highest value is 40
rather than 8, that pulls the mean all the
way from 2.3 drinks per week up to 2.9,
almost 3 drinks per week.
So, one person going up to 40 has a huge
influence on the mean.
This is only one person out of 50, but
it's having a big influence on the mean.
Now, I want to take a moment here and tell
you a little bit about,
I mentioned binary variables in an earlier
module this week.
Binary variables have only two categories
to them.
It might seem odd to, to, for me to tell
you that a binary variable can
have a mean, but in fact, a binary
variable can have a mean.
If you code that binary variable as a 0/1
variable.
And it turns out to be useful for a lot of
situations in statistics to think about
binary variables as a series of 0s and 1s
and to kind of think of them numerically.
So that you can treat them numerically,
you can calculate things like averages.
So for example, if you take, in my example
data set,
I asked the students whether or not they
played varsity sports in high school,
that's a binary variable, a yes/no
variable.
If I code that in my data set rather than
coding it as no and yes, if I code that
as 0 for no and 1 for yes, and I actually
think about those 0s and 1s as numbers.
I can in fact calculate an average for
this binary variable.
So again, here is the histogram for,
played varsity sports in high school.
30 or 60% of my sample had played varsity
sports, 40% had not.
What if you thought of that as a series of
0s and
1s, how would you calculate the average?
So let's do that.
How would I calculate the average here?
Well, I've got 20 people who have a value
of 0, 30 people who have a value of 1.
So I'm just literally going to add up
those 30 1s and
those 20 0s, which just gives me a value
of 30, and
I'm going to divide by the total number,
which in this case is 50.
So 30 divided by 50 gives me a value of
0.6.
So notice that the average here is just
the percentage of people who answered yes,
the percentage of those who played varsity
sports in high school.
But you can calculate an average, it comes
out to be 60%, 0.6 in this case.
The other way that we tend to
measure central tendency other than the
mean is something called the median.
The median is the exact middle value.
So that means if you were to rank
everybody from the lowest value to
the highest value on whatever variable
you're considering, it would be the,
the value that fell right smack in the
middle.
Now, if there are an odd number of
observations, like if
there was 101 observations, then there
will be one value right in the middle.
But actually, if you have an even number
of observations then
there's going to be two values that are
smack in the middle.
So what we do in that case is we take
those two values and we just average them.
We add them up and divide by 2.
So let me give you an example of how we
calculate the median.
So, from this hypothetical data set on
ages of participants to,
in order to calculate the median,
I have to line up the ages from the lowest
17 to the highest 38 which I've done here.
And then, I have an even number of
observations, so
I'm going to have two middle values.
So I'm going to take those two middle
values, 22 and 23, and
I'm going to average them.
Just add them up and divide by 2.
So my median occurs at 22.5.
That means, half of my observations are
below 22.5 and half are above 22.5.
So if 22.5 is here, four observations are
below, four are above.
Half are below, half are above.
That's the median.
So, for example, what if I asked what's
the median of homework?
So it turns out that the median of
homework in my data set was
10 hours per week.
So that means that half of my students
were doing less than 10 hours per week,
and half of my students were doing more
than 10 hours per week.
If you think of this again as masses,
those bars as masses,
that means 50% of the mass is below 10 and
50% of the mass is above 10.
For alcohol drinking, the median turned
out to be 2.0 drinks per week.
So, half of my students had less than two
drinks per week,
half had more than two drinks per week.
And, unlike the mean, the median is not
affected by extreme values.
So, because we're just talking about where
50% are above and
below, it doesn't matter if there are
extreme values in there.
It doesn't matter if in the top 50%,
somebody has a really high level of
drinking or whether the high, the highest
value of drinking isn't so high.
So for example,
if I took the highest drinking person,
which was only eight drinks per week.
And again, I made them an alcoholic.
I said that that value, the highest
drinker actually had 40 drinks per week.
How does that effect the median?
Well, it doesn't effect the median, right,
because 50% of people are still below two
and 50% of people are still above two.
It doesn't matter that the highest person
is, it doesn't matter whether they're at
eight or whether they're at 40, that
doesn't effect where the median lies.
So the median is not effected by extreme
values.
Now I asked whether or not varsity sports
has a mean, we can, that's
a binary variable does varsity sports, a
binary variable also have a median.
Sure.
Again,
if you think about a binary variable as a
series of 0s and
1s, then you just line up the 0s and 1s
from the lowest, the 0s,
to the highest, the 1s, and you find where
the middle number, number lies.
Well, in this case there are more 1s than
there are 0s, because more people had
played varsity sports than hadn't, so the
middle number, the median will occur at 1.
So, yes, it has a median.
It has a median of 1.