Now we're talking about the different
shapes of the distribution as
a left-skewed or right-skewed, so let me
just summarize this.
So left-skewed means that you have a left
tail.
So you have a few extreme values that are
low to the left.
Right-skewed means you have a right tail,
so
a few extreme values that are high to the
right.
And of course symmetric means just what it
sounds like,
you have a nice symmetric distribution.
There's a special type of symmetric
distribution called a bell curve or
a normal distribution that we're going to
talk about a lot in this course.
So I'm just going to introduce it now to
just get you thinking about it.
So a bell curve is just what it sounds
like, it follows the shape of a bell.
It turns out to be very important in
statistics for a number of reasons.
So I'll just say a little bit more about
it now.
So the reason it's important is, for
one thing, it has sort of a predictable
behavior that makes it very useful.
So it turns out that if you're on a
perfect normal curve
that 68% of your observations will fall
somewhere between one standard
deviation below the mean to one standard
deviation above the mean.
95% of your observations will fall within
two standard deviations of the mean and
99.7% will fall within three standard
deviations of the mean.
If you don't know what a standard
deviation is,
don't worry we're going to talk about that
in an upcoming module this week.
But, it has nice predictable behavior so
that's very useful for calculating
statistics.
Another reason the normal distribution
comes up a lot is that many traits that we
might measure in a population follow a
normal distribution.
There's lots of traits that don't follow a
normal distribution but
there's a number that actually follow a
normal distribution.
So things like IQ and height tend to fall
on a bell curve.
So that's another reason it comes up a
lot.
Finally, the most important reason that
the normal distribution is so
important in statistics is actually that
statistics themselves tend
to follow a normal distribution.
And this is a bit of a tricky concept.
But it's something that I want to plant in
your head now because we're going to
be talking about this in great detail in a
couple of weeks.
So it turns out that statistics, things we
measure from our data like means and
odds ratios and regression coefficients.
Those also have a distribution.
And it's a tricky concept because, if you
think, like I'm, I do a study.
I measure one mean in my sample.
How does a single mean have a
distribution?
Well, it's something that is a theoretical
construct.
But, it turns out that that distribution
if often a normal distribution.
And, that's really the reason that the
normal distribution is so so
important in statistics.
So I'm going to end here with just
showing you some histograms of the data
from my Stanford students.
I think it's always fun to look at
histograms of real data.
So for
example, I asked my students to rate their
optimism on a scale from 0 to a 100.
And you can see that, you know,
most of my students are feeling pretty
optimistic when they took this survey.
I did have a handful.
Out to the left, we would describe this as
having a bit of a left skew.
There were a some students who were more
on the pessimistic range.
[SOUND] I asked them about their daily
fruit and
vegetable consumption and servings per
day.
And you're suppose to ear five servings of
fruits and vegetables per day.
Not everyone was meeting that.
But in general my students are pretty
healthy.
They were doing a pretty good job.
I even have students eating six, eight,
ten fruits or vegetables a day.
Interestingly, this distribution would
have been a nice normal curve except that
we're missing the left tail, right?
There wasn't anybody who was eating no
fruits and vegetables everyday,
which is a good thing and so we're missing
a little bit of a left tail there.
If we would have had some people eating
none,
this would've made sort of a bell curve.
Here's another interesting variable.
I asked them how many, how much homework
they did in hours per week and
you can see that there was a wide eye.
I got a wide set of answers here.
So for those of you who're out there for a
full-time student you'll
be very interested in how much homework my
students were doing.
To be fair,
I asked some of the students this question
at the very beginning of the year.
So, maybe some of them didn't have any
homework yet but
that the homework by the way coming in
later.
I had a lot of students reporting 0 to 5
hours of homework per week but
then I have a really big right skew, a big
right tail here with
some students reporting as many as 40
hours per week of homework.
[SOUND] I ask my students about alcohol
drinking,
how many alcoholic drinks do you drink per
week?
My students are fairly light drinkers, as
you can see.
I don't tend to teach undergraduates.
I mostly teach graduate students and
medical students and doctors.
And they were fairly light drinkers.
The heaviest drinking I had reported here
was 7 or 8 drinks per week.
And most people are drinking just zero to
three drinks per week.
Finally a question I always like to ask my
students is how they feel about math.
And, I ask them to rate their feelings
about math on a scale of 0 to 100.
0 being really horrible feelings about
math, and 100 being they love math,
they go home every day and do math just
for fun.
And so, you can see there is a wide range
of feelings about math in my students.
A lot of the students tend to be
favorable.
But I definitely have some people in the
unfavorable range.
And interestingly enough, this variable of
all of the ones that I've shown you so
far, turns out to be the closest to a
normal distribution.
And certainly not a perfect normal
[INAUDIBLE] distribution.
A perfect normal curve.
But it's actually the closest of the
variables that I've shown you so far.