Welcome to our final online module for HRP
223.
This week we're going to cover
Comprehensive Example and
we'll incorporate most of the code you've
learned during this cover.
>> By covering everything all at once, we
hope you'll be a little bit
more comfortable by the time you have to
go out and work on data sets on your own.
For this unit we created a fake data set
about diabetes.
Before taking a look at our data
dictionary please pause the video and
download the Diabetes 223.csv data set
that goes along with this
comprehensive example.
Save it in the folder you created for this
class.
Remember, whenever you get a data set,
always make sure you have a data
dictionary.
Here's the data dictionary for our data
set.
>> The main variable is this binary
variable that represents
the disease outcome for each subject.
If they have a one they are diabetic, and
if they have a zero they are not diabetic.
We have variables for age in years, weight
in pounds and height in centimeters.
These are all continuous variables.
We also have some categorical variables.
Race ethnicity has five categories, 1 for
black, 2 for white, 3 for asian, 4 for
hispanic and five for other.
Smoking status is a binary variable with 1
representing smoker and
0 representing non smoker.
We also have a gender variable labelled
isfemale, with 1 for
females and 0 for males.
>> A great place to start before even
opening SAS,
is to make sure that you know the
variables in your data set.
Make sure you know which of the variables
are continuous, which are binary,
which are categorical, and etcetera.
Usually makes things easier when you
import the data set, and
are checking the define field attributes
window.
>> Let's open SAS and point to a permanent
library.
As you may recall, during the first few
modules,
we showed you how to use point and click
to create a permanent library.
We also recommended that you copy the code
located in the SAS log, so
that you could use it in the future.
We still have our library creating code,
so we'll start by creating a new program,
labeling it Library, and then pasting in
our live reference code.
Once we run this, we'll be able to import
our data.
Let's click on File > Import Data, and
navigate to the Diabetes 223 data set.
On the next page you can specify which
library you want to import your data into.
Now you want to save it into the permanent
library that we just created.
So click browse to find that library, and
click Save.
When you're done specifying your library,
click Next.
Make sure to check the box that says file
contains field names on record number one,
like we have here.
Also make sure to check the box for
renaming columns to comply with SAS naming
conventions.
This can fix any simple formatting errors
that might mess up SAS.
Click Next.
On the next page,
check to make sure that each variable is
being imported in their correct format.
We need to make sure that all of our
numeric variables are listed as number,
and all of our categorical variables are
listed as string.
[SOUND]
Great.
Now our variables are all correctly
specified.
Now click finish and you'll be able to
input your data set