In this next module I'm going to talk
about a very
important continuous distribution function
called the normal function, and
of course we've seen it already quite a
bit in this course.
So the normal distribution we saw already
has a bell shape.
It has 2 parameters that define it just
like the.
Binomial had 2 parameter that define it N
and P.
The normal has 2 parameter's mu and the
mean and sigma the standard deviation.
The nice thing about the normal is the
mean and
the sigma, the standard deviation are
already calculated for you.
They define the curve so you don't have to
calculate those by hand.
So, if you shift the mean, you shift the
distribution left or right.
If you, if you increase the, the sigma,
you widen the curve.
If you decrease the sigma, the curve
becomes more narrow.
And that is a whole family of curves, of
bell curves defined by mu and sigma.
Now, just for fun Don't get thrown by this
if you are a little, intimidated by math.
But just for fun I'm showing you here the
actual mathematical function that
defines the bell curve.
So all of this fancy math, all that it
say's is that if you were to
plug this into a graphing calculator, or a
graphing, program in a computer.
It would spit back out for you, a bell
curve.
And there's a whole bunch of constants,
the way, the reason it looks so bad is
here is we've got a bunch of constants in
here that make it look more complicated.
Like E is just the exponential function
that's just 2.71 blah, blah, blah.
And pi, you all know, is 3.14, etcetera.
And then there's 2 parameters, again,
that define exactly what the bell curve
looks like.
Those are your sigma and your mu.
So different, if you change sigma and mu,
you change the shape of the bell curve.
But they all belong to one single.
Mathematical family of functions.
And that again, is just a function there
just for
fun, and that's the probability density
function for a bell curve.
It's a probability function so we know
that the area under the curve of
any bell curve that follows this function,
must sum to one.
It must integrate to one.
And so, again this is purely for fun.
I'm never going to ask you to work out
this integral.
But if you were to integrate this
mathematical function,
from negative infinity to positive
infinity, it indeed integrates to one.
So that means, that that's the proof that
indeed the area under this curve is one,
so it is, that makes it a probability
function.
And the expected value of this function is
just mule.
But it turns out that you could, you could
show that,
you could apply the expected value formula
here.
Again if this bothers you, if all these
integrals bother you,
you can scroll ahead of this.
It's not absolutely necessary, but just
you understand, the.
If you were to multiply X times that
probability function, and
integrate, which is like summing up, that
would actually give you back mu.
You may not want to solve that integral by
hand, but if you do it gives you back mu.
And same thing if you apply the variance
formula here and solve that.
Yeah amazing integral here it would just
give you back sigma squared so
again we don't actually have to solve for
expected value of
our varience here because it turns out
that the the mean is new and
the varience is sigma squared those define
the curve.
So those, I just showing these for fun.
Now remember that, we have, when we, are
on a perfect normal curve,
perfect mathematical funtion, we have this
rule that we know that 68% of
observations will fall within one standard
deviation of the mean, 95 within two.
And 99.7% within 3.
We've seen this rule and used it with real
data before.
Well, where did that rule come from?
I just told you that rule, but why should
you believe me?
Well, what that rule came from is that, in
fact, if you integrate any normal
distribution bell curve, that follows that
particular mathematical function.
That it always turns out that 68% of the
area under the curve will fall
between one standard deviation below, up
to one standard deviation above the mean.
95% of the area will fall between two
standard deviations below to two
standard deviations above the mean.
So we, again saw this rule Earlier but now
I'm just telling you where it comes from.
It just comes from calculus, from the
math.
The area under the curve is always 68%
between one
standard deviation below to one standard
deviation above the mean and
you could actually, if you wanted, of
course.
You're not going to have to do this in
this course but if you wanted to,
you could do that integral and
you could show that if you're going from
mu minus sigma to mu plus sigma.
And you integrate here that that will give
you 68% etc.
Of course, you know, again your not
going to have to do those integrals, but
just understand that's why that's where
that 689599.7 percent rule comes from.
It just comes from the mathematical curve
from the areas under the curve.
Alright, so that's a really useful rule.
68, 95, 99.7, is useful for a lot
problems.
So suppose SAT scores, math SAT scores,
say follow a roughly normal distribution.
A lot of IQ tests and,
and standardized tests like this will end
up following a normal distribution.
And lets say that, the mean, math SAT
score is 500 and
the standard deviation is 50.
I'm just making those up,
but that's probably reasonably close to
what it actually is.
We know a whole bunch of things.
If we know it's on a normal curve, then
because of this 95, 90.
68-95-99.7 rule.
We know that 68% of students will have
scores 450 and 550,
that's one standard deviation below to one
standard deviation above the mean.
We also know that 95% of students will be
between 400 and
600, two standard deviations below to two
standard deviations above the mean.
And we know that 99.7% will be between 350
and 650.
Now that's all very useful but it's
limited, right?
We would like to be able to do more with
the normal curve.
So that answers some questions, but it
answers only particular questions.
What if I instead ask something like,
what's the probability of getting a math
SAT score of 575 or less?
Well 575 wasn't on one of those boundaries
that I just showed you,
it doesn't fall at either 1 standard
deviation or 2 standard deviations or
3 standard deviations away from the mean.
So our 68-95-99.7 rule doesn't help us
here.
So you might think oh, no we're going to
have to go to calculus and
do an integral to figure this out, right.
I mean you would get the answer if you, if
you know the math and
I'm like, here's my normal curve.
Here's my mean of 500.
It's got a standard deviation of 50, and
I literally could integrate from negative
infinity all the way up to 575.
I could do this integral under the curve,
right?
Now, again, I'm not going to, you're not
going to have to do this, I promise.
But that would be mathematically the w-,
one way.
To, to solve that, you could actually do
that integral and find out that,
that area under the curve, and that would
be the probability of getting 575 or less.
But here's the integral again, just for
fun.
Solve this integral?
No thanks.
It looks like a pain to solve, and we
don't want to,
should be a negative infinity, that we
don't really want to have to solve this.
All right.
So we need a, we need something else.
We need something else to do when it's not
right on, 68, 95, 99.7.
So, this is where we're going to bring in
a little trick.
We're going to bring in something called
the standard normal curve, or z scores.
And this is basically, we're going to take
all normal curves, and
we're going to make them fall on a single
normal curve.
And that's going to be the normal curve
where we have a mean of zero,
and a standard deviation of one.
You can see that it's in, it's
advantageous if the mean is zero, and
the standard deviation of 1 is 1, because
that simplifies all of the math.
So we're going to force every single
normal curve that we encounter to fall.
We're going to force it,
to instead, be on this universal currency
of the standard normal curve.
We're going to turn everything into what
we call z scores.
Z scores are just Standard deviation
units.
So all that we're doing here is instead of
talking about units of SAT score for
example, which are going to vary.
Your units of height or whatever units we
happen to be talking about.
We're going to translate everything
instead into standard deviation units.
We're going to convert all normal
distributions onto the standard
normal chart.
Essentially we're going to be talking
about units in standard deviation.
So, remember that 575 on the SAT score.
We just want to ask the question, well if
somebody gets a 575,
how many standard deviatoins are they
above the mean?
Well I can answer question I could just
reason it out.
I don't even need this formula over here.
If they're 575 and the standard is 50 and
mean is 500 75 is 1.5 standard deviation
above the mean.
That's all we're doing when we're
calculating the Z score.
So how did I get that?
I subtract the mean and I divided by the
standard deviation.
So, that person is, if they're 575 they're
1.5 standard deviations above the mean.
So we put everything, no matter what the
original curve we started with was,
we put everything into this common
standard deviation units.
And the reason is that this is really
nice, is that somebody went through and
did all of the integrals for the standard
normal curve and put them in a chart.
And of course, now you can get all of this
on a computer.
But and so all you have to do is, if you
can get back to the standard normal,
then you can figure out the probabilities
that are associated with
all possible different, different z
scores.
Again, well all we're doing here, is we're
taking the original curve,
where the mean was 500, the standard
deviation was 50.
And we were talking about figuring out if
we are 575,
what's the area to the left of 575.
Instead of figuring that out, which is
trickier,
we're going to convert into these Z
scores, standard deviation unit scores,
and say well, 575 is 1.5 standard
deviations above the mean.
Then we can go to a standard normal chart,
where somebody has already done
the integral to tell us what is the area
on a standard normal to the left of 1.5.
Somebody has already done that interval
for us, and
we can find it by going to a standard
normal chart.
So I'm going to show you how to use these
charts.
So, again, somebody has literally gone
through and done all of the integrals for
all the z, you know, up to a certain
decimal place
All the z values from negative, you know,
3.5 all the way up to positive 3.
So if you can get everything out of
standard normal then there's a chart that
gives you the probabilities that, of, that
go with all the different z values.
So if we want to know what's the
probability of getting 575 or
less you can see that, that probability is
going to be pretty big.
You can just see that from this picture,
right.
This probability's greater than 50%.
It's very likely that you're going to get
575 or less.
So what's that probability again?
We translate it into a Z score by
subtracting the mean and
dividing by the standard deviation to turn
it into standard deviation units, and
then we have to go to a standard normal
chart.
We're going to look this up in a standard
normal chart.
I'll show you how to look it up in a
minute.
When you look it up in a standard normal
chart you get that the probability of
being to the left of 1.5 z scores is
93.32%.
So your chance of getting 575 more or less
on the mathecity is 93.3 per cent.
So here is what these charts look like and
how do we read them.
Now, the reality is that these charts are
getting a little old-fashioned,
because most things we do nowadays, we do
them on a computer.
And it's very rare nowadays that I
actually have to go back to my good old
pen and paper standard normal chart but,
you should know how to read them.
They're a little bit of a relic, and
you know, a lot of this will get done on a
computer, but
you should still understand the standard
normal chart.
So, if I want to figure out what's the
area to the left of 1.5,
first of all most of these charts are set
up to give you the area to the left.
So, if you look at this picture up here,
it's telling you it's going to be
giving you the area to the left of a
particular z value or 0.
By convention it usually gives areas to
the left.
So, if I want to find out the area to the
left of 1.5,
I have to look up the z score 1.5 in my
chart.
So, I'm going to first look up 1.5 in the
row.
I start there, and then most of these
charts are set up so
that you can go out an additional decimal
place.
So we want to know the area to the right
of 1.50, so
then I'm going to go down the column that
corresponds to a zero in the decimal place
so this gives me the 1.50.
It turned out that the area is 93.32% so
that's the area to the left of a z-score
of 1.5.
What is the what if we gotten a Z of 1.51
just to
show you how to read this chart when you
don't have a 0 there.
So again if it was 1.51 you start on the
row that's the 1.5 and then you go for
the column for that decimal the 0.01 so
that gets you to the 1.51.
The area for
that would be 93.45%, just slightly bigger
because that Z is slightly bigger.
It's helpful here I think to just do a
practice problem.
The [UNKNOWN], this is the kind of thing
that if you
do a few practice problems you'll get the
hang of it.
If birth weights in our population are
normally distributed with a mean of
109 ounces and a standard deviation of 13
ounces then,
what is the chance of obtaining a birth
weight?
So, if you're giving birth to a random
baby what's the bi,
chance of obtaining a birth rate of 141
ounces or heavier or
if you're just kind of sampling birth
records at random.
What's the chance of that random baby is
going to have a weight of
141 ounces or heavier?
And what's the chance of obtaining a birth
weight of 120 or lighter?
So let's solve both of those problems.
Again, we're assuming that these
birthrates are normally distributed,
the mean is 109, the standard deviation is
13.
So to solve the first one, I think it's
helpful to always draw a picture,
especially when you start, when you're
just starting out these.
So let's think about what did the curve
look like.
So the birth weights, the mean birth
weight is 109, and
the standard deviation is 13.
So we're on that normal curve.
And then I want to figure out where am I
relative to 109 if I'm
talking about a weight of 141.
Well, 141 is pretty far out in the right
tail.
It's much higher than the mean.
And I'm asking to, for the probability of
getting a weight of 141 or heavier.
So, I'm asking for the area to the right
of 141, that small area in the tail.
If I draw the picture then I know the
probability that I'm going to get out at
the end of the day better be small.
If it's not, I know I'm going to have done
something wrong.
Now I need to convert this into a z score.
So the z score here is I'm going to say,
well 141 is 2.46 standard deviation above
the mean.
How did I get that?
I subtracted 141 minus 109.
That gives me the distance above the mean
and
then I divide it by 13 to get it in
standard deviation units.
So my z is 2.46.
That's pretty far in the tail of a normal
distribution.
I'm 2.46 standard deviations above the
mean.
What's the chance that a random baby is
2.46 standard deviations above the mean or
even higher than that?
So that's, I'm looking for the area to the
right of z equals 2.46.
So I can go to my standard normal chart.
First of all, I need to find the z for
2.46.
So i'm going to find, the z for 2.46.
Again, I get that by doing the row is 2.4.
The column is the .06 part.
And, I get an area, the area to the left,
remember the charts are setup to always
give you the area to the left.
So this is giving me the area to the left.
The area to the left, there's 2.46 which
we know is way out in the tail.
That area, not surprisingly is very big,
99.31%.
So what's the chance, what's the area to
the right then?
How do you get the area to the right?
You're going to have to subtract 1 minus
.9931 will give me the area to the right.
Which turns out to be .69%, a pretty
small, percentage there.
Because as you don't tend to have babies
that heavy.
Let's answer the 2nd practice question,
what's the chance of obtaining a birth
weight of 120 or lighter?
Again, let's draw out the picture, so
again, we're on a normal curve where the
mean is 109.
The standard deviation is 13.
I want to know, what's the chance of
obtaining a birth rate of 120 or
lighter, so now I'm looking for the area
to the left.
So 120 is above the mean, so
I know that my answer here is going to
have to be greater than 50.
Mo, a lot of babies are 120 or lighter.
How many, what's my Z here?
So 120 minus 109 divided by 13.
I, my Z is 0.85 so I'm not quite a
standard deviation above the mean.
I want to know the area to the left, so I
go to the standard normal chart.
And, again, I look in the row for .8, and
then I get the,
I want the .85, so I look in the column
for the .05, that second decimal place,
that gives me an area of 80.23%, and that,
I wanted the area to the left.
So there's an 80.23% that a random baby
will be 120 ounces or lighter.