[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, now that you have some of the basic
tools under your belt,
let's talk a little bit about some of the
thought processing in terms of
conducting that root cause analysis.
And it starts off with the concept of the
five why's.
The 5 Whys is primarily geared to be able
to focus on drilling
down on those individual reasons why a
particular cause was to occur.
You ask, the thought is, is if you ask the
why five times you may be
able to drill down to the point where you
actually get to the heart of the issue.
So, let's take one situation here not an
uncommon scenario is,
why did a patient get the wrong
medication.
And the response that was obtained was
because the staff did not do
the double-check, that is,
the double-check of the medication, the
identification of the patient.
Make sure the dosing is right, the route
is right the frequency is right.
You know, all those five rights, you know,
that needs to be done to make sure the
right patient gets the right medication.
Second why.
Why did the staff do not do the double
check?
Well, reason being because the computer
was not available to confirm the order.
Sounds reasonable.
There's a number of reasons why that
maybe, you know, it didn't happen.
But the fact is is that when you query the
staff about not doing the double check,
they'll give you an answer and in this
case, the computer was not available.
Why was the computer not available, you
ask?
Well, because many of the computers were
being charged up.
Starting to scratch your head a little bit
so,
we have all these computers, they're all
available, not being used or
not being able to be used because they're
being charged up, well why is that?
Well, because the batteries don't
necessarily seem to hold their charge.
Well, so, the computers, which we rely on,
as a core identify as tool to be able to
identify, who the patient is and
make sure the order and medication rights
are not available, because of the,
batteries in these computers are not able
to hold the charge.
So, why is the batteries not holding the
charge?
Because the batteries were not being
maintained as scheduled.
You should probably know a lot of our
technology relies on battery and
batteries also have maintenance issues,
maintenance concerns that needs to
be addressed as well as any other
electrical devices and as a result,
in this situation, the batteries are not
being maintained as scheduled.
So you ask, why the sixth time.
Why are the batteries not being maintained
as scheduled?
Because the budgeting did not anticipate a
need for replacement or
maintaining the batteries.
So, in this situation, when you drill
down, you're figuring out well,
let's get to the heart of the issue.
What's really going on here?
It's really kind of an issue of budgeting.
Why wasn't budgeting done to account for
battery maintenance?
Well, because the vendor said these
batteries will last forever.
So, if you drill it down, you look at the
core issues the root cause.
The reason, you know, you ask the five
whys and
drill down to the point where you can
really find out what that real reason is,
why something has actually contributed to
this adverse outcome.
If you looked at this question one or two,
you probably would've stopped and
said well, let's just make sure we go buy
more computers and
make sure they're all available so that
staff can do the double check.
Or, as we do in many cases, we go out and
fix the problem by addressing the first
thing we, we heard.
Which was, staff didn't do the double
check.
So, the immediate knee jerk reaction is,
well, let's go get the staff provide an in
service to them.
Review the policy and procedure, and make
sure they, you know, do that double-check.
And, you know, you may come to find, after
putting in that kind of a corrective
action plan, that within a few weeks,
maybe even a few days, you have the same
kind of event occurring again because you
really didn't address the root cause.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
So, we have a scenario.
We're going to do a mini root cause
analysis here.
And in this situation, you can, if you can
picture a block of
large very good Swiss cheese, you know,
I'm a kitchen table.
Few feet, few feet away from an open
screen door.
The weather outside is warm.
A, a man comes to the table for some wine
and cheese and sees a mouse in the cheese.
So, you got the vision in your head about
what you're looking at.
Well, you know, of course, we picked Swiss
cheese, because, you know,
if you, are aware of the James Reason's
model of why, you know, serious events,
accidents occur is that all the checks and
balances that are in place to try and
prevent a bad thing from happening, the
holes line up in this Swiss cheese, and
as a result, the outcome is going to be
that event.
So, in this case here,
we're actually going to try to enjoy the
cheese a little bit.
But it is a warm day and as a result, we
have the door open.
And the door's open because we need to get
some breeze into this room, and
we sit down, and you end up finding a
little mouse, inside that cheese.
So, here's the problem.
There is a mouse in the cheese,
that's the undesirable, unwanted,
untoward, event that was, that occurred.
So, what's our typical response, to this
kind of event,
in this little element of brainstorming,
or blue-skying, or,
you know, well what were some of the
things we can do as possible solution.
Well, you know, our immediate response it
throw out the cheese with the mouse and
put a new block of cheese on the table.
That fixed the problem and what's the
likelihood of
a mouse showing up in the cheese again if
we really don't address the core issue?
Well, partially addressing a core issue,
if the mouse came from the outside, if we
replace the screen door.
That fixed the problem, it might be a
little bit of an overkill but
never the less, you know, by replacing the
door, hopefully it keeps the mouse out.
Or, as we have a tendency to do in
healthcare, you know, is put a sign up.
Anytime there's a deficiency put another
sign up.
Put a poster up.
In my experience posters, signage, you
know, up on the wall if it's up for
more than 21 days, people don't pay
attention to it.
But, we can actually, you know, provide a
solution in this scenario to keep mouses,
mice from being inside the cheese is put a
note on the door.
And just say, close me.
Alright.
Or keep door closed.
That, you know, another typical fix.
And I mentioned this one earlier where
basically we could create a policy.
Have everyone read and
sign and agree to follow the policy of
keeping the door closed.
And sometimes it comes down to the knee
jerk responses.
Gotta blame somebody, so fire or sue the
cheese maker.
They must a created a situation where a
mouse,
mice are able to be able to hide and get
in the cheese, and
as a result we can go out and fire or sue
the cheese maker.
We all know if you did any one of these
things, it's, you know,
the likelihood of a, another mice showing
up, or
another mouse showing up in the cheese is
very high, you know, is highly likely.
So, mouse and cheese, you ask why?
Well, mouse in the house, why is the mouse
in the house?
Screen doors are left open, why?
Cat is gone, left the screen door open,
solution, it actually create,
create a situation where the screen door
with the spring latch is kept continuously
closed so that way you can enjoy that nice
breeze from the outside and
enjoy your wine and cheese.
You know, I like this little saying that
nothing changes unless you make it change,
but you can't change what you don't know
what needs to be fixed and
that's the whole concept behind root cause
analysis.
My experience with doing them over the
last several years is that sometime we
knee-jerk to come up with the root cause
of a particular problem.
Quickly put in solutions, thinking that's
going to fix the problem.
And in realty, because we never actually
addressed the root cause or
the system process issue, those events
occur, again down the road.
[BLANK_AUDIO]