The correct answer for this is D.
Quantity distribution, we are not
guaranteed that 95% of the area will fall
within 2 standard deviations of the mean,
even though this is,
a fact the normal distribution, this
include for the T-distribution.
Especially for when we have a small number
of observations.
The answer is true because the researchers
measured virtually the entire population.
We can safely say this is a true value and
there is No sample statistic involved.
So the correct answer is B, the standard
error is a measure of variability of
a sample statistic, A is incorrect because
of formula given in A is valid only for
a standard error of a mean.
But we could have standard errors of a lot
of other statistics as well.
For example we could have standard errors
for more, mores and medians, and
the formula for that will not be the
formula given in A.
The formula for the standard error in a
mean is the standard deviation divided by
the square root of the number of
observations In this case,
our standard deviation is 10.
We have 400 observation.
We see that the standard error comes out
to be 0.5.
The correct answer for this question is B,
the size of the smallest group, and
we can illustrate that using a very simple
example.
Let's say we had a case where A was 1, B
was 10, C was 100, and D was 1000.
We can see that the full expressions in
the formula come out to be 1 by 1,
less 0.1, less 0.01, less 0.001.
And we can see that the first expression
is the one that is going to impact
the standard error the most.
The correct answer here is D,
different statistics have different
formulas for standard errors.
We know that the standard, the formula for
standard error of the mean It's given by
the standard deviation divided by
the square root of the number of
observations but
this is only the formula for the standard
error of the mean.
We have very different formula for the
standard errors of the mean, the mode and
the median, for example.
The answer to this question is D, all of
the above.
The confidence interval gives us
information about the effect size,
the precision and the statistical
significance.
The correct answer is 8 changing from a 99
to a 95
percent confidence level because requiring
a high, low level of.
Confidence decreases the width of the
confidence interval.
And 95% confidence interval of
a mean will include the true population
mean 95% total time.
This is true by the definition of a
confidence interval.
If we sample both women and men together,
we would have a higher standard deviation
of heights because we would expect the men
to be Taller than the women.
It's the only sample of women we would
expect the, the heights to be
closer together because of which the
standard deviation would be lower.
The first confidence interval would be
naver,
narrower because it involved a larger
sample size.
You know that the formula for the margin
of
error is 1 by the square root of the
number of observations.
It comes out to 4%.
In this case we know that the mean is 55%.
In the previous question we calculated out
when we
have 625 observations the margin of error
is 4%.
So if we want to find.
The lower and upper bound for
a 95% confidence interval this would be
55% plus or minus 4%.
The lower bound would be 55% minus 4%
which is 51 and
the upper bound would be 55 percent plus
4%, which is 59%.
The correct answer is b.
Because the smaller standard error will
result in a smaller p-value.
The correct answer here is d.
There is not enough evidence to reject the
null hypothesis.
A is incorrect because we have [INAUDIBLE]
that the treatments differ.
But this is not equivalent to proving the
treatments are the same.
B is incorrect because we were not given
enough information about whether the drug
and the placebo improved the insomnia
symptoms.
C is incorrect because the high val-,
p value shows us that we cannot let the
null hypothesis.
[SOUND] In this question, the correct
answer is C.
There is only 2% chance that the observed
difference in cur rates could have
arisen if the drug had no effect.
This is by the definition of the p value.