In this next module, I'm going to talk
about multiple linear regression.
This is when we now going to add multiple
predictors to our regression model.
This allows us to do all kind of wonderful
things like improve our predictions and
statistically adjust for confounders.
[SOUND] Multiple linear regression just
means that you're adding more than
one predictor to the model, so
the right side of our regression equation
is now going to get bigger.
It's going to look something like this.
So this now, our expected value of y we
can predict is equal to
an intercept plus a slope corresponding to
one predictor variable,
another slope corresponding to another
predictor variable, so maybe even
a third variable in the model, so we can
put multiple variables in the model.
Those predictors can be continuous
variables.
They can be binary variables.
They can be categorical variables.
We'll talk more about that in the next
module.
Each regression coefficient, the way that
we interpret it is, it's the amount
of change in the outcome variable that
would be expected for one-unit change in
the predictor if all other variables in
the model were held constant.
So it's trying to get at the independent
effects of, say, X.
If you hold W and Z here constant, what's
the independent effect of X?
What's the slope for X once you've held
everything else in the model constant?
That's the idea, and I'm going to kind of
try and illustrate that concept now.
There are many functions of multivariate
analysis.
So, one of them is that it allows you to
control for confounders.
So you can put potential confounders in
the model, so that you
can try to gauge the independent effect of
the predictors you're interested in.
After adjusting for, after controlling for
confounders.
You're going to be able to isolate better.
The effect of the predictor you care
about.
Putting multiple variables in the
regression equation allows you
also to improve your predictions.
So now instead of saying it's our
political bent that predicts whether or
not we like Obama, maybe there are other
variables I
can come up with that also help improve
that prediction beyond political bent.
Are there other things that predict who's
going to like Obama?
Another thing that you can do in a
multivariate
analysis is tests for interaction.
I'm actually not going to talk about
interactions in any detail this week.
I'm going to give this a lot of time next
week.
I sort of alluded to interactions in Week
6.
So you may be familiar with the concept.
But it's something that you can easily
test for
in the multivariate regression analysis
context.
Again i'm going to get to that next week.
In this module I'm going to work on the
first two of these.
Controlling for confounders and improving
predictions.
So starting with the first one.
How does multivariate analysis how can it
be used to control for confounding?
I'm just going to illustrate this with an
example.
So lets start with the hypothetical data
that I had on vitamin D levels and
cognitive function.
I'm going to use the hypothetical data set
that had the strongest association between
those two things.
The one that had the slope of 1.5 per 10
nanomoles per liter.
Here's the regression equation.
We already fitted the best fit line here.
This is the simple linear regression
equation.
The intercept was 20, the slope here again
is 1.5.
Of course, I made up these data, so
I get to build anything into the data set
that I want to.
So I built in a confounder here.
And it makes sense that this particular
variable would actually be
a confounder here.
So, what if age is a confounder here?
So, we, we're seeing a relationship in the
data set between vitamin D levels and
poor cognition.
There's [INAUDIBLE] there's real
relationship in these data and
I know there's a real relationship because
I built it in.
But what if that relationship was coming
through confounding with age?
Remember, as you age,
it's definitely true that your cognition,
your cognitive function goes down.
That's true for everyone.
It's also true that as you age, you tend
to have lower vitamin D levels.
So, as you get older your nutrition isn't
as good,
that that would affect your vitamin D.
You also might be less likely to do
exercise and
go outside to do exercise and, and be
outside in general.
All of those things result in older people
having lower vitamin D.
So you can imagine a scenario where you're
seeing a relationship, if you just look at
vitamin D and cognitive function, you
might see a relationship there.
But it could be driven purely by the fact
that older men both have lower
vitamin D and they have poor cognition, so
it might not be that vitamin D is causing
the poorer cognition.
It might just be the fact that vitamin D,
poor cognition, and
age, older age tend to cluster.
Well we can task for this.
We can adjust for age simply by putting
age into our regression model.
Our outcome variable is [INAUDIBLE] still
the cognitive function test,
the DSST score.
We're still going to have an intercept.
But now, in addition to the slope for
vitamin D, we're going to add in a slope
for age.
If I have two slopes,
what I'm actually doing is fitting now not
a line, but I'm fitting a plane.
And I can try, it's again, always great to
graph things.
And I'm going to try here to graph this.
It gets very hard to graph things from
multivariate regression because you can
kind of graph a plan okay, but anything
beyond a plane I can't really graph.
But for two variables, again we're dealing
with something in three dimensions.
Here's my three dimensional plot, my
attempt to plot this.
Of course, with three dimensional plots it
completely,
what you're seeing completely depends on
the angle that you look at.
But I've tried to choose something that's
illustrative here.
What you're seeing is that vitamin D
levels,
that's your x-axis variable, your
cognitive score.
Is the y axis variable and age in this
plot is the z variable.
That's the one that's kind of going into
your computer screen.
So again, this is supposed to be three
dimensional.
What you can notice, is that when,
in this particular angle, when I'm
focusing on age is in the picture, but
I'm focusing on the relationship between
vitamin D and cognitive function,
it no longer looks like there's much of a
strong relationship there, right?
It kind of looks like a random scatter.
Compare that to when I kind of turn this
three-dimensional plot and
put age on the x-axis and vitamin D on the
z-axis.
So now vitamin D is kind of going into
your computer screen, so
you can, you can see it less.
And I'm kind of trying to isolate here the
effect of age and cognitive score.
Now you can see this strong relationship
as age goes up cognitive score goes down,
so based on the 3 dimensional pictures it
looks like there's a stronger effect for
age here then than for vitamin D.
We can actually fit a plane here rather
than a line.
That's what our model is doing.
We're fitting a plane rather than line.
Our plane is defined by two slopes.
One slope for vitamin D, and one slope for
age.
And what you're seeing here that, for
example, what you're seeing these
kind of vertical diagonal lines, those
are, that's the slope for age.
Notice here that there's a slope for age
at every different vitamin D level.
Of course, the slope for age is the same
at any vitamin D level.
So for example, at a vitamin D level of,
you know this is something like 60, here's
the slope for age, here's the relationship
between age and cognitive function.
There's a pretty strong positive
relationship,
as age goes up, cognitive function really
goes up strongly.
Contrast that to the slope for vitamin D.
Those are the more horizontal lines here.
So this, these horizontal lines represent,
this is the slope for vitamin D.
The relationship between vitamin D and
cognitive function at any given age.
For example if we take the age about 55
right here,
there's a particular slope between vitamin
D level and cognitive function.
The slope is constant.
The slope between vitamin D and
cognitive function doesn't depend on the
age, but we've isolated the effect of
age because we're talking about the slope
at any particular age.
And we're assuming that that slope is the
same at different ages.
So we've isolated the effect of vitamin D
in that way.
You can see that the slope for
vitamin D here is almost perfectly flat,
it's almost 0.
Suggesting that the relationship between
vitamin D and
cognitive function is basically 0 once we
adjust for, once we account for age.
If we're, if we're talking about a whole
group of just 55 year olds there
doesn't appear to be any relationship left
for vitamin D in cognitive function.
That's the idea here.
We fit this plane and we see the slope for
vitamin D is almost 0 where as the slope
for age is very strong.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here's the computer output that
corresponds to the model that that
corresponds to
the picture that I just showed.
I just showed you the visual picture of
this and
here's the actual fitted model that I've
run in a computer.
Again, you have to learn to kind of weed
through a computer output like this.
What we're interested in are the parameter
estimates, those are are,
that's our intercept and our betas or
slopes.
That's what the,
the model estimates, as pictured on the,
the graphic on the previous slide.
We're also interested in the p-values that
tell us whether or
not those slopes are statistically
significant or not.
The standard error here and the t value
directly combine with the effect size to
give us the p-value, so I most care here
about the actual size of the effect,
the parameter, and the p-value.
The standard error,
and the t value are really just useful for
just getting me to the p-value.
So I, I'm, going to probably report in my
paper,
if I were to write a paper about this,
that the betas, and the p-values.
Here's our final model.
Our outcome variables DSST score, our
intercept is 53, the slope for
age is negative 0.46, the slope for
Vitamin d is positive 0.039.
Remember that the slope for Vitamin D when
we didn't put age in the model,
in the simple linear regression was 1.5.
So we've now gone all the way from 1.5 per
10 nanomoles per liter, which was a pretty
big effect, a modest effect, down to 0.039
which is essentially zero.
This is highly non-significant.
Our p-value is 0.9.
There's no evidence here that this is
different than zero.
And we are, the magnitude of our effect of
the slope is very close to zero.
On the other hand, for age, the slope for
age is negative 0.46.
It's highly statistically significant.
This is indicating that every one year
increase in
age is correlated with a half point
decrease in the DSST score.
That's a pretty steep decline.
Here again is written out the equation of
the best fit plane.
The best fit plane here is again,
53 plus the intercept plus 0.039 times the
vitamin D.
And 10 nanomoles per liter minus 0.46
times age in years.
That's our final equation.
And you can see, again, that there isn't
much effect left for vitamin D.
All, essentially all of the relationship
we were seeing between vitamin D and
DSST score can be explained by age, due to
confounding by age.
We can say there's no independent effect
of vitamin D after accounting for age.
There's nothing left over in this case.
Now a lot of times confounding is not
going to be this strong.
This is a made up example, so I built in
essentially complete confounding by age.
Real examples are going to be a little bit
more subtle.
The the effect may not completely
disappear once you
control for compounding.
It might just be attenuated, but in this
case we're basically down to a sub of 0.
All of the effect that we observed between
vitamin D and
cognitive function was completely due to
compounding by age and this example.
The evidence of confounding is in the beta
coefficient.
So the way that you test for confounding
is, you calculate the unadjusted beta,
which, here, was 1.5 per 10 nanomoles per
liter.
Then, you calculate the adjusted beta,
adjusted for
the, for the potential confounders.
In this case, age.
When we do that adjustment here, it goes
down.
Our beta goes down to almost 0.039 per 10
nanomoles.
Moles per liter.
The evidence of confounding is in the
difference between the unadjusted and
the adjusted beta.
If there is the rule of [INAUDIBLE] thumb
that people use is,
if there is more than a 10% change from
the unadjusted to the adjusted beta,
then that 10% change could be an increase
as well as a decrease.
It doesn't always have to be an
attenuation, although that's more common.
If there's more than a 10% change we
usually would call that confounding.
Notice in this case there's a 97.4% change
from the unadjusted to age adjusted beta.
So there's you know the almost all of the
effect for
vitamin D was due to confounding by age.
Again the rule of thumb that you can use,
is a rule of thumb so
it's not a perfect rule.
But just kind of as a guide, if that beta
changes by more than 10% when you
put the confounder in the model, then you
would consider it a confounder.
And often it means you might want to
consider keeping it in
your model to account for that confounder
to adjust for.
Notice that I'm not judging confounders by
their effect on p-values.
So you want to look at the betas to judge
whether or not something's a confounder.
You don't want to look at the p-values.
You might be tempted in this particular
example to say, oh well, vitamin D had
a significant relationship with cognitive
function before I put agent to the model.
When I put agent to the model, that
significant effect disappeared.
Therefore, I've got a confounder.
But don't use the P value like that
because sometimes you'll have
confounders that aren't going to be strong
enough to
change the p-value from something
significant to something non-significant.
There's lots of things that, as we've
talked about, impact the p-value
beyond effect size as well, so you really
want to judge confounding simple by
looking at how it changes the effect size,
how it changes the slope.
So ignore what it does to the p-values.
In this case it happens to take the
p-value from significant to
non significant, but that won't always be
the case.