In this next module, I'm going to tell you
about the statistics that we use to
describe the variability of data.
So there's a number of different
statistics that we can use to
measure variability.
So the simplest is just look at the range.
That tells you about the spread of the
data.
The most common one that we use is
something called the standard deviation,
that we're going to talk a lot about.
We also might talk about the variability
or
spread of the data in terms of percentiles
or something like a inter-quartile range.
So the range is easy, because it's just
the difference between the largest and
smallest observations, but that's very
useful information.
So for example, when I asked my students
about how much homework they did in
hours per week, I got a range of anywhere
from zero hours per week,
all the way up to 40 hours per week.
So my range is 40 hours per week.
So it's quite a wide range,
it gives you a sense that the, the data is
fairly variable here.
Moving to the standard deviation, the
standard deviation is by far the most
common measure of variability that you're
going to see in, in statistics.
So, I'm going to spend quite some time
talking about the standard deviation.
Really get a good understanding of it.
First of all, however, I'm going to give
you a little challenge.
And, if you want you can even pause the
video and
think a little bit in terms of this
challenge.
My challenge to you, is what if somebody,
somebody were to ask you to devise a
statistic.
That would give you the average distance
from the mean.
We want a statistic that tells you what is
the average distance of any given
observation from the mean.
How would you calculate that?
How would you come up with a statistic
that does that?
If you want, pause the video, see if you
can think it out.
So, probably your first instinct on this
is to,
first of all you have to think about
what's distance from the mean.
How would I quantify distance from the
mean?
So to measure the distance from the mean,
what you're going to want to do is
subtract an observations value from the
mean value, that will give you a distance.
So we can represent that in mathematical
symbols as Xi,
that is any given observation in your data
set.
Minus x bar, that's your mean.
So if you take,.
If somebody.
If the mean, in the data set is a mean
height of say, 69 inches.
Then if somebody was 71 inches, they would
be 2 inches above the mean.
That would be their distance from the
mean.
Or if.
The mean homework that you do per week is
11 hours per week,
and if that's the mean and you happen be
somebody who does 40 hours per week,
then you would be 29 hours per week above
the mean, that would be your distance.
If you only did 0 hours per week,
you would be negative 11 hours per week
away from the mean.
So that would be the distance from the
mean.
So that's the quantity distance.
But then, how do you get the average
distance from the mean?
Well, we know how to calculate an average,
right?
So to get the average distance from the
mean.
Your instinct, your first instinct would
be just to calculate an average of
those distances, right?
So again in mathematical symbols, what you
would do is you would add up all of those
distances, so each observation in your
data set has a distance from the mean.
You could add all of those up and then
divide by n to get the average.
Right, that's a good first instinct.
Of course there's a problem with that.
There's going to be a problem with that
quantity, right.
So what's the problem with that?
Well, the problem with that is it's
going to fail,
because remember that some of the
distances are going to be negative,
and some of the distances are going to be
positive.
Some people do more homework, some people
do less homework.
In fact, if you add up all of those
negatives and
positives, you're going to get exactly
zero.
So when you try to calculate the standard
deviation in this way,
it actually completely fails because you
end up with a value of zero.
And that's because you've got negatives as
well as positives.
So the problem is the negative, so the
next thing you might think is,
well how am I going to get rid of the
negatives?
What do we do in math to, if we don't want
to deal with negatives?
So how can I get rid of negatives?
Your first instinct on this might be to
turn to absolute values, right.
You if you take the absolute value,
you could do the absolute values of the
distances.
And that would get rid of the negatives.
It's not going to add up to zero anymore.
However, it turns out that it's very
messy mathematically to deal with absolute
values.
Right?
If you remember back to
like algebra two in high school.
When you deal with absolute values, funny
things happens.
Like less than signs got flipped around to
greater than signs, and
all these kinds of funny things.
So, mathematically we don't want to deal
with absolute values.
So what's another way to get rid of
negatives?
Another way to get rid of negatives is to
square things.
So that's actually what we're going to do.
This is how we're going to calculate
standard deviation.
We're going to square all of the distances
from the mean in order to
eliminate the negatives.
So rather than take the raw distances from
the mean and add them up, we're going to
square those distances first and add up
these squared distances from the mean and
get the average squared distance from the
mean.
This is something that we call a variance
and
sym, in terms of symbols I represent this
as an S squared.
S will be the standard deviation so S
squared is what we call the variance.
So S squared, the variance is the average
squared distance from the mean.
And I'll just write it out one more time
here.
Formally, I just want to point out that
the official Formula for
variance which I've now got up.
We've got, we've got to the official
formula here for variance.
Again, S squared is my, this is symbols I
used to represent, sample variance.
Notice that the formula look, looks just
slightly different because there's, in
the denominator I'm not dividing by n to
calculate the average, which is the way.
We usually calculate average in dividing
by N minus 1 this is
a little technical point but I just want
you to understand why its there so
it turns out that the reason we're
dividing by N minus 1 here is that
we've lost what's called a degree of
freedom.
So.
When we calculate variance or
standard deviation, we have to calculate
something else first.
We have to calculate the mean first.
By calculating that mean, we loose what's
called the degree of freedom.
And we're therefore only have negative- 1
degrees of freedom, so
that's why we're dividing by n 1, rather
than 1.
For all practical purposes, it doesn't
usually make a huge difference, right,
whether you divide by n, or n - 1, because
as long as n is pretty big.
You know, whether you divide by 99 or
divide by 100, it's not going to make a
huge difference.
But that's why, technically, that's in the
denominator.
So what's a degree of freedom?
One degree of freedom is, is, let's say
I've got a data set of 100 people.
And I were to give you, and
I were to calculate the, the mean for that
100 people.
Let's say the, the mean age.
And I were to give you the mean, and I
were to give, and I were to give you 99,
the ages for 99 of the other people in the
data set.
If you had 99 of the ages and the mean
age,
you would be able to calculate back for me
exactly that hundredth person.
So that means that once you've calculated
the mean You only have 99 degrees of
freedom left because that last person,
that hundredth person, is fixed.
They can't be anything else.
Once you have 99 and the mean, there's
nothing else that that person can be.
So you've lost what we call a degree of
freedom.
Again, that's a technical thing, but
it will come up again, so I just want to
point out that that's there.
Of course we start by calculating the
variance,
the average squared distance from the
mean.
But that you would, you know, if you, you
don't ever report the variance in
your paper because that would mean you'd
be reporting things in,
like, age squared, years squared, homework
hours squared.
Of course, we're going to want to get back
to the units of the original data, so
we're going to Square rooted and
that's what the standard deviation is it's
the square root of the various so
we start with the various and we square
root it to get the standard deviation to
get back to the original units and I use
as a symbol for
that I use s so s squared is the various s
is the sample standard deviation.
So, that's just to take a square root to
get back to the original unit that's what
your standard deviation is.
Now I just want to point out that there
are consequences to
the fact that we did this little squaring
routine.
So the standard deviation, at the end of
the day,
is not exactly the average difference from
the mean.
It represents sort of the average spread
or
the average scatter but it's not exactly
the average distance.
We have this little squaring trick in
there, right?
And so one of the consequences of that
squaring trick is that
things that are farther from the mean are
actually going to have more influence.
Are going to contribute more to
the standard deviation than values closer
to the mean.
So, for example, if the mean is 5,
then if you're talking about a value of 6
you're only one away from the mean.
If you square 1 you're still at 1.
But if you were 5 away the mean and
square 5 your amplifying that distance so
now it's a distance of 25.
So we're going to,
all this says is when you have values that
are extreme those are going to have a lot
of influence on the standard devaition in
the same way they influence the mean.
Let me just give a, an example calculation
here of
how you'd actually go about calculating
the standard deviation by hand.
So remember we had this little
hypothetical data set,
which had eight people with eight ages in
it.
They ranged from 17 to 38.
We calculated in a previous module that
the mean for this data set was 23.25.
So again, we have to calculate the mean
before we
can calculate The standard deviation.
To calculate the standard deviation I'm
going to take each of
these individual ages and subtract the
means and then square it.
So, for example the person who's 17, they
are 6.25 years away from the mean.
So we're going to take 6.25 and I'm
going to square it.
Person who is 19 is 4.25 units away from
the mean.
So I'm going to take 4.25, and I'm
going to square that.
I'm going to do that for each of the 8
observations.
So I end up in the numerator with a sum of
8 squares.
I'm going to add those up, and then I'm
going to divide here by 8 minus 1.
Because, again, we've lost 1 degree of
freedom.
So we always divide by n minus 1.
So we're diving by 7.
And then let's take the square root of
that whole thing.
To get back to the standard deviation,
I come up if I calculate this all out with
a value of 6.3.
What does that value of 6.3 actually mean?
So again, this is trying to get at the
average distance from the mean.
So, this is saying that roughly the
average scatter around the mean
is 6.3 years.
Now, if you notice, if you look at Each
individual participant here, like.
There's a person who's 17.
Well 17 is, isalmost 6.3 away from the
mean, but not quite.
19, 21, 22, 23, 23, 23, they're all much
less than 6.3 away from the mean.
So it's not looking like the average
distance from the mean is really
anywhere around 6 but we have 1 person
whose really far from the mean.
Their 38 when everybody else is in their
early 20s or teens.
That person, is, is because they're far
from the mean,
they're having a lot of influence.
That person is driving the fact that this
6.3 value is so high.
So, again, you know,
if you're far from the mean you can have a
lot of influence on, on the variance or
the standard deviation, and so that's why
that comes out to be 6.3 there.