In this next module, I'm going to give an
introduction to Cox regression,
which is the multivariate regression
technique that you use
when you have a time-to-event outcome.
Very similar to the other types of
regression that we talked about.
But is a bit of a more sophisticated
model, so
this will just serve as an introduction to
the topic.
To give you the basics of the model, and
hopefully entice you to
take a more advanced course if you want to
hear more about this topic.
So where are we on our little statistical
chart of tests here.
We're talking about when we have an
outcome variable that's a time to
event variable.
So when we're doing survival analysis.
And I mentioned in the second week of the
course we talked about rate ratios which
were just ratios of incident rates.
So, just comparing two groups very simply
we would use a rate ratio.
If we want to do survival curves,
we talked about in the seventh week of the
course, Kaplan-Meier statistics.
And the material we're talking about today
is actually very related to Kaplan-Meier.
A lot of times in the literature what
you'll see is that,
in an analysis where you're doing,
you got a time-to-event outcome, a cohort
study, or a randomized trial.
There'll be a Kaplan-Meier curve, a nice
picture there, and
then you'll see a Cox regression.
Those are often tied together in the
literature.
The limitation of Kaplan-Meier of course
is that you can only use it for
comparing different groups.
It doesn't work for continuous predictors
unless you chop them up.
It also doesn't, you are not able to
adjust for
confounders and things like that.
So of course we want some kind of
regression technique for
time to event outcomes.
And that's where the Cox Regression comes
in.
It's the multivariate regression technique
for this type of outcome variable.
And of course regression allows you to do
all the things we've talked about.
You can have multiple predictors to
improve prediction in the model.
You can adjust for confounding, you can
test for
interaction, all those kinds of things.
So, Cox Regression is
sometimes also called the Proportional
Hazards Regression.
Because one of the key assumptions of this
model is something called the proportional
hazard assumption.
So I'll talk briefly about that.
It's the multivariate regression technique
for time-to-event outcomes.
When we have time-to-event outcomes
remember when we talked about
the Kaplan-Meier curves, one of the key
things is that.
These outcomes take into account
censoring,
we're following people over time and we're
able to say when people drop out of
the study even if they haven't yet had an
event.
So all of this, these methods take into
account that sensory.
Same, all the things we talked about for
Kaplan–Meier apply here.
What do you get out of Cox regression?
We actually alluded to this in the second
week of the course when we
were talking about relative risks, because
what you get out at the end of
the day from a Cox regression model, are
hazard ratios.
A hazard ratio is just yet another type of
relative risk.
It's very, very similar to a rate ratio
except it's a ratio of two hazard rates.
And a hazard rate is an instantaneous
incidents rate,
I'll talk about that in this module.
Because we're doing regression often what
comes out is in the adjusted hazard ratio,
it's been adjusted for other things in the
model.
Again I mentioned this briefly,
in the second week of the course just
recall that I talked a little bit
about hazard ratios In the context of the
concept of relative risk.
It's yet another measure of relative risk.
And it has a similar interpretation as
just a regular old basic rate ratio.
It's the ratio of instantaneous incidence
rates, however.
So it's just slightly different from a
rate ratio.
It has to be calculated from regression.
You're not going to be able to calculate
it by hand.
Since it comes from a regression, it's
again, usually multivariable-adjusted.
And I had presented this little example in
the second week of the course,
just to show you how to interpret a hazard
ratio.
They're actually straight forward to
interpret.
This table,
the hazard ratios in this table actually
came out a Cox regression model.
So just to review, this particular
example,
this was a randomized study comparing a
drug, ranolazine, to a placebo.
The primary end point that they were
looking at in
this study was a composite end point.
They were looking for either death,
myocardial infarction,
that's a heart attack, or recurrent
ischemia.
That's the primary end point.
The hazard ratio here turned out to be
0.92.
You can see that right here.
So, how do I interpret that hazard ratio?
Again, it's very similar to interpreting
any type of relative risk.
That is an 8% reduction in the mortality
and MI and recurrent ischemia.
This, again, primary end point.
The rate of this primary outcome in the
drug group
compared with the placebo group.
Now it's not statistically significant.
You can see that the confident interval
ranges from 0.83 to 1.02 so
it does, it does cross the null value of
1.4.
And the P value is 0.11.
So it's not statistically significant.
It's not a big, of a big magnitude either.
But that's the basic interpretation and
that hazard ratio came out of a Cox
regression.
By way of introduction, I'm going to show
you two more examples from the literature.
Just to show you how these things tend to
be presented in the literature, and
to motivate the Cox regression model for
you.
Here's an example from the literature that
was a study of publication bias.
And you can see as I mentioned,
usually a Cox regression is linked up with
the Kaplan-Meier curve, so
this study in their report, they start
with a nice Kaplan-Meier curve.
You can figure out a lot of the,
the results of this study just by looking
at the Kaplan-Meier curve here.
So what this study was, is kind of a cool
study, because they were looking at,
again, this problem of publication bias.
So they took a bunch of studies at the
time that they were funded.
So the baseline point here is when the
grants were approved and
these studies were funded, and
the event here is publication of the main
findings of this study.
So they actually track to, to see from the
time of funding,
until, you know, how long did it take
until the major publication, you know,
reporting the major finding of the, of
those studies, was released.
And so publication is a good thing, of
course, so the outcome here is, you know,
it's not the [INAUDIBLE] is a nice, it's a
good thing, it's publication.
And they wanted to know if the result at
the end of the day from
a study was something was that ended up
being statistically significant.
That they proved, you know, the hypothesis
they were after.
Would those studies be published more
quickly than studies that
had a null finding, than studies that
didn't find what they were after, and
indeed that's exactly what they found.
This is getting at the problem of
publication bias,
because what happens in the medical
literature is that people rush to
publish things when they find a
significant result.
But null findings, which are often just as
important,
may have a delay in publication or never
be published at all.
So you can see with just looking at the
Kaplan-Meier curve here.
You of course, you started 100%, this
means 100% were unpublished, and
then every time there's a dip in this
curve, that represents a publication.
And this dark line are all the studies
that found significant results at
the end of the day.
So you can see that that curve is dropping
off much more quickly.
So the rate of publication was much faster
for
the studies that ended up finding
something significant.
Now for the Null studies, that's this gray
line here,
you can see that there was definitely a
delay In the publication.
The rate of publication was slower for
cities that found a null result.
So this is kind of what the authors
expected.
Yeah, and that's indeed what they found.
What was interesting, though,
was that they actually ended up defining a
third group here.
Now it's small group, but this kind of
medium shaded line is a small group.
And what this group was is these were
studies that ended up
with what's called a non-significant trend
at the end of the day.
So this is a kind of thing where you come
out with a P value of like, 0.08, or
0.09, or 0.06.
It's not quite statistically significant,
and
it turns out that it looks like people
aren't quite sure what to do with that.
Reviewers, editors, even
authors themselves may not be quite sure
how to report those results.
And so those actually ended up taking the
longest to get published interesting,
interestingly enough.
That's kind of similar to the HIV vaccine
trial in that there was no delayed in
publication on that one.
But this is, you know, some of the p
values are not quite significant so
there's some controversy about what to do
with those.
Anyway, this is the Kaplan-Meier curve.
There's a lot of information in the
Kaplan-Meier curve.
The p value from the Log-Rank test did
come out to
be statistically significant here.
Telling us that at least one of those
groups is differed in the rate
of publication.
But the p value from a Log-Rank test
doesn't quantify the magnitude of
the effect.
So one of the reasons to do a Cox
regression, and get a hazard ratio, is so
that we can quantify, what is the size of
the effect here?
So they went ahead and ran a Cox
regression.
And I'm just going to show you the
results.
Again, I'll get into the details of the
Cox regression in a few minutes.
But just to show you the results here,
this is a very simple Cox regression
model.
So, all they had in the model, I'm just
going to write out the model.
What we're actually modeling in a Cox
regression is the natural log of
the hazard rate.
That's our outcome, don't worry about that
yet.
But we're modeling a regression model, and
what's in this regression model, there's
only one categorical predictor.
So they have a categorical predictor,
you're either in the null group,
the non-significant trend group, or the
significant group.
And they dummy coded that, so just to
review dummy coding here,
there was a beta in the model for a
non-significant trend group, and
there was a beta in the model for this
significant group.
And the null group is the reference group
so
there's no parameter in the model for
them.
And here's the result.
So you can see that the null group, again,
is the reference group.
So their hazard ratio is, by default, set
to 1.00.
What they found was that, indeed.
For the people, the groups that ended up
with a statistically signifigant result at
the end of the day.
They had a, more than a two fold increase
in the rate,
the incidence of publication, compared
with the null group.
So there is a doubling or more than a
doubling in the rate of
publication when you have significant
results compared with null.
That's how you would interpret that hazard
ratio.
They also calculated a hazard ratio for
the non-significant trend, and that
one came out to be 0.39, and that would
say that there was a delay, a slowing in
the rate of publication in that group as
we saw in the Kaplan–Meier chart.
What's kind of fun here is that the
confidence interval cross is one, so
this is not statistically significant.
But it kind of just barely crosses one.
So this, itself,
might be what we would call a non
significant trend towards ineffect.
So you know, it's sort of ironic that the
non-significant trend group showed
a non-significant trend.
Anyway, that's a use a Cox regression to
quantify the size of the effect.
Here's another fun example from the
literature.
So there were a series of studies that
looked at this idea of, you know?
When people get nominated for something.
They say, oh, it was an honor just to be
nominated.
They were trying to, the authors here were
trying to kind of look at that question.
So they were looking at Academy Award
winners.
And they actually started with actors and
actresses.
And they said, let's compare the longevity
of actors and
actresses who actually won a, an Academy
Award.
Let's compare that to actors and
actresses who were nominated for an
Academy Award but never one.
And interestingly, they found a survival
advantage For the actors and
actresses who actually won the Academy
Award.
I'm not showing you those results here.
What I'm showing you here is the
Kaplan-Meier curve from
a related study that they did.
Where the same kind of idea, except that
they looked at Academy Award winners.
For screenwriting rather than acting.
And so interestingly, they found the
opposite thing here.
I find this of interest,
because my other hat that I wear at
Stanford is I do a lot of writing.
The red line are those who were nominated
but never won and
the blue line are the winners, so take a
quick look at that Kaplan-Meier curve.
What you see is we're looking at survival
here, so in fact,
the winners did worse than the nominees
only in screen writing.
It was the opposite of what they found
with actors and actresses.
So, maybe for actors and actresses, you
get some boost in longevity if you
win because you get more visibility, more
money.
But the same is not true of screenwriters.
The P-value from the log rank test here
comes out to be statistically significant,
saying that those curves really are
different.
Of course, this is just an unadjusted
curve.
And we would like to do a Cox regression
to quantify the effect and to adjust for
potential confounders.
One other thing I just want to point out
in this analysis.
Notice that the Kaplan-Meier curve the
time scale is actually not in time,
but is in age.
So usually so far we've been talking about
the time scale for
time to event outcomes being just the
amount of time that you spend in a study.
But if you're doing a long term cohort
study.
This is a retrospective core study but,
retrospective or
prospective, you're following people for a
long amount of time.
Often it makes more sense to use age as
the timescale and
what you're essentially doing is lining
people up by ages.
So you're comparing 70-year-olds to
70-year-olds, for example.
And you can do that very easily in
survival analysis is to treat age as
the type, so just point out that they're
doing that here.
So they went on and did a Cox regression.
Now they were, this was based on internet
research.
So they didn't go out and actually collect
data ques, you know,
questionnaire's on people, so
they could only find limited information
about these people on the internet.
But they tried to adjust for
basic confounders that they could find on
the internet.
So what you're looking at here is first of
all,
the very first row here, that's the hazard
ratio from the basic analysis.
So un-adjusted.
So that corresponds kind of directly to
the Kaplan-Meier curve.
So the winners compared with the nominees,
have a 37% higher rate of death,
the higher mortality rate here, and it is
statistically significant.
Then they went on and tried to adjust for
all of these different confounders that
you see listed here.
And you can see that as they adjust for
confounders, the hazard ratio really
doesn't budge much.
And they finally at the end adjust for all
the potential confounders at once.
The hazard ratio there is 1.35.
So basically there was no change in the
hazard ratio, at least adjusting for
these confounders.
The ones that they had.
We couldn't explain away the effect by
confounding.
And there maybe unmeasured confounders
that they were unable to adjust for here.
There also have been some legitimate
concerns brought up
about these particular analyses.
I'm not going to go into these, those in,
in this course.
I'm just going to leave it as a kind of a
fun example of Cox regression
and Kaplan-Meier.
Alright.
Now, let's dive into the nitty-gritty
details of the Cox regression model.
So just to review, we talked last week
about linear regression, so
let me draw the linear regression picture
now.
The linear regression,
we were trying to say something about the
relationship of a predictor x.
That could be a binary, categorical, or
continuous predictor.
Here I'm showing a continuous predictor.
We were trying to say that the
relationship between that predictor and
some outcome variable y.
In a linear regression we were just
directly modeling y itself.
We were fitting a line to a scatter plot
like this.
So our model was just that y.
Can be predicted as alpha plus beta x as
the equation of a line.
And of course, we could put more than 1
beta x in the model.
But this is a very simple picture of
linear regression.
We have an intercept, we have a slope, so
we fit a line directly to these data, that
was linear regression.
Logistic regression which I told,
told you about earlier this week was
actually very similar.
Because if you look at the right hand side
of the equation it's,
it's exactly the same.
We have an alpha plus beta x and
we're taking some predictor x, whether it
be binary, categorical or continuous.
And again I'm going to draw the picture
where its continuous, and
we're trying to fit a line to some outcome
variable.
Now, the complication here,
is that the outcome variable from logistic
regression is a binary predictor.
And we're not going to model directly to
the binary predictor.
We're going to a little transformation of
We're going to model the outcome here as
the logit of our binary outcome,
that's the log odds of getting the
outcome.
So, we fit a line to logit in logistic
regression for binary outcomes.
But it's still fitting a line.
Same basic idea, the beta by the way from
logistic regression as I've told you.
If you exponentiate that, that just gave
you the odds ratio.
So, what we got out at the end of the day
was an odds ratio.
But the regression pictures look pretty
similar and
then let's add to that now Cox regression.
So Cox regression not surprisingly looks
kind of similar,
the right hand side of the regression
equation.
Looks pretty much like linear regression,
logisitic regression.
And again you can add more beta's and more
x's if you do multivariable.
So the only question then for
Cox regression is what goes on the
left-hand side of that equation.
so, what are, what's the outcome variable
that we're actually modeling and
fitting a line to for Cox Regression.
So, again, we have some predictor x, what
are we trying to link it to.
So what we are trying to link it to for
Cox regression is actually.
The a, something called a hazard rate.
So I'm going to tell you in more detail
what a hazard rate is in a minute.
But a hazard rate is basically your
instantaneous incidence rate.
So it's just the rate at which events are
occurring.
Now, technically, we're actually the
outcome variable here
is the natural log of the hazard rate.
So just as with logistic regression, which
ended up involving a natural log,
we add a little natural log because of
the hazard rate itself can only go from 0
to positive infinity.
We would like y to range from negative
infinity to positive infinity.
So by dropping on a natural log there, we
then the hazard that can
go that quantity can go from negative to
positive infinity.
So it's just for
mathematical reasons that we end up
actually modeling the log hazard rate.
The log has nice mathematical properties.
Again, while we're just fitting a line.
We're linking.
We're seeing whether or not x can predict
the log hazard rate.
Okay.
So, notice that Cox regression looks a lot
like all the other regression techniques.
All the kinds of things we've talked about
are going to apply here.
So first of all, it has to be linear.
In terms of, you know, if you have a
continuous predictor it
has to have a linear relationship with the
natural log of hazard rate.
That's a little difficult to test and I'm
not going to get into that in this module,
but just kind of keep that in the back of
your mind.
The, If you want to put a categorical
variable,
you're going to be doing dummy coding.
Sort of, you can put interactions in, in
the same way that we talked about.
Everything else is kind of the same.
The beta for, for Cox regression is
going to end up,
as I mentioned, translating into a hazard
ratio.
So it's actually, if you exponentiate the
beta from a Cox regression,
you end up with a hazard ratio.
Let me just say briefly what a hazard rate
is.
So, what is a hazard rate?
Hazard rate is just,
again, the instantaneous rate at which
events are occurring.
The hazard rate, notice that when I wrote,
write down the hazard rate,
I'm always writing this h and then in
parentheses, t.
That, what I'm saying there, what I mean
by that mathematical symbol
is that the hazard rate is a function of
time.
So, this is where the Cox regression model
gets a little more sophisticated than the,
the other models we've talked about so
far.
We are following people over time when we
have a time to event outcome.
And so the hazard rate itself, what we're
modeling here is, it's a something that's
allowed to change over time, potentially,
it could change over time.
So the rate at which events occur don't
have to be constant.
They could be constant, so
your hazard rate could be totally constant
over time, but it doesn't have to be.
You could have a very complicated hazard
rate function, like you're, your.
Event rates could be doing something like
that.
So that's actually what we're modeling in
a Cox regression model.
It's this instantaneous hazard rate which
is a ilttle complicated because it's
allowed to change over time.
At the end of the day, though, you're
going to see in a minute that we,
end up, because it's hard to model that.
It could be a very complicated function.
We actually end up deciding to avoid
modeling the hazard rate itself,
the absolute value.
What we end up doing instead, in Cox
regression, is the following.
We just say, well, all we really want to
do at the end of the day is compare
different risk factors, compare different
groups.
So as long as the basic hazard rate
function is the same between two groups,
so let's say we have smokers and we want
to
compare them to non-smokers on the rate
of, say, the development of lung cancer.
Something like that.
Or hypertension, or whatever the outcome
might be.
If we were actually able to measure the
hazard rate at every instant maybe we
could plot it and it looks like that, that
top curve for
smokers, that bottom curve for non
smokers.
Well that's pretty hard to estimate.
Right?
This might be some complicated curve and,
and specifying that curve exactly is
going to be hard.
So what we do instead in Cox Regression is
we just say,
well you know what I don't really care too
much what that underlying curve is,
whatever its complicated function might
be.
What I care about is the difference in the
hazard rate between
smokers and nonsmokers.
So, what we end up modeling instead, is
just that the difference in those curves.
And then, one assumption, what we're
going to make.
Is that we're going to assume that that
difference in the relative difference in
those two curves, is constant over time.
That's what's called the proportional
hazards assumption.
So no matter what that underlying hazard
rate function is, we're going to
assume that the difference between smokers
and non-smokers does not change over time.
So that we can estimate a single hazard
ratio that
represents the relative risk for smokers
versus non-smokers.
So that's what we're going to do at the
end of the day.
And that gets rid of having, us having to
deal with the very complicated function of
the actual hazard rate itself.
In mathematical terms, just to tell you
very specifically what
the hazard function is, you can specify
this a the limit here.
I'll leave that for those of you who like
that kind of thing.
But in words, the hazard function is just
the probability that if you
make it up until this instant T, that
you're going to succumb to the event,
whatever it is, in the next instant.
So literally, it's the instantaneous
incident rate.
It's the instantaneous rate at which
events are occurring.
And because it's instantaneous, again,
it's allowed to change over time.
It could completely change over time.
So, the Cox regression model has, looks
like the following.
Again, we're modeling the natural log of
this hazard rate that's allowed to
change over time.
And again, the little key here just means
that this function.
This is a complicated outcome, 'cuz it's
allowed to change over time.
We're modeling that as some intercept,
which I'm representing here as.
The, the as a base line hazard rate.
So this is a,
kind of just like, for every, for, if you
had a 0 for all the x's in the model.
This would considered to be the starting
point for the hazard rate.
And what we're assuming again, is that
everybody sort of has the.
The same underlying shape here.
And we're actually not going to try to
estimate this.
It's in the model implicitly, but we're
going to avoid estimating it.
And, then, we have this linear function of
betas and
x's, same as we did with logistic and, and
linear regression.
So again, we're going to take, we'll allow
this hazard rate function to take on
any form, just avoid estimating it which
is a great thing.
We going to estimate these betas?
The betas have a direct translation.
If you exponentiate these betas they are
hazard ratios so that's kind of nice.
So, what we're getting out of the model is
something simple at the end of the day.
Even though what's going on underneath
might be kind of complicated.
Let me just show you how it is that those
betas have
a translations as a as a hazard ratio.
It's sort of similar when I showed you
that the betas from
logistic regression have a translation as
an odds ratio.
Where does that come from?
How do we arrive there?
So let me just show you that.
I'm going to start with a binary
predictor.
So let's start with, let's say we're doing
a Cox regression, and
the model that we run, again, the outcome
is this natural log and
it has a ratio there's some intercepts.
The natural log of the baseline hazard
function that we're
actually going to kind of avoid estimating
but
I'll just, I'll write it in there for now
to show you that it's going to cancel out.
And let's say that we're modeling say lung
cancer, and
we have two predictors in the model.
I'm going to have a beta for smoking.
And I'll make that a binary variable,
smoker or not smoker.
And I'm going to have a beta for age and
that's going to be a continuous predictor.
So I have those two predictors in the
model.
Well, what is a hazard ratio?
A hazard ratio is a ratio of two hazard
rates.
So, the hazard rate for one type of person
divided by the hazard rate for
another type of person.
So say I want to get the hazard ratio for
smoking versus non smoking.
Smokers versus non smokers.
I want to get the hazard ratio for lung
cancer, which is our outcome here.
If I fit this Cox regression model, I'll
get out a beta for smoking and
a beta for age.
So if I then wanted to get to the fact
that is a hazard ratio here,
I can exponentiate both sides of the model
to get rid of this natural log.
So that's what I'm doing here.
Get rid of the natural logs, and we see
that the hazard rate for
a smoker is going to be this base line
hazard function right here.
And then e raised to beta smoking,
whatever value that turns out to,
to have in the model plus beta age.
And then I'm just going to, I'm going to
pick an age here.
So I, I don't care.
I don't want to get the hazard ratio for
age yet.
So I'm just going to say that I want to
compare a 60 year old in
the numerator to a 60 year old in the
denominator.
I could pick any age here, as long as I'm
holding that constant.
That's what statistical adjustment means.
It means that I'm holding that covariant
age constant.
Then I'm going to in the denominator.
I'm going to have a nonsmoker of the same
age, and what you can show is this is
according to my Cox regression model, this
is the hazard for
a nonsmoker in the denominator, a hazard
for a smoker in the numerator.
The baseline hazards will cancel.
The betas for age will also cancel because
I'm holding those fixed.
So we're left with that the hazard ratio
for, for
smokers is just the whatever the beta for
smoking is exponentiated.
So that turns out to be the hazard ratio
for smoking adjusted for age.
For a continuous predictor for age, it's
the same logic.
So now the only thing is that I would hold
smoking fix.
So the smoking variable's going to cancel.
I can have two nonsmokers or two smokers.
Again, the baseline hazard we're going to
assume is the same for everybody.
And then I can put an older person in the
numerator,
compared to a younger person in the
denominator.
Here I'm looking at a ten unit jump in
age.
If I multiply the beta for age by ten and
then exponentiate.
That will give me the hazard ratio for
lung cancer for
a ten-unit increase in age.
Very similar to the logic we went through,
in getting a,
an odds ratio, an adjusted odds ratio, out
of logistic regression.
Now, when you do this all in the computer,
the computer is going to even do the
exponentiation for you and
it's going to give you out that hazard
ratio.
You're not going to have to think through
that.
But I just want to show you,
mathematically, how it is that, that beta
translates to a hazard ratio.
As I mentioned, we have this proportional
hazards assumption.
So whenever you do Cox regression, a very
important thing to do is
actually to test the proportional hazards
assumption.
And it's just easiest to show this with a
picture again.
So imagine that the hazard rate as a
function of time differs for
smokers and nonsmokers.
And I'm just making this function up
completely, but
let's say here's non-smokers and here's
smokers.
The proportional hazards assumption says
that it doesn't matter what that
underlying shape of the hazard function
is.
But what we need is that the difference
between smokers and
non-smokers always has to be this same.
And that's because at the end of the day,
we report a single hazard ratio for
smoking, and that, the assumption is that
that's constant over time.
So we have to test that assumption.
It turns out to be not easy to directly
plot the hazard rate itself.
We'll, we do something else called a log
log plot, and
the, if the log plot, if the lines are
parallel in a log log plot,
that would imply that the proportional
hazards assumption is met.
If the lines are not parallel,
that implies that the proportional hazard
assumptions is not met.
And this is just one of many ways that we
can test proportional hazards.
Again, this module is really meant to
serve as an introduction to
Cox regression.
So let me just show you a log-log plot,
because it's probably the simplest way to
test for proportional hazards.
So here is a log-log plot where you can
see that the lines are kind of crossing in
the two groups.
This is a, you know, a treatment versus a
placebo group here, or, or
two different treatments.
And you can see that the orange line and
green lines kind of cross.
So this was an example from a study where
we did not meet proportional hazards for
this predictor treatment, versus, one
treatment versus another.
Because the lines seem to cross, so they
don't seem to be truly parallel lines.
I'll show you an example in a minute where
we do seem to meet proportional hazards.
And, it's not only by looking at this plot
that I know that I have some other test
proportional hazards that I can look at to
kind of back up my intuition on
just looking at this plot.
I want to just end here with an example
that I showed showed you when we
did the unit on Kaplan-Meyer curves,
we showed you an example looking at
patterns with hepatitis.
Some were given a steroid and some were
given a control.
The control group is in red and
they died off much faster than he people
who were given the steroid.
So, clearly, the steroid was quite
effective here,
as we saw, the Kaplan-Meyer statistic, the
log range statistic here,
was significant, and those curve
definitely look different.
So what I'm going to add to that Kaplan
Meyer now.
As I'm going to show you the Cox
regression results from just that simple
analysis comparing the two groups.
And again, we could when we do Cox
regression also adjust for other things.
But I just want to show you some simple
output from a computer for
from Cox regression.
So when I run those data in my computer in
a Cox regression I get a model out.
Now notice, very interesting here, think
about
the difference between the output I showed
you from linear regression and
logistic regression, there is no intercept
here.
And that's the whole point, right?
With Cox Regression, we don't estimate
that intercept.
So you actually, in your output,
will not get an intercept, because your
not estimating.
But you do get a hazard ratio, and you get
a p value.
And so
when I compare treatment versus control in
this case, I get a significant p value.
The Log-Rank test was significant so
it makes sense that this p value would
also be significant.
And we also quantify the effect.
The hazard ratio is 0.43 indicating about
a 57% decrease
in the mortality rate for those on on the
drug, on the steroid here.
And then finally, if we're running a Cox
regression,
we would want to test proportional
hazards.
We can run very easily, most computer
programs will easily generate for
you the log-log plot, so I did generate
the log-log plot here.
So this is the, control group on the top,
the treatment group on the bottom here.
And, again, we're looking for parallel
lines.
Now, those lines are not perfectly
parallel, but they're pretty close to
parallel, so I would probably look at that
log-log plot and say.
Well, they're, they're pretty close, so
I'm going to assume that proportional
hazards are met here.
And again there are many other tests that
we use to test proportional hazards, and
that's just one of them.
I just want to as introduce you to it as a
way of introduction.