In this next module,
I'm going to talk about the alternative
test that you can use.
Instead of the ttest and
ANOVA, when you violate the assumptions of
ttest and ANOVA.
These are called non-parametric tests.
I'm going to be talking in this module
about Wilcoxon sign-rank,
Wilcoxon rank-sum and Kruskal-Wallis test.
These are all what's called non-parametric
statistics.
And all we mean by non-parametric is that
we're not estimating any parameters.
So, when you do a ttest or ANOVA, you're
estimating the means in
those different groups and the standard
deviations in those different groups.
We're not going to be estimating any
parameters like that in the Wilcoxon and
the Kruskal-Wallis test.
We're just going to get a p-value at the
end of the day.
So, there won't be any estimation
involved, only hypothesis testing.
So, I'll start here with the Wilcoxon
rank-sum test.
Because actually, in very,
the very first week of this course, we saw
a Wilcoxon rank-sum test.
So, I'm going to use that same example
now.
The Wilcoxon rank-sum test is used as the
alternative to the two sample ttest.
When you have a small sample, and you have
a non-normally distributed outcome.
So, if you have a small sample and
it looks like your outcome variable is not
normally distributed.
You might choose to, instead of running a
ttest, to run a Wilcoxon rank-sum test.
Remember that we had this hypothetical
weight loss trial that I showed you in
the very first week of the course.
Ten dieters were randomized to follow diet
one, and
ten dieters were randomly assigned to
follow diet two.
Group one lost an average of 34.5 pounds.
Group two lost an average of 18.5 pounds.
And you might just look at those numbers,
and think that diet one is better.
The mean is higher, the mean weight loss
is higher in group one.
That would be a natural conclusion, but
let's look at the data more closely.
When you look at the histogram for diet
two,
turns out that the mean was a loss of 18.5
pounds, the median is a loss of 19 pounds.
It's pretty even, you know, it's not
exactly a normal curve, but
it might be close enough to a normal
distribution.
However, when you look at the histogram,
the raw data from diet one.
It turns out that there was one person in
that group of ten, who lost 300 pounds.
So, the mean weight loss was huge, 34.5
pounds.
But that's mostly driven by that one
person.
The median loss was only 4.5 pounds.
If you were to look at these data and were
to analyze these data using a two
sample ttest, you would not find a
significant difference between the groups.
Now, let's look at the raw data.
Here's diet one.
We can actually look at the numbers
because there's only 10
people in each diet.
And here's the weight loss in pounds, the
change in weight in pounds.
So, for example, one person gained four
pounds, one person lost 300 pounds,
that's for diet one.
For diet two, here are the changes in
weights.
You'll notice that if you look at the raw
data,
there's a much more consistent weight loss
in diet two.
If I were going to be recommending a diet
to patient it
seems like everybody in diet two lost a
pretty good chunk of weight.
Whereas, diet one it was much more
variable, one person did great.
But there were a lot of people who didn't
do as terrific on diet one.
So if I'm looking at the data now, I might
just intuitively,
instinctively think well diet two seems
somewhat better.
We can actually apply a statistical test
to evaluate which diet is better.
We're going to apply something called the
Wilcoxon rank-sum test.
It's also sometimes called the
Mann-Whitney U test.
I would prefer the term Wilcoxon rank-sum
test,
because rank-sum test tells you exactly
what it does.
You rank the data and then you sum it.
So, we want to know if there is a
difference in
weight loss between the two diets.
The outcome variable is weight change.
It is a continuous variable.
However, it is not a normally distributed
variable.
If you look at those histograms, there is
a huge left tail for diet one.
So, it might have been normally
distributed, but
we had that one outlier which made it a
non-normal distribution.
We have a small n, only 10 in each group.
So, we have to worry about the normality
assumption here.
A ttest is not going to be appropriate
here.
It's also not going to be appropriate to
just throw out the one weight,
the one person who lost a lot of weight in
diet one.
Because that person's a real person who
lost a lot of weight,
we want to give them credit for that.
We don't want to just throw out that
outlier.
But Wilcoxon rank-sum test can keep the
outlier in.
Are the observations correlated?
No, we have independent groups here.
Are groups being compared?
Yes, and how many are being compared?
There's two groups.
Normally we would, if it weren't for the
violation of the normal,
the normality assumption, we would be
doing a two sample ttest.
But, because we've violated the normality
assumption here,
our outcome variable is not normally
distributed.
We have have small n, we're going to
choose for the Wilcoxon rank-sum test.
Again, another it is also called the
Mann-Whitney U test, those are equivalent.
So, first up in the rank-sum test is just
to rank the data.
We're going to take all, everybody, and
we're going to ignore the group they're in
the for the moment.
We're going to order the diets.
Order the weight losses ignoring diet.
So, we're going to order from the worst
weight loss, to the best weight loss.
The person who lost the least is the
person who gained four pounds.
They get a rank of one.
The person who did the best,
the person who lost 300 pounds, they get a
rank of 20.
Then, we rank everybody else in between.
Again, ignoring groups.
So, the ranks both groups can have, both a
sense of ranks.
You'll notice just looking at the ranks,
that most of the high ranks go to diet
two.
So we rank the data, ignoring which group
people are in,
from the lowest to the highest 1 to 20.
Notice, that we are including the person
who lost the 300 pounds.
They're getting the highest credit.
They're getting that highest rank of 20.
But a difference between, the difference
between 19 and 20 is much,
much smaller than the difference between
negative 30 and negative 300.
So, that outlier is not having so much
Influence here.
By looking at ranks data,
we're essentially comparing the medians
rather than comparing the means.
We then sum the ranks within each group.
So, we're going to sum the ranks for group
one, comes out to be 73.
We're going to sum the ranks for group
two, that comes out to be 137.
The one with the bigger sum of the rank is
going to be the better diet.
What the Wilcoxon rank-sum test then does
is it looks at those
sums of the ranks, and tells you whether
or not they're statistically different.
This is a little tricky if you have
different sample sizes, right?
What if one group only had five people and
the other group had 20 people.
Well, of course, the sum of the ranks is
going to be higher for the bigger group.
So, the Wilcoxon rank-sum test accounts
for differences in sample sizes as well.
Theory of the same sample size.
You just need to answer the question, is
137 statistically different than 73?
And in fact, when we apply that test,
it does turn out that the p-value here
comes out to be statistically significant.
It actually shows us that diet two is
superior to diet one,
despite the fact that the mean weight loss
was higher in diet one.
So, by applying the correct statistical
test here,
we are able to say that diet two is
superior.
I'm not going to go into the nitty gritty
details of the actual
mathematical calculations of
distinguishing that 73 from that 170, 37.
If you want the details on that, there is
an optional material on that for you.
Now, I want to briefly review the Wilcoxon
sign-rank test.
This is the non-parametric alternative to
the paired ttest.
Recall that we talked last week about a
randomized trial DHA oil to treat eczema.
Here's a table, a figure from that trial.
I showed you part B from that trial last
week.
There is a bunch of p-values on this
figure,
and you can see where do those p-values
come from?
Well, these are showing the p-values for
whether or
not the placebo group and the DHA group.
The control group and the DHA group.
Whether or not their score add scores,
went down at all a significant amount over
time.
So, all the p values I've circled here
came from Wilcoxon sign-rank tests.
So, when you're doing the within group
comparison,
over time those p-values come from the
Wilcoxon sign-rank test.
Here, we were comparing only week zero to
week eight, so
we're actually only comparing two time
points.
The score add index, the score add score
turns out to be non-normally distributed.
Our sample size was small here.
We only had 53 people, so we're going to
want to use a non-parametric equivalent to
the pair ttest, rather than use the pair
ttest.
So again, how did I get there?
I wanted to know whether or not the
patients improved in SCORAD score from
baseline to eight weeks, just two time
points.
The outcome variable's SCORAD, the
severity score of eczema.
It is a continuous variable, but it is not
normally distributed, and
we they have small numbers, so we cannot
apply a ttest here.
Are the observations correlated?
Yes, it's the same people before and
after.
So, we also have correlated data here.
So, we would normally do a paired ttest.
But because we violated the normality
assumption,
we're going to use the non-parametric
equivalent to the pair ttest,
which is the Wilcoxon sign-rank test.
There's only two time points being
compared,
which is why we can used a pair two test
or a Wilcoxon sign-rank test.
The mechanics or the Wilcoxon sign-rank
test just briefly,
it's very similar to the Wilcoxon rank-sum
test.
It's going to involve some ranking.
Except this time, it's sort of, [COUGH]
we're going to be looking at signs,
the signs, rather than at two groups.
So, you're going to calculate the change
in SCORAD score for each participant.
So, just like what you do for
the pair ttest, everybody has an
improvement score, change score.
You then rank the absolute values of the
changes in SCORAD score,
from the smallest to the largest.
So, the person who had
the biggest absolute change would get the
biggest rank.
We're ignoring sign for
the minute, [COUGH] the null hypothesis
here is that there's no change.
We're ignoring sign for the minute.
We would then add up the ranks, sum up the
ranks from the people who improved.
That's the people who would have a
negative sign.
And we would add up the ranks from the
people who got worse.
That's the people who had a positive sign.
So, that's where the sign part comes in.
We're comparing people who improved to
people who got worse.
Does either sum of the ranks dominate.
The Wilcoxon sign-rank test compares these
values to determine
whether the improvements significantly
exceeded the declines or vice versa.
Remember, the null hypothesis here is that
there is no change.
So, we just want to know if there is a
significant change in either direction,
either going up or going down.
If we, and under the null, you'd expect
there is some of
the ranks to be about equal for the
negatives as for the positives.
If you violate the null, if you reject the
null, that would suggest that there
was either a significant improvement or a
significant decline.
And all we're asking in this particular
example is whether or
not there was a significant improvement
over time, in the DHA group alone or
in the control group alone.
So, and we saw that, indeed, these
p-values the p-value for
the DHA group from the Wilcoxon sign-rank
test,
that p-value comes from the Wilcoxon
sign-rank test.
That came out significant the p-value from
the Wilcoxon sign-rank test
applied just to the control group, did not
come out significant.
So, those within group change was
significant for the DHA group, but
not significant for the control group.
But, the p-value that really mattered here
is not the within group changes,
but the p-value we should have cared about
here is the between group difference.
Did the DHA group improve more than the
control group?
To get that p-value, we had to apply a
Wilcoxon rank-sum test.
The between group to compare the two
groups and
their improvement in SCORAD scores, and
that came out to be non-significant.
So, as we said, even though within group
improvement, it,
it is significant in one group but not the
other.
It doesn't mean that the between group
differences are going to be significant.
And they weren't here.
All of those were done.
All those p-value were done by
non-parametric because the SCORAD score is
not normally distributed.
Finally if you want, if you want to do
compare two or
more groups, and you have a non normally
distributed outcome variable.
The non non-parametric equivalent to the
ANOVA is
something called the Kruskal-Wallis test.
And it basically, I'm not going to go over
the mechanics,
because it basically works in the exact
same way as the Wilcoxon rank-sum test.
You're going to rank everybody ignoring
group, and
then your going to sum up the ranks within
the groups and sum outcome.