Welcome to our module on creating graphics
and SAS Enterprise Guide.
As you're probably learning in your HRP
classes, data visualization is really
important when you're doing epidemiology
and clinical research.
>> There may be times that patterns are
too difficult to
interpret simply by looking at the numbers
in a table.
In situations like this, graphics can
become extremely essential.
>> That being said, there are important
differences between good and bad graphics.
Graphics can be really helpful if they
highlight the key points,
if they're clearly labeled and they don't
contain unnecessary information.
>> Generally, make sure your graphics
related to your conclusions and
inferences made in the study.
Overall, bad graphics consist of pie
charts.
>> Anything that's 3D or too much ink.
>> Anything shaped like a donut, and
graphs that are stacked.
>> Here's a 3D exploding pie chart.
This is a pretty bad graphic for a lot of
reasons.
First of all it's 3D, so the first
perspective can make it hard to
tell the difference between stuff in the
foreground versus the background.
In general, graphs like these take up way
too much ink and
it's hard to tell what they're trying to
convey.
Avoid using 3D bar charts like these,
because again the 3D perspective can make
it hard to tell.
Where does the line go?
Is it based on the front of the bar or the
back of the bar?
>> Donuts are similar to pie charts.
They do not give you a lot of information
and they take up a lot of ink.
>> Stacking is really bad because it's
hard to tell the relative size of
the stacked bars, because they don't have
the same baseline.
These graphs combine all the worst
features of the ones we showed you so far.
They're 3D, they're stacked, and they're
using pie charts.
It's really hard to interpret what's going
on and it can be really misleading, and
it's not very clear what they're trying to
convey with this kind of graphic.
>> As Dr. Ray Belise said, if you get a
glossy handout with a 3D pie chart,
assume someone is lying to you.
SASS enterprise has many procedures for
graphing we will be using PROC SG plot and
proc G plot.
>> There are endless changes that can be
made to graphics an entire course can be
dedicated to SASS syntax for graphics.
In the following modules we're going to
show you the basic code for
the essential graphics and once we're done
with this we'll let you out on
your own to work with a SASS
documentation.