Hi and welcome to the final module on data
steps.
At this point you should have all the
tools that you need to start managing your
own data sets using data steps.
Here's a review.
>> Remember, you always start a data step
with the word data and
you end it with the word run.
And never forget, you always have to end
yours lines with a semi-colon.
You can use a data line statement to
manually generate a data set by
specifying a specific values like we've
done here.
You can also use the point and
click to import a data set like we showed
you earlier.
You can use a set statement to fill in
data from another data set that you
have already imported.
>> Keep and drop statements will let you
prune down the columns.
Here we've stated drop weight so
that we can create a new data set with the
weight variable dropped.
The retain statement will let you reorder
the variables in your data set.
By writing retain, id, marital and
eversmoke we asked to create a new data
set with these variables listed first.
>> You can use IF-THEN-ELSE statements.
To create new variables or do complex
tasks under a specific conditions.
You can use SELECT-END statements to do
the same thing while also checking to
make sure you have considered every case
in your data set.
>> And that's all you need to know for
now.
Coming up next, SAS procedures