[BLANK_AUDIO]
Welcome to week three of Statistics in
Medicine.
This week, I'm going to introduce you to
probability theory,
including conditional probability, and
Bayes' rule.
And we're going to apply these concepts in
the clinical context of
diagnostic testing.
Now, I just want to warn you that
probability is
an extremely challenging topic.
In fact, my Stanford students usually find
the probability component of this course,
to be one of the most challenging parts of
the course.
My goal here is just to familiarize you
with some basic concepts in probability,
and to give you the tools to be able to
calculate some simple probabilities.
I do not expect you to gain complete
mastery in probability through a,
a one week set of modules.
Probability is the kind of thing that you
would need to take an entire course and
do hundreds of practice problems before
you could really gain complete mastery.
It's that challenging.
So don't get discouraged if you find that
the material this week seems a little bit
more difficult than the previous weeks,
and
also don't get discouraged if you don't
end the week feeling like you've
got total mastery because that's really
not expected.
Again, I'm just hoping that you'll have a
basic familiarity with the concept of
probability and be able to calculate some
very simple probability.
If you want to delve into some more
advanced calculations, there
are a number of optional modules for you
this week if you want to delve a little
bit deeper into probability theory and you
find these kinds of calculations fun.
going to just start with two teasers for
this week.
So the first one is a classic statistics
problem.
So if you've taken a course in statistics
before,
you may have encountered this problem
previously.
But it's called the Monty Hall Problem and
it goes like this.
You're on, a game show, the Monty Hall
Gameshow, and
your host Monty Hall shows you three
doors, and behind one of these doors is
some kind of fabulous prize like a new car
or a trip around the world.
Behind the other two doors is nothing or
some kind of booby prize.
So, you get to pick one of the doors, and
lets say you pick door A to start with.
And you want to see what's behind door A,
well then Monty Hall says,
well I'm going to show you that there's
nothing behind door B.
So he shows you behind door B, so that's
no longer an option.
Now, he gives you the option of either
sticking with door A,
your sort of original gut feeling or
switching to door C.
Do you want to stay with door A, or
do you want to switch to door C, you have
that option.
And the question here is,
should you stick with A, or should you
switch to C, or, does it not matter?
And in fact the answer to this one is a
little bit counter intuitive.
We're going to come back to this in a
couple of modules.
The second teaser for this week has to do
with the Cellulite DX test.
And it's a genetic test for moderate to
severe cellulite.
The idea is that a young woman would take
this test, and if she finds out that
she's at increased risk of moderate to
severe cellulite, she would, she could do
something to maybe prevent that cellulite
from developing later in her life.
So this company has de, has identified a
genetic variant that seems to
be linked to moderate to severe cellulite
in women.
So you can take the test, and
find out if you carry this genetic
variant, and here's the company's pitch in
terms of the information that this test is
going to give you.
So a patient who tests positive has
approximately a 70% chance of
developing moderate to severe cellulite.
So, so if a women tests positive that
sounds like a high probability,
she might want to then intervene and do
something about it.
Now, a patient who tests negative,
has approximately a 50% chance of not
developing moderate to sever cellulite.
And I think that's supposed to be
reassuring.
So, the question we're going to try to
answer about this genetic test is,
is it useful?
Is this information, from a positive or a
negative test, is it really useful?
And if you look carefully at the numbers
I've already given you,
you can start to really answer that
question.
But it turns out that it gets even a
little more interesting than
what I'm showing you here.
It's a pretty amusing example.
So this is something we're going to return
to in the last module for this week so,
stick with it, get through the hard
probability stuff and the last module this
week has a pretty fun and amusing example
that you have to look forward to.
[BLANK_AUDIO]