In this next module, I'm going to show you
how linear regression accommodates
categorical predictors, and I'll also show
you the link between T-tests and
ANOVA and linear regression.
So how does linear regression handle
categorical predictors?
In the case of a binary predictor, it's
actually really easy.
In the very first week of this course, I
talked a lot about binary variables,
and thinking about them as 0, 1 as new
miracle variables.
Well, that becomes useful now.
Because the way that we handle binary
variables is just to put them in
the linear regression model and treat them
as numbers as in 0 and a 1.
And that makes it easy to model and I'll
show you the picture in a minute.
Categorical variables are just slightly
more tricky.
These are variables that have more than
two categories.
We are essentially going to turn them into
a series of binary, of 0, 1 variables,
and that's the way we're going to
accommodate them in the regression module.
We call this dummy coding and
I'm going to get to this dummy coding idea
in a few minutes.
But let's start with the easier case, with
the binary case.
Imagine for a moment that I wanted to use
vitamin D as a binary predictor.
We've been talking about this example all
week where I've been
treating vitamin D as a continuous
predictor.
But there might be some reason that I end
up wanting to treat vitamin D
as a binary predictor.
Maybe I didn't measure, maybe in for some
reason my datas that I don't have it as
the continuous predictor or maybe for some
reason I'm clinically interested in
comparing the insufficient group to the
sufficient group.
So for whatever reason I'm using this
vitamin D as binary predictor.
If I look at my data set, and let's say
this is an arbitrary, but it was a less a,
less than 50 nanomoles per liter, it has
some clinical reasons for
calling that insufficient, more than that,
we'll call that sufficient.
We're going to code this insufficient
variable as a 1, 0, so if you're a 1,
that means you're in the insufficient
group.
If you're a 0, that means you're in the
sufficient group, you know,
I actually looked in my data set and the
mean DSSTs for
the mean cognitive score in the
insufficient group indeed was lower.
That in the sufficient group it was 32.5
and in the sufficient group it was 40.
Now, you might just think about the
lectures that we had last week, and
you might say oh well, here I've got a
situation where I have a continuous,
normally distributed outcome variable.
I've got two groups I want to compare.
I want to compare the means of that
continuous variable between two groups.
Why wouldn't I just use the t-test here?
And indeed, you absolutely could use a
t-test here.
I'm going to show you how to also use
linear regression to analyze this
same data.
And then, I'll show you how the liner
regression and
the t-test actually give you identical
answers.
Let me graph this for you.
So again, we're treating our, our binary
variable as a 0, 1 variable.
So, 1 means you're in the insufficient
group,
0 means you're sufficient, you're in the
normal level group.
The linear regression line here is the
easiest possible line you can draw.
So what I'm showing you here, these little
individual points represent all of
the DSST levels for all the people in the
normal group.
Their mean level is right here at 40, that
was the mean in
the in the normal group, the vitamin D
insufficient group over here,
this is all their DSST levels, their mean
as I mentioned was 32.5.
So what's this line?
All I did to draw this line was connect
the two means.
It's really, it's like the simplest line
you can possibly draw.
Any two points, you can connect them and
draw a line and
it's, we don't have to test the linearity
assumption here,
because when you have two points, it's
automatically going to make a line.
So that's nice.
The intercept of this line as you can see
here is 40.
What's the slope of this line going to be?
Well, the x variable only goes from 0 to
1, so there's only a one unit change in x.
What happens to y when x goes from 0 to 1?
Well, y goes from 40 down to 32.5.
So the slope of this line is going to be
40 minus 32.5 or 7.5.
Notice that that's just the difference in
means between the two groups.
I then took these data, and
actually ran them officially in a linear
regression program.
And indeed, not surprisingly, what I get
out in the model is,
here is my parameter estimates.
So the, the intercept is 40 and the
difference in means, the,
the beta here is negative 7.5,
because we're decreasing as we're going
from sufficient to insufficient.
It's highly statistically significant as
you can see.
This is just given back the equation of
this line, we could also kind of
look at the graph again to, to see the
equation of that line.
Again, the intercept represents the mean
value in the sufficient group.
The slope here just represents the
difference in
means between the two groups and it is
statistically significant.
Now, I want to show you, what if, what
would have happened had we just ran these
data in a t-test rather than bothering to
get fancy and run a linear regression?
Well, we would have got the same answer.
Again, and we have two groups, we want to
compare means.
We can evaluate these data with a t-test.
It turns out that the slope we get from
linear regression is exactly equal to
the difference in means, which is the
effect of size of interest for a t-test.
And the p-values we get out are also I,
exactly identical.
So here's the t-test that we would run.
We would, in the numerator goes the
difference in means,
again, which is 40 minus 32.5 or 7.5.
We can calculate this standard error in
the denominator.
That turns out to be the same standard
error that you get in
the linear regression model on the earlier
slide.
The t-value comes out to be 3.46, the
p-value comes out to be 0.0008.
And actually, if you look at the previous
slide,
you can see that that is the t-value and
the p-value from the linear regression.
So there's nothing new here
mathematically, a t-test and
a linear regression are exactly the same.
You could say we don't even really need to
have a t-test in the world, because you
could always run that problem, that
particular problem in linear regression.
It's just of course, that linear
regression is more, you know,
seems more complicated and a t-test seems
very simple.
So a lot of times if it, we have the
simplest problem,
we end up just defaulting to t-test rather
than calling it a linear regression.
But in fact, a t-test is a special case of
linear regression.
Now, I'm going to move to the more tricky
concept,
which is what to do when you have more
than two categories?
You have a categorical predictor
with more than two categories.
What we're going to have to do here is to
do some dummy coding.
We're going to translate our categories
into a series of binary variables,
so that we can deal again with binary
variables.
So, what what if our vitamin D variable
had been
a categorical predictor rather than a
continuous predictor?
What if there were three levels we cared
about?
The deficient, that's like the really low
people,
insufficient kind of mildly low and, and
sufficient.
Sometimes people will divide it up this
way.
I want to know about the difference in
DSST scores between those three groups.
I could analyze those data then with an
ANOVA, a simple ANOVA as we
talked about last week, and I also could
analyze it with linear regression.
So let me just tell you what the means.
The mean DSST score in all these three
groups were.
So the sufficient group,
the normal groups is still the same here,
the average was still 40.
The insufficient group now excludes the
ones who are lower than 25.
So the average in that group is now 33.13.
And in the deficient group, it turns out
that the mean DSST score is 30.13.
So it does seem to go down across those
groups.
How do we dummy code this?
How do we dummy code these three
categories?
So here's dummy coding.
If I want to take a three-level
categorical variable,
I can represent it as a series of binary
variables.
I actually only need two binary variables
if it's a three-level variable.
If it was a four-level categorical
variable,
I would need three binary variables, and
so on.
There's going to be one group that's the
reference group and
that's going to be the variable that has a
0 on all the, on all the binary variables.
Let me illustrate that here.
So I'm going to make two new variables.
I'm going to create a new variable that is
deficient, Yes or No.
It's binary, you're either in the
deficient category or you're not.
And another one, insufficient, that's a
variable,
another binary, that says your either in
the insufficient group or you're not.
So if you're somebody in the deficient
group,
you're going to get a 1 on the deficient
variable, but
a 0 on the insufficient variable.
If you're in the insufficient group,
you're going to get a 0 on the deficient
group, because you're not,
you're not deficient, but you're going to
get a 1 on the insufficient.
If you're in the sufficient group,
however, you're going to get a 0 on both
of those.
So notice that two binary variables is
sufficient to uniquely identify all
three of those categories.
Now, we have a reference group and we have
a series of binary variable that tell us
about the deficient group and the
sufficient group and
the difference between the insufficient
group and the sufficient group.
How do we represent this in pictures?
So it looks a lot like the pictures we did
for the simple binary predictor.
The insufficient group, the, again the
mean level of DSST for
the insufficient group was about 33, the
mean for the normal group is 40.
That forms a simple line, the intercept is
40, the slope is about negative 7.
For the deficient group, same intercept,
because we're still comparing against the
normal group.
The slope here, the, the mean for the
deficient group is about 30.
So the slope here is almost 10.
Now technically, this is a multivariate
regression because we
now have two predictors in the model.
I could represent these pictures on a
plane, it's just harder to
draw that plane, so I have represented
this as two separate graphs here.
I took though, the data and
I put them into the computer and ask it to
run a linear regression with this dummy,
these dummy coded variables and here are
the results that I get.
So here is my model, here is my key
values.
Again, the intercept represents the mean
value in the reference group.
That's 40, that's the normal growth.
The beta coefficient, the slope for the
insufficient group represents
the difference in the DSST levels between
the normal group and
the insufficient group, the difference
from the reference.
So the insufficient group was about almost
seven units lower in
cognitive score than the normal group.
The deficient group was almost ten units
lower in the cognitive score than
the normal group, so that's the sub for
them.
Both are highly statistically significant.
That's the linear regression equation
written out.
And we can use that to then predict what's
the mean value for
those in the insufficient group, those in
the deficient group, and
those in the the normal group.
And you're going to see that for the
simple model, it's nothing too profound.
The 40 is the mean, in the reference
group.
Negative 6.87 represents the difference of
means between insufficient and
sufficient groups.
Of course then, negative 9.87 represents
the difference in
means between deficient and sufficient
groups.
And you can just show this by applying the
equation.
So, if I've got a person in the deficient
group,
how do I apply this equation to them?
Well, they get they get the intercept.
They get a 0 because they are not an
insufficient group and
they get a 1 for being deficient.
So when you do 40 minus 9.87, that's, that
just gives you
back out what we already knew was the mean
in the the deficient group.
A person in the insufficient group, when
you apply the equation, they get a 1 for
insufficient, a 0 for deficient when you
add that up, it comes out to be 33.13.
Again, what we already knew was the mean
in the insufficient group.
And the person who's in the sufficient
group gets a 0 for
both the insufficient and deficient
variables, so they're just left with 40,
which again, we knew was the mean in the
normal group.
So it, it's a little, like this isn't, you
know,
it's just spitting back out the means.
It doesn't seem all that profound.
It doesn't seem all that useful but the
reason it's
going to be useful is because we might
want to adjust for other variables.
ANOVA is just linear regression.
So the p-value that you would get if you
ran an ANOVA here is exactly the same as
the p-value you're going to get for the
overall model fit for linear regression.
So again mathematically, these things are
identical.
So when you, you, you could argue that you
never need an ANOVA,
you can always just run a linear
regression.