In the last module, we showed you how to
make a data set from scratch.
When you use SAS for your data analysis,
usually is a real data set.
But the methods we showed to you are
useful for
making toy data sets to test things out.
>> The code we showed you last time used
what is called a Data Step,
which is a really important function in
SAS.
Data steps are a group of statements that
always begin with the word data.
Data steps modify data sets one row at a
time.
This means, that if you want to create a
new variable that combines multiple rows
of other variables, data steps are what
you should use.
Data steps could be used to create, and
manipulate data, create new variables.
Find important information and present
your data.
>> When you make changes to your data set,
you don't want to modify the original
copy.
First, I'll show you how to make a
duplicate copy of your data set, so
you could make some changes.
Let's take a look at this code.
First, you make a new data set called
calculations.
You may have noticed I didn't specify any
library like, I did before.
If you don't specify a library for
a data set like this, it'll be made in the
work library by default.
>> So the first line makes a new data set
called calculations,
which is going to be made in the work
library.
The next line, sets the new data set equal
to the people data set we made earlier.
That means that the new data set will have
all the same variables, attributes, and
data as our old one.
And finally, we'll end with the run
statement.
>> When we run this code,
we'll have a copy of our old data set,
which we can make changes to.
Let's run this code.
If we look at a process flow, we can see
that this code icon has an arrow
pointing towards the data set icon, called
calculations.
Let's open it up.
As you can see, it's an exact copy of our
old data set.
We can now do some calculations on
this data set without affecting the
original one.
Let's go back to the code.
As you can see from the code, I've added
in a new variable called weightPlusFive,
weightSquared, weight_in_kg and fun.
>> This is also a good time to say
something about naming conventions in SAS.
As you mentioned before, SAS does not
differentiate between weightSquared
with lowercase and WeightSquared with the
w and s capitalized.
Size is not case sensitive.
So you can use capitals and lowercase
letters to make things easier to read.
You can also use underscores to make it
easier to read,
as in the case with weight in kilograms.
But remember, you can't have any spaces in
your variable names.
Overall, it is important to be consistent
with your naming conventions.
You want other people to be able to read
your code.
>> You can do all sorts of mathematical
operations using data steps.
Let's run this program and look at the
output.
Remember, we set this equal to our old
data set first.
But now we have a new column for each of
the new variables that we made.
Let's look at the column weight plus 5.
Remember, data steps work with data one
row at a time.
Just as we specified in our formula,
each row weight plus 5 column is equal to
the weight column plus 5.
This is similar to the way formulas work
in Excel,
which you've probably seen before.
>> Sometimes, you might have columns in
your data set that you don't need anymore.
Now, I'll show you how to reshuffle the
columns and
remove columns from your data set.
I don't think we need this variable called
weight squared anymore, so
let's remove that column.
>> In this chunk of code, we create a new
data set called dropping columns.
Remember, since I do not specify a
library,
this will be created in the work library
by default.
We set this new data set equal to the
calculations data set that we
made earlier.
Then, the next line of code will drop the
weight squared column from our data set.
If we run the code and look at the output,
we can see that it has everything from
the data calculations data set, except for
the column called weight squared.
>> The data sets we have looked at so far
have been pretty small, but
sometimes you might be working with really
large data sets with dozens of columns and
thousands of rows.
If you need to get rid of a lot of
columns,
it gets really cumbersome to just use the
drop statement.
I'll show you another way to do this.
Here's a data set I imported earlier.
As you can see there are a ton of columns.
Of the 68 columns in this data set, I am
only really interested in working with
the ID numbers, marital status and smoking
status.
Let's write some code to fix that.
>> First, I make a copy of the original
data set, like we have seen before.
I just wanted to mention that you can
specify if a data set is in a work
library, but it is not needed.
This data set is called final_broad.
So, we're making a new data set called
keep columns and
we're setting it equal to the original
data set, final_broad.
While we'd rather keep statement as
specify some variables,
SAS will only keep these columns in our
data set.
Everything else will be removed.
>> Let's run the code and look at the
output.
Now we only have the variables we want.
ID, marital and eversmoke.
>> Sometimes we just want to reorder the
variables and
their data set, we can do that with a
retain statement.
Let me show you the code for doing that.
This time, we're going to make some
changes to an existing data set.
We'll start the data set with the name of
the original data set.
The next line will specify the order of
the variables.
We want the ID to come first, then marital
then eversmoke.
Now we use set final_broad to fill in the
data from the original data set.
The order of this code is really
important.
First, you use retain to specify the order
of the variables,
then you use set to to fill in the data.
If you use set first and then retain, your
code will not work correctly.
>> Let's run the code and look at the
output.
As we can see from the output, we still
have all the columns, but
the ones we want are now all the way to
the left, in the order we specify.
The other columns come afterwards, in
their original order.
This makes it easier to see the variables
we are most interested in,
without having to scroll around a whole
lot.