Finally you often get the question in my
descriptive table one in my paper.
Should I present the means or should I
present the medians?
Well you'll see if you read a lot of the
medical literature,
that most people go with the means.
I think most people feel very comfortable
with the means.
That's what they're typically used to
seeing.
So a lot of authors will present means.
It turns out, however, there are cases, a
lot of cases, actually,
where it would be better to report the
median.
Because if you have skewed data, if you
have extreme values,
as we've seen, those extreme values can
influence, can affect the mean,
and so the mean might be misleading.
Where as the median doesn't get affected
by those extreme values.
So the median might be a better
representation in that case of
the center of the data.
So let me just illustrate that.
I'm going to harken back now to one of the
teasers that I
presented at the beginning of this week.
I had presented some hypothetical data.
About a, a randomized trial on diets.
So that we had,
20 dieters who were randomly assigned to
follow one of two diets.
Let's call them diet one and diet two.
Again, these are hypothetical data, made
to illustrate a point.
But, they're still interesting.
So, it turns out, here is the results of
that trial, as I mentioned in the teaser.
So group one, those on diet one, lost an
average of 34.5 pounds.
Group two lost an average of 18.5 pounds.
So both dieting groups were highly
successful,
these are really good results for a
dieting trial.
But if you were just to look at those
numbers, you'd probably say oh well,
if I've got patients and I want to figure
out what diet to put them on,
based on these numbers I think I'm
going to put them on diet one.
Diet one looks better right, if you just
look at the means.
Is diet one better, however?
Well, let's dig down deeper into the data
to answer that question.
So, here's the histogram.
I'm going to start with diet two.
Here's the histogram of the weight loss
from the ten dieters in diet two.
So, as I mentioned the mean was 18.5
pounds, an 18.5 pound loss of weight.
The median was a weight loss of 19 pounds
and
if you graph it on the histogram you can
see that they're pretty well clustered,
everybody's losing some amount of weight
and there the variability isn't very high.
Now let's turn to the histogram for diet
one.
Okay, you can see that this is made up
data, but, you know,
this could really happen.
So here's the histogram from diet one so
what do you notice so.
The mean is weight loss of 34.5 pounds.
But, the median is only a weight loss of
4.5 pounds.
And of course, the reason is,
is that we have this extreme value out at
negative 300.
Somebody was very highly successful on
this diet, and lost 300 pounds.
That 300, that negative 300.
When you average it in with the other nine
values, has a huge influence on the mean;
it completely draws the mean to the right,
and it's a, it's misleading, right?
It makes the mean look much bigger.
The median here is really a better
representation,
because most people weren't losing
anywhere near 30 pounds.
Most people were losing four or five
pounds.
Let me just show you the raw data.
Cause there's only ten data points in each
group so
I can actually show you the raw data.
So here's the raw data from diet one.
Here are the weight losses for diet one.
And I've ordered them from the the least
weight loss to the most weight loss.
For diet two you can see the same thing.
Here are the weight loss, the raw weight
loss values.
Now, if you look at the raw data like
this,
you suddenly get a different feeling for
diet one versus diet two, right.
If you're looking at this raw data, you
might change your mind now and
actually want to recommend diet two for
your patients.
because what you can see is that on diet
one,
one out of ten people lost a huge amount
of weight.
But everybody else's weight loss was non
existent or
moderate, whereas in diet two, everybody
was highly successful.
Everybody lost a good amount of weight so
it was a very, you know, you could see
that it was successful for everybody.
So it changes your opinion when you see
all of the data like that, now.
When you're actually going to analyze this
data, to run a formal statistical test.
We haven't talked about any formal
statistical tests and
we won't get there for another couple of
weeks.
But the way that your, your instinct might
be to compare those
groups by just comparing the means, the
345.5 versus the 18.5 pound weight loss.
If you did that,
you would compare those two means with a
test that we called a T-Test.
Some of you may of heard of.
If you do that you will find.
That there is no significant difference
between the groups.
So what you need to compare in this case
is not the means but
you need to compare the medians.
You need to compare the data using a
ranked data procedure something called
a non-parametric test.
And don't worry to much about this
terminology right now we're going to
talk a lot about non-parametric tests in a
future week.
But some of you may have heard that term
before.
So this is an example,
what I'm going to show you now is an
example of a non-parametric test.
That just means that we're going to be
ranking the,
the data and running tests on the ranks of
the data rather than the raw values.
And it's, the tests that I'm actually
going to run now I'm going to tell you
the name of it only because it has a very
informative name.
It's something called the Wilcoxon
rank-sum test and don't worry about
the details of that yet, we'll return to
that test in another couple of weeks but
it's very easy to figure out what the test
does because it is a rank-sum test.
So literally we're going to rank the data
and
then we're going to sum the data and that
part is easy to understand without knowing
anything about non-parametric tests so
we're going to do that.
We can do that right now.
So let's rank the data.
So what do I mean by ranking the data?
So what we're going to do, is we're
going to order the data from the lowest
weight loss, the, the worst weight loss to
the highest, the best weight loss.
And for the moment,
we're going to rank the data ignoring
which group people are in.
So, there are 20 people here.
The person who lost the least weight,
which was the person who gained four
pounds.
They're going to get a rank of one.
The person who lost the most weight, which
was the person who was
just did really well and lost 300 pounds,
they're going to get a rank of 20.
And we're going to rank everybody in
between.
And again, for the moment we're ignorning
diet.
So, you can see that most of the low ranks
go to diet one.
The, the six lowest ranks go to diet one.
The sixth lowest person lost only five
pounds, and then we jump to diet two.
The eight pound weight loss in diet two
was the seventh lowest.
And then the negative ten, the ten pound
weight loss was the eighth, and
then we jump back to diet one to get the
ninth rank, and so on.
So you can see, that now we're treating
everything rather than using
the underlying values like the negative
300, which is so highly influential.
We're giving everybody a rate, and
the rate values you can see everybody is
only one unit apart.
So that's going to have less influence on
the statistics.
Notice, however though, that we did not
take that 300 pound weight loss and
throw it out, that would be a mistake,
because there really is
somebody who did have a fabulous success
on diet one for whatever reason.
That person gets counted, they get the
best rate, they get the 20, but
that, that the 20 has much less influence
on the statistics than that negative 300,
that's the idea.
So we ranked everybody from 1 to 20,
ignoring which group you're in.
And then, we sum up the ranks within each
of those groups,
we just add them up, literally sum them
up.
So, we take the ranks from diet one and we
add them up,
we come up with a sum of the ranks of 73,
do the same thing with diet two,
we come up with a sum of the ranks of 137.
Notice that 137 is much bigger than 73,.
Where we need the official, the formal
Wilcoxon sum-rank test is to
actually say whether or not that 137
versus that 73.
Whether that's a different set, could have
arisen by chance or
does that represent likely a real
difference between those diets.
And so when we actually apply the formal
Wilcoxon sum-rank test,
something we're going to learn in a few
weeks, to say whether or
not 137 is really different than 73, in
fact, we get a significant p-value here.
So, in fact, when you apply the correct
statistical test here,
you find out that diet two is
significantly better than diet one.
Exactly the opposite of what you might
have concluded if you had
just looked at the means.