Welcome back.
In the last module, we reviewed how to
check your data dictionary,
point to a permanent library and import
your data set.
We are now going to about data cleaning.
Let's open up our data set and
double check to see if our variables are
in the right format.
It looks like everything is all right.
We have isDiabetic, isFemale, isSmoker and
race as string variables and
age, weight and height as continuous
numeric variables.
>> You can tell which type of variables
they are.
Based on the icon next to the variable
name.
String variables have this red triangle.
Whereas numeric variables have this blue
circle.
Also notice that, for
the numeric variables, missing values are
represented by the period.
Whereas for string variables, a missing
value is represented by a blank.
SAS has different ways of representing
missing values,
based on the type of variable that you're
using.
>> It's important for us to get a sense
about the amount of missing data we have
before writing a certain analysis.
Let's use Proc Freq and
Proc Univariate to determine whether we
have a problem with missing data.
I'm going to open up a program and let's
take a look at some code.
>> Here we have Proc Freq, for
the categorical variable, and Proc
Univariate for the numeric variables.
These procedure will tell us the number of
missing values for
each of these variables.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
As you can see, the disease outcome
variable and
the gender variable have no missing value.
The smoker variable, has 101 missing
values.
Race, has 93 missing values.
Age, had 114 missing values.
Height, has 99 missing values.
And weight has 92 missing values.
Since for each of these variables the
number of missing values is around 10% or
less, we don't really need to use any
amputation methods, so we should be fine.
Now that we have a feel for how much
missing values we have,
let's take a look at our data to make sure
we don't have any miscoded entries.
>> We can do this using a data step.
We'll start by creating a new data set in
the work library called flag.
And fill in the data from our original
diabetes data set.
We'll then create a new flag variable
called flag.
For now, we'll give missing values to all
records by default.
Let's think about the conditions that
would need to be flagged.
Age, Weight, and Height are all continuous
variables which all should be positive.
If any of these are negative we'll give
them a flag value of one.
These variables also have certain ranges
that we expect.
We wouldn't expect anyone to have an age
greater than 120 years, so
we'll flag anyone that is older than that.
We also wouldn't expect anyone to weigh
more than 500 pounds.
So, we'll flag anyone heavier than that as
well.
It would also be unreasonable based on our
data set to have anyone over 250
centimeters tall which is around eight
feet.
We'll flag those subjects.
We can flag all erroneous values with
simple if then statements.
>> In this first if then, we flag everyone
who has a negative value for
age, weight or height.
Remember, when SAS encodes a missing value
for
a numeric variable, missing is encoded as
negative infinity.
So, if we just have just negatives for
age, weight and
height, it'll also flag any missing
values.
So to correct for this, we have to say if
age is less than zero and
if it's not missing, then we'll flag it.
And then the same for weight and height.
This way, it'll only flag the negative
values and not the missing values.
In the next if then statement, we flag
anyone over 120 years old.
We also flag anyone over 500 pounds and
anyone that's over 250 centimeters tall.
As you can see we now have a new variable
called flag, which
will have a non missing value for any of
the erroneous records in our dataset.
Now that we've flagged all these erroneous
records.
Let's create a new data set that only has
these flag records, so
we can see what's going on.
>> This code will create a new data set
called flag only, fill in
the data from the flag data set, but only
include records that have been flagged.
Now we can see exactly what has been
flagged in our data set.
>> As we can see we have five records
which were flagged.
One of them had a negative value for
weight, and the rest had ages that were
over 120 years old.
Clearly these must be erroneous in some
way,
and we shouldn't include them in our data
when we do the analysis.
>> Let's create a new clean data set
without the flag variables.
For a code we'll create the new clean
diabetes data set, fill in the information
from the flagged, and focus only on those
with flag value of period or missing.
>> This will keep anyone that wasn't
flagged in our data set.
Now we have a clean data set that doesn't
have any of the flagged records.
Now that the data is all cleaned up, we're
ready to prepare for the analysis.