In this next module,
I'm going to talk about one of the
assumptions of linear regression that you
really should test if you've got
continuous predictors in your model.
I think it's often an ignored assumption.
So when you're reading papers, you should
look to see whether or
not it was tested, and
if you're doing your own data analysis, it
would be important to run this test.
This assumption is something called linear
in the logit, and it's as simple as just
when we do a linear regression, remember,
what do you want to do, of course?
When you do a linear regression, you
want to do the plot.
And you want to see if it actually looks
like a line.
This one looks like a line.
Here's a scatter plot that doesn't look
like a line.
It actually looks like a quadratic.
So, for linear regression, it's really
easy, because we can just plot x
against y, and we can see immediately if
if looks like the, the scatter plot.
Roughly fits a line.
For logistic regression,
we're still fitting lines, but it's harder
to draw this graphic.
Because the outcome remember, is this
logit function, and
there's no way to directly see the logit
function.
The best you can do is, I did some logit
plots in the first module for
this week, and how I did that, in order to
be able to do that,
I had to group people according to their
level on the predictor.
So I can group people who did the lowest
number, amount of homework.
And you know like the 10 lowest, 10 people
with the lowest homework time.
And then the next 10, and then the next
10, so
I have to somehow group people in order
that I can calculate the proportion who
have had the binary outcome from the
proportion I can then calculate the logit.
If you do that then you can make some
plots.
But, of course, the plot is going to
depend slightly on how you bend people,
how you group people.
So I'm going to show you in a minute some
examples of testing this linear in
the logit assumption and you will see that
I,
we'll usually run several different graphs
with several different bin sizes.
So that I can get a sense of the data
without you know, being too arbitrary.
And we're looking for that what we're
testing is that,
if you have a continuous predictor in
logistic regression.
What we're doing is we're fitting a line
that says, that continuous predictor acts
Has a linear relationship, roughly, with
the logit of the outcome.
So you actually want to make that plot as
best you can, and
see if the relationship is really linear
or if maybe it's not.
If it's something else, if the
relationship looks, you know,
quadratic, that means you're going to have
to model a quadratic variable for x.
You're going to put in the x squared into
the model.
Or you might have to transform that
continuous variable into
a categorical variable.
It may not be simply fine to just put that
continuous predictor directly into the
model.
Notice if you have a binary or
a categorical predictor, you do not have
to worry about this assumption.
Because if you have a binary variable, a
binary predictor,
you're only doing a 0, 1.
You've got only two dots, therefore, and
any time you connect two dots,
it's automatically a line.
If you have a categorical predictor,
you're going to be dummy coding it, so
you're going to have a series of zero
ones.
Those are all going to make lines, so this
is only a worry when you have a continuous
predictor in logistic regression.
I want to show you some real examples with
real data.
Various examples where I've had to draw
linear in the logit plots.
This example was from a data set where the
outcome is heart disease.
The predictor that we're looking at here
called tobacco,
this is the number of cigarettes smoked
per day.
And I grouped the data set-up into four
bins, as well as ten bins,
just to give us a sense of the
relationship between the number of
cigarettes per day and the logit of heart
disease.
And again, I have to group people, and
what I'm graphing here is the,
I'm graphing their mean cigarettes per
day.
The mean cigarettes per day for the group
against the logit for that group.
The observed logit for that group.
What you can see here is that, for
this particular variable, the number of
cigarettes per day.
It does not look linear in the logit.
The relationship between cigarettes per
day, and our,
the logit of having heart disease appears
curvilinear.
There appears to be a curved relationship.
In both of these graphics, you can see it,
that there's sort of a curved relationship
here.
Why is that?
Well, think about the variable, cigarettes
per day.
You have a bunch of people who smoke 0
cigarettes per day and
then you got people increasing on their
cigarettes per day.
What you're seeing in this graphic here,
is when you
jump from being a non-smoker to smoking,
you know, some little amount per day,
there's a huge jump in your odds at risk
getting heart disease.
There's a major steep jump, jump.
But then there's sort of diminishing
returns,
once you're already a smoker, whether you
smoke.
A couple cigarettes per day, or more, it,
your risk does go up but it doesn't go up
as steeply.
And then when you go from being a moderate
smoker to being a heavy smoker,
your risk also goes up but it goes up even
less steeply.
So the relationship is really curved,
rather than linear.
How might you account for this?
Probably the best way is to think about
cigarette smoking as
a categorical variable.
You might want to model this as non
smokers versus light to
moderate smokers versus heavy smokers.
And that might be the best way to actually
model this.
This might be the case where it makes
sense to treat tobacco smoking
cigarettes per day as a categorical
variable rather than continuous.
So that's an example that violated the
linear in the logit assumption.
Here's an example where we're actually
meeting the linear in the logit
assumption pretty well.
This was some data I had On women
athletes.
And the outcome variable here is low bone
mineral density.
So, low skeletal strength.
It turns out that women athletes sometimes
don't menstruate normally.
And, if you don't have normal menses, that
actually can reduce your,
your skeletal strength, your, your bone
mineral, bone mineral density.
So that, this was the data set.
Looking at that, again, I did too many in
the linear pot so
I'm getting a sense depending on how I bin
things.
How many people per group that I'm getting
the right relationship.
So I grouped into about twelve bins, as
well as five bins, and
you can see that there's of course more
local noise when you have twelve bins.
But the pattern looks pretty similar in
both cases.
I would say that this is pretty close to
fitting lines.
Not a perfect line, but
it looks like it actually is reasonably
linear in the logit.
In both cases you can imagine kind of a
drawing a line again with lots of points.
There's going to be some local variability
but essentially that's well fit by a line.
So, in this case our predictor variable
here is
the number of menses the number of
menstral periods per year.
So, normal is sort of around 12.
A lot of women athletes are having many
less than that.
And it turns out, there is a linear
relationship here as the number of
menstrual periods goes up, from 0 to all
the way up to normal, 12,
the chances, the odds of getting low or
having low bone density go down.
It appears to be well modeled as linear,
so
I could put the number of menstrual cycles
per year as the predictor variable.
And get an odds ratio for every one unit
increase in menstrual, in menses.
How does that decrease my odds of getting
low bone marrow density?
This one seems reasonably modeled as a
linear variable.