What's the reference group here?
Well we can see that from the table so
you'll notice that the category of greater
than or equal to four months, they all
have odds ratios here of 1.0, so
you, you know that that was set as the
reference group.
So the correct answer here is b.
Predominant breastfeeding of at least four
months.
So how do we interpret this adjusted odds
ratio of 1.24 42 for
the women, for the men who were breast fed
less than one month.
This is the, increase in odds in those
breastfed less than one month.
Compared with those breastfed at least
four months.
That's our reference group.
And it, the confidence interval crosses
one.
So the effect is not statistically
significant.
So we have a 43% increase in the odds of
being obese at 18 years but it is not a
statistically significant.
The you might have got confused here
because there's a significant p value for
linear trend over here.
That only tells us that the decrease in
the prevalence of
obesity across different breast feeding
categories is statistically significant.
That's not the same as saying that this
particular comparison between the less
than one month group.
And the the reference group is
statistically significant, so that's
a little tricky there but this confidence
interval you can see does cross one.
You can see that across this table, the
difference between the crude ratio and
the adjusted odds ratio was not very large
really anywhere.
That tells you that this, the correct
answer here, is false.
The crude and adjusted odds ratios are
extremely similar.
It looks like there's very little
confounding going on.
There's very, it's unlikely that there are
any strong confounders here.
If we had strong con founders,
it would greatly change the magnitudes of
these odds ratios.
So the data coefficient for a cardiac
surgery is negative.
This means that A is correct.
The patients who had cardiac surgery were
less likely to
die after discharge than patients with
other conditions.
If you have a negative data,
remember we're exponentiating here to get
the hazard ratio.
That would give us a hazard ratio below
one which would say that the rate of
death for these patients was lower than
the other groups.
To translate the beta coefficient of
0.2501 into an odds ratio we're
just going to exponentiate here.
If you exponentiate 0.2501 you get an odds
ratio of 1.28, so
that's the correct answer there.
So this question is asking about the
length of ICU stay as a predictor.
If you look at the data coefficient here,
and if you exponentiate that,
you see that you get an odds ratio of
1.046.
That seems like a really small odds ratio,
right, it's very close to, to one.
You look at the P value, however, and it's
statistically significant.
Well, what's going on here is that b is
correct.
The odds ratio here is giving the change
in odds for every one day
increase in ICU stay, so the units here
for ICU stay are in only one day units.
That's a small unit, cause somebody can
stay in the ICU for
many, many days, even weeks.
So because we'er only talking about the
odds ratio associated with
a one unit increase, it looks pretty
small.
Obivously if we were talking about staying
a whole week,
this odds ratio would be much bigger.
So it depends on the units.
The odds ratio depends on the units, when
you have continuous variables.
So, b would be correct here.
So age is a continuous variable here.
This is given in units of one year
increases in age.
Our beta is given in one year increments.
In, increases in age.
If you wanted to say, what's the odds
ratio for a ten year increase in age,
you'd have to take that beta coefficient
and multiply it by 10.
You would see that that gives you a value
of 0.532, and
then you exponentiate that value.
0.532 to get the corresponding odds ratio.
So the odds ratio here would be 1.70.
The goal of this model, this was a
predictive model so
the goal here was to find the combination
of variables that
identifies the patients most likely to die
after discharge.
So the correct answer is a.
They really weren't after a particular
hypothesis here, so
they're not try to adjust for con founders
or test for interactions here.
They're really trying to do prediction
here, so a is the correct answer.
So this next one you literally just have
to crank through,
plug into the model here.
So we get our intercept is negative 4.58.
This person had a ICU stay of 10, so I'm
multiplying that by the beta for ICU stay.
Their age here was 50, so we multiply
0.0532 times 50.
They have one on both the chronic health
points and the acute physiology points, so
each of those gets a one.
When you do this all out, you get that the
predicted logit is 1.182 ,
and then if we want to get from there the
predicted probability.
We have to do this little trick of raising
e to the predicted logit, and
then dividing by 1 plus e raised to the
predicted logit.
If you calculate that all that out, you
get a a percentage,
a predicted probability of 54% so the
correct answer here is e.
In including continuous predictors in the
model, the authors are assuming that these
predictors have a linear relationship with
our outcome here,
which is the logit of death.
So the correct answer here is b.
The correct answer here is a.
Our hazard ratio is 1.35 so that indicates
a 35%
increase in the rate of dementia after
accounting for confounders.
And it is statistically significant,
because that confidence interval does not
cross one, it goes from 1.14 to 1.60, so
that is statistically significant.
So, how do we interpret these hazard
ratios for the underweight for women?
So, what you'll notice is that they are
all elevated by similar amounts as
the overweight and the obese, compared
with normal weight.
However all of the confidence intervals
cross one.
Well how do we interpret this?
Well, what's probably going on here is
that, that under weight category is small,
there aren't that many people running
around who are under weight.
So it does look like there's some
elevation in the risk of dementia here,
but perhaps because of the small sample
size we have low statistical power.
And that's why the findings don't reach a
statistical significance.
So the best choice here would be a.
Being underweight may increase the risk of
dementia, but the findings are not
statistically significant, likely due to
small sample size.
For this question you have to be careful
about how you determine interaction.
In fact, the correct answer here is c, we
don't have enough information in
this table alone to tell whether or not we
have a significant act.
Interaction between gender with the weight
category and
our outcome here, dementia in midlife.
It does look like there's less of a
relationship, right?
For men, it doesn't look like there's a
It's a huge relationship between
the weight and the outcome.
And for women it does look like there's a
significant relationship.
But remember, that's not proof of
interaction.
Just because it's, the relationship is
significant in one group but
not significant in the other group, that
does not constitute proof of interaction.
We'd actually have to do a formal
statistical test, in which we compared
these particular relationships to say
whether or not, say for
example, this 2.07 is significantly higher
than this 1.3 for men.
So that's a little bit of a trick, a
tricky question there,
but you have to do a formal test of
interaction to know if these were
actually statistically different from one
another.
The, the relationship in men versus the
relationship in women.
The correct answer here is actually false.
You'll notice that as we adjust for
confounders here,
what's happening is that the hazard ratios
are actually going up, so, for
example, for the obese, it goes from 1.59
to 1.8 to 2.07.
So, we've seen some examples in the
modules where you, when you adjust for
things, the relationship attenuates, but
it can go the other direction.
Sometimes, adjusting for things will
actually increase the relationship, so
the adjusting is kind of going the other
direction.
So this, therefore, this is not likely to
be due to residual confounding,
because, if anything failing to adjust for
confounding here seems to be
underestimating our effects.
Also, a value of 2.07 is beyond the range
that we would normally consider for
residual confounding usual.
Usually residual confounding, confounding
would give us spurious relationships
in the range of like a 0.6 to 1.6 hazard
ratio, so
this is probably beyond the range we would
expect for just residual con founding.