[BLANK_AUDIO].
Already we've talked about the phrase root
cause analysis.
And many of you have probably heard the
phrase thrown out and never really
understood what it really meant or what
the intent of a root cause analysis.
So looking at this graphic, the symptom of
the problem is the weed.
It is above the surface.
It's obvious.
It's visible, and it's very, very clear.
The underlying causes, the root, is below
the surface, not obvious.
And we all know that if you trim the weed
without getting to the root, it's a good
likelihood that you're going to have that
weed come back up again.
So the word root in root cause analysis
generally refers to
the underlying causes, not just the one
apparent cause.
And that is a tendency of folks who
conduct root
cause analysis indicating that hey, we
found what the single problem is.
We fixed that single problem.
And then three weeks, three months later
the same event occurs.
So we're going to take you through a
little bit more in-depth of
what the expectations of a root cause
analysis is, so
that way you can help understand the
process and help your
organization prevent from having one of
these bad type of patient care events.
The goals of the root cause analysis is to
identify what those root causes are and
contributing factors.
Contributing factors are, may not be
directly responsible for
contributing to the outcome that occurred
with your patient, but it may be
something that kind of assisted the
process along to lead to a system failure.
Another goal is to focus on the structure,
systems and process variations.
We are going to go through some of the
techniques and tools that are used to
unveil or uncover what some of those root
causes are and the contributing factors.
And the third bullet, the goal is not to
focus on individual staff or
physician performance.
This is really the role of the
organization peer review or
human resource process.
So we try to take out the, blame the
individual but
look at more of what's the system process
issue that led to the adverse outcome?
So when you actually look at the goals of
the root cause analysis or
RCA, you kind of have to look at, what are
the questions we need to ask?
What happened?
Did it actually lead to a bad patient care
event?
Or was it a close call that if it followed
this progression it
could have lead to an adverse patient care
situation.
Some of the questions regarding what
happened is that what happened that day?
What usually happens, what normally
standard practice is and then what
should have happened, which typically is
outlined in policy and procedures.
We all know that the event itself led to a
bad outcome is not something we
expect everyone to have every single day.
I mean, how many people in healthcare
comes to work thinking I'm going to go
out and kill a patient or, you know, do
some damage.
You know, I mean that should be the
significant variation [LAUGH] and
it really should be thinking about well,
the standard norm in terms of what we do
or the tolerance that we have in terms of
variation from our policy is it something
that's actually acceptable and what really
should have happened is what's typically
outlined in policies and procedures.
Another question, and we'll get into this
much further in terms of
the drill down is, why did it actually
happen?
You know, you've heard about the five
why's, we're going to
talk a little bit more about that later
when we get into more of the details, but
you have to ask the question, why did it
happen?
Another question, what are we going to do
to prevent it from happening again?
What are the actions or system process
changes, and
what kind of outcomes can we tolerate in
our organization so
that we make sure that we don't have to
have these kind of events happening again?
How will we know that our actions improve
patient safety and
that's the need, as part of the plan do
check act process is like checking to
make sure that we're heading in the right
direction, that our outcomes,
the metrics that we're setting as
expectation are being met.
And, if they're not being met, we may have
to go back and
re-review what we had done to make sure
that we have actually identified the right
root causes, contributing factors, and
make those appropriate adjustments.
The what.
Process for identifying contributing or
causal factors that underlie
variations in performance associated with
adverse event or close calls.
So really it comes down to the done
obedience concept of quality that
if your structure is put together well,
that you have good system process,
the outcome should be very consistent or
very reliable.
Any time there's a change in process,
there is usually a ramification of action.
And so that's where we tend to focus on,
is looking at those system process issues,
knowing that the structure typically, you
know,
has been outlined in a particular way to
have a particular outcome.
The what question also features
interdisciplinary involvement of
those closest to and, or most knowledgable
about the situation.
You remember I said that in high
reliability organizations there's
a deference to expertise and there's a
sensitivity to operation.
You need both of those many times to drill
down to figure out what actually happened,
what was the process modification or what
was the practice in order to
understand what we need to do to correct
the problem.
The root cause analysis can also be used
for either a single significant event or
it could be used for a group or set of
similar occurrence.
Or if you're like many organizations they
track and trend their data.
There are some adverse trend and less
significant occurrence, you can
certainly apply the root cause analysis
technique to drill down and figure out
what do we need to do to change things to
meet our performance expectation.
Realistically, what we must change or put
in place to prevent this from
happening again is really the core
fundamental goal of a root cause analysis.
And this particular slide actually is a
good graphic to
show you what is not and what is a root
cause analysis.
It's not about people making mistakes.
It's not about affixing blame or
disciplining those involved.
It's not about the history.
It's not justifying what happened as
expected, acceptable or
inevitable but it is about improving
system,
preventing recurrence, understanding what
we need to do to change the system, and
ultimately a way to improve patient care,
specifically patient safety.
Some of the components of an effective
root cause analysis include,
recreating the event.
This may require interviews or statements
from witnesses, a review of
the medical records, a review of the
physical site where the event occurred.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
A review of personnel or
medical staff files, internal documents,
policy and procedures.
There is a need to actually map out a
timeline.
Until you actually map out the sequencing
of an event and
I know that, you know, there's often times
disputes about when
a particular thing happened at a
particular point.
But nevertheless, putting it on a piece of
paper, or putting it on a flip chart, or
a diagram, PowerPoint slide can help
recreate what had actually occurred.
There's a need to do some maybe,
potentially some process mapping because,
as we mentioned, this is the next size of
evaluation of the process of what it takes
to figure out what had happened.
So process mapping is a technique and tool
that we often use to try to drill down to
figure out, well, what are the steps
involved in a particular process so
that we could figure out where the
variations are.
Fishbone diagram, or
the Ishikawa diagram, is a great tool to
be able to drill down further to
figure out what really are root causes,
and what may be just contributing factors.
Since nowadays, more and more
organizations are publishing their
learning and findings from their
experience, research of literature and or
professional organization is real helpful
to be able to understand what might be
lessons learned from other organizations.
And then, ultimately,
the presentation of the findings to senior
leadership and/or the governing board,
which is something the joint commission
requires for accredited hospitals.
But for most organizations, by sharing it
with leaderships and
governing board, you know, certainly
governing board has a vested interest in
what's going on within the organization.
And, of course, from a professional
standpoint, reputation standpoint,
you know, health plan standpoint,
organizations governing board often
times would like to know what kind of
things are happening and
what are we going to do to prevent them
from happening again.
The scope of that whole focus, you know,
really does fall on senior leadership and
the governing board.
[BLANK_AUDIO]