This is a review of VDJ recombinations.
Starting from the beginning and I mean
really starting from the beginning and
then going through the whole process.
So here we are at the beginning of time,
actually not really.
Around the time when jawless fish were
swimming in the ocean.
And around that time, there was a
transposable element,
mobile element, that hops around from
genome to genome.
And mobile elements have, are like retro
viruses.
They have sequences at their ends that
allow them, to jump around.
And so here's a mobile element and it's
got, two sequences at the end.
They're not quite the same but they're
very similar and one is in red and
one is in blue.
And what they do, is they surround two
genes.
And those two genes are now known as rag
one and rag two.
And I'll abbreviate it this way.
And rag one and rag two, now called the
recombination activating genes,
were really and integrates for the mobile
element,
that allow the mobile element to integrate
and hop out of genomes.
So I'm going to draw you the genome of
this ancient jawed fish, and
here is the genome, or a little segment of
the genome.
The place where the mobile element is
destined to hop in.
And here, is an ancient gene that's
going to
turn out to be the immunoglobulin gene.
So this is the ancient immunoglobulin
gene.
And this mobile element is going to hop
into this gene, just so
and as a result of hopping in at that
location the mobile element
will split the split the immunoglobulin
gene into two pieces, so
now I'm going to show you the mobile
element as it appears.
Here's the mobile element and here's the
other side of it and
it's hopping to that location there and.
[SOUND] Okay, and so the ancient
immunoglobulin
gene has now been split into 2 pieces and
here are the 2 pieces, all right?
And it could hop into a 2nd time and
we'll draw in the mobile element hopping
in the second time.
Imagine, that the same mobile element is
now reversed,
so the red and blue it's turned upside
down.
Well, I'll just turn it upside down for
you.
Here it is.
And turn it backwards.
Cause this is going to happen to hop in,
to this ancient immunoglobulin gene,
just happens to be right next door.
This will be the second hopping event.
[COUGH] And what you end up with is two
mobile elements in the genome,
very close together.
So, here's one mobile element and
here is the other mobile element and
it's really the same mobile element
that's happened to two locations.
And it's in the genome.
All right?
And it's ended up splitting the
immunoglobulin gene into three pieces.
These three pieces are now known as the
ancient V region,
ancient D region and ancient J region of
the immunoglobulin heavy chain.
[SOUND]
And now imagine that this mobile element.
So, so we've got three steps now.
Starting with the ancient immunoglobulin
gene,
the ancient gene split into two different
pieces.
So here's, so we, we split the ancient
immunoglobulin gene into two piece, and
then with a second insertion of a mobile
element split it into three pieces.
And now we have the genes split into three
pieces.
And then the next step is each of these
little pieces could undergo
a gene duplication.
So, for example, the V region here could
end up getting copied multiple times.
So that you would have multiple V regions
and you'd have multiple D and multiple J.
So I'll just draw what model V regions
would look like, would have the following.
And then, there would be a little v piece,
here.
And then, since it's duplicated actually,
let me, make this a neat diagram.
So, there's another mobile element another
V segment.
And here's another V segment.
And let me fill in the details.
So, there's a V region.
There's another V region there.
And there's another V region there.
So, so what have is, we have this V region
being duplicated into three regions.
So let's call them V1, V2 and V3.
And they arose from the original
primordial V
region via a process called chain
duplication.
And the same thing, this could happen 500
times for V regions and
a dozen times, or four times and a dozen
times for the J region and so on.
So you end up with the current and modern,
immunoglobulin heavy chain gene.
So that's what this is.
With after the gene duplications.
So, that's were it all got started.
>> The preceding program is copyrighted by
the Board of Trustees,
of the Leland Stanford Junior University.
Please visit us at med.stanford.edu.