All right.
Now this is Part 2 of the V(D)J
Recombination Story and
Part 2 is the Mechanism of the V(D)J
Recombination.
What happens in V(D)J Recombination is ,.
There is going to be recombine, recombine,
recombination to bring a D segment next to
a J segment, and a V next to a DJ segment;
so we're going to show that.
And of course all these segments, there
are many other D segments and
many J segments, and many other V
segments.
We're just going to, talk about the chosen
ones and,
use hatch marks here to indicate that
there are some indetermined amount of
space between these segments that I've
drawn,.
There are two kinds of recombination
signal sequences which are donated in blue
here and red.
And each of those recombination signal
sequences is really DNA
sequence denoted by a triangle.
So in the red, let's say, that really
stands for the following type of sequence.
That.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There are two conserve sequences.
Represented by, the red.
And one is a 7mer.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
A 7 nucleotide, 7 base pair sequence, and
one is a 9 nucleotide sequence.
And they're separated by a spacer.
And in the reds, for example, that spacer
could be 12 nucleotides.
All right?
12 nucleotide spacer.
And then, the blue segment is exactly like
the red segment with one exception.
It also has a 7mer and a 9mer or nonimer
or
[UNKNOWN]
and nonimer separated.
By a spacer, but that spacer is different.
That spacer is, 23-base pairs alone.
So, I'll put a 23 there.
So, this thing, these things are called
recombination signal sequence dash 23.
And, recombination.
Signal sequence, dash 12, to indicate the
difference, is only in the spacers.
And a VDJ recombination always occurs,
between a, a RSS23 and an RSS12.
So that's the 12/23 rule.
The reason for that rule, is that the
first.
The first mobile element to hop in, to the
[UNKNOWN] genome.
I'm going to show you that say, say this
was, this was the original mobile element.
And remember, the mobile element hopped
in, and any mobile element hopped in,
can also hop out.
And so, this particular mo, mobile element
hops out.
And it came in with one, RSS-12 and one
RSS-23.
And it hops out in the same way.
It excises itself because, rag 1 and rag 2
for example, in code
in integrates that's also, a disintegrates
that allows it to hop out.
So.
Let me erase this bracket just to show you
that when, when this thing hops out Rag 1
and Rag 2 will do a cleavage at two
points.
All right, and that cleavage at the two
Leads to four different ends from two
different double strand
cuffs, and those four ends now have to be
rejoined.
Let me sort of show a blow up of one of
those two, of those cuts.
So here's a blow up of the cut.
It's going to be a little bit.
Alright and I'm just going to separate the
DNA there to show the cut.
Okay there's the cut there and there is
going to be a cut here.
[SOUND]
And the cut is going to be there.
And now, I'm going to draw for you, the
new cut over here.
So there is a cut at these two locations,
that, that occurred with the cleavage.
And now we've got ends,.
That are free,.
Four different ends that have been created
by the cleavage event.
And what happens now, is, that the non
homologous and joining proteins.
I'll, I'll draw an arrow here for you.
The non homologous and joining proteins
will take these ends.
And join them in a way that it recombines
the genome.
And, and the reason, and they're going to
only join them in a particular order.
They're going to take the J segment and
the D segment and join them.
And the two recombination signal sequence
ends and join them.
And the reason it's going to do it that
way is because.
Rag 1 and Rag 2 after making the cleavage
end up bound to the recombination signal
sequences to prevent the joining of the
two ends for a little bit,
to delay the joining so that the only two
ends that can be joined are D to J.
So as a result of the joining event, you
get the following.
You get the D segment joined to the J
segment, okay?
And then of course, the DNA extends out
here and the DNA extends out here.
And, the rest of the genome is upstream.
Just put that in there.
And here's the upstream v region,
ready for recombination.
And.
At the same time this, this, the DNA
that's been excised from the genome,
containing the two recombination signal
sequences now becomes available for
joining, and the two ends there are joined
in the following way so
that the blue segment and the red segment.
Get joined.
So that, you get junction, like this.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] So the excision, comes out as a
circle.
and.
In the absence of nonhomogsenjoining of
course,
the excision looks like excision of a
mobile element but
because nonhomogsenjoining is out there,
cleaning up the end.
It'll just take the excised segment and
join the two ends.
So you have two pieces of DNA.
You have the intact chromosome.
Which I'll designate here.
And you have a circle and the chromosome
is now the immunoglobulin, heavy chain.
After D to J joining has occurred, and
what happens next of course is V to D J
joining.
And you just go through the whole thing
all over again.
So that is a quick overview of the
mechanism of V D J recombination.
Thank you.