Now this is the third part of this story.
It's kind of an add on to explain to
students how inversions can occur during
VDJ recombination.
I'm going to draw for
you the kind of an abbreviated version of
the aminoglobulin gene.
So I'm going to give you [SOUND] a D
region.
Here's a D region.
Just as in the previous diagrams, here's
the D region.
[SOUND]
And I'm going to give you a J region.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That's downstream from it.
Here's J region.
And I'm going to draw upstream, a V
region.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND]
D region.
And so we're going to do D to J joining
except remember that
recombination activating genes RAG-1 and
RAG-2 always do cleavages between at a red
RSS and a blue RSS.
A red recombination signal sequence and a
blue recombination signal sequence.
So just, it doesn't really know how
they're oriented,
because it doesn't really care.
And DNA can fold up anyway.
So, suppose RAG-1 and RAG-2 do their
cleavages at these arrows.
There's no reason why they can't, they
just follow the rules.
They just recognize recombination signal
sequences and do the cleavage.
And so you end up with the following
cleavage.
So let me draw that cleavage for you.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this is the uncleaved part,
and this is, the cleaved part.
Oh, let's, let me do that, and make it
cleaner for you.
So, there we are.
Okay, there's the J, there's the D,
and then there are spaces for the two
cleavages.
And now having done this remember the
recombination, RAG-1 and
RAG-2, the recombination activating genes,
stay stuck on the signal ends,
covering them up and not allowing them to
be joined right away.
So, as a result, there are two coding
ends.
One end for the D, one end for the J.
And they're going to end up getting joined
to each other.
So, in order for that to happen, this
piece of
DNA has to swing around to come over here.
And so obviously, the other side of the
DNA,
swing around and come over here.
So, let's, let's draw the swing around, so
that you can see everything.
It's now going to look like this.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And.
I'm just swinging everything around, so
it's all backwards.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay?
So you can see that all I've done is take
that middle segment and
rotate it around so that the D region over
here is now backwards, and
I'm going to designate it as backwards by
drawing D in a backwards fashion.
And the J region is still sitting here
waiting to be joined to the D region.
And this, this peripheral signal sequences
are,
are still there right, waiting to be
joined.
And now when the joining occurs, boom,
you've, you've now got an inversion
of the segment containing the D, from the
D segment all the way up to
a recombination signal sequence, so that's
how the inversion will occur.
Okay, thank you.