Now this is the third part of the story,
it's a kind of an add on
to explain to students, how inversions can
occur during D to J recombination.
I'm going to draw for
you the kind of an abbreviated version of
the immunoglobulin gene.
So, I'm going to give you
[BLANK_AUDIO]
A D region.
Here's a D region.
Just as in the previous diagrams, here's
the D region.
And I'm going to give you a J region
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That's downstream from it.
Here's the J region.
And
I'm going to draw upstream of D region.
[SOUND]
V region.
And so, we're going to do D to J joining,
except remember the recombination
activating genes are RAG1 and RAG2, always
do cleavages between.
A red RSS and a blue RSS.
A red recombination signal sequence and a
blue recombination signal sequence.
So just it doesn't really know how they're
oriented, because it doesn't really care.
And DNA can fold up anyway.
So, suppose.
Rag one and rag two do their cleavages at
these arrows.
So there's no reason why they can't, they
just follow the rules.
They just recognize recombination signal
sequences, and do the cleavage.
And so you end up with the following
cleavage.
So let me draw that cleavage for you.
[SOUND]
And this
is their uncleaved part.
And this is.
The cleaved part.
Oop, looks, hm, let me do that and make it
cleaner for you.
And so, there we are.
Okay there's the J, there's the D,
and then there are spaces for the two
cleavages.
And now having done this, remember the,
the recombination rag one and rag two,
the recombination activating genes, stay
stuck on the signal ends,
covering them up and not allowing them to
be joined right away.
So as a result, there are two coating
ends.
One end for the D, one end for the J.
And they're going to end up getting joined
to each other.
So in order for that to happen, this piece
of DNA has to swing around,
to come over here.
And so, ,.
Obviously, the other side of the DNA swing
around, and come over here.
So, let's, let's draw the swing around, so
that you can see everything.
It's now going to look like this.
[SOUND]
And I am just swinging everything around.
So it's all backwards.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hm, okay.
So you can see, that all I've done is take
that middle segment,
and rotated it around.
So that, the D region over here, is now
backwards.
And I'm going to designate it as
By drawing d in a backwards fashion and
the J region's still sitting
here waiting to be drawn to the delusion.
And the, the perferial sequel sequences
are,
are still there right waiting to be
joined.
And now when the joining occurs.
Boom.
You've, you've not got an inversion of the
segment containing the D.
From the D segment all the way up to a
recombination signal sequence.
So that's how the inversion will occur.
Okay, thank you.