All right.
Now, this is part two of the VDJ
recombination story.
And part two is the mechanism of VDJ
recombination.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
What happens in VDJ recombination is there
is going to be recombi, recombinant,
combinations to bring a D segment next to
a J segment and a V next to a DJ segment.
So we're going to show that, and of course
all these segments, there are many other d
segments and many other J segments and
many other V segments, we're just going to
talk about the chosen ones and use hash
marks here to indicate that there's some
indeterminate amount of space between
these segments that I've drawn.
There are two kinds of recombination
signal sequences which are denoted in
blue, here, ver, and red.
And each of those recombination signal
sequences is really DNA
sequence denoted by a triangle.
So, in the red, let's say, that really
stands for the following type of sequence.
That.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There are two conserved sequences,
represented by the red.
And one is a sevenmer.
A seven nucleotide, seven base pair
sequence, and
one is a nine nucleotide sequence, and
they're separated by a spacer.
And in the reds, for example, that spacer
could be twelve nucleotides.
All right.
Twelve nucleotide spacer.
And then the blue segment is exactly like
the red segment with one exception.
It also has a sevenmer, and a ninemer, or
nonomer or heptomer and nonomer, separated
by a spacer.
But that spacer is different.
That spacer is 23 base pairs long.
So I'll put a 23 there.
And so this thing, these things are called
recombination signal sequence
dash 23 and recombination signal
sequence dash 12, to indicate the
difference is only in the spacers.
And VDJ recombination always occurs
between an RSS-23 and an RSS-12.
So that's the 12/23 rule.
The reason for that rule is that the
first,
the first mobile element to hop in to the
vertebrate genome.
I'm going to show you that, say, say this
was, this was the original mobile element.
And remember the mobile element hopped in.
And any mobile element hopped in can also
hop out.
And, so this particular mobile element
hops out.
And it came in with one RSS-12 and one
RSS-23 and it hops out in the same way.
It excises itself because RAG-1 and RAG-2
for
example encode an integrase that's also a
disintegrase that allows it to hop out.
So, let me erase this bracket just to show
you that when,
when this thing pops out, RAG-1 and RAG-2
will do a cleavage at two points.
All right?
And that cleavage at the two points
leads to four different ends from two
different double strand cuts,
and those four ends now have to be
rejoined.
Let me sort of show a blow up of one of
those two, of those cuts.
So here's a blow up of the cut.
It's going to be a little bit.
All right, and, I'm just going to separate
the DNA there to show the cut.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, there's the cut there.
And there is going to be a cut here.
And the cut is going to be there.
And now I'm going to draw for you the new
cut over here.
So, there's a cut at these two locations
that, that occurred with the cleavage.
And now we've got ends that are free
four different ends that have been created
by the cleavage event.
And, what happens now, is that the
non-homologous and
joining proteins, I'll, I'll draw an arrow
here for you,
the non-homologous and joining proteins
will take these ends,
and join them in a way that recombines the
genome.
And, and the reas, and they're going to
only join them in a particular order.
They're going to take the J segment and
the D segment and join them,
and the two recombination signal sequence
ends and join them.
And the reason it's going to do it that
way is because, RAG-1 and RAG-2,
after making the cleavage, end up bound to
the recombination signal sequences to
prevent the joining of those two ends for
a little bit, to delay the joining.
So, that the only two ends that can be
joined are D to J.
So, as a result of that joining event.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You get the following.
You get the D segment joined to the J
segment.
Okay.
And then of course, the DNA extends out
here,
and the DNA extends out here.
And, the rest of the genome is upstream.
Let's put that in there.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here's the upstream V region ready for
recombination.
And, at the same time, this, this,
the DNA that's been excised from the
genome, containing the two
recombination signal sequences now becomes
available for joining.
And the two ends there are joined in the
following way so
that the blue segment and the red segment
get joined so
that you get a junction like this.
[SOUND] So the excision comes out as a
circle.
And in the absence of non-homologous end
joining, of course,
the excision looks like excision of a, a
mobile element.
But because non-homologous end joining is
out there cleaning up the ends,
it'll just take the excised segment and
join the two ends.
So you have two pieces of DNA.
You have the intact chromosome which
I'll designate here, and you have a
circle.
And, the chromosome is now the
immunoglobulin heavy chain,
after D to J joining has occurred.
And what happens next of course, is V to
DJ joining.
And you just go through the whole thing
all over again.
So that is a quick overview of the
mechanism of VDJ recombination.
Thank you.