[BLANK_AUDIO]
This is a review of VDJ recombination
starting from the beginning.
And I mean really starting from the
beginning and
then going through the whole process.
So here we are, at the beginning of time.
Actually, not really.
Around the time when jawless fish were
swimming in the ocean and around that
time, there was, there was transposable
element, mobile element, that hops
around from genome to genome and mobile
elements have are, are like retro viruses.
They have sequences at their ends that
allow them to jump around.
And so here's a mobile element.
And it's got two two sequences at the end.
They're not quite the same but they are
very similar and one is in red and
one is in blue.
And what they do is they surround two
genes.
And those two genes, are now known as RAG
1 and
RAG 2, and I'll abbreviate it this way.
And RAG 1 RAG, and
RAG 2 [COUGH] now called the recombination
activating genes were really ,.
And integrates for the mobile element that
allowed the mobile element to
integrate and hop out of genomes.
So I'm going to draw you the genome of
this ancient jawed fish.
And here is the genome, or a little
segment of the genome.
The place where the mobile element is
destined to hop in.
And.
Here is an ancient gene that's going to
turn out to be the immunoglobulin gene.
So this is the ancient immunoglobulin
gene, and this mobile element is going
to hop into this gene, just so, and as a
result of hopping in at that location.
The mobile element will split the
immunoglobulin gene into two pieces.
So now I'm going to show you the mobile
element as it appears.
Here's the mobile element.
And here's the other side of it.
And it's hopped in into that location
there.
And.
Okay.
And so the ancient immunoglobulin gene has
now been split into two pieces.
And here are the two pieces.
All right?
And it could hop in the second time.
And, we'll draw in the mobile element
hopping in the second time.
Imagine in the same mobile element, is now
reversed so they're red and
blue, it's turned upside down, well I'll
just turn it upside down for you.
Here it is and, turned backwards.
because it's going to happen to hop in to
this ancient amino globin gene.
Just happens to be right next door.
And this'll be the second hopping event.
[COUGH] And what you end up with, is two
mo,
mobile elements in the genome very close
together.
So here's one mobile element.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And here is the other mobile element.
And it's really the same
mobile element that's hopped into two
locations.
And it's in the genome.
All right?
And it's ended up splitting the
immunoglobulin gene now into three pieces.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And [COUGH] these three pieces are now
known as the Ancient V-Region,
an, Ancient D-Region, and Ancient J-Region
of the anemia hemoglobin heavy chain.
[COUGH]
And now imagine that this mobile element.
So, so we've got three steps now.
The, starting with ancient immunoglobulin
gene,
the ancien gene split into two different
pieces.
So here's, so we, we split the ancient
immunoglobulin gene into two pieces and
then with a second insertion of a mobile
element, split it into three pieces.
And now we have the gene split into three
pieces.
And then the next step is,
each of these little pieces could undergo
a gene duplication.
So for example, the V region here, could
end up getting copied multiple times,
so that you would have multiple V regions,
and you'd have multiple D and multiple J.
So I'll just draw.
What multiple V regions would look like.
You would have the following.
And then there would be a little V piece
here.
And then, since it's duplicated.
Actually let me make this a neat diagram.
So here's another element,
another V segment and here's another V
segment and
let me fill in the details so, there's a V
region.
There's another V region there.
So, so what we have is.
We have this V region being duplicated
into three regions.
So let's call them V1, V2 and V3.
And, they arose from the original
primordial region, via a process called
gene duplication and the same thing, this
could happen 500 for V regions and
a dozen times, er, four times, and a dozen
times for the J region and so on.
So you end up with, the.
Current than modern.
Immunoglobulin heavy chain gene.
So that's what this is.
With after the gene duplications.
So that's where it all got started.
The preceding program is copyrighted by
the Board of Trustees of
the Leland Stanford Junior University.
Please visit us at med.stanford.edu.