[BLANK_AUDIO]
This is the day new mom of our series of
lectures on VDJ recombination.
Because that whole process of VDJ
recombination culminates in
the formation of an antibody molecule.
And I've drawn for you up here an antibody
molecule.
And the antibody molecule consists of two
identical heavy chains and
the two identical heavy chains are heavy
chains because they're bigger.
And I'll show you the heavy chains, little
arrows.
There's one here and there's one there and
two identical light chains.
And they're are two identical light
chains,
one over here and one over here.
Okay.
And each of those chains, light chain and
heavy chain, have in them a variable
region.
And the variable region has been drawn in
black.
So the variable regions are in black.
Right?
Variable regions.
And the colors.
Let's draw a red and blue arrow.
Red and blue arrow correspond to constant
regions.
The red to the constant region of the
heavy chain and
the blue to the constant region of the
light chain.
Okay.
So, these antibodies can
have incredible variation.
In fact, the variation is ab, absolutely
mind boggling.
And because these antibodies have to
recognize all kinds of foreign antigens.
And I'm going to show you exactly how we
get to such huge
numbers using VDJ recombinations.
It turns out that we mentioned that there
was a heavy chain gene.
And I'm going to draw for you the heavy
chain gene.
Okay.
So here's a single heavy chain gene.
And it's the germ line heavy chain gene.
All right.
There's the germ line heavy chain gene
all the way across there.
There's the long germ line heavy chain
gene.
And let me just say, germ line,
heavy chain gene.
So, the antibody's a protein, but
now we've got a gene, germ line heavy
chain gene.
And the germ line heavy chain gene
consists of a number of variable regions.
I'm going to draw a few of them, dot, dot,
dot.
Okay.
And in the human, it turns out, every
animal is somewhat different, but
in the human there are roughly 50 variable
regions.
Okay?
In addition to that, we don't string.
Let's put a stagger mark down there.
There are a number of D regions and, I'm
going to
draw a few of them, dot, dot, dot.
And so there are a number of D regions,
and in fact, there are about 25 D regions
in the human.
D1, D2, and D25.
Okay?
So, downstream of that there are a number
of J regions.
And in the humans, there are six J
regions.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Dot, dot, dot six J regions.
Hm.
Okay.
J1, J2 and J6.
So all of these are a little bit
different.
So, I'm going to make them a little bit
All right.
So there's the heavy
chain gene, right up here.
And as we described before, VDJ
recombination picks one of the V regions,
one of the D regions, and one of the J
regions, and brings them together.
All right?
So there's a tremendous amount of
diversity,
that's produced, from this recombination
event.
Now, downstream from the J region.
I'm out of space, so I'm just going to
curl it around.
I'm going to draw a block corresponding to
the constant region of the heavy chain,
and of course, because, if anybody has it
in red, I'll also draw a red here.
So, this is the constant region for the
heavy chain.
All right.
And notice that I've drawn the V, the D
and the J all in black,
because they're going to end up
encoding the variable region of the heavy
chain, which is up here.
So how many different variable regions can
we
get out of this single heavy chain gene?
Well, for any one of the J regions, you
can have 25 different D regions.
But there are six J regions.
Each of which can go with 25 D regions.
So the number of D to J combinations.
Let me draw it in black to emphasize.
Gotta get the colors [SOUND].
You can get 25 times 6, D to J
combinations.
But each of these D to J combinations can
go with any one of 50 V regions.
So, you can get a total of 50 times 25
times 6.
Recombinant from V, D, and J.
So 50 times 25 times 6 is equal to 7500,
7500.
So from one gene you
can get 7500 different heavy chains, just
by combinatorics.
All right.
But that's not all because remember, there
are light chain genes.
And so there are two kinds of light chain
genes.
There is a Kappa light chain gene and a
Lambda light chain gene.
So the germ line Kappa light chain gene.
Kappa light chain looks like this.
It has a number of V regions and a number
of J regions upstream of a constant
region, so we're going to make that blue.
All right.
And so we have a number of V regions
[SOUND] in
the Kappa light chain, dot, dot, dot.
V1, V2 and in the Kappa Light Chain in
humans anyway there are about 40 of these.
And then downstream of them there are some
J regions and
the J regions look like so, dot, dot, dot.
And there are five J regions, J1, J2 and
J5.
So, how many recombinant can we get from
the Kappa light chain for
each one of the J regions?
We can have 40 V regions.
So, there are a total of 40 times 5 but
there is also a lambda light chain.
Now, it's interesting,
the lambda light chain [SOUND]
looks a little bit different and actually
if you go to the chapter
on gene duplication at the beginning of
the very origins of the VDJ recombination.
You can imagine that the duplication could
have occurred in a way to
produce the lambda light chain.
It's just a little bit of a different
pattern of duplication.
So, the way the duplication happened was
for
the lambda light chain dot, dot, dot.
There are a total of also, about 40 V
regions.
Okay?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then there are four J segments, each
of which,
is upstream of its own constant region.
So the, gene duplication that occurred is,
looks like this.
So here's one J region.
Upstream of its own constant region, I'm
going to draw a different kind of
constant region because this is now the
lambda light chain.
And then, there's another J region and
dot, dot, dot.
Let's just, save some time here.
Another J region.
And there's a total of four of
these, so, J4, upstream of its own
constant region.
So as a result of this, we have a total
for the Kappa light chain,
we have a total of 40 times 5
possibilities.
For the lambda light chain we have a total
of 40 times 4 possibilities.
So, the total number of different ways you
can have light chains.
Is 40 times 5 plus the number of ways you
can have lam,
that's the number of ways you can have
kappa light
chains plus the number of ways you can
have lambda light chains.
So this is kappa, kappa, and the number of
ways you can have lambda light chains,
which would be 40 times 4.
That's lambda.
Okay?
And that equals 200 plus 160, that equals
360.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, every antibody has to have two
identical heavy chains and
two identical light chains.
There are a total of 7,500 different
combinations that
can produce a heavy chain.
And a total of 360 different ways you can
produce a light chain.
The germ, the germ line heavy changing
undergoes VDJ recombination.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And the light chains undergo VJ
recombination.
That's why, the D is in parenthesis.
Because heavy chain does the D,
and light chains only do V and J.
So the total number of combinations of
heavy chain and
light chain is 7,500 times 360.
7,500 times 360 and
that equals 2,700,000, a truly staggering
number.
So just by combinatorics, three measly
little genes,
one germ line heavy chain gene and two
different light chains, Kappa and Lambda.
Three genes can produce two, 2,700,000
different combinations.
That gives you incredible diversity in,
encoding for antibodies.
And as a result of that,
we can fight off infections from bugs that
we haven't even seen before.
Because we have that many different ways
of making antibodies.
Now contrast this to another strategy,
which would be to make a separate gene for
every different antibody that you could
make.
You'd have to make 2,700,000 different
genes.
Well, it turns out our genome really
doesn't have enough room for
that, because the human genome contains
only about 20,000 genes.
So there's no way you could have an immune
system with this kind of diversity if
you didn't use the combinatorics that are
involved in VDJ combination.
So you've got 2,700,000 ways to make
anti-bodies out of three genes.
And so you're only using up three of your
20,000 genes to make antibodies.
Pretty amazing.
Thank you.