[BLANK_AUDIO]
This is the denouement of our series of
lectures on VDJ recombination,
because that whole process of VDJ
recombination culminates in
the formation of an antibody molecule.
And I've drawn for you up here an antibody
molecule.
And the antibody molecule consists of two
identical heavy chains, and
the two identical heavy chains are heavy
chains because they're bigger.
And I'll show you the heavy chains with
little arrows.
There's one here.
And there's one there.
And two identical light chains.
And there are two identical light chains.
One over here and one over here.
Okay.
And each of those chains, the light chain
and heavy chain.
Have in them a variable region and the
variable region has been drawn in black.
So the variable regions are in black.
Alright, variable regions.
And the colors.
Let's draw a red and blue arrow.
Red and blue arrow.
Correspond to constant regions.
The red to the constant region of the
heavy chain and
the blue to the constant region of the
light chain.
Okay.
So, these antibodies can have incredible
variation.
In fact, the variation is absolutely mind
boggling and
because these antibodies have to recognize
all kinds of foreign antigens, and I'm
going to show you exactly how we get to
such huge numbers using VDJ recombination.
It turns out that we mentioned that there
was a heavy chain gene.
And I'm going to draw for you the heavy
chain gene, okay.
So here's a single heavy chain gene.
And it's the germ line heavy chain gene.
All right, there's the germ line heavy
chain gene, all the way across there.
So long germ line heavy chain gene.
And let me just say, germ line, heavy
chain gene.
Heavy chain gene.
So the antibodies a protein but now, we
got a gene.
Germ line heavy chain gene.
And the germ line heavy chain gene
consists of a number of variable regions.
I'm going to draw a few of them.
Dot, dot, dot, okay, and
in the human, it turns out, every animal
is somewhat different.
But, in the human there are roughly 50
variable regions.
Okay, in addition to that, way down
stream,
let's put a stagger mark down there, there
are a number of D regions,
and I'm going to draw a few of them, dot,
dot, dot.
And so there are a number of D regions and
in fact there are about 25 D regions in
the human.
D1, D2, and D25.
Okay.
So,
downstream of that, there are a number of
J regions.
And in the human, there are six J regions.
Dot, dot, dot, six J regions.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay.
J1, J2, and J6.
So all of these are a little bit different
so
I'm going to make them a little bit
different.
All right.
So there's the heavy chain gene
right up here.
And as we described before,
VDJ recombination picks one of the V
regions, one of the D regions and
one of the J regions and brings them
together, all right?
So there's a tremendous amount of
diversity that's produced from this
recombination event.
Now, downstream from the J region.
Now I've run out of space so I'm just
going to curl it around, I'm going to
draw a block corresponding to the constant
region of the heavy chain, and
of course, because the anybody has it in
red I'll also draw it in red here.
So this is the constant region for the
heavy chain.
All right, and notice that I've drawn the
V,
the D, and the J all in black because
they're going to end up encoding
the variable region of the heavy chain
which is up here.
So how many different variable regions can
we get out of
this single heavy chain gene?
Well, for any one of the J regions, you
can have 25 different D regions,
but there are six J regions, each of which
can go with 25 V regions.
So, the number of D to J combinations.
Let me draw it in black to emphasize.
Gotta get the colors.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You can get 25 times six D to J
combinations.
But each of these D to J combinations can
go with any one of 50 V regions.
So, you can get a total of
50 times 25 times six recombinants from V,
D, and J.
So 50 times 25 times six is equal to 7500.
7,500.
So from one gene, you can get 7,500
different heavy chains just by [UNKNOWN].
Alright.
But that's not all,
because remember, there are light chain
genes.
And so there are two kinds of light chain
There is a kappa light chain gene and a
lambda light chain gene.
So the germ line kappa light chain gene,
kappa light chain.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Looks like this.
It has a number of V regions and a number
of J regions,
upstream of a constant region, so, we're
going to make that blue.
Alright.
And so we have a number of V regions in
the kappa light chain.
Dot, dot, dot.
V1, V2 and in the Kappa light chain in
humans anyway,
there are about 40 of these, and then
downstream of them,
there are some J regions and the J regions
look like so, dot, dot, dot.
And there are five J regions, J1, J2, and
J5.
So, how many recombinants can we get from
the kappa light chain for
each one of the J regions?
We can have 40 V Regions.
So there are a total of 40 times five, but
there's also a lambda light chain.
Now, it's interesting.
The lambda light chain, looks a little bit
different and,
actually, if you go to the chapter on gene
duplication,
the beginning, the very origins of the VDJ
recombination.
You can imagine that the duplication could
have occurred in a way to
produce the lambda light chain.
It's just a little bit of a different
pattern of duplication.
So, the way the duplication happened was
for
the lambda light chain [SOUND] dot dot
dot.
There are a total of also about 40 V
regions.
Okay.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then there are four
J segments, each of which is upstream with
its own constant region.
So the gene duplication that occurred.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Is, looks like this.
So here's one J region.
Upstream of its own constant region, I'm
going to draw a different kind of
constant region because this is now the
lambda light chain.
And then, there's another J region.
And dot dot dot, let's just save some time
here.
Another J region.
And there's a total of four of these, so
J4, upstream of its own constant region.
So as a result of this, we have a total,
for the kappa light chain,
we have a total of 40 times five
possibilities.
For the lambda light chain we have a total
of 40 times four possibilities.
So the total number of different ways you
can have light chains
is 40 times five, plus the number of ways
that you can lambda,
that's the number of the ways you can have
kappa light chains.
Plus the number of ways you can have
lambda light chains, so this is kappa.
Kappa.
And the number of ways you can have lambda
light chains which would be 40 times four,
that's lambda, okay?
And that equals 200 plus 160, that equals
360.
So.
Every antibody has to have two identical
heavy chains and
two identical light chains.
There are a total of 7,500 different
combinations that can produce a heavy
chain, and a total of 360 different ways
you can produce a light chain.
The germ, the germ line heavy chain gene
undergoes VDJ recombination.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And the light chains undergo VJ
recombination.
That's why the D is in parentheses.
Because heavy chain does the D, and light
chains only do V and J.
So the total number of combinations of
heavy chain and
light chain is 7,500 times 360.
7,500.
Times 360.
And that equal 2,700,000.
A truly staggering number.
So just by common [UNKNOWN], three measly
little genes.
One germ line heavy chain gene and two
different light chains, kappa and lambda.
Three genes can produce 2,700,000
different combinations.
That gives you incredible diversity in, in
coding for antibodies.
And as a result of that, we can fight off
infections from bugs that we haven't
even seen before, because we have that
many different ways of making antibodies.
Now contrast this to another strategy
which would be to make a separate gene for
every different antibody that you could
make.
You would have to make 2,700,000 different
genes.
Well it turns out our genome really
doesn't have enough room for
that because the human genome contains
only about 20,000 genes.
So there's no way you could have an immune
system with this kind of diversity if
you didn't use the common [UNKNOWN] that
are involved in VDJ recombination.
So you've got 2,700,000 different ways to
make antibodies out of three genes.
And so you're only using up three out of
your 20,000 genes to make antibodies.
Pretty amazing.
Thank you.