Hi, my name is Sharon Chen, and I'm from
Stanford University.
And in this video, we're going to be
talking about basics of bacterial
structure and function which is part of
our Introduction to Microbiology module.
The learning objectives are to describe
the key structural and
functional features unique to bacteria.
To explain how horizontal gene transfer
relates to virulence, and
antimicrobial resistance.
To explain how the bacterial cell wall is
involved in identification and
classification of bacteria and as a target
for antibiotics, to understand the role of
pathogen associated molecular patterns and
infection.
And to visualize the major groups of
bacteria that cause disease.
Bacteria are the oldest and smallest life
form, if we look at the tree of life.
They are the first life form to branch out
from our most ancient common ancestor.
This means that they arose over 1 and a
half billion years.
Before even the simplest single cell,
eukaryotic cells,
that we call protozoa, began populating
the earth.
It took animals another billion years to
appear.
Thus the bacteria have been evolving
sophisticated strategies to survive,
colonize, and infect us for much longer
than we have existed.
Bacteria are also the smallest living
forms,
about ten times smaller than a single cell
in our body.
And they colonize almost every available
niche,
from our skin to all of our internal
mucosal surfaces.
In some ways, we are walking planets since
about 1 trillion bacteria live on
the surface of our skin alone.
There are more bacteria living on our
bodies than the number of
cells that make our tissues.
And many will accompany us, from the day
we are born, to our deathbed.
In fact, most interactions between our
bodies and
bacteria may be beneficial and do not
result in disease.
The bacteria living on us are much more
diverse than the subset that
cause disease.
This is called the microbiome.
In fact, we can't even culture a great
number of them.
And most of what we know comes from
analyzing their genomes.
We're learning that the bacteria living on
our external and
internal surfaces have important roles in
our physiology.
For example, in the intestine, they help
us digest nutrients, produce vitamins and
teach our immune system.
By simply being there,
they also protect us from pathogens that
could take over or invade.
In this course we will speak mainly about
the pathogenic bacteria.
Those that cause diseases in humans.
Let's start with a very basic description
of their structure and
then discuss some features that are more
specifically involved in disease.
Bacteria are relatively simple small bags
of cytosol surrounded by a membrane and
other layers of a tough envelope.
If we start from the inside, we'll find
cytosol rich in macro molecules,
including DNA, RNA, and proteins, but with
no internal membranes or organelles.
There is no nucleus, but
similar to eukaryotes, the genome is
encoded by double stranded DNA.
Usually, there is a single circular
chromosome that is
tightly coiled to fit in a very tiny
volume.
In addition to the chromosome,
some bacteria have extra chromosomal
genetic elements called plasmids,
which are smaller, usually circular
molecules of DNA.
Plasmids often carry genes that are not
essential for general bacterial survival.
But that can encode properties such as
antibiotic resistance.
Horizontal gene transfer is the exchange
of genetic information between bacteria.
This is different from inheritance which
is transfer of
information from one generation to
another.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Horizontal gene transfer is a way to
quickly share genetic information even
between bacteria of different families.
In infectious diseases,
this is particularly important because
both pathogenic traits as well as
antibiotic resistance can be transferred
in this way making evolution much faster.
In this picture, we also
highlighted the bacterial ribosomes which
are factories for protein production.
Bacterial ribosomes are different enough
from our eukaryotic ribosomes that they
are good targets for antibiotics.
This is a short list of common antibiotics
that effect each of the two subunits of
the bacterial ribosomes and interfere with
protein synthesis.
The cytosol is packaged and held together
by several layers of the envelope.
A simple lipid bilayer called a cell
membrane, as seen here in green,
with transmembrane proteins within it.
Surrounding the cell membrane is the cell
wall made of peptidoglycan.
The peptidoglycan cell wall is a structure
unique to bacteria.
The peptidoglycan cell wall is a flexible,
but
strong molecular mesh made of a single
molecule.
It consist of parallel strands of
repeating disaccharides,
that means two sugars and cross length to
each other by short peptide chains.
The wall is important for maintaining and
determine the shape of the bacteria.
And protects the bacteria from osmotic
pressure.
It needs to be constantly modified and
assembled to accommodate growth and
division.
And thus a very important second target
for
antimicrobials, called cell wall agents.
The cell wall and cell membrane together
are called the cell envelope.
One group of bacteria have a cell membrane
surrounded by a thick cell wall.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
A second group of bacteria evolved a
second membrane or
outer membrane that surrounds a thin cell
wall.
These two groups can be distinguished by a
very common microbiological stain used in
the clinic called the Gram-stain.
The structure of the envelope determines
the difference in the staining.
Here's an example of the stain.
Gram-positive bacteria have thick cell
walls that stain strongly and
retain the purplish stain.
While gram-negative bacteria stain poorly
and remain pink.
The outer cell membrane of gram-negative
bacteria is a barrier that
allows further control of diffusion of
substances in and out of the bacteria.
This makes them naturally resistant to
antibiotics that cannot penetrate
the outer membrane.
It also makes them resistant to enzymes
that degrade the cell wall,
like lysisime in our tears and saliva.
There are many important modifications of
the cell wall and
the outer cell membrane that change the
properties of the envelope.
One that is very important in medicine is
on the outer leaflet
of the outer membrane.
These are special lipids cross-linked to
sugar chains called
Lipopolysaccharides or LPS.
LPS is important for
the structural integrity of the outer
membrane and its permeability.
It is also an extremely potent signaling
molecule.
When LPS is released from dying bacteria,
it can be sensed by our innate immune
system in the blood stream.
The response can be so
dramatic that it acts like a toxin and can
cause shock and even death.
In fact, it's also known as endotoxin,
as opposed to toxins that are secreted by
that bacteria, exotoxins.
The response to LPS is an example of our
body's ability to
detect specific molecules from bacterial
pathogens and even from commensals.
We call these Pathogen-Associated
Molecular Patterns, or PAMPs.
Other optional structures in the bacteria
envelope can be quite important in
colonizing us, or in causing disease.
For example, many bacteria swim, propelled
by rotating flagella,
which is a tubular polymer anchored to an
nano motor that spins the flagella.
The envelope may be covered with other
structures, like fimbriae or
pili, long polymers with a molecular hook
at the end,
that allow the bacteria to attach to the
cell surface, or to each other.
Several types of molecular syringes,
known as secretion systems may be embedded
in the envelope.
These can secrete or transfer molecules
from the bacteria to the host cells.
Finally, a conspicuous external addition
to the envelope is a mucoid substance made
of sugars, polysaccharides, called the
capsule.
It can help bacteria either avoid being
seen by our immune systems,
by hiding their surface structures,
prevent them from drying out, or
make them difficult to phagocytose by our
white blood cells.
There are many specialized molecules that
are involved in disease, and
are usually not essential to the survival
of the bacteria.
We often call these bacterial products
virulence factors,
because they enhance the ability of
bacteria to cause disease.
One example of a specific virulence factor
is a protein that
the vibrio cholera produce to induce
massive, watery diarrhea.
This is an example of a virulence factor
that can quickly lead to dehydration
because of the action of a single molecule
with a powerful biological effect.
Many virulence factors are shared through
horizontal gene transfer.
As we explore the many fascinating
microbes that cause disease in humans,
think about these adaptations and
which virulence factors are involved in
the diseases you learn about.
We will end with a short list of the
bacteria that cause disease in humans and
will be mentioned in the course.
This list organizes the bacteria in a
clinical way that would help you
come back and place the microbes in
context.