Hi, my name is Sharon Chen and I'm from
Stanford University.
This video is on entry.
How microbes enter the host.
And as part of our Introduction to
Microbiology module.
From the point of view of a microbe,
the first step of causing infection is to
gain entry into the host.
In this video,
we will discuss the common entry portals
that microbes use to infect humans.
For physicians, it is important to
understand where the infection began.
How a microbe enters the host can help
with diagnosis.
And prevention of infection transmission.
The learning objectives are to recognize
the portals of entry that microbes use to
enter the host and
to describe some ways that microbes gain
access to the entry portals of the host.
Microbes enter hosts through many
different portals.
Any break in the skin apatheia layer is an
entry portal.
Skin can be disrupted through trauma
including a scape on a knee,
surgical incisions and bites from animals
or vectors like mosquitos.
Mucosa including conjunctiva, nares,
oropharynx, vagina, and
rectum are also entry portals.
Some entry portals are specialized.
For example, the umbilical cord and
umbilicus are important portals for
the fetus in neonate.
In order for microbes to enter the via
portals,
the microbes must gain access to these
entry portals.
Access to entry is determined by host
behaviors, motility of the microbe and
sensing cues, among others.
Several examples of host behaviors allow
access to entry portals.
What we eat and drink is an important
determinant.
For example, drinking contaminated water
can lead to
cholera resulting in profuse watery
diarrhea.
People who don't wash hands properly and
touch their eyes, nose, or
mouth allow potential entry of influenza
virus and other respiratory viruses.
Unprotected sexual intercourse allows
potential entry of HIV or
Treponema pallidum, the bacteria that
causes syphilis.
Even scratching a bug bite could allow
potential entry of microbes.
Chagas disease is caused by a protozoa
called [UNKNOWN].
Trypanosomes in the feces of the reduviid
bug, can access through breaks in
the skin from a person scratching the
intensely peridic bite.
Microbes can also gain access to entry
portals by swimming or crawling.
Free-living organisms, such as round
worms, use this strategy.
Vectors gain access to hosts by using
sensing cues.
Production of carbon dioxide is a common
strategy used by
mosquitoes which can transmit Plasmodium,
the protozoa that causes malaria.
And it's also used by ticks which can
transmit Borrelia burgdorferi,
the bacteria that causes lyme disease.
Vectors can also use temperature,
vibration, shadows, and
colors as sensing cues.
[BLANK_AUDIO]