Hi, my name is Sharon Chan and I am from
Standford University.
This video is on strategies microbes use
to exit the host.
It is part of our introduction to
microbiology module.
Exiting the host is an important step on
the lifestyle of a microbe.
Microbes must exit a host in order to
transmit to another host.
For physicians understanding how microbes
exit can help with strategies to prevent
transmission in, of infection to another
person and for diagnosing microbes.
For some microbes exit and entry portals
are the same.
For other microbes, they are different.
In this video, we will discuss some common
exit strategies used by microbes.
Bacteria can employ virulence factors for
examples for toxins for exiting the host.
Vipera Cholera the bacteria that causes
Cholera toxin that results in
production of watery stools.
Vipera Cholera exist the host within the
watery stool.
People with Cholera produce up to one
liter hour of watery stool.
Each liter contains one trillion bacteria.
So much stool is released that a special
bed was developed to
measure the fluid loss.
It is called a cholera cot and is shown in
this image.
Viruses can produce skin lesions to exit a
host.
Herpes simplex virus produces a vesicular
lesions which contain infectious virus.
When the vesicle ruptures, herpes simplex
virus can exit the host.
The virus can be transmitted to another
person by a simple kiss.
For fungi, dermatophytes such as this one
causing a severe athlete's foot
exit the host within skin cells that are
normally shed by the host.
However invasive fungi, do not exit the
host and
thus are not transmissible to another
host.
Invasive Fungi, such as aspergillus are
not communicable.
For parasites a common means of exiting a
host is to
shed eggs within the hosts stool.
The shape of parasite eggs can be useful
for diagnosis.
When examining these two samples under a
microscope.
The image shows a picture of an egg from a
schistosoms a type of
worm called a [UNKNOWN].
The position of the it's hook on the egg
distinguishes this schistosoms from
other species.
These eggs have to survive harsh
conditions outside of their host.
Potentially for long periods of time.
Thus eggs are developed to be resistant to
many types of environments and chemicals.
Another type of worm is the pin worm, a
nemetode.
Unlike schistosoms, pin worms are a much
more common infection in the US.
Pin worms are in fact the most common
helminth infection in the United States.
The video shows an embroyanted egg with a
pinworm inside.
In contrast the shishisomes which shed
eggs in host stool female pinworms
migrate to the anus to deposit eggs, both
the migrating worm and
the egg are irritating to the skin causing
intense itching in the parianal region.
The eggs are sticky when deposited by the
worm.
School-age children will scratch around
the anus,
picking up eggs on their fingers and
fingernails.
Invariably, these contaminated fingers
find their way into mouths,
depositing the egg into the
gastrointestinal tract.
Where it will later hatch a larvae,
completing the life cycle.
With the help of host behaviors,
pinworm eggs are a good example of a
successful exit strategy.
For some microbes, exiting the host can
also be done via vector.
Some members of bacteria, virus and
protozoa exit through blood sucking
vectors like this mosquito.
Microbes that use these strategies,
avoid harsh environments by using an
intermediate host.
[BLANK_AUDIO]