Hi, my name is Sharon Chen and I'm from
Standford University.
This video is on Establishing Infection.
Part of our Introduction to Microbiology
module.
After entering the host pathogens must
colonize a specific niche in order to
establish an infection.
Colonization usually involves avoiding the
host barriers in
clearance mechanisms that protect us from
invasion.
This stage of the infectious cycle takes
place during the incubation period,
which is silent and without clinical
symptoms.
The learning objectives of this video is
to
describe how pathogens reach a location to
establish an infection.
To explain the different mucosal clearance
mechanisms that pathogens must overcome.
To explain different ways in which
microbial attachment is
involved in pathogenesis.
To discuss how microbes cross the
epithelial barrier to establish infection.
And to describe how pathogens invade
cells.
In this video we will discuss how microbes
reach a particular location and
how attachment, crossing the epithelial
barrier and
invading cells are involved in
establishing infection.
We will give you examples from bacterial,
viral, fungal and parasitic infections.
Once a microbe has entered a host, it
needs to reach its preferred location.
This may involve active motility and
sensing by the microbe.
In the case of bacteria, there are
multiple mechanisms of directed movement.
The most prominent is Flagellar motility,
coupled to Chemotaxis.
Flagella are appendages that propel the
bacteria as they swim.
In this movie, the bacteria swim randomly
until a needle releases an attractant.
Their ability to respond and concentrate
at the source is called Chemotaxis.
This microbe is Helicobacter Pylori, a
bacterium that
colonizes the human stomach and uses this
ability to avoid being killed by acid and
to reach the surface of the stomach
epithelium, it's preferred location.
In contrast to bacteria, neither viruses
nor
pathogenic fungi can move on their own.
Yet, they are very efficient pathogens.
Virus and fungi can reach their prefered
sites of infection by
random diffusion called Brownian motion.
And by the flow of body fluids.
In addition, although they cannot move,
fungi can extend their reach by growing
Hyphai.
Parasites refer to both single-celled
protozoa,
as well as multi-cellular organisms, each
with distinct types of motility.
Some protozoa move using specialized
appendages called Cilia.
Other, like amoeba, crawl by extending
pseudopodia.
Still others use gliding motility.
In this video,
you can see a stage of the protozoa that
causes malaria gliding over a surface.
This is a stage that the mosquito injects
into the skin.
The parasite uses this movement to enter
blood or lymph vessel.
To glide over the surface of endothelial
cells, and eventually,
to reach liver cells and invade.
Helminths and arthropods use muscles to
move.
Here, you can see a free swimming
schistosome cercaria.
Trying to penetrate the skin.
It's first uses its tail to reach the
skin,
and then loses it as it penetrates the
epidermis.
It then crawls into deeper tissues.
Eventually, it will travel through the
body and
establish an infection in the liver.
Colonization also involves microbes
surviving very harsh environments.
The mucosal surface is equipped with
numerous mechanisms to clear microbes.
These include mucus, which traps microbes,
cilia in our airways,
which pushes mucus and trapped microbes
outward.
In the gastrointestinal tract,
microbes also need to overcome the
peristalsis that transports contents out.
Our bodies produce numerous microbocidal
chemicals.
The human stomach is a vat of acid that
can reach a PH of one and
destroy most microbes.
This is followed by a shower of bial in
the duatamin that functions as
a detergent stripping membranes off of
organisms and off of viruses.
Finally, there are specialized molecules
secreted to injure microbes,
such as Antimicrobial peptides that poke
holes in bacteria, Lysozyme that
digest the cell wall, and Antibodies that
specifically bind to microbial structures.
Once they reach their prefered location,
microbes have multiple mechanisms to
attach and avoid clearance.
Attachment is so important for
pathogens that they have molecules and
appendages for this purpose.
Attachment is often essential for
disease and thus they are considered
virulence factors.
For example, E, coli is a commensal
colonizing our large intestine.
Some strains have evolved pili that can
attach to the surface of
cells lining the urinary bladder.
The strains that have these pili are
responsible for
most urinary tract infections.
Other bacteria use surface molecules as
adhesins rather than pili.
For example, the agent that causes
whooping cough,
is a bacterium that can directly attach to
cilia in our airwaves,
the same structures that would clear most
other microbes.
Attachment is not just important for
bacteria, for viruses it often determines
which cells they can invade.
Viral infection of specific cell types is
called Viral tropism.
This is often determined by the specific
attachment of
viral surface molecules to host-cell
receptors.
Only cells that express the receptors can
be infected.
An important example of this is Influenza.
A virus that infects our airway epithelial
cells by
binding to cialic acid residues on
[UNKNOWN] proteins.
This interaction is so specific that
variations in the cialic acid arrangement.
Determines which spices of animal and
influenza virus can affect.
Avian influenza viruses cannot easily
infect humans.
During establishment of an infection,
attachment can occur between microbes and
the host.
But, also between each other, and even to
foreign material.
Some bacteria can secrete myocyte
compounds that glue them together,
forming biofilms.
These can grow on catheters and prosthetic
devices.
Biofilms allow bacteria to hide from the
immune system and from antibiotics.
Making these infections hard to treat and
many times requiring removal of the
device.
Catheters are also an example of a way in
which microbes can
penetrate the epithelial barrier to
establish invasive infection.
Breakdown of the epithelial barrier is a
common theme in
the establishment of infection.
In addition to catheter, others skin
defects, such as burns and
wounds can predisposed to infection.
Patients with recurrent infections may
have breakdown of their
epithelial barriers due to anatomic
defects.
For example, epithelial injury and
inflammation can cause a formation of
a fistulous connection between the colon
and the urinary bladder.
This can lead to recurrent and difficult
to treat urinary tract infections.
Breakdown over the epithelial barrier can
also be caused by drugs such as
chemotheraputic agents used to treat
cancer.
It predisposed patients to bloodstream
infections with their
own microbial colonizer.
Some microbes are able to cross intact
epithelial barriers,
to establish an invasive infection.
One mechanism is to invade specialized
cells of the immune system, whose job is
to transiently open the epithelial
junctions to survey and sample the mucosa.
Dendritic Cells, for
instance, can sample the mucosa by
extending thin cellular processes.
Between the intercellular junctions of the
epithelium.
Some pathogens like HIV, [INAUDIBLE] this
process by invading the dendritic cells
and then spreading to other cells once
they are brought across the epithelium.
This is thought to be how HIV first
processed some
mucosal epithelial surfaces.
Without the need for a wound.
There are other specialized mucosal
epithelial cells that survey and
sample the contents of the intestine.
They are called M cells, microfold cells.
Found on the surface of the Peyer's
patches in the intestine.
Several bacterial pathogens like
Salmonella can invade
the epithelium through M cells and thus
cross the epithelial layer.
Like Salmonella.
Many pathogens invade cells as a way to
establish an infection.
This is true of all viruses since they
required the host so
machinery for replication.
There are several ways to invade cells for
intercellular growth.
Some, bacteria like tuberculosis infect
macrophages through phagocytosis and
then survive inside the phago zone.
Viruses mostly enter through endocytosis
and then invade the cytosol.
Parasites like plasmodium and
toxoplasmosis as seen in this video.
Use a sophisticated mechanism of active
invasion to
squeeze themselves into host cells.
Remember though that invasion is just one
pathogenic strategy.
In other pathogens, for
example Bordetella pertussis, the bacteria
that causes whooping cough,
stay on the epithelial surface and do not
invade cells to cause disease.
[BLANK_AUDIO]