Hi, my name is Sharon Chen, and
this video is on, Virus structure
classification and pathogenesis.
This is part of our Introduction to
Microbiology module.
The Learning Objectives are to identify
the distinctive structures of a virus, and
describe their function.
To describe viral virulence, to describe
viral pathogenesis, to recognize
that viruses constantly evolve and adapt
to changing selective pressures, and
to distinguish the different ways of
cataloging viruses.
What is a Virus?
A Virus is defined as a small infectious
agent.
It is Submicroscopic.
It is not a living organism in contrast to
bacteria.
And it does not have ribosomes.
A Virus is an obligate intracellular
parasite.
It is completely dependent on a living
host cell for reproduction.
The infectious virus particle is called a
Virion and
is composed of a limited number of
structures.
The Capsid is a protein coat that protects
the nucleic acid genome.
The Capsid can also be used for attachment
to a host cell.
The Envelope is found only in some viruses
and
consists of a Lipid membrane derived from
host cell membrane.
The envelope functions as an extra
protective layer.
Glycoproteins are anchored in the envelope
and are used by the virus for
attachment to a host cell.
The origin of viruses is debated.
Theories include one, that viruses were
once just Genetic elements that
gained the ability to exit one cell and
enter another.
Two, viruses transformed from a free
living organism into a parasite.
Could viruses be the Precursor of life?
Viruses are not a living organism.
They are not part of the tree of life, as
you can see in the image.
However, viruses infect all living things,
including Bacteria, Fungi, and Animals.
In fact, viruses are part of us.
Each bacteria in our intestines can be a
home for a virus.
And a portion of our DNA, comes from
endogenous retroviruses.
Viruses have evolved and will continue to
evolve.
Emerging viruses, prove this point.
Most of the recent, new emerging viruses
are zoonotic.
The viruses is transmitted from animal to
man, either directly or via a vector.
The animal serves as a reservoir, and
wild animals, wildlife, are increasingly
implicated in zoonoses.
New viral infections on humans evolve
based on two concepts.
One New viruses arise from mutations,
reassortment, or recombinations.
These new viruses attempt to achieve
successful replication within old and
new host.
Two, New environments develop that place
humans in closer contact to animals.
Ecology changes and an increase in world
travel can create these new environments.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Virus replication is host cell-dependent.
The virus life cycle steps include the
virus attaches to
specific receptors on a host cell.
It then enters the cell through
endocytosis.
The virus uses the host cell machinery to
replicate its nucleic acid and
to make necessary proteins.
The nucleic acids and structural
components are assembled into new virions.
The new virions are released from the host
cell by budding or lysis.
Envelope viruses release with a layer, an
envelope, of the host cell membrane.
Viral Pathogenesis is how a virus
infection causes disease in a host.
Disease in a host is an effect of both
viral replication and
host immune response.
Viral pathogenesis is determined by,
Interaction with specific host cells.
Interaction with immune system.
Host immune response causing pathology.
And virus are host immune response changes
to cell growth potential.
First, the interaction with specific host
cells.
Disease manifestation in human is dictated
by the specific host cell that
the virus attaches and enters.
For example, HIV attaches and enters into
CD4T cells,
which are important for protecting against
many types of infections.
Patients with HIV infection, have low
numbers of CD4T cells, and
subsequently succumb to many different
types of infections.
Interactions with the immune system
includes multiple concepts.
First, Viral Immune Escape.
One main mechanism of escaping from the
immune system is to
change what the immune cells recognize.
Immune cells recognize pieces of protein
called Antigens.
HIV is a good example of the tremendous
amount of antigenic variation that
occurs during replication.
This image shows you antigenic variation
of HIV in red,
compared to influenza virus in black.
Although the image shows a relatively
small amount of antigenic variation for
influenza, the antigen changes necessitate
a change in
the seasonal influenza vaccine, year to
year.
Development of an HIV vaccine continues to
be a challenge.
Immune modulation or immune evasion.
Viruses depend on and have co evolved with
its host.
Thus for successful propagation, viruses
have to overcome host immune defenses.
Viruses have evolved mechanisms to
modulate or
evade almost every aspect of the host
immune system.
For example, many viruses block or inhibit
interference.
A side of kind that functions as a key
first line anti viral defense for a cell.
Many viruses also block [UNKNOWN] of the
cell in order to
complete its replication cycle.
Avoiding immune surveillance.
Another strategy that some viruses use is
to hide in a location that
has low immune surveillance, that is
patrolling by immune cells.
An example would be Virusella oster virus
hiding in the dorsal root, ganglion.
The host immune response alone can cause
pathology.
Acute lung injury and acute respiratory
distress syndrome are a result of
a runaway immune response of
pro-inflammatory cytokines.
Certain respiratory viruses can induce
this clinical picture, including the 2009
Pandemic H1N1 influenza virus and SARS
corona virus.
Virus Pathogenesis can also be determined
by virus or host immune response
changes to the cell growth potential, this
is called viral transformation.
Viral transformation of cells can lead to
uncontrolled cell replication and
formation of tumors, thus some viruses can
cause cancer.
These are called Oncogenic viruses.
Hepatitis B is an example of an oncogenic
virus.
Chronic Hepatitis B infection could lead
to hepatocellular carcinoma,
which is depicted in the pathology image.
It is important to note that inducing
cancer is not required for
the virus to propagate.
Viral Virulence is the capacity of the
virus to cause disease and
can be affected by both the virus and the
host.
In virology, the determine of virulence is
predominantly based
on viral genetics with a focus on
mutations in viral genes.
Mutations in viral genes can change Viral
replication.
Higher replication rates may be associated
with higher virulence and
can change Viral spread.
The ability of a virus to disseminate may
be associated with higher virulence.
The host can also affect Viral Virulence.
A virus may be much more virulent in an
immunocompromised host.
Compared to one who is immunocompetent.
Although much focus is on viruses with
increased virulence the concept of
reduced virulence is equally important.
It has called Attenuation and is the
Conceptual basis for
many live viral vaccines.
Viruses can be organized by their
architecture.
The shape, Icosahedral, cylindrical or
complex.
The presence or not of an envelope
surrounding the capsid and
by their size which can range from 20 to
400 nanometers.
Viruses can also be organized by their
nucleic acid, DNA or RNA.
A common organizational scheme used by
virologists.
Is the Baltimore Classification.
It catalogs all viruses into seven groups
based on the specific type of DNA or RNA.
In order to fully propagate,
the virus must produce messenger RNA, mRNA
to then produce protein.
Messenger RNA is the central link for
all seven groups in the Baltimore
classification.
The image on this slide also highlights
the diversity of
viral nucleic acid compared to nucleic
acid for all living things.
All the non viruses, only have double
stranded DNA.
Biologically, RNA and DNA viruses are
different.
During RNA synthesis, RNA viruses do not
have proofreading mechanisms.
So these viruses are prone to replication
error.
DNA viruses are not because they do have
proofreading mechanisms.
RNA viruses must encode their own enzymes
for RNA replication.
DNA viruses can use host cell enzymes.
RNA viruses tend to cross species barriers
and infect several different hosts.
DNA viruses tend to be species-specific.
Differences between the RNA and DNA
viruses have clinical implications.
Mutations from replication errors can
affect virulence,
that is capacity of the virus to cause
disease.
Mutations can also enable a virus to be
con-resistant to an antiviral medication.
This concept is the basis of using
multiple antiviral medications to
treat HIV infections.
The use of virus encoded enzymes is an
ideal target for antivirals medications.
Less side effects will be observed in the
host compared to
antiviral medications that target host
cell enzymes.
Viral transmission among different types
of hosts and prevention of transmission
should be considered more often for RNA
viruses compared to DNA viruses.
Viruses can be classified into viral
families.
The family names end with viridae, for
example, Herpesviridae.
In this family are multiple species
including herpes simplex virus, HSV, and
[UNKNOWN] zoster virus, VZV.
Of the virus that infect humans, there are
seven families of DNA viruses and
13 families of RNA viruses.
[BLANK_AUDIO]